<Poem ID="38" Name="" BookID="08" BookName="زبورِعجم" SectionID="02" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جہان کورست و از آئینۂ دل غافل افتاد است
ولی چشمی کہ بینا شد نگاہش بر دل افتاد است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The world had lost its sight and the glass of the heart forsook, but an eye now sees the light that into the heart can look.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شب تاریک و راہ پیچ پیچ و بی یقین راہی
دلیل کاروان را مشکل اندر مشکل افتاد است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Dark is the night, twists the road, all faithless the wayfarers; and the caravan’s guide what load of problems oppressive bears!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رقیب خام سودا مست و عاشق مست و قاصد مست
کہ حرف دلبران دارای چندین محمل افتاد است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Raqib-e-khaam souda must-o-ashiq must-o-qasid must; Drunk are the feckless spy, the lover, the messenger; so the words of the sweethearts lie in how many loads to wear.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یقین مومنی دارد گمان کافری دارد
چہ تدبیر اے مسلمانان کہ کارم با دل افتاد است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Its faith of believer true, its doubt of the infidel – O Muslims, what shall I do with the heart that in me doth dwell?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گہی باشد کہ کار ناخدائی میکند طوفان
کہ از طغیان موجی کشتیم بر ساحل افتاد است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Sometimes the helmsman’s skill the storm doth display, and more! Lo, the waves, impetuous will hath cast our craft on the shore.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نمیدانم کہ داد این چشم بینا موج دریا را
گہر در سینۂ دریا خزف بر ساحل افتاد است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Who fashioned these seeing eyes in the wave, far in ocean lost, that the pearl in the sea’s heart lies, and the potsherd breaks on the coast?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نصیبی نیست از سوز درونم مرز و بومم را
زدم اکسیر را بر خاک صحرا باطل افتاد است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        No part of my soul’s unrest hath stirred in my Native land; with my magic I tried my best, it was lost on the desert sand.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اگر در دل جھانی تازہ ئی داری برون آور
کہ افرنگ از جراحتہای پنہان بسمل افتاد است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If a New World thou hast in thy bosom, declare thy faith! Wounded in heart and breast, Europe is nigh to death.
(Translated by A.J. Arberry.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>