<Poem ID="03" Name="" BookID="11" BookName="ارمغانِ حجاز" SectionID="01" SectionName="حضور حق">
  <Para Name="(1)">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دلی در سینہ دارم بے سروری
نہ سوزی در کف خاکم نہ نوری
بگیر از من کہ بر من بار دوش است
ثواب این نماز بے حضوری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میرے سینے میں ایک بے کیف دل ہے، نہ میری کف خاک میں سوز ہے نہ نور۔ 
مجھ سے نماز بے حضور کا صواب واپس لے لے، یہی میرے کندھوں پر بوجھ ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My heart knows not the bliss of His flame, no pangs nor light in my earthen frame.
So take off this burden as oft I brood, a prize for prayers in absence of mood.
(Translated by Q A Kabir)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(2)">
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چہ گویم قصہ دین و وطن را
کہ نتوان فاش گفتن این سخن را
مرنج از من کہ از بے مہری تو
بنا کردم ہمان دیر کہن را
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میں دین و وطن (کی کشمکش ) کا قصّہ کیا بیان کروں ، یہ بات ا علانیہ نہیں کہی جا سکتی۔ 
مجھ سے ناراض نہ ہونا، کیونکہ تیری عدم توجہی کے باعث میں نے پھر وہی پرانا بتخانہ تعمیر کر لیا ہے (کیونکہ آپ اہل دین کی دلجوئی نہیں فرماتے، اس لیے انہوں نے وطن کے بت کی پرستش شروع کر دی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        How to tell tale of ‘Deen’ and father land? No words I have on a difficult stand.
So do not take ill if due to thy ways, I cherish to revive the good old days. 
(Translated by Q A Kabir)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(3)">
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مسلمانی کہ در بند فرنگ است
دلش در دست او آسان نیاید
ز سیمائی کہ سودم بر در غیر
سجود بوذر و سلمان نیاید
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جو مسلمان فرنگی (تصورات) کے بندھن میں گرفتار ہے، وہ آسانی سے دل کی دولت نہیں پا سکتا ۔ 
جو پیشانی غیر اللہ کے دروازے پر گھسی جاتی ہے؛ وہ ابوذر غفاری (رضی اللہ) اور سلمان فارسی (رضی اللہ) جیسے سجدے کرنے سے قاصر ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A Muslim tied up with a foreign land, his heart cannot he with ease in his hand.
The forehead I place on an alien’s place, to Boozer and Salman it can’t replace.
(Abu zar Ghaffari and Salman Farsi of Persia were the companions of the Prophet Muhammad S.A.)
(Translated by Q A Kabir)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(4)">
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نخواہم این جھان و آن جہان را
مرا این بس کہ دانم رمز جان را
سجودی دہ کہ از سوز و سرورش
بوجد آرم زمین و آسمان را
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        نہ میں اس جہاں (دنیا) کی خواہش رکھتا ہوں، نہ اس جہاں (آقا) کی۔ 
مجھے ایسا سجدہ عطا فرما ، جس کے سوز و سرور سے، میں زمین و آسمان کو وجد میں لے لوں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I wish not this world, nor cosmos whole, save that I know the essence of soul.
So kindle my kowtows with melting glee,* move the world and heavens in trance with me.
* The highest bliss (melting glee) of direct link with God, when heart starts saying ALLAH, ALLAH while the lips are tight. An initial state in which the man feels as if his heart is one foot long due to its quick movements a phase of highest bliss which cannot be compared with any mundane joy. This experience is quite common with hundreds of men in each city. Then the heart also visualises the light of a Prophet of Allah with whom his temperament is analogous (similar.) Sometimes in this phase a Moslem sees the wonderful light of the Jesus (Isa alaihis salam), the Moses, Abraham, Adam, Muhammad (God’s blessings be upon them). It happens in a natural way, sometimes without any meditation. This experience may be for few hours a few days or months or more.
(Translated by Q A Kabir)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(5)">
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چہ میخواہی ازین مرد تن آساے
بہ ہر بادی کہ آمد رفتم از جای
سحر جاوید را در سجدہ دیدم
بہ صبحش چہرہ شامم بیارای
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        آپ اس آرام طلب بندے (اقبال) سے کیا توقع رکھتے ہیں، جسے ہوا کا ہر جھونکا اپنی جگہ سے ہٹا دیتا ہے۔ 
صبح میں نے جاوید کو سجدے میں دیکھا ، اس کی صبح سے میری شام کو آراستہ کر دیں (اس کی جوانی میرے بڑھاپے کے لیے باعث فخر ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What ye hopes from an easy going bloke, whither the wind blows he changes his cloak.
I espied Javed in ‘Sajdah’ this dawn, deck my even face by his shining dawn. 
(Translated by Q A Kabir)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>