<Poem ID="14" Name="توحید" BookID="03" BookName="ضربِ کلیم" SectionID="01" SectionName="اسلام اور مسلمان">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زندہ قوت تھی جہاں میں یہی توحید کبھی 
آج کیا ہے، فقط اک مسئلہء علم کلام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        علم کلام: وہ علم جس میں اسلامی عقائد کو دلیلوں کے ذریعے سے ثابت کیا جاتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ONENESS OF GOD
There were times when God's oneness was a living force in world of clay: But subtle points by pedants raised have changed the trend of times today.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        روشن اس ضو سے اگر ظلمت کردار نہ ہو 
خود مسلماں سے ہے پوشیدہ مسلماں کا مقام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ضو: روشنی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If conduct dark is not illumed by means of bright and dazzling glow it means that rank of Muslim true he himself also does not know.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میں نے اے میر سپہ! تیری سپہ دیکھی ہے 
'قل ھو اللہ، کی شمشیر سے خالی ہیں نیام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        سورہ اخلاص کی طرف اشارہ ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O Marshal of this great array, I have descried your mighty hordes they don't repeat ‘Say God is One’, their sheaths devoid of piercing swords.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آہ! اس راز سے واقف ہے نہ ملا، نہ فقیہ 
وحدت افکار کی بے وحدت کردار ہے خام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Mullah and Jurist both alas about this fact are not aware; as long as thoughts are not the same; the ripeness of acts leads nowhere.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        قوم کیا چیز ہے، قوموں کی امامت کیا ہے 
اس کو کیا سمجھیں یہ بیچارے دو رکعت کے امام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Mullahs who lead prayers brief, don't know a nation's goal and aim. How can they learn a nation's weight, when things like this they do not claim?
(Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>