<Poem ID="18" Name="نصیحت" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میں نے اقبال سے از راہ نصیحت یہ کہا 
عامل روزہ ہے تو اور نہ پابند نماز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        One day by way of advice I said to Iqbal: Neither you fast nor are regular in prayers.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تو بھی ہے شیوہ ارباب ریا میں کامل 
دل میں لندن کی ہوس، لب پہ ترے ذکر حجاز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ارباب ريا: ریا کار لوگ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You are also perfect in the ways of hypocritical people; you pine for London in the heart but you talk of Hijaz.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جھوٹ بھی مصلحت آمیز ترا ہوتا ہے 
تیرا انداز تملق بھی سراپا اعجاز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تملق: خوشامد۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your lies are also based on what is expediency; the manner of your flattery also is fully miraculous.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ختم تقریر تری مدحت سرکار پہ ہے 
فکر روشن ہے ترا موجد آئین نیاز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مدحت: خوشامدی تعریف۔
موجد: ایجاد کرنے والا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your lecture ends on glorification of the government; your bright thought is the inventor of methods of entreating.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        در حکام بھی ہے تجھ کو مقام محمود 
پالسی بھی تری پیچیدہ تر از زلف ایاز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مقام محمود: پسندیدہ مقام۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Officials’ doors are also like Maqam-i-Mahmud* to you; your designs are more interlocked than locks of Ayaz’ hair.
* Maqam-i-Mahmëd – This is the elevated place and the elegant status of the Holy Prophet (S.A.W.) on the Day of Judgment from where he will request God for forgiveness for his Ummah.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اور لوگوں کی طرح تو بھی چھپا سکتا ہے
پردہ خدمت دیں میں ہوس جاہ کا راز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ہوس جاہ: دنیاوی جاہ و جلال کی خواہش۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Like other people you can also conceal secrets of self aggrandizement in your cloak of din’s service.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نظر آجاتا ہے مسجد میں بھی تو عید کے دن 
اثر وعظ سے ہوتی ہے طبیعت بھی گداز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You are seen in the mosque also on the Eid day; your heart is also softened by the sermon’s effect.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دست پرورد ترے ملک کے اخبار بھی ہیں 
چھیڑنا فرض ہے جن پر تری تشہیر کا ساز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تشہير: شہرت۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You practice reading country’s newspapers also which are obligated to sing your repute’s songs.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اس پہ طرہ ہے کہ تو شعر بھی کہہ سکتا ہے 
تیری مینائے سخن میں ہے شراب شیراز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        طرہ: اس سے بڑھ کر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        On top of all this you can also write verse; your poetry’s goblets are full of the wine of Shiraz.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جتنے اوصاف ہیں لیڈر کے، وہ ہیں تجھ میں سبھی 
تجھ کو لازم ہے کہ ہو اٹھ کے شریک تگ و تاز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Whatever are the attributes of leaders, you have them all incumbent on you is rising and joining the struggle.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        غم صیاد نہیں، اور پر و بال بھی ہیں 
پھر سبب کیا ہے، نہیں تجھ کو دماغ پرواز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You are not afraid of hunters, as you have wings also then why are you not inclined for flight?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عاقبت منزل ما وادی خاموشان است 
حالیا غلغلہ در گنبد افلاک انداز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        آخر شب کو مرنا ہے اور مردہ لوگوں کی وادی میں پہنچنا ہے لہذا اس گنبد افلاک کے نیچے کچھ تو ہنگامہ کرنا چاہيے ۔ (الطاف حسین حالی)
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ‘The end of our life is the cemetery; presently raise tumult in the sky’s vault.’ 
(Translated by M.A.K. Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>