<Poem ID="12" Name="" BookID="03" BookName="ضربِ کلیم" SectionID="06" SectionName="محراب گل افغان کے افکار">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لا دینی و لاطینی، کس پیچ میں الجھا تو 
دارو ہے ضعیفوں کا 'لاغالب الا ھو'
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اغالب الا ھو: اللہ کے سوائے اور کوئی غالب نہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In maze of Latin script and sin, your bearings, no doubt, you have lost belief that none has might save God, is cure for weak that acts so fast.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        صیاد معانی کو یورپ سے ہے نومیدی 
دلکش ہے فضا، لیکن بے نافہ تمام آہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        بے نافہ تمام آہو: تمام ہرن بغیر مشک کے ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A man who likes to hunt the facts must quit all hopes of West, is clear its atmosphere is full of charm, but one can't find musk-yielding deer.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بے اشک سحر گاہی تقویم خودی مشکل 
یہ لالہ پیکانی خوشتر ہے کنار جو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تقویم: قیام، مضبوطی، 
الہ پیکانی: یہاں مراد ہے خودی۔ 
کنار جو: ندی کے کنارے ؛ مراد ہے سحر گاہی کے آنسو،۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The self of man derives much strength from tears he sheds at early morn much good that tulip, like the dart, the marge of some brook may adorn.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        صیاد ہے کافر کا، نخچیر ہے مومن کا 
یہ دیر کہن یعنی بتخانہ رنگ و بو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This idol-house of hue and scent, or fane so ancient, old and hoar hunts hose who don't believe in God, on Muslims has effect no more.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے شیخ، امیروں کو مسجد سے نکلوا دے 
ہے ان کی نمازوں سے محراب ترش ابرو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ترش ابرو: ناراض، خفا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O Shaikh, get all the rich expelled from precincts of the Holy mosque
For niche of mosque is angry with them all for their much impious task.
[Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>