<Poem ID="08" Name="سلطان ٹیپو کی وصیت" BookID="03" BookName="ضربِ کلیم" SectionID="02" SectionName="تعلیم و تربیت">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تو رہ نورد شوق ہے، منزل نہ کر قبول 
لیلی بھی ہم نشیں ہو تو محمل نہ کر قبول
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE TESTAMENT OF TIPU SULTAN
If you traverse the road of love, don't yearn to seek repose or rest; if Laila be your companion close that litter shun with great contempt.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے جوئے آب بڑھ کے ہو دریائے تند و تیز 
ساحل تجھے عطا ہو تو ساحل نہ کر قبول
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جوئے آب: ندی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O steamlet, onward flow and get transformed to torrent strong and deep, if bank is e'er on you bestowed, abstain, flow on with mighty sweep.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کھویا نہ جا صنم کدہ کائنات میں 
محفل گداز ! گرمی محفل نہ کر قبول
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Don't lose your bearings in this world, because with idols it is full: The assemblage here can cast a spell, disdain, or strings of heart shall pull.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        صبح ازل یہ مجھ سے کہا جبرئیل نے 
جو عقل کا غلام ہو، وہ دل نہ کر قبول
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Gabriel on Creation's Early Morn, a piece of useful counsel gave: He bade me not accept a heart enchained by mind of man like slave.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        باطل دوئی پسند ہے، حق لا شریک ہے 
شرکت میانہ حق و باطل نہ کر قبول!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Untruth conceals in various masks, but Truth and God are both unique. There can't be pool 'twixt good and bad, this fact is known from times antique.
[Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>