<Poem ID="03" Name="پیام" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="2a" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عشق نے کر دیا تجھے ذوقِ تپش سے آشنا
بزم کو مثل شمع بزم حاصل سوز و ساز دے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ذوقِ تپش: تڑپ کی لذت۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE MESSAGE
Love made you acquainted with the taste of affliction; like assembly’s candle give affliction’s gift to the assembly.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شانِ کرم پہ ہے مدار عشقِ گرہ کشاے کا
دیر و حرم کی قید کیا! جس کو وہ بے نیاز دے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مدار: انحصار۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The illuminating Love depends on God’s Benevolence; to whomever He may give without restriction of temple or Haram.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        صورتِ شمع نور کی ملتی نہیں قبا اُسے
جس کو خدا نہ دہر میں گریۂ جاں گداز دے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        دہر: دنیا۔ 
گریۂ جاں گداز: ایسا رونا جس سے جان میں گداز پیدا ہو۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Like the candle the mantle of light he does not get; whom God does not give effective wail in the world.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تارے میں وہ، قمر میں وہ، جلوہ گہِ سحر میں وہ
چشم نظارہ میں نہ تو سرمۂ امتیاز دے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ُرمۂ امتیاز: مراد ہے تعصب۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He is in the star, the moon, the dawn’s theatre of display; you need not apply discrimination’s collyrium to the Sightful eye.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عشق بلند بال ہے رسم و رہِ نیاز سے
حسن ہے مست ناز اگر تو بھی جوابِ ناز دے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        رسم و رہِ نیاز: عاجزی کا طریقہ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Love is exalted above the customs and usages of prayers; if Beauty has ecstasy of elegance you too give elegant reply.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پیر مغاں! فرنگ کی مے کا نشاط ہے اثر
اس میں وہ کیف غم نہیں، مجھ کو تو خانہ ساز دے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        نشاط: خوشی۔
پیرِ مغاں: شراب خانے کا مالک۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O Tavern-keeper! Pleasure is the only effect of West’s wine; it does not have pleasure of affliction, give me the home-made wine.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تجھ کو خبر نہیں ہے کیا! بزم کہن بدل گئی
اب نہ خدا کے واسطے ان کو مے مجاز دے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        بزم کُہن : پرانی تہذیب۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Do you not know? The old congregation has changed; for God’s sake do not give them materialism’s wine.
[Translated by Dr M A K Khalil]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>