<Poem ID="12" Name="" BookID="07" BookName="پیامِ مشرق" SectionID="03" SectionName="می باقے">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آشنا ہر خار را از قصۂ ما ساختی
در بیابان جنون بردی و رسوا ساختی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You have made every thorn prick us and know our tale. You took us to the wilderness of madness, and let everybody know.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جرم ما از دانہ ئی تقصیر او از سجدہ ئے
نے بہ آن بیچارہ میسازی نہ با ما ساختی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Our fault was we ate of a grain, and his that he refused to bow. You never pardoned that poor devil, nor have You yet forgiven us.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        صد جہان میروید از کشت خیال ما چو گل
یک جہان و آنہم از خون تمنا ساختی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A hundred worlds spring up like flowers from our imagination’s soil. There is but one real world; and that too you have made of the blood of murdered wishes.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پرتو حسن تو می افتد برون مانند رنگ
صورت می پردہ از دیوار مینا ساختی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Like colour the reflection of Your beauty shines through the glass. You have made of the goblet’s wall a screen for Yourself, just like wine.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        طرح نو افکن کہ ما جدت پسند افتادہ ایم
این چہ حیرت خانہ ئی امروز و فردا ساختی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O, lay some new foundation, for we happen to like novelty. What is this giddy peep-how You have made of yesterdays, to-morrows and to-days?
(Translated by M. Hadi Husain)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>