<Poem ID="44" Name="ارتقا" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ستیزہ کار رہا ہے ازل سے تا امروز 
چراغ مصطفوی سے شرار بولہبی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        EVOLUTION
Struggle has continued from eternity till the present day between the lamp of Mustafvi and the spark of Bu Lahab.’
(He was one of the uncles of the Holy Prophet (S.A.W.) but was still one of the strongest enemies of him and of Islam.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حیات شعلہ مزاج و غیور و شور انگیز 
سرشت اس کی ہے مشکل کشی، جفا طلبی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Life is flame-tempered, high-minded and fervent; its nature is resolving difficulty, bearing cruelty.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سکوت شام سے تا نغمہ سحر گاہی 
ہزار مرحلہ ہائے فعان نیم شبی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        From the evening’s quietude till the morning’s song there are many a stage of the midnight wailing!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کشا کش زم و گرما، تپ و تراش و خراش 
ز خاک تیرہ دروں تا بہ شیشہ حلبی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Struggle exists between the heat and cold, throbbing and shaping from the dark dust to the polished glass of Halab!
(Halab or Aleppo was a famous place for the manufacture of quality glassware.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مقام بست و شکت و فشار و سوز و کشید
میان قطرئہ نیسان و آتش عنبی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The phenomena of making and breaking, squeezing, heating and distilling exist between the drop of spring rain and the heat of the grape wine!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اسی کشاکش پیہم سے زندہ ہیں اقوام 
یہی ہے راز تب و تاب ملت عربی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Nations live by this continuous struggle alone; this alone is the secret of the Arab nation’s struggle!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مغاں کہ دانہء انگور آب می سازند 
ستارہ می شکنند، آفتاب می سازند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ‘The tavern-keepers making wine from the grape; break the stars and construct the sun.’
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>