<Poem ID="05" Name="ابر کوہسار" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="1a" SectionName="حصہ اول">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے بلندی سے فلک بوس نشیمن میرا
ابر کہسار ہوں گل پاش ہے دامن میرا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        فلک بوس: آسمان کو چومنے والا یعنی بہت بلند۔ 
گل پاش: پھول برسانے والا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE CLOUD ON THE MOUNTAIN
Elevation bestows the sky's nearness to my abode; I am the mountain's cloud, my skirt sprinkles roses.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کبھی صحرا، کبھی گلزار ہے مسکن میرا
شہر و ویرانہ مرا، بحر مرا، بن میرا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Now the wilderness, now the rose garden is my abode, city and wilderness are mine, ocean is mine, forest is mine.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کسی وادی میں جو منظور ہو سونا مجھ کو
سبزہ کوہ ہے مخمل کا بچھونا مجھ کو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If I want to return to some valley for the night; the mountain's verdure is my carpet of velvet.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مجھ کو قدرت نے سکھایا ہے درافشاں ہونا
ناقہ شاہد رحمت کا حدی خواں ہونا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ناقہ: اونٹنی۔
درافشاں: موتی بکھیرنا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Nature has taught me to be a pearl spreader’ to chant the camel song for the camel of the Beloved of Mercy.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        غم زدائے دل افسردہ دہقاں ہونا
رونق بزم جوانان گلستاں ہونا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        To be the comforter of the dispirited farmer's heart; to be the elegance of the assembly of the garden's trees.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بن کے گیسو رخ ہستی پہ بکھر جاتا ہوں
شانہ موجہ صرصر سے سنور جاتا ہوں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        شانہ موجہء صرصر: ہوا کا جھونکا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I spread out over the face of the earth like the locks; I get arranged and adorned by the breeze's.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دور سے دیدہ امید کو ترساتا ہوں
کسی بستی سے جو خاموش گزر جاتا ہوں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I tantalize the expecting eye from a distance as I pass silently over some habitation.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سیر کرتا ہوا جس دم لب جو آتا ہوں
بالیاں نہر کو گرداب کی پہناتا ہوں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        لب جو: ندی کنارے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        As I approach strolling towards a brook's bank; I endow the brook with ear rings of whirlpools.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سبزہ مزرع نوخیز کی امید ہوں میں
زادہ بحر ہوں پروردہ خورشید ہوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مزرع نوخیز: نئی اگی ہوئی کھیتی۔ 
زادہ بحر: جو سمندر سے پیدا ہوا ہو۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I am the hope of the freshly grown field's verdure; I am the ocean's offspring, I am nourished by the sun.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چشمہ کوہ کو دی شورش قلزم میں نے
اور پرندوں کو کیا محو ترنم میں نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I gave ocean's tumult to the mountain spring; I charmed the birds into thrilling chants.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سر پہ سبزے کے کھڑے ہو کے کہا قم میں نے
غنچہ گل کو دیا ذوق تبسم میں نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        قم: اٹھ، کھڑا ہو۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I pronounced ‘Rise’* standing by the verdure's head; I conferred the taste for smile to the rose-bud.
* This is an allusion to the miracle of Ibn-e-Maryam (A.S.) in which, he used to raise the dead to life by pronouncing ‘Qum bi Idhnillah’ (Rise with the permission of God) Just as he used to raise the dead to life with the permission of God so does the rain from cloud raise the apparently dead vegetation to life with the permission of God: The Holy Qur’an 78:14-16.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فیض سے میرے نمونے ہیں شبستانوں کے
جھونپڑے دامن کہسار میں دہقانوں کے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        شبستانوں: امیر لوگوں کے سونے کی جگہ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        By my benevolence farmers' huts on the mountain side are converted into bed chambers of the opulent.
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>