<Poem ID="04" Name="" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3b" SectionName="غزلیات 3">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پردہ چہرے سے اٹھا، انجمن آرائی کر 
چشم مہر و مہ و انجم کو تماشائی کر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Lift the veil from Thy Face and be manifest in the assembly; make the eyes of the sun, moon and stars Thy spectators.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تو جو بجلی ہے تو یہ چشمک پنہاں کب تک 
بے حجابانہ مرے دل سے شناسائی کر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Thou art the lightning; how long this secret winking? Make acquaintance with my heart without a veil.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نفس گرم کی تاثیر ہے اعجاز حیات 
تیرے سینے میں اگر ہے تو مسیحائی کر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The warm breath’s effect is the miracle of life; if it is on Thy breast perform life-giving miracles.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کب تلک طور پہ دریوزہ گرمی مثل کلیم 
اپنی ہستی سے عیاں شعلہ سینائی کر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        How long should begging be on the Toor like Kalim! Make the flame of Sinai manifest with Thy Existence.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہو تری خاک کے ہر ذرے سے تعمیر حرم 
دل کو بیگانہ انداز کلیسائی کر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Let the Haram be built with every speck of Thy dust. Make the heart alien to the ways of the Church.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اس گلستاں میں نہیں حد سے گزرنا اچھا 
ناز بھی کر تو بہ اندازئہ رعنائی کر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It is not good to exceed limits in this garden; if Thou showeth elegance make its show with grace.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پہلے خوددار تو مانند سکندر ہو لے 
پھر جہاں میں ہوس شوکت دارائی کر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        First become self-respecting like Alexander; then make the show of desire of Dara’s grandeur.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مل ہی جائے گی کبھی منزل لیلی اقبال! 
کوئی دن اور ابھی بادیہ پیمائی کر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You will reach the destination of Lailah one day, O Iqbal! For some more days continue wandering in the wilderness. 
(Translated by Naeem Siddiqui)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>