<Poem ID="01" Name="ہمالہ" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="1a" SectionName="حصہ اول">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے ہمالہ! اے فصیل کشور ہندوستاں
چومتا ہے تیری پیشانی کو جھک کر آسماں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        HIMALAYA
O Himalaya! O rampart of the realm of India! Bowing down, the sky kisses your forehead.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تجھ میں کچھ پیدا نہیں دیرینہ روزی کے نشاں
تو جواں ہے گردش شام و سحر کے درمیاں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        دیرینہ روزی: لمبی عمر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your condition does not show any signs of old age; you are young in the midst of day and night's alternation*. 
* The alternation of the day and night is what produces time. This verse also alludes to the relative recentness of the Himalayas in terms of geological ages. This range came into existence 5-10 million years ago in the Pliocene epoch.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ایک جلوہ تھا کلیم طور سینا کے لیے
تو تجلی ہے سراپا چشم بینا کے لیے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        چشم بینا: دیکھنے والی آنکھ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Kalim of Toor-e-Seina witnessed but one Effulgence for the discerning eye you are an embodiment of Effulgence.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        امتحان دیدئہ ظاہر میں کوہستاں ہے تو
پاسباں اپنا ہے تو، دیوار ہندستاں ہے تو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        دیدئہ: آنکھ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        To the outward eye you are a mere mountain range; in reality you are our sentinel, you are India's rampart.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مطلع اول فلک جس کا ہو وہ دیواں ہے تو
سوئے خلوت گاہ دل دامن کش انساں ہے تو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        دامن کش: دامن کھینچنے والا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You are the diwan whose opening verse is the sky. You lead Man to the solitudes of his heart's retreat.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        برف نے باندھی ہے دستار فضیلت تیرے سر
خندہ زن ہے جو کلاہ مہر عالم تاب پر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        دستار فضیلت: برتری کی پگڑی۔ 
کلاہ مہر عالم تاب: دنیا کو روشن کرنے والے سورج کی ٹوپی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Snow has endowed you with the turban of honour* which scoffs at the crown of the world-illuminating sun.
* The successful completion of education in the institutions of higher learning in the Muslim world culminates in a turban being conferred on the scholar as an insignia of his academic degree. It corresponds with the cap and academic hood in the Western world.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تیری عمر رفتہ کی اک آن ہے عہد کہن
وادیوں میں ہیں تری کالی گھٹائیں خیمہ زن
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Antiquity is but a moment of your bygone age; dark clouds are encamped in your valleys.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چوٹیاں تیری ثریا سے ہیں سرگرم سخن
تو زمیں پر اور پہنائے فلک تیرا وطن
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ثریا: دو ستارے جو بہت دور ہیں۔ 
پہنائے فلک: آسمان کی وسعت۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your peaks are matching with the Pleiades in elegance; though you are standing on earth your abode is sky's expanse.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چشمہ دامن ترا ئنہ سےال ہے
دامن موج ہوا جس کے لیے رومال ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ا ئنہ سیال: بہنے والا؛ رواں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The stream in your flank is a fast flowing mirror, for which the breeze is working like a kerchief.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ابر کے ہاتھوں میں رہوار ہوا کے واسطے
تازیانہ دے دیا برق سر کہسار نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کوڑا۔ تازیانہ
رہوار ہوا: ہوا کا گھوڑا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The mountain top's lightning has given a whip in the hands of cloud for the ambling horse.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے ہمالہ کوئی بازی گاہ ہے تو بھی، جسے
دست قدرت نے بنایا ہے عناصر کے لیے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        بازی گاہ: کھیل کی جگہ، کھیل کا میدان۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O Himalah! Are you like a theater stage which nature's hand has made for its elements?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہائے کیا فرط طرب میں جھومتا جاتا ہے ابر
فیل بے زنجیر کی صورت اڑا جاتا ہے ابر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        فیل: ہاتھی۔
فرط طرب میں: بے حد خوشی میں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Ah! How the cloud is swaying in excessive joy; the cloud like an unchained elephant is speeding.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جنبش موج نسیم صبح گہوارہ بنی
جھومتی ہے نشہ ہستی میں ہر گل کی کلی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        موج نسیم جنبش : ہوا کی لہر کی رواانی۔
گہوارہ: جھولا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Gentle movement of the morning zephyr is acting like a cradle; every flower bud is swinging with intoxication of existence.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یوں زبان برگ سے گویا ہے اس کی خامشی
دست گلچیں کی جھٹک میں نے نہیں دیکھی کبھی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        برگ: پتّہ۔ 
دست گلچیں: پھول چننے والے ہاتھ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The flower bud's silence with the petal's tongue is saying ‘I have never experienced the jerk of the florist's hand.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کہہ رہی ہے میری خاموشی ہی افسانہ مرا
کنج خلوت خانہ قدرت ہے کاشانہ مرا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کاشانہ: ٹھکانہ، گھر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Silence itself is relating the tale of mine; the corner of nature's solitude is the abode of mine’.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="31">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آتی ہے ندی فراز کوہ سے گاتی ہوئی
کوثر و تسنیم کی موجوں کی شرماتی ہوئی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        فراز کوہ: پہاڑ کی بلندی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The brook is melodiously descending from the high land putting the waves of Kawthar* and Tasnâm* to embarrassment.
* Kawthar and Tasnâm: They are two fountains in Paradise. The name includes their streams also.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آئنہ سا شاہد قدرت کو دکھلاتی ہوئی
سنگ رہ سے گاہ بچتی، گاہ ٹکراتی ہوئی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        شاہد قدرت: قدرت کی خوبصورتی؛ مراد ہے معشوق۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        As if showing the mirror to Nature's beauty; now evading now rowing against the rock in its way.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="35">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چھیڑتی جا اس عراق دل نشیں کے ساز کو
اے مسافر دل سمجھتا ہے تری آواز کو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        عراق: موسیقی کا ایک راگ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Play in passing this orchestra of beautiful music O wayfarer! The heart comprehends your music.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="37">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لیلی شب کھولتی ہے آ کے جب زلف رسا
دامن دل کھینچتی ہے آبشاروں کی صدا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When the night's Lailah unfurls her long hair; the sound of water-falls allures the heart.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="39">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وہ خموشی شام کی جس پر تکلم ہو فدا
وہ درختوں پر تفکر کا سماں چھایا ہوا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تکلم: گفتگو۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        That silence of the night whose beauty surpasses speech. That state of silent meditation overshadowing the trees.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="41">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کانپتا پھرتا ہے کیا رنگ شفق کہسار پر
خوشنما لگتا ہے یہ غازہ ترے رخسار پر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        غازہ: چہرے پر استعمال کا پوڈر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        That dusk's beauty which shivers along the mountain range; very beautiful looks this rouge on your cheeks.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="43">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے ہمالہ! داستاں اس وقت کی کوئی سنا
مسکن آبائے انساں جب بنا دامن ترا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مسکن: رہنے کی جگہ۔ 
آبائے انساں: انسان کے باپ دادا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O Himalah! Do relate to us some stories of the time when your valleys became abode of Man's ancestors*.
* This refers to the antiquity of the Himalayas in archaeological times. Kashmir was an inhabited area at the time of the Indus Valley civilization in the third millennium B.C. It also alludes to the tradition that the Hindu sages wrote the Vedas in the Himalayas under the inspiration of its beauty.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="45">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کچھ بتا اس سیدھی سادی زندگی کا ماجرا
داغ جس پر غازئہ رنگ تکلف کا نہ تھا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Relate something of the life without sophistication which had not been stained by the rouge of sophistication.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="47">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہاں دکھا دے اے تصور!پھر وہ صبح و شام تو
دوڑ پیچھے کی طرف اے گردش ایام تو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O Imagination! Bring back that period O Vicissitudes of Time speed backwards*.
* This is an outpouring of the poet's heart in which he yearns for the revival of the Islamic civilization, of which the Asian civilization was a precursor and a part.
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>