<Poem ID="04" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="01" SectionName="حصہ اول">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اثر کرے نہ کرے، سن تو لے مری فریاد 
نہیں ہے داد کا طالب یہ بندہء آزاد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Whether or not it moves you, at least listen to my complaint; it is not redress this free spirit seeks.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ مشت خاک، یہ صرصر، یہ وسعت افلاک 
کرم ہے یا کہ ستم تیری لذت ایجاد!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This handful of dust, this fiercely blowing wind, and these vast, limitless heavens: Is the delight You take in creation; a blessing or some wanton joke?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ٹھہر سکا نہ ہوائے چمن میں خیمہء گل 
یہی ہے فصل بہاری، یہی ہے باد مراد؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The tent of the rose could not withstand the wind blowing through the garden: Is this the spring season, and this the auspicious wind?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        قصور وار، غریب الدیار ہوں لیکن 
ترا خرابہ فرشتے نہ کر سکے آباد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I am at fault, and in a foreign land, but the angels never could make habitable that wasteland of yours.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مری جفا طلبی کو دعائیں دیتا ہے 
وہ دشت سادہ، وہ تیرا جہان بے بنیاد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        That stark wilderness, that insubstantial world of Yours; gratefully remembers my love of hardship.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خطر پسند طبیعت کو ساز گار نہیں 
وہ گلستاں کہ جہاں گھات میں نہ ہو صیاد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        An adventurous spirit is ill at ease in a garden where no hunter lies in ambush.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مقام شوق ترے قدسیوں کے بس کا نہیں 
انھی کا کام ہے یہ جن کے حوصلے ہیں زیاد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The station of love is beyond the reach of Your angels; only those of dauntless courage are up to it.
(Translated by Mustansir Mir)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>