<Poem ID="11" Name="" BookID="07" BookName="پیامِ مشرق" SectionID="03" SectionName="می باقے">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        از ما بگو سلامی آن ترک تند خو را
کاتش زد از نگاہی یک شہر آرزو را
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Convey my salutation to that fire-eating Turk who set aflame with one glance a city full of longing.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        این نکتہ را شناسد آندل کہ دردمند است
من گرچہ توبہ گفتم نشکستہ ام سبو را
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The point of this will be seen by a sympathetic heart: I swore to drink no more, but did not break the jar of wine.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے بلبل از وفایش صد بار با تو گفتم 
تو در کنار گیری باز این رمیدہ بو را
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O nightingale, I warned you many times against the rose’s infidelity; but you persist in clinging to its scentless skeleton.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رمز حیات جوئی جز در تپش نیابی
در قلزم آرمیدن ننگ است آب جو را
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The secret of life, if you want to know it, lies in restlessness. It would be shameful for a stream to go on resting in the sea.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شادم کہ عاشقان را سوز دوام دادی
درمان نیافریدی آزار جستجو را
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O I am happy that to lovers you have granted restless souls and that You have created no cure for the malady of seeking.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گفتی مجو وصالم بالا تر از خیالم
عذر نو آفریدی اشک بہانہ جو را
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ‘Do not seek union with Me, for I transcend all thought.’ By saying this You gave my tears a new excuse for flowing.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        از نالہ بر گلستان آشوب محشر آور
تا دم بہ سینہ پیچد مگذار ہای و ہو را
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Create a furor in the garden, storm it with your lament. Until breath gets choked in your breast do not give up your wailing. 
(Translated by M. Hadi Husain)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>