<Poem ID="64" Name="شیکسپیر" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شفق صبح کو دریا کا خرام آئینہ 
نغمہ شام کو خاموشی شام آئینہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        SHAKESPEARE
To the dawn’s twilight the river’s graceful flow is a mirror! To the evening’s song the evening’s silence is a mirror.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        برگ گل آئنہ عارض زبیائے بہار 
شاہد مے کے لیے حجلہ جام آئینہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        حجلہ جام: پیالے کی جلوہ گاہ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        To the spring’s beautiful cheek flower petal is a mirror! To the lover of wine the cup’s cavity is mirror.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حسن آئنہ حق اور دل آئنہ حسن 
دل انساں کو ترا حسن کلام آئینہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Beauty is God’s mirror and heart is Beauty’s mirror! To the human heart the beauty of your marks is a mirror.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے ترے فکر فلک رس سے کمال ہستی 
کیا تری فطرت روشن تھی مآل ہستی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        فکر فلک رس: آسمان تک پہنچنے والی سوچ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        By your heaven-embracing thought is the perfection of existence. Was your bright nature the aim of existence?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تجھ کو جب دیدئہ دیدار طلب نے ڈھونڈا 
تاب خورشید میں خورشید کو پنہاں دیکھا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When the eye searching for your sight sought you; it saw the sun veiled in the brightness of the sun.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چشم عالم سے تو ہستی رہی مستور تری
اور عالم کو تری آنکھ نے عریاں دیکھا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مستور: چھپا ہوا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your existence surely remained veiled from the world’s eye and your eye saw the world completely unveiled.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حفظ اسرار کا فطرت کو ہے سودا ایسا 
رازداں پھر نہ کرے گی کوئی پیدا ایسا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        سودا: جنون۔
حفظ اسرار: بھید چھپانا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Nature has such a strong desire for guarding secrets that another confidante like you it will never create!
(Translated by M.A.K. Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>