<Poem ID="18" Name="جہاد" BookID="03" BookName="ضربِ کلیم" SectionID="01" SectionName="اسلام اور مسلمان">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فتوی ہے شیخ کا یہ زمانہ قلم کا ہے 
دنیا میں اب رہی نہیں تلوار کارگر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        HOLY WAR
It is the verdict of the Shaikh that pen is stronger than the sword: ‘The sword has lost its might and force, tile pen has gained a firmer hold’.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لیکن جناب شیخ کو معلوم کیا نہیں؟ 
مسجد میں اب یہ وعظ ہے بے سود و بے اثر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        But does not the august Shaikh take cognizance of this bitter fact: That this lecturing in the mosque can never make the least effect?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تیغ و تفنگ دست مسلماں میں ہے کہاں 
ہو بھی، تو دل ہیں موت کی لذت سے بے خبر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تفنگ: بندوق۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In hands of Muslims of the world, where can the gun and sword be seen? If equipped with such deadly arms, to suffer death they won't be keen.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کافر کی موت سے بھی لرزتا ہو جس کا دل 
کہتا ہے کون اسے کہ مسلماں کی موت مر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        At sight of heathen's natural death, if one with fear and fright is filled; no one directs a man like that to get in Holy War be killed.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تعلیم اس کو چاہیے ترک جہاد کی 
دنیا کو جس کے پنجہ خونیں سے ہو خطر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        پنجہ خونيں: خون سے بھرا ہوا ہاتھ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A man, whose bloody claws for world with risk and danger much are fraught; must avoid the Holy Wars, to give up wars he must be taught.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        باطل کی فال و فر کی حفاظت کے واسطے 
یورپ زرہ میں ڈوب گیا دوش تا کمر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        فال و فر: شان و شوکت۔ 
دوش تا کمر: کندھے سے کمر تک۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The West is bent to mount a guard on false, untrue pretentious show. It is armed with weapons dread, is clad in mail from top to toe.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہم پوچھتے ہیں شیخ کلیسا نواز سے 
مشرق میں جنگ شر ہے تو مغرب میں بھی ہے شر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کليسا نواز: گرجا نواز، عیسائیوں کو خوش کرنے والا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        We like to ask the holy Shaikh, who holds the shrine in high esteem; if war for West is heinous crime, how far in East can harmless seem?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حق سے اگر غرض ہے تو زیبا ہے کیا یہ بات 
اسلام کا محاسبہ، یورپ سے درگزر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        محاسبہ: پوچھ گچھ، احتساب۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A man concerned with truth alone can never this much proper deem that East for sins must reckoning face, but crimes by West may lighter seem.
[Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>