<Poem ID="04" Name="" BookID="11" BookName="ارمغانِ حجاز" SectionID="05" SectionName="بہ یاران طریق">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        من و تو از دل و دین نا امیدیم
چوبوی گل ز اصل خود رمیدیم
دل مامرد و دین از مردنش مرد
دو تامرگی بیک سود اخریدیم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میں اور تو دل و دین سے نا امید ہیں، پھول کی خوشبو کی طرح ہم اپنی اصل سے دور جا چکے ہیں۔
ہمارا دل مرا تو اس کے مرنے سے دین بھی مر گیا، ہم نے ایک سودے میں دوہری موت خریدی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        We are despaired of heart and faith’s way, from faith like smell we are running away. 
My heart whom died it killed the faith too, by a bargain lone I got losses two.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مسلمانے کہ داندرمز دین را
نساید پیش غیر اللہ جبین را
اکر گرد ون بکام او مکردد
بہ کام خود بگر داند زمین را
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        وہ مسلمان جو دین کی روح سے باخبر ہے، وہ غیر اللہ کے سامنے اپنی پیشانی نہیں رگڑتا۔
اگر آسمان اس کی مرضی کے مطابق گردش نہ کرے، تو وہ زمین کو اپنی مرضی کے مطابق گھما لیتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        His path’s true sign if a Muslim could know. To else save God, he would never bow.
If the heaven moves not to his own will. He can move the earth whole to his will, still.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دل بیگانہ خوزین خاکدان نیست
شب و روزش زدور سمان نیست
تو خود وقت قیام خویش دریاب
نماز عشق و مستی را اذان نیست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        دل بے نیاز کا تعلق اس دنیا سے نہیں، اس کے شب و روز آسمان کی گردش سے پیدا نہیں ہوتے،
تو (اپنی نماز کے) قیام کا وقت خود دریافت کر، نماز عشق و مستی کی کوئی آذان نہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O callous heart make not a link with clay, the nature changes not her night and day.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مقام شوق بے صدق و یقین نیست
یقین بے صحبت روح الامین نیست
گر از صدق و یقین داری نصیبی 
قدم بیباک نہ کس در کین نیست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        (محبت و) شوق کا مقام صدق و یقین کے بغیر نہیں ملتا ، اور یقین جبریل امین (علیہ) کی صحبت کے بشیر حاصل نہیں ہوتا۔
اگر تجھے صدق و یقین حاصل ہے، تو بیباکی سے قدم اٹھا ، کوئی (شیطان) تیری گھات میں نہیں ہو گا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In Truth and certitude lies the love’s place, no certitude lies without the Gabe’s face. 
If truth and certitude lies in thy fate, put a daring step, none lies in-thy-wait.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مسلمان را ہمین عرفان و ادراک
کہ در خود فاش بیندر مزلولاک
خدا اندر قیاس مانگنجد
شناس نرا کہ گوید ما عرفناک
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مسلمان کا عرفان و ادراک (معرفت و فہم و دین ) یہی ہے، کہ وہ اپنے اندر لولاک کا انداز عیاں دیکھتا ہے۔ (حضور ( صلعم) کو اپنا مقصود حیات سمجھتا ہے۔)
اللہ تعالے تو ہماری سوچ میں نہیں سماتے ، تو انہیں پہچان جنہوں نے فرمایا تھا: کہ ہم نے اللہ تعالے کی معرفت کا حق ادا نہیں کیا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        For Muslim ‘this is the gnosis and ken, in self he sees vivid Laulak’s ken when. 
We cannot hold God as in our thought, be conscious of whom who said, ‘you knew not’. 
(Laulak: Lamma Khuliqat-il-Aflak (A Hadith). If you had not been the whole skies would have not been. Ma’araf na ka (haqqa marifatika): We admit O God that we did not fulfill the debt and duty of Thy gnosis (acquaintance). M’arifat, knowledge gained through experience, enough for recognition, but not as deep as certitude.)
[Translated by Q A Kabir]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بہ افرنگی بتان خود را سپردی 
چہ نامردانہ درتبخانہ مردی 
خرد بیگانہ دل سینہ بے سوز
کہ از تاک یناکان می نخوردی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تو اپنے آپ کو فرنگی حسیناؤں کے حوالے کر کے ، بتکدہ میں کیا نا مردوں کی موت مرا!
تیری عقل، دل (عشق) سے بیگانہ اور سینا نور (ایمان) سے خالی ہے، کیونکہ تو نے اپنے بزرگوں کی شراب (روحانیت) سے استفادہ نہیں کیا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You handed over thee to idols white, and died in the fane, in a coward’s plight. 
The wits missed heart, sans a flame’s least shine. No wines as you took from the father’s vine.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہ ہرکس خود گردھم خود گد از است
نہ ہرکس مست ناز اندر نیاز است
قبای لا الہ خونین قبانی است
کہ بربالای نامردان درا راست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ہر شخص اپنی شخصیت کو گداز کر کے اس کی از سر نو تعمیر نہیں کر سکتا، نہ ہر شخص نیازمندی کے اندر مست ناز رہ سکتا ہے۔
لا الہ کی قبا خونیں قبا ہے، یہ نامردوں کے قد سے بہت بڑی ہے (نا مرد اسے نہیں پہن سکتے)۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A self maker and melter each cant be, nor each Beau dives in the Beauty’s sea.
The Lailah’s gown is stained with blood, which fits not ever on a coward dud. 
Service means a form of worship. It is difficult to perform a prayer of devotees. We just do a service and we do not worship God (in the light of that Hadith) for which the Gabe came personally in the form of man in presence of a large number of the Prophet’s companions a few months before his death. The Gabe asked three questions from the Prophet when all the companions were hearing and seeing the Gabe sitting too close to the Prophet while he had joined both his knees with him, which no companion could dare to sit in such a way. The Gabe asked three questions from the Prophet (S.A.W.): O Prophet of God what is Islam? O Prophet of God what is Iman? O Prophet of God what is Ihsan? For details see Mishkaut Shareef.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بسوزد مومن از سوز و جودش
گشود ہرچہ بستند از گٹودش
جلال کبریائی در قیاش
جمال بندگی اندر سجودش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مومن اپنے وجود کے سوز سے جلتا ہے، ہر سر بستہ راز اسی کے ہاتھوں کھلتا ہے۔
اس کے مقام میں جلال کبریائی ہے، اور اس کے سجود میں جمال بندگی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A Momin burns thus in his being’s own heat, all ties ope quick if he so wished to treat. 
His stay is an air of grandeur and grace, a beauty of service at his bow’s place.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چہ پرسی از نماز عاشقانہ
رکوعش چون سجودش محرمانہ
تب و تاب یکی اللہ اکبر
نگنجد در نماز پنجگانہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        عاشقوں کی نماز کا کیا پوچھتا ہے، اس نماز کا رکوع بھی اس کے سجدے کی طرح مقام قرب ہے۔ 
اس کی ایک تکبیر اللہ اکبر، پانچوں نمازوں سے بڑھ کر ہو۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What is lovers s service, prayers of beaus? His bows like kowtows a tete-a-tete close. 
His shine and vigour big, the God is Great, in the five time service I miss this state.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="37">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دوگیتی را صلا از قرأت اوست
مسلمان لایموت از رکعت اوست
ند اندکشتۂ این عصربی سوز 
قیامتہا کہ درقد قامت اوست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        نماز عشق کی قرآت دونوں جہانوں کے لیے صلا (دعوت) ہے، اس کی ایک رکعت ، مسلمان کو زندہء جاوید بنا دیتی ہے۔
اس دور بے سوز کا مارا ہوا انسان کیا جانے، کہ اس نماز کی اقامت میں کیا قیامت (پوشیدہ ) ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He calls both worlds to Quran by prays, by such one prayer, Muslim dies nay.
Never knew thus the swains of this Age, in his prayer hid a doomsday’s rage.
(The literal translation of line 3 and 4 would be: This flameless age’s victim-knows not, nay, the dooms days are hidden in his calls for Pray. Iqbal has expressed this thought in another verse: Save God a Muslim to none would how, to Pharoahs his head is never low.)
(Translated by Q A Kabir)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>