<Poem ID="43" Name="شبلی و حالی" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مسلم سے ایک روز یہ اقبال نے کہا 
دیوان جزو و کل میں ہے تیرا وجود فرد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        SHIBLI AND HALI
One day Iqbal said to the Muslim: ‘Your existence is unique in the universe.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تیرے سرود رفتہ کے نغمے علوم نو 
تہذیب تیرے قافلہ ہائے کہن کی گرد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The tunes of your old songs are the basis of new knowledge; civilization is the dust of your old caravans.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پتھر ہے اس کے واسطے موج نسیم بھی 
نازک بہت ہے آئنہ آبروئے مرد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Even the zephyr’s current is like stone to it; very delicate is the mirror of Man’s honour.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مردان کار، ڈھونڈ کے اسباب حادثات 
کرتے ہیں چارئہ ستم چرخ لاجورد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        چرخ لاجورد: گہرا نیلا آسمان۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The men of action by discovering the causes of phenomena find the cure for the azure-colored sky’s cruelties.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پوچھ ان سے جو چمن کے ہیں دیرنیہ رازدار 
کیونکر ہوئی خزاں ترے گلشن سے ہم نبرد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ہم نبرد: لڑنے والا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Ask them who are the old secret keepers of the garden: How the autumn became engaged in fight with your garden.’
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مسلم مرے کلام سے بے تاب ہوگیا 
غماز ہوگئی غم پنہاں کی آہ سرد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        غماز: ظاہر کر دینا یعنی چغلی کھانا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Muslim became restless with my conversation; the sad sigh became betrayer of the inner sorrow.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کہنے لگا کہ دیکھ تو کیفیت خزاں 
اوراق ہو گئے شجر زندگی کے زرد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He said ‘Just look at the autumn’s condition; the leaves of the tree of life have become pale.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خاموش ہو گئے چمنستاں کے رازدار 
سرمایہ گداز تھی جن کی نوائے درد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Those garden’s secret keepers became silent; whose tune of pathos was the means of mellowness.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شبلی کو رو رہے تھے ابھی اہل گلستاں 
حالی بھی ہوگیا سوئے فردوس رہ نورد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        سوئے فردوس رہ نورد: جنت کی طرف روانہ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The garden’s inhabitants were still mourning Shibli when Hali also became a traveler towards Paradise.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اکنوں کرا دماغ کہ پرسد زباغباں 
بلبل چہ گفت و گل چہ شنید و صبا چہ کرد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اب یہ جرات کس میں ہے کہ باغباں سے استفسار کرے کہ بلبل نے کیا کہا، گل نے کیا سنا اور صبا نے کیا عمل کیا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ‘Still he is a fool who is asking the gardener: What did nightingale say, what did rose hear, what did zephyr do?’
[Translated by Dr M A K Khalil]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>