<Poem ID="39" Name="ابوالعلامعری" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="04" SectionName="منظومات">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کہتے ہیں کبھی گوشت نہ کھاتا تھا معری 
پھل پھول پہ کرتا تھا ہمیشہ گزر اوقات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ABU AL ‘ALA AL-MA‘ARRI
It is said that Ma‘arri never ate meat; he lived on fruit and vegetables.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اک دوست نے بھونا ہوا تیتر اسے بھیجا 
شاید کہ وہ شاطر اسی ترکیب سے ہو مات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A friend sent him a roasted partridge, to allure that clever gentleman into eating meat.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ خوان تر و تازہ معری نے جو دیکھا 
کہنے لگا وہ صاحب غفران و لزومات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        رسالتہ الغفران ، معری کی ایک مشہور کتاب کا نام ہے لزومات اس کے قصائد کا مجموعہ ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When Ma‘arri saw that elegant tray he, the author of Ghufran* and Lazumat** said;
* Risalah Ghufran is a famous book of Ma‘arri.
** This is collection of his poetical works.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے مرغک بیچارہ! ذرا یہ تو بتا تو 
تیرا وہ گنہ کیا تھا یہ ہے جس کی مکافات؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ‘O You helpless little bird, would you tell me your sin for which this punishment has been awarded to you?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        افسوس، صد افسوس کہ شاہیں نہ بنا تو 
دیکھے نہ تری آنکھ نے فطرت کے اشارات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Alas, you did not become a falcon; your eye did not perceive the directives of Nature.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تقدیر کے قاضی کا یہ فتوی ہے ازل سے 
ہے جرم ضعیفی کی سزا مرگ مفاجات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It is the eternal decree of the Judge sitting in Judgement on destinies: That weakness is a crime punishable by death. 
(Translated by M. Munawwar Mirza)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>