<Poem ID="02" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="02" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ کون غزل خواں ہے پرسوز و نشاط انگیز 
اندیشہ دانا کو کرتا ہے جنوں آمیز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Who is this composer of ghazals, who is burningly passionate and cheerful? He makes the thoughts of the wise full of madness.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گو فقر بھی رکھتا ہے انداز ملوکانہ 
نا پختہ ہے پرویزی بے سلطنت پرویز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Although poverty also has royal characteristics, kingship is only half complete without a kingdom.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اب حجرہ صوفی میں وہ فقر نہیں باقی 
خون دل شیراں ہو جس فقر کی دستاویز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Now in the cell of the Sufi, the same poverty has not remained: The poverty whose charter is written in the blood of the hearts of lions.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے حلقہ درویشاں! وہ مرد خدا کیسا 
ہو جس کے گریباں میں ہنگامہ رستا خیز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Ah circle of dervishes, see how the man of God is, in whose collar is the tumult of Judgment’s Day!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جو ذکر کی گرمی سے شعلے کی طرح روشن 
جو فکر کی سرعت میں بجلی سے زیادہ تیز!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Who is as bright as a flame by the heat of repetition of God’s name; who is quicker than the lightning by the swiftness of his thought.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کرتی ہے ملوکیت آثار جنوں پیدا 
اللہ کے نشتر ہیں تیمور ہو یا چنگیز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Kingship gives rise to signs of madness: They are the scalpels of Allah, be they Taimur or Genghis.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یوں داد سخن مجھ کو دیتے ہیں عراق و پارس 
یہ کافر ہندی ہے بے تیغ و سناں خوں ریز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Thus Iraq and Persia give me praise for my verse: This Indian infidels sheds blood without swords or spears. 
(Translated by D.J. Matthews)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>