<Poem ID="13" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="01" SectionName="حصہ اول">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وہی میری کم نصیبی، وہی تیری بے نیازی 
میرے کام کچھ نہ آیا یہ کمال نے نوازی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Mine ill luck the same and same, O Lord, the coldness on Your part: No useful aim has been served, by skill in poetic art.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میں کہاں ہوں تو کہاں ہے، یہ مکاں کہ لامکاں ہے؟ 
یہ جہاں مرا جہاں ہے کہ تری کرشمہ سازی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Where am I and where are You; is the world a fact or naught? Does this world to me belong, or is a wonder by You wrought?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اسی کشمکش میں گزریں مری زندگی کی راتیں 
کبھی سوزو ساز رومی، کبھی پیچ و تاب رازی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The precious moments of my life, one by one have been snatched: But still the conflict racks my brain, if heart and head are ever matched.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وہ فریب خوردہ شاہیں کہ پلا ہو کرگسوں میں 
اسے کیا خبر کہ کیا ہے رہ و رسم شاہبازی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A hawk forgetful of its breed, upbrought and fed in midst of kites; knows not the wont and ways of hawks, and cannot soar to mighty heights.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہ زباں کوئی غزل کی، نہ زباں سے باخبر میں 
کوئی دلکشا صدا ہو، عجمی ہو یا کہ تازی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        For song no tongue is set apart, no claim to tongues is laid by me: What matters is a dainty song, no matter what its language be.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہیں فقر و سلطنت میں کوئی امتیاز ایسا 
یہ سپہ کی تیغ بازی، وہ نگہ کی تیغ بازی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Faqr and Kingship are akin; though at odds may these appear: One wins the heart with single glance, the other rules with sword and spear.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کوئی کارواں سے ٹوٹا، کوئی بدگماں حرم سے 
کہ امیر کارواں میں نہیں خوئے دل نوازی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Some have left the caravan train, and some on Ka‘bah turn their back; for leaders of the Faithful Band, winsome mode and manners lack.
(Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>