<Poem ID="38" Name="محاصرہ ادرنہ" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یورپ میں جس گھڑی حق و باطل کی چھڑ گئی 
حق خنجر آزمائی پہ مجبور ہو گیا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE SIEGE OF ADRIANOPLE
When the struggle between Truth and falsehood began in Europe; the Truth was compelled on wielding the dagger.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گرد صلیب گرد قمر حلقہ زن ہوئی 
شکری حصار درنہ میں محصور ہو گیا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The dust of the Cross circled round the Crescent; Shakree became besieged in the fortress of Adrianople.
(Shakree: He was the commander of the army of the Uthmaniyah Khilafah defending Adrianople.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مسلم سپاہیوں کے ذخیرے ہوئے تمام 
روئے امید آنکھ سے مستور ہو گیا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Provisions of Muslim soldiers became exhausted; the face of hope from the eye became concealed.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آخر امیر عسکر ترکی کے حکم سے 
'آئین جنگ' شہر کا دستور ہوگیا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        At last by the Turkish army commander’s orders ‘Martial Law’ was proclaimed the law of the city.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہر شے ہوئی ذخیرہ لشکر میں منتقل 
شاہیں گدائے دانہء عصفور ہو گیا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Everything was transferred to the army camp’s store; the eagle became beggar for the grain of the sparrow.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لیکن فقیہ شہر نے جس دم سنی یہ بات 
گرما کے مثل صاعقہ طور ہو گیا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        But when the Faqih of the city heard this news he exploded with anger like the thunderbolt of Toor.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ذمی کا مال لشکر مسلم پہ ہے حرام 
فتوی تمام شہر میں مشہور ہو گیا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ‘Dhimmi’s’ wealth is forbidden for the Muslim army’; this edict was published throughout the whole city.
(Dhimmi: This is a non-Muslim who lives in an Islamic State and pays Jizyah, which is a tax which exempts him from military service and makes the Islamic government responsible for his protection and welfare.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چھوتی نہ تھی یہود و نصاری کا مال فوج 
مسلم، خدا کے حکم سے مجبور ہوگیا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The army would not touch the Jews’ and Christians’ wealth; the Muslim became compelled by the Command of God! 
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>