<Poem ID="22" Name="خطاب بہ جوانان اسلام" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کبھی اے نوجواں مسلم! تدبر بھی کیا تو نے 
وہ کیا گردوں تھا تو جس کا ہے اک ٹوٹا ہوا تارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ADDRESSED TO THE YOUTH OF ISLAM
O Muslim youth! Have you ever used your prudence; what was that sky of which you are a fallen star?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تجھے اس قوم نے پالا ہے آغوش محبت میں 
کچل ڈالا تھا جس نے پائوں میں تاج سر دارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        That nation has nurtured you its lap of love, whose feet had trampled the crown of Dara’s head.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تمدن آفریں خلاق آئین جہاں داری 
وہ صحرائے عرب یعنی شتربانوں کا گہوارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        آفریں: تہذیب پیدا کرنے والا۔ تمدن
خلاق آئین جہاں داری: حکومت کے اصول وضع کرنے والا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Civilization’s formulator, creator of rules of world government was that desert of Arabia; that is the cradle of camel drivers.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سماں 'الفقر فخری' کا رہا شان امارت میں
بآب و رنگ و خال و خط چہ حاجت روے زیبا را
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس لیے کہ خوبصورت چہرہ رنگ ، نسل اور سامان و آرائش کا محتاج نہیں ہوتا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ‘Al Faqru fakhri’s’ state* even in glory of authority existed. ‘Why would the beautiful face need beautifying and cosmetics?’**
(This is a famous Hadith of the Holy Prophet (S.A.W). It means ‘Faqr is my pride’. It is difficult to translate Faqr correctly into English. Nevertheless its correct comprehension is necessary to understand this Hadith as well as this verse. Literally it means poverty but in Tasawwuf it is a technical term, which also is difficult to understand. **This is the second hemistich of a verse of Hafiz Shirazi which reads: The beauty of the beloved does not need our incomplete love: Why would the beautiful face beautifying and cosmetics need?)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گدائی میں بھی وہ اللہ والے تھے غیور اتنے 
کہ منعم کو گدا کے ڈر سے بخشش کا نہ تھا یارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        منعم: دولتمند۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Even in poverty those men of God were so high-minded that the rich could not avoid charity for beggar’s fear.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        غرض میں کیا کہوں تجھ سے کہ وہ صحرا نشیں کیا تھے 
جہاں گیر و جہاں دار و جہاں بان و جہاں آرا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In short what should I tell you what those wanderers in wilderness were? They were world conquerors, world rulers, world administrators, and world adorners.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اگر چاہوں تو نقشہ کھینچ کر الفاظ میں رکھ دوں 
مگر تیرے تخیل سے فزوں تر ہے وہ نظارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        فزوں تر: زیادہ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If I wish to present their picture in words I can, but that scene is beyond the comprehension of your imagination.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تجھے آبا سے اپنے کوئی نسبت ہو نہیں سکتی 
کہ تو گفتار وہ کردار، تو ثابت وہ سےارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You cannot have any relationship with your ancestors; you are talk, they were action, you are stars, they were planets.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گنوا دی ہم نے جو اسلاف سے میراث پائی تھی 
ثریا سے زمیں پر آسماں نے ہم کو دے مارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        We have wasted the heritage obtained from our ancestors. The sky has thrown us down from the Thurayyah * to the earth.
* Thurayyah called the Pleides in English and is a collection of seven stars in the constellation Taurus.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حکومت کا تو کیا رونا کہ وہ اک عارضی شے تھی 
نہیں دنیا کے آئین مسلم سے کوئی چارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Why should we cry for suzerainty, as it was temporary’ there is no escape from the world’s established principles.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مگر وہ علم کے موتی، کتابیں اپنے آبا کی 
جو دیکھیں ان کو یورپ میں تو دل ہوتا ہے سیپارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        But those pearls of wisdom, those books of our ancestors; by seeing them in Europe the heart is rent asunder.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        غنی! روز سیاہ پیر کنعاں را تماشا کن 
کہ نور دیدہ اش روشن کند چشم زلیخا را
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        غنی پیر کنعان ، یعنی حضرت یعقوب (علیہ) کے نصیب کا تماشا دیکھ؛ کہ ان کی آنکھوں کا نور (حضرت یوسف علیہ) زلیخا کی آنکھوں کو روشن کر رہا ہے۔ (یہ شعر غنی کشمیری کا ہے)
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ‘O Ghani*! Witness the dark day of the saint of Kina‘an,** because the light of his eyes brightens Zulaikhah’s eyes.
* Mullah Muhammad Tahir Ghani Kashmtri (d. 1668): He is a Persian poet of Kashmir and is considered to be high ranking. He was a Sufi and lived in Kashmir all his life, except for a short period in central India. 
** Allusion to Yusuf A.S. for whom see the Holy Qur’an, Surah 12
[Translated by M.A.K.Khalil]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>