<Poem ID="14" Name="چاند" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے چاند! حسن تیرا فطرت کی آبرو ہے 
طوف حریم خاکی تیری قدیم خو ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE MOON
O moon! Your beauty is the dignity of creation; circumambulating the earthly sanctuary is your old habit.
(Earthly Sanctuary: Metaphor for Earth.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ داغ سا جو تیرے سینے میں ہے نمایاں 
عاشق ہے تو کسی کا، یہ داغ آرزو ہے؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This something like a spot which appears on your breast: Are you someone’s Lover? Is this the Longing’s scar?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میں مضطرب زمیں پر، بے تاب تو فلک پر 
تجھ کو بھی جستجو ہے، مجھ کو بھی جستجو ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I am restless on the earth; you are impatient in the sky: You are also in search, I am also in search.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        انساں ہے شمع جس کی، محفل وہی ہے تیری؟ 
میں جس طرف رواں ہوں، منزل وہی ہے تیری؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Man is the candle of the congregation which is also yours; the direction in which I am going is also your destination.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تو ڈھونڈتا ہے جس کو تاروں کی خامشی میں 
پوشیدہ ہے وہ شاید غوغائے زندگی میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The one you are searching for in the stars’ silence; perhaps is concealed in the commotion of life.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        استادہ سرو میں ہے، سبزے میں سو رہا ہے 
بلبل میں نغمہ زن ہے، خاموش ہے کلی میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It is standing is the cypress tree, is sleeping in the verdure: Is singing in the nightingale, is silent in the flower bud!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آ ! میں تجھے دکھاوں رخسار روشن اس کا 
نہروں کے آئنے میں شبنم کی آرسی میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Come, I shall show you His luminous cheek in rivers’ mirror, in dew’s looking glass.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        صحرا و دشت و در میں، کہسار میں وہی ہے 
انساں کے دل میں، تیرے رخسار میں وہی ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In forest, in mountains in everything only He exists; In the heart of Man, in your cheek only He exists.
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>