<Poem ID="31" Name="جہان عمل" BookID="07" BookName="پیامِ مشرق" SectionID="02" SectionName="افکار">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہست این میکدہ و دعوت عام است اینجا
قسمت بادہ بہ اندازۂ جام است اینجا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE WORLD OF ACTION
This world is a free tavern, and to all who come to it wine is served in accordance with their bowl’s capacity.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حرف آن راز کہ بیگانۂ صوت است ہنوز
از لب جام چکید است و کلام است اینجا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The secret that has not yet been expressed in words has been expressed here in wine’s over-brimming character.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نشہ از حال بگیرند و گذشتند ز قال
نکتۂ فلسفہ درد تہ جام است اینجا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Those who come here get drunk with action and not with mere words. Dregs at the bottom of life’s cup is mere philosophy.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ما درین رہ نفس دھر برانداختہ ایم
آفتاب سحر او لب بام است اینجا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        We have endeavoured hard to make life take to action’s path, and now its morning’s sun is near the margin of the sky.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے کہ تو پاس غلط کردۂ خود میدارے
آنچہ پیش تو سکون است خرام است اینجا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O you who try to be consistent with your past mistakes, whatever you regard as rest is here mobility.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ما کہ اندر طلب از خانہ برون تاختہ ایم
علم را جان بدمیدیم و عمل ساختہ ایم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        We who have come out to pursue the path of seeking have converted knowledge into action and thus made it live. 
(Translated by M. Hadi Husain)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>