<Poem ID="09" Name="ذوق و شوق" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="04" SectionName="منظومات">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دریغ آمدم زاں ہمہ بوستاں 
تہی دست رفتن سوئے دوستاں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ECSTASY
Most of these Verses Were Written in Palestine.

I could not go to my friends empty-handed from an orchard! – Saadi.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        قلب و نظر کی زندگی دشت میں صبح کا سماں 
چشمہ آفتاب سے نور کی ندیاں رواں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The morning sun’s silver beams are absorbed in the sand; the eyes are bathed in radiance; the mind is lost in thought.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حسن ازل کی ہے نمود، چاک ہے پردئہ وجود 
دل کے لیے ہزار سود ایک نگاہ کا زیاں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Eternal beauty is revealed, and life’s image unveiled; the heart is softened in ravishment, the eyes are dazed by the sun.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سرخ و کبود بدلیاں چھوڑ گیا سحاب شب 
کوہ اضم کو دے گیا رنگ برنگ طیلساں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The night clouds are drifting, in scattered colours on the hill; the balmy air has bathed the trees, and the sand is soft as silk.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گرد سے پاک ہے ہوا، برگ نخیل دھل گئے 
ریگ نواح کاظمہ نرم ہے مثل پرنیاں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The rain storm has cleansed the air, leafs of date-palm tree have been washed; the sand dunes (of anger) in my heart have turned soft like silk.
(English translation by Naim Siddiqui has been in case of this verse.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آگ بجھی ہوئی ادھر، ٹوٹی ہوئی طناب ادھر 
کیا خبر اس مقام سے گزرے ہیں کتنے کارواں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Ashes of a fire and ropes of tents is all that remains behind: The only imprints that the caravans have left behind as they marched.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آئی صدائے جبرئیل، تیرا مقام ہے یہی 
اہل فراق کے لیے عیش دوام ہے یہی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I heard the angel Gabriel saying to me: This indeed is your station – for those acquainted with the pleasure of separation, this is the everlasting comfort.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کس سے کہوں کہ زہر ہے میرے لیے م ے حیات 
کہنہ ہے بزم کائنات، تازہ ہیں میرے واردات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        To whom should I say that the wine of life is poison to me: I have new experiences while the universe is decadent entire.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کیا نہیں اور غزنوی کارگہ حیات میں 
بیٹھے ہیں کب سے منتظر اہل حرم کے سومنات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The temples reared by holy men are waiting to be demolished: Is there no idol-breaker new-born; no Ghaznavi in the battlefield?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ذکر عرب کے سوز میں، فکر عجم کے ساز میں 
نے عربی مشاہدات، نے عجمی تخیلات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        There is neither Arab passion, nor Ajami refinement, in the deeds of the one, in the thought of the other.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        قافلہء حجاز میں ایک حسین بھی نہیں 
گرچہ ہے تاب دار ابھی گیسوئے دجلہ و فرات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The regions of Euphrates have waited, and waited in vain, for a martyr like Hussain, on a death-defying march.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عقل و دل و نگاہ کا مرشد اولیں ہے عشق 
عشق نہ ہو تو شرع و دیں بت کدئہ تصورات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Love is the mentor of the eye, of the heart and reason; faith without Love is a pantheon of fantasies.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        صدق خلیل بھی ہے عشق، صبر حسین بھی ہے عشق 
معرکہء وجود میں بدر و حنین بھی ہے عشق
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Love is Abraham’s faith; Love is Hussain’s endurance; Love is Badr and Hunayn, on the battlefield of life.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آیہء کائنات کا معنی دیر یاب تو 
نکلے تری تلاش میں قافلہ ہائے رنگ و بو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Of this varied world thou art the meaning long sought: Long sought by multitudes of men, from every corner of the earth.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جلوتیان مدرسہ کور نگاہ و مردہ ذوق 
خلوتیان مے کدہ کم طلب و تہی کدو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The disciples in tile schools are insipid and purblind; the esoteric few have an empty unseening soul.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="31">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میں کہ مری غزل میں ہے آتش رفتہ کا سراغ 
میری تمام سرگزشت کھوئے ہووں کی جستجو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My song seeks to recapture the flame that has been lost: To rediscover the great and noble souls of the past.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        باد صبا کی موج سے نشوونمائے خار و خس 
میرے نفس کی موج سے نشوونمائے آرزو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        As the breeze infuses life into the green earth, my fire-breathing song infuses passion into men.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="35">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خون دل و جگر سے ہے میری نوا کی پرورش 
ہے رگ ساز میں رواں صاحب ساز کا لہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It is my life-blood that nourishes my song; the harpist’s blood streams in the strings of the harp.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="37">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فرصت کشمکش مدہ ایں دل بے قرار را 
یک دو شکن زیادہ کن گیسوے تابدار را
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Let not this anxious heart of mine have a spasm to struggle; bright are Thy tresses, brighten them even more.
* The verses hereafter are devoted to the Holy Prophet (S.A.W.) and wherever the reference is made to Rasool Pak the first letter of the word is typed in capital.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="39">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لوح بھی تو، قلم بھی تو، تیرا وجود الکتاب 
گنبد آبگینہ رنگ تیرے محیط میں حباب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Thou writest my book of fate; Thou art my arbiter; the starlit dome, in its expanse, is but a bubble in Thy Sea.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="41">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عالم آب و خاک میں تیرے ظہور سے فروغ 
ذرہ ریگ کو دیا تو نے طلوع آفتاب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The myriad-coloured earth is illumined by Thee; Thou makest even a piece of sand as radiant as the sun.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="43">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شوکت سنجر و سلیم تیرے جلال کی نمود 
فقر جنید و بایزید تیرا جمال بے نقاب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The majesty of kings is but a reflection of Thy power; the sanctity of pious men is a mirror of Thy beauty.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="47">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شوق ترا اگر نہ ہو میری نماز کا امام 
میرا قیام بھی حجاب، میرا سجود بھی حجاب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If my prayer is not inspired by a love of Thee, my prayer is futile; my bowing to Thee is a pose.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="49">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تیری نگاہ ناز سے دونوں مراد پا گئے 
عقل غیاب و جستجو، عشق حضور و اضطراب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        To my reason Thou didst give the quest born of Absence, and to my love for Thee, Thy Presence and anxiety.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="51">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تیرہ و تار ہے جہاں گردش آفتاب سے 
طبع زمانہ تازہ کر جلوئہ بے حجاب سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The earth is dark, benighted; revolving round the old sun, bring the dawn of life to the earth, with Thy glimpse unveiled.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="53">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تیری نظر میں ہیں تمام میرے گزشتہ روز و شب 
مجھ کو خبر نہ تھی کہ ہے علم نخیل بے رطب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Thou knowest all about my past and my present; I had not known that knowledge is a tree without fruit.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="55">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تازہ مرے ضمیر میں معرکہء کہن ہوا 
عشق تمام مصطفی، عقل تمام بولہب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        That old battle was raged in my heart again, between love, which is all good, and reason, which is all evil.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="57">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گاہ بحیلہ می برد، گاہ بزور می کشد 
عشق کی ابتدا عجب، عشق کی انتہا عجب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Love has a strange beginning, and a strange end: It snatches by excuses sometimes, and drags by force at others.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="59">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عالم سوز و ساز میں وصل سے بڑھ کے ہے فراق 
وصل میں مرگ آرزو، ہجر میں لذت طلب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In the world of passion, Absence is greater than Presence, Absence is the pleasure of yearning, Presence is desire’s death.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="61">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عین وصال میں مجھے حوصلہء نظر نہ تھا 
گرچہ بہانہ جو رہی میری نگاہ بے ادب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In fulfilment in the past, perception I had none; though my audacious eye was looking for pretences.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="63">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گرمی آرزو فراق، شورش ہاے و ہو فراق 
موج کی جستجو فراق، قطرے کی آبرو فراق!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The wave’s enduring quest, the rain-drop’s search to be a pearl, the heart’s eternal yearning, are all before fulfilme
[Translated by Naim Siddiqui]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>