<Poem ID="31" Name="قرب سلطان" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تمیز حاکم و محکوم مٹ نہیں سکتی 
مجال کیا کہ گداگر ہو شاہ کا ہمدوش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        CLOSENESS TO KINGS
The distinction between the ruler and the ruled cannot disappear; the beggar cannot have the audacity of being equal to the king.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جہاں میں خواجہ پرستی ہے بندگی کا کمال 
رضاے خواجہ طلب کن قباے رنگیں پوش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In the world adoration of the master is the climax of devotion: ‘Seek the pleasure of the master and have the beautiful tunic’.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مگر غرض جو حصول رضائے حاکم ہو 
خطاب ملتا ہے منصب پرست و قوم فروش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        But if you aim to have the good pleasure of the ruler; you will have the title of self-seeker and anti-national.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پرانے طرز عمل میں ہزار مشکل ہے 
نئے اصول سے خالی ہے فکر کی آغوش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The old way has thousands of difficulties; in the new principle the lap is free of worries.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مزا تو یہ ہے کہ یوں زیر آسماں رہیے 
ہزار گونہ سخن در دہان و لب خاموش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The real joy comes by passing one’s life like this: ‘Thousand words in the mouth and have silent lips’.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہی اصول ہے سرمایہء سکون حیات 
گداے گوشہ نشینی تو حافظا مخروش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اے حافظ! تو دنیا ترک کر کے ایک گوشے میں پڑا ہے اس لیے تمہیں شور کرنے کی بجائے خاموش رہنا چاہئے ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This principle alone is the mainstay of peaceful existence: ‘The recluse beggar you are, O Hafiza make no clamour’.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مگر خروش پہ مائل ہے تو، تو بسم اللہ 
بگیر بادئہ صافی، ببانگ چنگ بنوش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس کے لیے شراب خالص کا حصول ضروری ہے تا کہ اس سے راگ و رنگ کی محفل میں نوش جاں کیا جا سکے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        But, if you are inclined to clamour let us begin: ‘Grasp holy wine, then drink it to the harp’s tune’. (This means drink openly)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شریک بزم امیر و وزیر و سلطاں ہو 
لڑا کے توڑ دے سنگ ہوس سے شیشہء ہوش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Join the assemblies of the rich, the minister and the king; smash to pieces conscience’ goblet with greed’s stone.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پیام مرشد شیراز بھی مگر سن لے 
کہ ہے یہ سر نہاں خانہء ضمیر سروش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        However, listen to the message of the Saint of Shiraz also that this is the secret of the conscience seller’s closet.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        محل نور تجلی ست راے انور شاہ 
چو قرب او طلبی درصفاے نیت کوش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        شاہوں کی رائے پر تجلّیوں کا نور برستا ہے، جب تو اس کے پاس بیٹھنے کا طلب گار ہو تو نیت صاف رکھنے کی کوشش کر ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ‘Light of effulgence is the king’s brilliant opinion; if you want his closeness try to have clean intention’.
[Translated by Dr M A K Khalil]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>