<Poem ID="06" Name="دوزخی کی مناجات" BookID="04" BookName="ارمغانِ حجاز" SectionID="01" SectionName="ابتدا">
  <Para>
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اس دیر کہن میں ہیں غرض مند پجاری
رنجیدہ بتوں سے ہوں تو کرتے ہیں خدا یاد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        دير کہن: پرانی دنیا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE HYMNS OF HELL DWELLER
The selfish priests live in this temple old, when grieved by idols they take the God’s fold.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پوجا بھی ہے بے سود، نمازیں بھی ہیں بے سود
قسمت ہے غریبوں کی وہی نالہ و فریاد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Their worship is vain, their prayers in vain; the poor are destined to weep in old pain.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہیں گرچہ بلندی میں عمارات فلک بوس
ہر شہر حقیقت میں ہے ویرانہء آباد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        فلک بوس: آسمان کو چھونے والی۔ 
ويرانہء آباد: ظاہر میں آباد اور حقیقت میں ویران۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In height are buildings which kiss the sky, in fact each city makes ruins by and by.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تیشے کی کوئی گردش تقدیر تو دیکھے
سیراب ہے پرویز، جگر تشنہ ہے فرہاد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        سيراب: پانی پینے والا۔ 
جگر تشنہ: جگر سے پیاسا، انتہائی پیاسا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Let some one ponder the fate of axe yet, Pervez well watered, the beau thirsty yet.
[Pervez: King of Persia (known in amatory legend of Shirin and Farhad on whose behest Farhad dug the canal with his axe. Thus the beau is Farhad, who could not yet win the hand of his lady love.]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ علم، یہ حکمت، یہ سیاست، یہ تجارت
جو کچھ ہے، وہ ہے فکر ملوکانہ کی ایجاد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        فکر ملوکانہ: بادشاہ کی سوچ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This knowledge, this science, statecraft and trade; for kingship alone these games were made.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اللہ! ترا شکر کہ یہ خطہ پر سوز
سوداگر یورپ کی غلامی سے ہے آزاد!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I thank thee O God! That this radiant tract; of bondage of West has no signs in fact.
[Translated by Q A Kabir]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>