<Poem ID="09" Name="" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="1b" SectionName="غزلیات 1">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جنھیں میں ڈھونڈتا تھا آسمانوں میں زمینوں میں
وہ نکلے میرے ظلمت خانہ دل کے مکینوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The one I was searching for on the earth and in heaven appeared residing in the recesses of my own heart.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حقیقت اپنی آنکھوں پر نمایاں جب ہوئی اپنی
مکاں نکلا ہمارے خانہ دل کے مکینوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When the reality of the self became evident to my eyes; the house appeared among residents of my own heart.
(The word ‘house’ represents the abode of God and it really exists in the human heart of His true Lover. The human heart is so represented in tasawwuf literature.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اگر کچھ آشنا ہوتا مذاق جبہہ سائی سے
تو سنگ آستاں کعبہ جا ملتا جبینوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If it were somewhat familiar with taste of rubbing foreheads, the stone of Ka‘bah’s threshold would have joined the foreheads.
(The pleasure of earnest beseeching before God in prostration is so great that if the stone of the threshold of the Ka’bah was aware of that pleasure it would have preferred to be the forehead itself, and participate in such a prostration than be merely the stone towards which such prostrations are performed.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کبھی اپنا بھی نظارہ کیا ہے تو نے اے مجنوں
کہ لیلی کی طرح تو خود بھی ہے محمل نشینوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O Majnun! Have you ever glanced at yourself that like Lailah* you are also sitting in the litter.
(If the Lover realizes his own self, i.e. develops his own Khudi or self, the difference between the Lover and the Beloved would disappear. This amounts to the concept of Fana Fi Allah of Wahdat al-Wujood. This verse is one of the verses which indicate ‘Allamah Iqbal’s inclination towards Wahdat al-Wujood in early life.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مہینے وصل کے گھڑیوں کی صورت اڑتے جاتے ہیں
مگر گھڑیاں جدائی کی گزرتی ہیں مہینوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The months of the union continue flying like moments, but the moments of separation linger for months!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مجھے روکے گا تو اے ناخدا کیا غرق ہونے سے
کہ جن کو ڈوبنا ہو، ڈوب جاتے ہیں سفینوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O seaman, how will you protect me from being drowned as those destined to drowning get drowned in the boats also.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چھپایا حسن کو اپنے کلیم اللہ سے جس نے
وہی ناز آفریں ہے جلوہ پیرا نازنینوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The one who concealed His Beauty from Kalim Allah, the same Beloved is manifest among beloveds. 
(God exists everywhere if His Lover has developed his insight enough to see Him.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جلا سکتی ہے شمع کشتہ کو موج نفس ان کی
الہی! کیا چھپا ہوتا ہے اہل دل کے سینوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The breath of Lovers can light up the extinguished candle; O God! What is kept concealed in the breast of the Lovers? 
(The power of God is Supreme.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تمنا درد دل کی ہو تو کر خدمت فقیروں کی
نہیں ملتا یہ گوہر بادشاہوں کے خزینوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Serve the faqirs if you have the longing for Love; this pearl is not available in the treasures of kings.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہ پوچھ ان خرقہ پوشوں کی، ارادت ہو تو دیکھ ان کو
ید بیضا لیے بیٹھے ہیں اپنی آستینوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Do not ask of these Devotees, if you have faith, you should look at them; they have the illuminated palm up their sleeves.
(This and the following verse describe the unlimited power of the Lover of God.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ترستی ہے نگاہ نا رسا جس کے نظارے کو
وہ رونق انجمن کی ہے انھی خلوت گزینوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The unsightful eye for whose spectacle is tantalized; that elegance of congregation is in these very recluses.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کسی ایسے شرر سے پھونک اپنے خرمن دل کو
کہ خورشید قیامت بھی ہو تیرے خوشہ چینوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Burn the produce of your heart with some such spark that the Last Day’s sun may also be among your gleaners.
(The sun of the Last Day is proverbial for its torturing heat. However, the power of the true Love of God is such that even that sun will come down to collect flowers from the Lover’s heap.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        محبت کے لیے دل ڈھونڈ کوئی ٹوٹنے والا
یہ وہ مے ہے جسے رکھتے ہیں نازک آبگینوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        For Love search for some heart which would become mortified; this is the wine which is not kept in delicate wine glasses.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سراپا حسن بن جاتا ہے جس کے حسن کا عاشق
بھلا اے دل حسیں ایسا بھی ہے کوئی حسینوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Beauty itself becomes the Lover of whose Beauty O Heart! Does someone among the beautiful has that beauty?
(The universal Beauty of God itself becomes the Lover of a true Lover of God.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="229">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پھڑک اٹھا کوئی تیری ادائے 'ما عرفنا' پر
ترا رتبہ رہا بڑھ چڑھ کے سب ناز آفرینوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Someone became highly excited at your grace of ‘Ma ‘arafna’; your rank remained among the most elegant of all the Lovers.*
* Allusion to the Holy Qur’an 5:83 (with slight change), the perusal of which will clarify the meaning of this verse.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="31">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نمایاں ہو کے دکھلا دے کبھی ان کو جمال اپنا
بہت مدت سے چرچے ہیں ترے باریک بینوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Manifest Thyself and show them Thy Beauty some time; talks have continued among the sagacious since long time.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خموش اے دل!، بھری محفل میں چلانا نہیں اچھا
ادب پہلا قرینہ ہے محبت کے قرینوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Silent, O Heart! Crying in the full assembly is not good; decorum is the most important etiquette among the ways of Love.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="35">
      <Text Language="Original">
        برا سمجھوں انھیں مجھ سے تو ایسا ہو نہیں سکتا
کہ میں خود بھی تو ہوں اقبال اپنے نکتہ چینوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It is not possible for me to deem my critics bad, because Iqbal, I am myself among my critics.
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>