<Poem ID="04" Name="مرزا غالب" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="1a" SectionName="حصہ اول">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فکر انساں پر تری ہستی سے یہ روشن ہوا
ہے پر مرغ تخیل کی رسائی تا کجا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Through you the secret was revealed to the human intellect that innumerable enigmas are solved by human intellect.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تھا سراپا روح تو، بزم سخن پیکر ترا
زیب محفل بھی رہا محفل سے پنہاں بھی رہا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You were the complete soul; literary assembly was your body. You adorned as well as remained veiled from the assembly.
(This is an allusion to the lack of recognition of Ghalib's genius at the court of Bahadur Shah, the last Mughal Emperor of India. It also means that, though you adorned the literary assemblies and were bodily visible, your real self could not be seen except by those with insight.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دید تیری آنکھ کو اس حسن کی منظور ہے
بن کے سوز زندگی ہر شے میں جو مستور ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your eye is longing to witness that veiled Beauty which is veiled in everything as the pathos of life.
(This refers to the Sufi concept of Wahdat al-Wujood according to which everything in the universe is God in different forms.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        محفل ہستی تری بربط سے ہے سرمایہ دار
جس طرح ندی کے نغموں سے سکوت کوہسار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The assemblage of existence is rich with your harp as mountain's silence by the brook's melodious harp.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تیرے فردوس تخیل سے ہے قدرت کی بہار
تیری کشت فکر سے اگتے ہیں عالم سبزہ وار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The garden of your imagination bestows glory on the universe from the field of your thought worlds grow like meadows.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زندگی مضمر ہے تیری شوخی تحریر میں
تاب گویائی سے جنبش ہے لب تصویر میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Life is concealed in the humour of your verse picture's lips move with your command of language.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نطق کو سو ناز ہیں تیرے لب اعجاز پر
محو حیرت ہے ثریا رفعت پرواز پر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Speech is very proud of the elegance of your miraculous lips; Thurayyah is astonished at your style's elegance.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شاہد مضموں تصدق ہے ترے انداز پر
خندہ زن ہے غنچہ دلی گل شیراز پر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Beloved of literature itself loves your style: Delhi's bud is mocking at the rose of Shiraz.
(This is an allusion to Muhammad Shams al-Din Hafiz, who was an eminent Persian poet of Iran and lived in Shiraz.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آہ! تو اجڑی ہوئی دلی میں آرامیدہ ہے
گلشن ویمر میں تیرا ہم نوا خوابیدہ ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Ah! You are resting in the midst of Delhi’s ruins; your counterpart is resting in the Weimar's* garden.
* German poet Goethe who is buried in Weimar, Germany.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لطف گویائی میں تیری ہمسری ممکن نہیں
ہو تخیل کا نہ جب تک فکر کامل ہم نشیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Matching you in literary elegance is not possible till maturity of thought and imagination are combined.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہائے! اب کیا ہو گئی ہندوستاں کی سر زمیں
آہ! اے نظارہ آموز نگاہ نکتہ بیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Ah! What has befallen the land of India! Ah! The inspirer of the super-critical eye!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گیسوئے اردو ابھی منت پذیر شانہ ہے
شمع یہ سودائی دل سوزی پروانہ ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The lock of Urdu's hair still craves for combing this candle still craves for moth's heart-felt pathos.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے جہان آباد، اے گہوارہ علم و ہنر
ہیں سراپا نالہ خاموش تیرے بام و در
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O Jahanabad*! O cradle of learning and art your entire super-structure is a silent lament.
* Abbreviation for Shahjahanabad, which is the original name of Delhi after its construction under the Mughal Emperor Shahjahan.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="31">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ذرے ذرے میں ترے خوابیدہ ہیں شمں و قمر
یوں تو پوشیدہ ہیں تیری خاک میں لاکھوں گہر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The sun and the moon are asleep in every speck of your dust; though innumerable other gems are also hidden in your dust.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دفن تجھ میں کوئی فخر روزگار ایسا بھی ہے؟
تجھ میں پنہاں کوئی موتی آبدار ایسا بھی ہے؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Does another world-famous person like him also lie buried in you? Does another gem like him also lie concealed in you?
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>