<Poem ID="02" Name="ستارہ" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        قمر کا خوف کہ ہے خطرہء سحر تجھ کو 
مآل حسن کی کیا مل گئی خبر تجھ کو؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Are you afraid of the moon or the dawn? Are you conscious of the end of beauty?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        متاع نور کے لٹ جانے کا ہے ڈر تجھ کو 
ہے کیا ہراس فنا صورت شرر تجھ کو؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Are you afraid of being robbed of light’s wealth? Are you afraid of annihilation like the spark?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زمیں سے دور دیا آسماں نے گھر تجھ کو 
مثال ماہ اڑھائی قبائے زر تجھ کو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The sky has settled you far from the earth; it has wrapped you in gold’s mantle like the moon.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        غضب ہے پھر تری ننھی سی جان ڈرتی ہے! 
تمام رات تری کانپتے گزرتی ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It is outrageous that your feeble life is still in fear; your whole night passes in trembling with fear.
* The reply to the questions in the first three verses is obviously in the negative. In that case the fourth verse expresses surprise at the conditions stated in it. The amazement is satisfied in the last four verses according to which all creation, irrespective of its beauty and station in the universe is ephemeral and is destined to die or be annihilated.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چمکنے والے مسافر! عجب یہ بستی ہے 
جو اوج ایک کا ہے، دوسرے کی پستی ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O shining traveler! This habitation is strange; the rise of one leads to the fall of the other.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اجل ہے لاکھوں ستاروں کی اک ولادت مہر 
فنا کی نیند مے زندگی کی مستی ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The birth of one sun is the death of a myriad stars; annihilation’s sleep is the ecstasy of life’s wine.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وداع غنچہ میں ہے راز آفرینش گل 
عدم، عدم ہے کہ آئینہ دار ہستی ہے!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Flower bud’s departure is the secret of flower’s birth. Is annihilation life’s end, or is the equivalent of life!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سکوں محال ہے قدرت کے کارخانے میں 
ثبات ایک تغیر کو ہے زمانے میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Quiescence is difficult in the universe; only change is permanent in the universe.
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>