<Poem ID="05" Name="نمود صبح" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہو رہی ہے زیر دامان افق سے آشکار 
صبح یعنی دختر دوشیزہ لیل و نہار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        MORNING’S APPEARANCE
From under the horizon’s skirt is appearing; the day and night’s virgin daughter that is dawn.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پا چکا فرصت درود فصل انجم سے سپہر 
کشت خاور میں ہوا ہے آفتاب آئینہ کار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The sky has completed benedictions for the star’s crop. The sun has decorated the eastern horizon with mirrors.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آسماں نے آمد خورشید کی پا کر خبر 
محمل پرواز شب باندھا سر دوش غبار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The sky, getting news of the arrival of the sun has packed up night’s litter on dust-cloud’s shoulders.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شعلہء خورشید گویا حاصل اس کھیتی کا ہے 
بوئے تھے دہقان گردوں نے جو تاروں کے شرار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The sun’s flame seems to be the produce of this field which was sown by sky’s farmer as sparks of stars.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے رواں نجم سحر، جیسے عبادت خانے سے 
سب سے پیچھے جائے کوئی عابد شب زندہ دار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The morning star is on the way from the sky retrieving as the last nightly worshiper from the mosque be retrieving.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کیا سماں ہے جس طرح آہستہ آہستہ کوئی 
کھینچتا ہو میان کی ظلمت سے تیغ آب دار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What a beautiful sight it is as somebody slowly draws the bright sword from the sheath’s darkness.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مطلع خورشید میں مضمر ہے یوں مضمون صبح 
جیسے خلوت گاہ مینا میں شراب خوش گوار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The dawn’s meaning in the eastern horizon is hidden aas inside the goblet the pleasant wine is hidden.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے تہ دامان باد اختلاط انگیز صبح 
شورش ناقوس، آواز اذاں سے ہمکنار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The dawn is under the skirt of the friendly breeze; the noise of the conchis mixed with the call of adhan.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جاگے کوئل کی اذاں سے طائران نغمہ سنج 
ہے ترنم ریز قانون سحر کا تار تار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        All the singing birds woke up by the cuckoo’s call; every string of dawn’s system has become musical.
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>