<Poem ID="48" Name="غزل" BookID="03" BookName="ضربِ کلیم" SectionID="01" SectionName="اسلام اور مسلمان">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تیری متاع حیات، علم و ہنر کا سرور 
میری متاع حیات ایک دل ناصبور!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        دل ناصبور: بیقرار دل۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A restless aching heart that throbs with Love; is my life's only stock and hoard your joys of life consist of wealth and gold that worldly Science and Arts to you afford.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        معجزہ اہل فکر، فلسفہء پیچ پیچ 
معجزہ اہل ذکر، موسی و فرعون و طور
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The marvel wrought by thinkers wise and sage consists of problems stiff that thought provoke: Mount Sinai, Pharoah's rout and Moses' Staff are miracles worked by those who God invoke.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مصلحتاً کہہ دیا میں نے مسلماں تجھے 
تیرے نفس میں نہیں، گرمی یوم النشور
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        یوم النشور: قیامت کا دن۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I have conferred a Muslim's name on you for sake of courtesy, custom and routine though your breath is quite bereft of heat of Reckoning Day that shall emit blazing sheen.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ایک زمانے سے ہے چاک گریباں مرا 
تو ہے ابھی ہوش میں، میرے جنوں کا قصور
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My vest is torn to shreds and pieces since long and this is due to my mind's frenzy great; your mind is still intact and sound, wherefore impute the blame to me and slate?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فیض نظر کے لیے ضبط سخن چاہیے 
حرف پریشاں نہ کہہ اہل نظر کے حضور
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You ought to keep your words within control, if you seek the bounteous glance of Guide: When you talk with those who insight own be courteous much, by conduct nice abide.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خوار جہاں میں کبھی ہو نہیں سکتی وہ قوم 
عشق ہو جس کا جسور، فقر ہو جس کا غیور
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جسور: بیباک، جراتمند۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        That nation cannot come to shame at all, nor shall e'er come across or face disgrace, whose youth are blessed with. pluck and courage great, and guard with zeal the prestige of their race. 
(Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>