<Poem ID="02" Name="بڈھے بلوچ کی نصیحت بیٹے کو" BookID="04" BookName="ارمغانِ حجاز" SectionID="01" SectionName="ابتدا">
  <Para>
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہو تیرے بیاباں کی ہوا تجھ کو گوارا
اس دشت سے بہتر ہے نہ دلی نہ بخارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        AN ADVICE OF OLD BALUCH TO HIS SON
I pray desert breeze would harmonize thee, to desert tops not, Delhi Basra’s glee.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جس سمت میں چاہے صفت سیل رواں چل
وادی یہ ہماری ہے، وہ صحرا بھی ہمارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Like a moving gale, move any where, this desert and dales would hail thee there.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        غیرت ہے بڑی چیز جہان تگ و دو میں
پہناتی ہے درویش کو تاج سر دارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In tug and pull’s race envy is a grace, which puts Darius1 crown on poor man’s face.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حاصل کسی کامل سے یہ پوشیدہ ہنر کر
کہتے ہیں کہ شیشے کو بنا سکتے ہیں خارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        خارا: سخت پتھر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Get this hid skill from a paragon* lone, it is said that glass can be turned to stone.
* A model of excellence.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        افراد کے ہاتھوں میں ہے اقوام کی تقدیر
ہر فرد ہے ملت کے مقدر کا ستارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In each man’s hand lies the nation’s fate, each man is a star of nation’s great.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        محروم رہا دولت دریا سے وہ غواص
کرتا نہیں جو صحبت ساحل سے کنارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        غواص: غوطہ خور۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        That diver was robbed of wealth of sea, who was afraid to leave the shore with glee.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دیں ہاتھ سے دے کر اگر آزاد ہو ملت
ہے ایسی تجارت میں مسلماں کا خسارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If his freedom hangs on the faith’s bargain, in such a bargain he stands not to gain.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دنیا کو ہے پھر معرکۂ روح و بدن پیش
تہذیب نے پھر اپنے درندوں کو ابھارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The soul and body yet face a clash; this culture has made her wild beasts rash.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اللہ کو پامردی مومن پہ بھروسا
ابلیس کو یورپ کی مشینوں کا سہارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Allah has faith in Momin’s might and will, on Europe’s hardware Satan makes his skill.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تقدیر امم کیا ہے، کوئی کہہ نہیں سکتا
مومن کی فراست ہو تو کافی ہے اشارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        On the fate of nations none can’t foretell, on the Momin’s shrewd look you can always dwell.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اخلص عمل مانگ نیا گان کہن سے
شاہاں چہ عجب گر بنوازند گدا را!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کیا عجب کہ بادشاہ بھکاری کو نواز دیں۔ 
قدیم زمانے کے بزرگ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A selfless life learn from foremost in deen, the kings may favour a man of poor means. 
(Translated by Q A Kabir)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>