<Poem ID="05" Name="حکمت فرعونی" BookID="10" BookName="پس چہ بائد کرد" SectionID="01" SectionName="پس چہ بائد کرد">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حکمت ارباب دین کردم عیان
حکمت ارباب کین را ہم بدان
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میں نے اہل ایمان کی حکمت ظاہر کی ہے اب کینہ دوز (فرعونوں) کی حکمت بھی سمجھ لے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE WISDOM OF THE PHARAOHS
I have unfolded the wisdom of the people of faith; now learn the wisdom of the people of malice.
(People of malice, as distinguished from the people of faith, who pass their days totally divorced from the spiritual reality of life and are therefore involved only in material welfare, regard moral values absolutely irrelevant. The result is total moral anarchy in social life. Iqbal employs this contrast in several contexts.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حکمت ارباب کین مکر است و فن
مکر و فن تخریب جان، تعمیر تن
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        فرعونوں کی ڈپلومیسی مکر و فن ہے، یعنی وہ روح کو بگاڑتے اور تن کو سنوارتے ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The wisdom of the people of malice is deceit and artifice; what are deceit and artifice? They destroy the soul and build the body.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حکمتی از بند دین آزادہ ئی
از مقام شوق دور افتادہ ئی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ان کی پالیسی دین سے آزاد اور مقام شوق و محبت سے دور ہوتی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This is wisdom that has freed itself from faith’s bonds and has strayed far away from the station of Love.
(Station of love (maqam-i shauq) is loyalty to the spiritual values of life.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مکتب از تدبیر او گیرد نظام
تا بکام خواجہ اندیشد غلام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ان کی تدبیر سے ایسا نظام تعلیم جاری کیا جاتا ہے، جس سے تعلیم یافتہ نوجوانوں کی سوچ اپنے آقاؤں کے مفاد کے مطابق ہو جائے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The school follows in his (Pharaoh’s) ways so that the servant learns to think in line with the master’s desires.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شیخ ملت با حدیث دلنشین
بر مراد او کند تجدید دین
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        علمائے (سوء) دلنشین حدیثیں سنا کر اپنے آقاؤں کے مطابق دین کی تجدید کرتے ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The religious leader of the millat, in a charming way, reinterprets religion to his (Pharaoh’s) liking.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        از دم او وحدت قومی دو نیم
کس حریفش نیست جز چوب کلیم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        حکمت فرعونی کے فسوں سے قوم کی وحدت ٹکڑے ٹکڑے ہو جاتی ہے؛ عصائے موسی (علیہ) کے علاوہ اس کا کوئی علاج نہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The unity of the people is sundered through his machinations; nothing can withstand him except Moses’ Staff.
(Moses’ Staff is a reference to events in the life-history of Moses, where his staff helped him overcome the crises, first in combating the deceit of the magicians and then in crossing the river when pursued by Pharaoh and his hosts... Moses’ Staff, in Iqbal, therefore, stands for power, might, without acquiring which the people of the exploited societies cannot hope to meet successfully the challenge of the West, both political and economic.’
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        واے قومی کشتۂ تدبیر غیر
کار او تخریب خود تعمیر غیر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        افسوس اس قوم پر جو غیروں کی ڈپلومیسی کا شکار ہو کر اپنی تخریب کرے اور دوسروں کی تعمیر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Woe to a people that, prey to others’ stratagems, destroy themselves and build up others.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        می شود در علم و فن صاحب نظر
از وجود خود نگردد با خبر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        وہ علم اور آرٹ میں تو صاحب نظر ہو جائے مگر اپنے آپ سے غافل رہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        They gain knowledge of science and art, but remain unaware of their own self-identity.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نقش حق را از نگین خود سترد
در ضمیرش آرزوہا زاد و مرد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اپنی آنگوٹھی کے نگینہ سے اللہ تعالے کا نقش مٹا دے اس کے ضمیر میں آرزوئیں پیدا ہوتی اور مرتی ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        They erase the Lord’s impress from their signet; aspirations arise in their heart only to die away.
(Lord’s impress, naqsh-i Haqq, God’s image. It stands for voluntary submission to God’s Will)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بے نصیب آمد ز اولاد غیور
جان بتن چون مردہ ئی در خاک گور
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        وہ غیرتمند اولاد سے بے نصیب رہے، اس کے بدن میں جان ایسے ہو جیسے قبر میں مردہ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        They are not blessed with a progeny imbued with a sense of honour; their children have souls in their bodies like corpses in graves.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        از حیا بیگانہ پیران کہن
نوجوانان چون زنان مشغول تن
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس کے بوڑھے حیا سے خالی ہوں اور نوجوان عورتوں کی طرح اپنے بدن کی آرائش میں مشغول رہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Their old people lack modesty; the young are busy decking themselves out like women-folk.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        در دل شان آرزوہا بی ثبات
مردہ زایند از بطون امہات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ان نوجوانوں کی آرزوؤں میں ثبات نہیں (کبھی کچھ سوچتے ہیں، کبھی کچھ) وہ اپنی ماؤں کے پیٹ ہی سے مردہ پیدا ہوتے ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The desires that spring from their hearts are unstable; they are born dead from the wombs of their mothers.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دختران او بزلف خود اسیر
شوخ چشم و خود نما و خردہ گیر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ایسی قوم کی لڑائیاں اپنی زلف میں اسیر ، شوخ چشم، خود نما اور دوسروں کی سوچ سے متاثر ہوتی ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Their daughters are caught in the snares of their curling locks, bold-eyed, fond of display and carping;
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ساختہ پرداختہ دل باختہ
ابروان مثل دو تیغ آختہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        وہ آرائش ، زیبائش اور دل بختگی کی شوقین ہوتی ہیں، ان کے ابرو یوں ہوتے ہیں جیسے دو کھینچی ہوئی تلواریں ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Well-dressed, with exquisite make-up, coquettish; their eyebrows like two unsheathed swords;
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ساعد سیمین شان عیش نظر
سینۂ ماہی بموج اندر نگر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ان کے چاندی جیسے سفید بازو نظر کے لیے عیش (کا سامان مہیا کرتے) ہیں (انہیں دیکھنا یوں ہے) جیسے کوئی موج (آب) کے اندر مچھلی کا سینہ دیکھے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Their white silvery forearms pleasing to the eyes; their bosoms showing like fish in water.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="31">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ملتی خاکستر او بی شرر
صبح او از شام او تاریکتر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        یہ ایسی قوم ہے جس کی راکھ میں کوئی چنگاری باقی نہیں، اس کی صبح اس کی شام سے بھی زیادہ تاریک ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A nation whose ashes are devoid of any live spark, whose morn is darker than its eve.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہر زمان اندر تلاش ساز و برگ
کار او فکر معاش و ترس مرگ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        وہ ہر دم روپے پیسے کی تلاش میں رہتی ہے، اس کا کام معاش کی فکر اور موت سے ڈرنا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It is always in search of material goods, its only preoccupation is anxiety for livelihood and fear of death.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="35">
      <Text Language="Original">
        منعمان او بخیل و عیش دوست
غافل از مغزاند و اندر بند پوست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس کے دولتمند بخیل اور عیش پرست ہوتے ہیں، وہ (رسوم کے) چھلکے میں گرفتار اور ( حقیقت کے) مغز سے غافل ہوتے ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Its rich are miserly, pleasure-loving, intent upon seeking the shell, and neglectful of the kernel.
(Kernel and shell: The distinction of what is visible, what appears to the eye, the apparent, the external and what is real, the hidden, the essence, is very much relevant in moral evaluation of one’s behaviour. Rumi has discussed this problem in hundred different contexts in which he tries to bring home to the people the value of the kernel in contrast to the shell, the intention behind one’s action rather than the action as it appears to our eyes.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="37">
      <Text Language="Original">
        قوت فرمانروا معبود او
در زیان دین و ایمان سود او
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        حکمران کی قوّت ان کی معبود ہے، وہ دین و ایمان کے نقصان میں اپنا فائدہ دیکھتے ہیں (دینوی فائدہ کی خاطر دین و ایمان بیچ دیتے ہیں)۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The might of its ruler is the object of its adoration, in loss of faith and belief lies its gain.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="39">
      <Text Language="Original">
        از حد امروز خود بیرون نجست
روزگارش نقش یک فردا نبست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ایسی قوم 'آج' (فوری مفاد) کی حد سے باہر نہیں نکلتی؛ اس کی زندگی میں ایک کل کا نقش بھی ثبت نہیں ہوتا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It never looks beyond its today and never creates a tomorrow for itself.
(Iqbal thinks that a true leader is one who produces dissatisfaction among the people about the present and urges them on to a brighter and better future.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="41">
      <Text Language="Original">
        از نیاکان دفتری اندر بغل
الامان از گفتہ ہای بے عمل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        وہ اپنے آباء (کے کارناموں ) کا دفتر بغل میں دبائے پھرتی ہے، مگر اس کے پاس باتیں ہی باتیں ہیں عمل کوئی نہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It has the annals of its ancestors under its arms, but, alas! It only discourses on them without acting on them.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="43">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دین او عہد وفا بستن بغیر
یعنی از خشت حرم تعمیر دیر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس کا دین غیروں سے عہد وفا باندھنا ہے، وہ گویا حرم ( کو گرا کر اس) کی اینٹوں سے بت کدہ تعمیر کرتی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Its creed is to offer loyalty to others, to build temples with the material of the mosque.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="45">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آہ قومی دل ز حق پرداختہ
مرد و مرگ خویش را نشناختہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        افسوس اس قوم پر جس نے اللہ تعالے سے دل ہٹا لیا، جو مر چکی ہے، مگر اپنی موت کو پہچانتی نہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Alas! For a nation which has cut itself adrift from God, which is dead, but does not know that it is dead.
(Translated by Jamil Naqvi)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>