<Poem ID="24" Name="سسلي جزيرہ صقليہ" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="2a" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رو لے اب دل کھول کر اے دیدہء خوننابہ بار
وہ نظر آتا ہے تہذیب حجازی کا مزار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        خوننابہ بار: خون برسانے والی، لہو رونے والی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE ISLAND OF SICILY
O blood-dripping eye! Now cry to your heart's content; there you can see the mausoleum of the civilization of Hijaz.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تھا یہاں ہنگامہ ان صحرا نشینوں کا کبھی
بحر بازی گاہ تھا جن کے سفینوں کا کبھی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This was the rendezvous of those Arab Bedouins once; the ocean was the play ground of whose boats once.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زلزلے جن سے شہنشاہوں کے درباروں میں تھے
بجلیوں کے آشیانے جن کی تلواروں میں تھے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Who shook up the audience halls of emperors; thunderbolts were harboured in whose swords.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اک جہان تازہ کا پیغام تھا جن کا ظہور
کھا گئی عصر کہن کو جن کی تیغ ناصبور
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        عصر کہن: پرانا زمانہ۔
تيغ ناصبور: بے صبر تلوار۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Whose appearance was the message of birth of a new world; whose restless sword destroyed the whole ancient world?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مردہ عالم زندہ جن کی شورش قم سے ہوا
آدمی آزاد زنجیر توہم سے ہوا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The dead world with whose ‘Qum’ was infused with life. Man was freed from the chains of superstitious beliefs.
(Qum: This is an allusion to the miracle of Issa A.S. by which he could bring the dead to life with the permission of God. The first line of this verse means that just as Issa A.S. brought the dead to life the Muslim civilization brought the Europe's dark ages to new life. It is also a reference to the re birth of Europe under the influence of the Islamic civilization of Spain and Baghdad.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        غلغلوں سے جس کے لذت گیر اب تک گوش ہے
کیا وہ تکبیر اب ہمیشہ کے لیے خاموش ہے؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The ear is still full of pleasures from whose zeal is that Takbâr now silenced for ever?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آہ اے سسلی! سمندرکی ہے تجھ سے آبرو
رہنما کی طرح اس پانی کے صحرا میں ہے تو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Ah! O Sicily! You are giving dignity to the ocean; you are like a guide post in the water's expanse.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زیب تیرے خال سے رخسار دریا کو رہے
تیری شمعوں سے تسلی بحر پیما کو رہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        بحر پيما: سمندر ناپنے والا یعنی سمندر کا سفر کرنے والا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        May the ocean's cheek ever remain elegant with your mole! May your lights ever remain a comfort for the ocean sailor!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہو سبک چشم مسافر پر ترا منظر مدام
موج رقصاں تیرے ساحل کی چٹانوں پر مدام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ہمیشہ۔	:مدام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        May your sight ever remain beautiful to traveler’s eyes! May the wave on your shore's rocks ever remain dancing!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تو کبھی اس قوم کی تہذیب کا گہوارہ تھا
حسن عالم سوز جس کا آتش نظارہ تھا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You were the cradle of that nation's civilization once, whose universal beauty was the object for spectacle.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نالہ کش شیراز کا بلبل ہوا بغداد پر
داغ رویا خون کے آنسو جہاں آباد پر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        نالہ کش: نوحہ کرنے والا۔ 
شيراز کا بلبل: مراد ہے سعدی شیرازی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Nightingale of Shiraz was the lamentor on Baghdad; Dagh shed the tears of blood on Jahanabad.
(The Nightingale of Shiraz: This is the honorific title of Sheikh Musleh al-Din Sa’adi of Shiraz. This hemistich alludes to Sheikh Sa’adi’s elegy on the destruction, pillage, mass murders and unprecedented atrocities at the hands of Halaku Khan at the time of invasion of the Tartars on Baghdad in 1258. Baghdad was the capital of the Abbasid Khilafah headed by al-Musta‘a-Åam Billah. Sheikh Sa’adi wrote two allegies, one in Persian and the other in Arabic, of which the first is very famous… Dagh: The Urdu poet Nawab Mirza Khan Dagh. Jahanabad: This is an abbreviation for ‘Shahjahanabad’ which was the name given to Delhi by the Mughal Emperor Shahjahan after rebuilding it. The allusion refers to the allegy of Dagh on the destruction of Delhi at the time of the First War of Indian Independence in 1857.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آسماں نے دولت غرناطہ جب برباد کی
ابن بدروں کے دل ناشاد نے فریاد کی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When the sky destroyed the State of Gharnatah; the unhappy heart of Ibn Badrën lamented.
(Gharnatah: The Arabic name for the Kingdom of Grenada, established in the southern part of Spain about 1160 and destroyed in 1492, which removed the last vestiges of Muslims from Spain. Ibn Badrën: Abu al Qasim Abd al Malik Ibn Abd Allah Ibn Badrën, the Muslim who had chronicled the history of Muslim rulers of Spain. His book was similar to Firdawsi's ‘Shah Namah’ in Persian and ‘Shah Namah-i-Islam’ by Hafiz Jalandhari.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        غم نصیب اقبال کو بخشا گیا ماتم ترا
چن لیا تقدیر نے وہ دل کہ تھا محرم ترا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The ill fated Iqbal has been conferred mourning for you. Destiny has selected the heart that was your confidante.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے ترے آثار میں پوشیدہ کس کی داستاں
تیرے ساحل کی خموشی میں ہے انداز بیاں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        آثار: کھنڈر، پرانی عمارتوں کے نشان۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Whose story is concealed in your relics? In your shore's silence is a style of speech.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        درد اپنا مجھ سے کہہ، میں بھی سراپا درد ہوں
جس کی تو منزل تھا، میں اس کارواں کی گرد ہوں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Tell me your pathos, I am also embodiment of pathos; I am the dust of the caravan of which you were a stage.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="31">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رنگ تصویر کہن میں بھر کے دکھلا دے مجھے
قصہ ایام سلف کا کہہ کے تڑپا دے مجھے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Show me the old picture painted again; make me restless by relating the tale of bygone days.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میں ترا تحفہ سوئے ہندوستاں لے جاوں گا
خود یہاں روتا ہوں، اوروں کو وہاں رلوائوں گا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I will take your gift towards India; I myself weep here, and will make others weep there.
[Translated by Dr M A K Khalil]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>