<Poem ID="40" Name="ایک مکالمہ" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اک مرغ سرا نے یہ کہا مرغ ہوا سے 
پردار اگر تو ہے تو کیا میں نہیں پردار!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مرغ ہوا: آزاد پرندہ۔
مرغ سرا: پالتو پرندہ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A DIALOGUE
A domesticated bird once said to the wild bird: ‘If you have wings, do not I also have wings?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گر تو ہے ہوا گیر تو ہوں میں بھی ہوا گیر 
آزاد اگر تو ہے، نہیں میں بھی گرفتار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If you are air-borne, I am also air-borne. If you are free I am also not a prisoner.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پرواز، خصوصیت ہر صاحب پر ہے 
کیوں رہتے ہیں مرغان ہوا مائل پندار؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مائل پندار: مغرور۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        All winged creatures are characterized by flight: Why then are wild birds inclined to be arrogant!’
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مجروح حمیت جو ہوئی مرغ ہوا کی 
یوں کہنے لگا سن کے یہ گفتار دل آزار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        As the wild bird’s self-respect became wounded; he spoke thus on hearing this heart-rending talk:
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کچھ شک نہیں پرواز میں آزاد ہے تو بھی 
حد ہے تری پرواز کی لیکن سر دیوار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ‘There is no doubt you also are free for flight. But, the limit of your flight is only up to the wall.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        واقف نہیں تو ہمت مرغان ہوا سے 
تو خاک نشیمن، انھیں گردوں سے سروکار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Are you unacquainted with the courage of the wild birds? You live on the dust; they are concerned with the sky.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تو مرغ سرائی، خورش از خاک بجوئی 
ما در صدد دانہ بہ انجم زدہ منقار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You are a household bird; you seek food in the dust. We strike the star with our beak in search of the grain.’
[Translated by Dr M A K Khalil]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>