<Poem ID="14" Name="کوشش ناتمام" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="2a" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فرقت آفتاب میں کھاتی ہے پیچ و تاب صبح
چشم شفق ہے خوں فشاں اختر شام کے لیے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE UNSUCCESSFUL EFFORT
The dawn is vexed by separation from the sun; the twilight's eye is raining blood for the evening star.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رہتی ہے قیس روز کو لیلی شام کی ہوس
اختر صبح مضطرب تاب دوام کے لیے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The day's Qais has the pining for the night's Lailah; the morning star is restless for perpetual radiance.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کہتا تھا قطب آسماں قافلہ نجوم سے
ہمرہو، میں ترس گیا لطف خرام کے لیے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The sky's polar star was saying to the stars' caravan: ‘Companions! I am tantalized for the pleasure of walking.’
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سوتوں کو ندیوں کا شوق، بحر کا ندیوں کو عشق
موجہء بحر کو تپش ماہ تمام کے لیے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Springs desire rivers, rivers love the ocean; the ocean wave is in love with the full moon.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حسن ازل کہ پردہء لالہ و گل میں ہے نہاں
کہتے ہیں بے قرار ہے جلوہء عام کے لیے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The eternal Beauty which is veiled in tulips and roses is considered to be restless for general manifestation.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        راز حیات پو چھ لے خضر خجستہ گام سے
زندہ ہر ایک چیز ہے کوشش ناتمام سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Ask Khizar of blessed steps for the secret of life: Everything is alive with un-achieved effort.
(An important attribute of Khizar A.S. is his traditional restlessness and incessant activism. Similarly an object is living only as long as it is in incessant search of its Creator and ‘activism’ is that effort. It becomes lifeless if it loses these attributes and it will disappear once it finds the Creator.)
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>