<Poem ID="12" Name="دختران ملت" BookID="11" BookName="ارمغانِ حجاز" SectionID="03" SectionName="حضور ملت">
  <Para Name="(1)">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بہل اے دخترک این دلبری ہا
مسلمان را نزیبد کافری ہا
منہ دل بر جمال غازہ پرورد
بیاموز از نگہ غارتگری ہا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        بیٹی! دلبری کا یہ انداز (آرائش و زینت) چھوڑ دے؛ مسلمان کو کافری زیب نہیں دیتی۔
ایسے حسن سے دل نہ لگا ، جو غازہ کا مرہون منت ہو؛ بلکہ نگاہ سے غارت گری سیکھ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        TO DAUGHTERS OF THE NATION
Learn O’ daughterling this loveliness trend; to Muslim suits not the heathen’s blend.
You need not a beauty of rouge and scent; with the chaste eyes teach thy charming bent.*
* Iqbal has used ‘Gharat Gari’ again in line 4 which means ‘robbery’. In amatory language of this sub-continent and Persia, it means loveliness.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(2)">
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نگاہ تست شمشیر خدا داد
بہ زخمش جان ما را حق بما داد
دل کامل عیار ن پاک جان برد
کہ تیغ خویش را ب از حیا داد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تیری نگاہ شمشیر خداداد ہے ؛ اسی کے زخم سے حق تعالے نے ہماری جان عطا کی ہے۔ 
صرف وہی عفت مآب (خاتون) قلب کامل شکار کرتی ہے : جو اپنی تیغ (نگاہ) کو حیا سے آبدار بناتی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A God-given sword thy glance to thee; whose wounds thus gave my full right to me. 
The heart of great sage that holy soul took; as she tempered her sword with bashful look.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(3)">
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ضمیر عصر حاضر بے نقاب است
گشادش در نمود رنگ و ب است
جہانتابی ز نور حق بیاموز
کہ او با صد تجلی در حجاب است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        دور حاضر کا ضمیر عیاں ہے ؛ اس (ضمیر) کا کشاد رنگ اور چمک دمک کی نمود میں ہے۔ 
مگر تو اللہ تعالے کے نور سے جہان کو منوّر کرنا سیکھ؛ جو صد ہا تجلیات کے باوجود حجاب میں ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        At last modern age shows her conscience lo! They feel quite happy with false pomp and show. 
A tip for world’s tight learn from His light; with hundred visions who hids from sight.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(4)">
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جہان را محکمی از امہات است
نہادشان امین ممکنات است
اگر این نکتہ را قومی نداند
نظام کار و بارش بے ثبات است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        دنیا کی پائیداری ماؤں (کے دم قدم ) سے ہے؛ کیونکہ ان کی نہاد ممکنات کی امانتدار ہے (ماؤں کی گود سے ایسے بچے پیدا ہوتے ہیں ، جن کا ذریعہ ممکنات کے دروازے کھولتے ہیں)۔
جو قوم یہ نکتہ نہیں سمجھتی ؛ اس کا نظام حیات درہم برہم ہو جاتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The world is stable from the mother’s grace; her kind nature guards the whole human race.
To this point if the nations didn’t get; the whole world order would soon up set.*
* Here a ‘mumknat’ means the mankind, all possible (created things. It also means possibilities but it does not apply here.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(5)">
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مرا داد این خرد پرور جنونی 
نگاہ مادر پاک اندرونی
ز مکتب چشم و دل نتوان گرفتن
کہ مکتب نیست جز سحر و فسونی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مجھے یہ خرد پرور جنون اپنی پاک طینت ماں کی نگاہ سے ملا ہے۔
مکتب سے چشم (بینا) اور دل (آگاہ ) حاصل نہیں کیے جا سکتے ؛ کیونکہ مکتب سحر و فسوں کے علاوہ اور کچھ نہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        That nation is lucky in whose hard race; a change the world espied on each man’s face.
What happen’d to him in this world’s race; can be seen now from their mother’s face.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(6)">
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خنک ن ملتی کز وارداتش
قیامتہا ببیند کایناتش
چہ پیش ید، چہ پیش افتاد او را
توان دید از جبین امہاتش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مبارک ہے وہ ملت جس کے کارناموں کے سبب ؛ اس کے دور نے کیا قیامتیں دیکھیں۔ 
کسی قوم کو کیا پیش آنے والا ہے اور کیا پیش آ چکا ہے؛ (یہ سب) اس کی ماؤں کی جبینوں سے دیکھا جا سکتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This craze she gave me for sharp wits sense; my kind mother’s sacred inner glance.
In schools, my heart and eyes did’nt get calm; no schools are these but magic and charm.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(7)">
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اگر پندی ز درویشی پذیری 
ہزار امت بمیرد تو نمیری
بتولی باش و پنھان شو ازین عصر
کہ در غوش شبیری بگیری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اگر تو اس درویش کی نصیحت پلّے باندھ لے؛ تو ہزار قومیں مر جائیں ، مگر تو نہیں مرے گا۔
سیّدہ فاطمہ التزہرا (رضی الّہ) بن اور اس دور سے پنہاں رہ؛ تاکہ تو کسی شبیر کو جنم دے سکے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If you pay a heed once, to this poor guy; may die thousand nations but ye won’t die.
Hid from this Age like Batool if you can; in thy lap too there may be a Hussain.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(8)">
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ز شام ما برون ور سحر را
بہ قر ن باز خوان اہل نظر را
تو میدانی کہ سوز قرأت تو
دگرگون کرد تقدیر عمر را
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        پھر قرآن پاک کی تلوار سے اہل نظر کو متاثر کر کے؛ ہماری شام سے سحر پیدا کر۔
تو جانتی ہے کہ تیرے سوز قرآءت نے؛ حضرت عمر (رضی اللہ ) کی تقدیر بدل دی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        From my evening’s dusk get a dawn new; to seeing eyes read the Koran anew. 
From thy reading’s flame you know that fate; had totally changed Omar the Great.*
* Before embracing Islam, Hazrat Omar (R.A.) heard that her sister alongwith her husband had embraced Islam. In rage he went to her house and heard her reciting the Holy Quran, which melted his heart, and he too joined the fold of Islam.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>