<Poem ID="16" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="02" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میر سپاہ ناسزا، لشکریاں شکستہ صف 
آہ! وہ تیر نیم کش جس کا نہ ہو کوئی ہدف
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ہدف: نشانہ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A recreant captain, a battle-line thrown back, the arrow hanging target-less and slack!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تیرے محیط میں کہیں گوہر زندگی نہیں 
ڈھونڈ چکا میں موج موج، دیکھ چکا صدف صدف
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Nowhere near you that shell which holds life’s pearl; I have dragged the waves and searched the ocean’s track.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عشق بتاں سے ہاتھ اٹھا، اپنی خودی میں ڈوب جا 
نقش و نگار دیر میں خون جگر نہ کر تلف
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Plunge in your self, on idols dote no more, pour our no more heart’s blood for paint to deck their shrines.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کھول کے کیا بیاں کروں سر مقام مرگ و عشق 
عشق ہے مرگ با شرف، مرگ حیات بے شرف
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I unveil the courts of Love and Death: Death – life dishonoured; Love – death for honour’s sake.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        صحبت پیر روم سے مجھ پہ ہوا یہ راز فاش 
لاکھ حکیم سر بجیب، ایک کلیم سر بکف
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I gleaned in Rumi’s company: one bold heart is worth of learned heads the whole tame pack.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مثل کلیم ہو اگر معرکہ آزما کوئی 
اب بھی درخت طور سے آتی ہے بانگ' لا تخف
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Once more that voice from Sinai’s tree would cry fear not! If some new Moses led the attack.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خیرہ نہ کر سکا مجھے جلوہ دانش فرنگ 
سرمہ ہے میری آنکھ کا خاک مدینہ و نجف
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        No glitter of Western science could dazzle my eyes: The dust of Medina stains, like collyrium, black. 
(Translated by V.G. Kiernan)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>