<Poem ID="05" Name="ہسپانیہ" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="04" SectionName="منظومات">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہسپانیہ تو خون مسلماں کا امیں ہے 
مانند حرم پاک ہے تو میری نظر میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        SPAIN
Spain! You are the trustee of the Muslim blood: In my eyes you are sanctified like the Harem.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پوشیدہ تری خاک میں سجدوں کے نشاں ہیں 
خاموش اذانیں ہیں تری باد سحر میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Prints of prostration lie hidden in your dust; silent calls to prayers in your morning air.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        روشن تھیں ستاروں کی طرح ان کی سنانیں 
خیمے تھے کبھی جن کے ترے کوہ و کمر میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کوہ و کمر: پہاڑ اور اس کا دامن۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In your hills and vales were the tents of those; the tips of whose lances were bright like the stars.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پھر تیرے حسینوں کو ضرورت ہے حنا کی؟ 
باقی ہے ابھی رنگ مرے خون جگر میں!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Is more henna needed by your pretties? My lifeblood can give them some colour!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کیونکر خس و خاشاک سے دب جائے مسلماں
مانا، وہ تب و تاب نہیں اس کے شرر میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        How can a Muslim be put down by the straw and grass; even if his flame has lost its heat and fire!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        غرناطہ بھی دیکھا مری آنکھوں نے و لیکن 
تسکین مسافر نہ سفر میں نہ حضر میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My eyes watched Granada as well, but the traveller’s content neither in journey nor in rest:
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دیکھا بھی دکھایا بھی، سنایا بھی سنا بھی 
ہے دل کی تسلی نہ نظر میں، نہ خبر میں!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I saw as well as showed, I spoke as well as listened; neither seeing nor learning brings calm to the heart!
(Translated by Naeem Siddiqui)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>