<Poem ID="06" Name="طارق کی دعا" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="04" SectionName="منظومات">
  <Para Name="اندلس کے ميدان جنگ ميں">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ غازی، یہ تیرے پر اسرار بندے 
جنھیں تو نے بخشا ہے ذوق خدائی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        TARIQ’S PRAYER: In the Battlefield of Andalusia.
These warriors, victorious, these worshippers of Thine, whom Thou hast granted the will to win power in Thy name.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دو نیم ان کی ٹھوکر سے صحرا و دریا 
سمٹ کر پہاڑ ان کی ہیبت سے رائی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Who cleave rivers and woods in twain; whose terror turns mountains into dust!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دو عالم سے کرتی ہے بیگانہ دل کو 
عجب چیز ہے لذت آشنائی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        They care not for the world; they care not for its pleasures; in their passion, in their zeal, in their love for Thee, O Lord!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شہادت ہے مطلوب و مقصود مومن 
نہ مال غنیمت نہ کشور کشائی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کشور کشائي: حکمرانی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        They aim at martyrdom, not the rule of the earth.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خیاباں میں ہے منتظر لالہ کب سے 
قبا چاہیے اس کو خون عرب سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        خياباں: پھولوں کی کیاری۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Red flower in the flower-bed (Spain) is waiting since long; it requires an apron made of Arab blood
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کیا تو نے صحرا نشینوں کو یکتا 
خبر میں، نظر میں، اذان سحر میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Thou hast united warring tribes; in thought, in deed, in prayer.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        طلب جس کی صدیوں سے تھی زندگی کو 
وہ سوز اس نے پایا انھی کے جگر میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The burning fire that life had sought; for centuries, was found in them at last.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کشاد در دل سمجھتے ہیں اس کو 
ہلاکت نہیں موت ان کی نظر میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        They think of death, not as life’s end; but as the ennobling of the heart.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دل مرد مومن میں پھر زندہ کر دے 
وہ بجلی کہ تھی نعرہ لاتذر، میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Bring the heart in the chest of true believer back to life; lightening that lied in cry of La-tazar. (Reference to prayer of Noah (A.S.) in which he had prayed for replacing darkness of infidelity with the light of belief).
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عزائم کو سینوں میں بیدار کردے 
نگاہ مسلماں کو تلوار کردے!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Awaken in them an iron will; and make their eye a sharpened sword.
(Translated by Naeem Siddiqui)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>