<Poem ID="67" Name="دریوزہ خلافت" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اگر ملک ہاتھوں سے جاتا ہے، جائے 
تو احکام حق سے نہ کر بے وفائی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        BEGGING FOR KHILAFAH
If the territory is being lost let it be lost; you should not be disloyal to God’s commands.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہیں تجھ کو تاریخ سے آگہی کیا 
خلافت کی کرنے لگا تو گدائی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Do you not have knowledge of history? You have started begging for theKhilafah!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خریدیں نہ جس کو ہم اپنے لہو سے 
مسلماں کو ہے ننگ وہ پادشائی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If we do not purchase with our own blood; such sovereignty is a disgrace to the Muslim!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مرا از شکستن چناں عار ناید 
کہ از دیگراں خواستن مومیائی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میرے لیے اپنے جسم کی ہڈیاں ٹوٹ جانا اس قدر باعث شرم نہیں، جس قدر دوسروں کے سامنے مومیائی کے لیے ہاتھ پھیلا نا ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ‘I do not feel as much ashamed of being broken down as in asking others for momiya’i* for my treatment. 
* This is a medicinal substance which appears from rocks in lime stone formations in mountains. It is believed to have extraordinary tonic and healing properties. Geologically the closest substances to momiya’i are ‘stalactite’ and ‘stalacmite’. The former is formed very slowly when the water containing calcium bicarbonate drips down slowly from the roof of a cave of lime stone rock. The deposit hangs from the roof of the cave like icicles. The latter is also made up of calcium bicarbonate and is formed in the same way at the bottom of the cave. The verse means that being defeated is better than gaining success through begging help from others.)
(Translated by Dr. M.A.K. Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>