<Poem ID="07" Name="" BookID="03" BookName="ضربِ کلیم" SectionID="06" SectionName="محراب گل افغان کے افکار">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رومی بدلے، شامی بدلے، بدلا ہندستان 
تو بھی اے فرزند کہستاں! اپنی خودی پہچان 
اپنی خودی پہچان 
او غافل افغان
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Romans, Syrians, Hindus too have changed and made a great advance; O son of hills, discern your Self and sharpness of your Self enhance. O Afghan unaware, of your self take much care.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        موسم اچھا، پانی وافر، مٹی بھی زرخیز 
جس نے اپنا کھیت نہ سینچا، وہ کیسا دہقان 
اپنی خودی پہچان 
او غافل افغان
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If weather is fine, water quite enough and terrain fertile and plain, but peasant does not water fields, he is odd and can nothing gain. O Afghan unaware, of your self take much care.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اونچی جس کی لہر نہیں ہے، وہ کیسا دریاے 
جس کی ہوائیں تند نہیں ہیں، وہ کیسا طوفان 
اپنی خودی پہچان 
او غافل افغان
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        That river has no weight at all whose billows do not swell and rise that tempest is too weak and low, whose gales by fury don't surprise. O Afghan unaware, of your Self take much care.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ڈھونڈ کے اپنی خاک میں جس نے پایا اپنا آپ 
اس بندے کی دہقانی پر سلطانی قربان 
اپنی خودی پہچان 
او غافل افغان
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A person, who stire up and down his clay, to Self can find a clue: Kings who possess vast, mighty states, can be ransomed for peasant true. O Afghan unaware, of your self take much care.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تیری بے علمی نے رکھ لی بے علموں کی لاج 
عالم فاضل بیچ رہے ہیں اپنا دین ایمان 
اپنی خودی پہچان 
او غافل افغان
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Self-respect of unlettered men your ignorance has saved from harm though scholars and savants sell their Faith to keep their bellies warm. O Afghan unaware, of your self have much care.
[Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>