<Poem ID="45" Name="صدیق" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اک دن رسول پاک نے اصحاب سے کہا 
دیں مال راہ حق میں جو ہوں تم میں مالدار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ABU BAKR SIDDIQ R.A.
One day the Holy Prophet (S.A.W.) to his companions appealed: ‘All who have wealth should give some in God’s cause.’
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ارشاد سن کے فرط طرب سے عمر اٹھے 
اس روز ان کے پاس تھے درہم کئی ہزار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        On hearing this command Umar rose in intense happiness; that day he had acquired several thousand dirhams.
(Dirham: This was the coin current in the Arab world at that time and even at present in some countries.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دل میں یہ کہہ رہے تھے کہ صدیق سے ضرور 
بڑھ کر رکھے گا آج قدم میرا راہوار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He was saying to himself that certainly that day he would excel Siddiq by far that day.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لائے غرضکہ مال رسول امیں کے پاس 
ایثار کی ہے دست نگر ابتدائے کار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        At last he brought the wealth before the Holy Prophet (S.A.W.). Starting the action is a prelude to the necessary sacrifice.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پوچھا حضور سرور عالم نے، اے عمر! 
اے وہ کہ جوش حق سے ترے دل کو ہے قرار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Holy Prophet (S.A.W.) asked him, ‘O Umar! To whom God’s Love is the solace of the heart!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رکھا ہے کچھ عیال کی خاطر بھی تو نے کیا؟ 
مسلم ہے اپنے خویش و اقارب کا حق گزار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Have you kept anything for the family? Muslim is responsible for family’s rights.’
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کی عرض نصف مال ہے فرزند و زن کا حق
باقی جو ہے وہ ملت بیضا پہ ہے نثار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He exclaimed, ‘Half wealth is the son and wife’s share; the rest is made a present to the Ummah in sacrifice.’
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اتنے میں وہ رفیق نبوت بھی آگیا 
جس سے بنائے عشق و محبت ہے استوار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Soon after, that friend of prophethood also arrived; on whom the foundation of Love is established.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لے آیا اپنے ساتھ وہ مرد وفا سرشت 
ہر چیز، جس سے چشم جہاں میں ہو اعتبار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        That man of proved loyalty brought with him everything which is creditable in the world’s eye.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ملک یمین و درہم و دینار و رخت و جنس 
اسپ قمر سم و شتر و قاطر و حمار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        All that right hand possessed, in cash, kind, chattel beautiful horses, camels, mules and donkeys.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بولے حضور، چاہیے فکر عیال بھی 
کہنے لگا وہ عشق و محبت کا راز دار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Holy Prophet (S.A.W.) said, ‘You also need to care for the family’; replied that secret-keeper of Love and Fidelity:
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے تجھ سے دیدئہ مہ و انجم فروغ گیر! 
اے تیری ذات باعث تکوین روزگار!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ‘O you who give light to the eyes of the moon and the stars; who was made the reason for creation of the universe;
(Allusion to the Hadith-i-Qudsi according to which God would not have created the universe if He had not intended to create the person of the Holy Prophet S.A.W).
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پروانے کو چراغ ہے، بلبل کو پھول بس 
صدیق کے لیے ہے خدا کا رسول بس
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Lamp to the moth, flower to the nightingale is sufficient; for Siddiq only the Prophet of God (S.A.W.) is sufficient!’
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>