<Poem ID="54" Name="مسلمان اور تعلیم جدید" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="تضمين بر شعر ملک قمی">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مرشد کی یہ تعلیم تھی اے مسلم شوریدہ سر 
لازم ہے رہرو کے لیے دنیا میں سامان سفر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        شوريدہ سر: دیوانہ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The preceptor’s teaching was, O foolish Muslim! ‘Necessary preparations are incumbent on the traveler.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بدلی زمانے کی ہوا، ایسا تغیر آگیا 
تھے جو گراں قمیت کبھی، اب ہیں متاع کس مخر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        متاع کس مخر: ایسا مال جسے کوئی نہ خریدے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The world’s ways have changed, such changes have come that those who were invaluable once are not even saleable now.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وہ شعلہ روشن ترا ظلمت گریزاں جس سے تھی 
گھٹ کر ہوا مثل شرر تارے سے بھی کم نور تر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        That bright flame of yours from which darkness escaped now is reduced to a spark, less bright than stars.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شیدائی غائب نہ رہ، دیوانہء موجود ہو 
غالب ہے اب اقوام پر معبود حاضر کا اثر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ديوانہء موجود: موجودہ چیز کا دیوانہ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Cease to be the Invisible’s Lover, be the visible’s lover; now influence of the visible God is triumphant over nations.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ممکن نہیں اس باغ میں کوشش ہو بار آور تری 
فرسودہ ہے پھندا ترا، زیرک ہے مرغ تیز پر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        زيرک: ہوشیار، چالاک۔
فرسودہ: پرانا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In this garden success for your efforts is not possible; your snare is worn out and the fast-flying bird is clever.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اس دور میں تعلیم ہے امراض ملت کی دوا 
ہے خون فاسد کے لیے تعلیم مثل نیشتر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        خون فاسد: گندہ خون۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In this age education is the cure for nations’ maladies: Education is like a lancet for the diseased blood.’
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رہبر کے ایما سے ہوا تعلیم کا سودا مجھے 
واجب ہے صحرا گرد پر تعمیل فرمان خضر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        By the leader’s suggestions love of education developed in me. Obeying the command of Khizar is incumbent on the wanderer of the wilderness.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لیکن نگاہ نکتہ بیں دیکھے زبوں بختی مری 
رفتم کہ خار از پا کشم،محمل نہاں شد از نظر

یک لحظ غافل گشتم و صد سالہ را ہم دور شد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میں اپنے پاؤں سے کانٹا نکالنے لگا اور اتنی دیر میں محمل نظر سے اوجھل ہو گیا؛ ایک لمحہ کی غفلت میں سینکڑوں سال پیچھے رہ گیا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        But the discerning eye should see my misfortune: ‘Went to pull thorn from foot, the litter disappeared from the sight; I was negligent for a moment it moved by a hundered years.’ 
(This is the climax and the raison d`etre of this poem. It means that the apparently slight error of the Muslim Ummah in obtaining and accepting Western education uncritically has resulted in its doom.)
(Translated by M.A.K. Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>