<Poem ID="06" Name="ایک مکڑا اور مکھی" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="1a" SectionName="حصہ اول">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اک دن کسی مکھی سے یہ کہنے لگا مکڑا
اس راہ سے ہوتا ہے گزر روز تمھارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A SPIDER AND A FLY
One day a spider said to a fly: ‘Though you pass this way daily.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لیکن مری کٹیا کی نہ جاگی کبھی قسمت
بھولے سے کبھی تم نے یہاں پائوں نہ رکھا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کٹیا: جھونپڑی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My hut has never been honoured by you by making a chance visit inside by you.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        غیروں سے نہ ملیے تو کوئی بات نہیں ہے
اپنوں سے مگر چاہیے یوں کھنچ کے نہ رہنا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Though depriving strangers of a visit does not matter; evading the near and dear ones does not look good.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آئو جو مرے گھر میں تو عزت ہے یہ میری
وہ سامنے سیڑھی ہے جو منظور ہو آنا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My house will be honoured by a visit by you; a ladder is before you if you decide to step in.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مکھی نے سنی بات جو مکڑے کی تو بولی
حضرت! کسی نادان کو دیجے گا یہ دھوکا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Hearing this the fly said to the spider: ‘Sire, you should entice some simpleton thus:
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اس جال میں مکھی کبھی آنے کی نہیں ہے
جو آپ کی سیڑھی پہ چڑھا، پھر نہیں اترا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This fly would never be pulled into your net, whoever climbed your net could never step down.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مکڑے نے کہا واہ! فریبی مجھے سمجھے
تم سا کوئی نادان زمانے میں نہ ہو گا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The spider said: ‘How strange, you consider me a cheat, I have never seen a simpleton like you in the world.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        منظور تمھاری مجھے خاطر تھی وگرنہ
کچھ فائدہ اپنا تو مرا اس میں نہیں تھا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I only wanted to entertain you. I had no personal gain in view.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اڑتی ہوئی آئی ہو خدا جانے کہاں سے
ٹھہرو جو مرے گھر میں تو ہے اس میں برا کیا!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You have come flying from some unknown distant place; resting for a while in my house would not harm you.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اس گھر میں کئی تم کو دکھانے کی ہیں چیزیں
باہر سے نظر آتا ہے چھوٹی سی یہ کٹیا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Many things in this house are worth your seeing; though apparently a humble hut you are seeing.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لٹکے ہوئے دروازوں پہ باریک ہیں پردے
دیواروں کو آئینوں سے ہے میں نے سجایا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Dainty drapes are hanging from the doors and I have decorated the walls with mirrors.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مہمانوں کے آرام کو حاضر ہیں بچھونے
ہر شخص کو ساماں یہ میسر نہیں ہوتا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Beddings are available for guests’ comforts; not to everyone’s lot do fall these comforts’.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مکھی نے کہا خیر، یہ سب ٹھیک ہے لیکن
میں آپ کے گھر آئوں، یہ امید نہ رکھنا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The fly said: ‘All this may very well be, but do not expect me to enter your house.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ان نرم بچھونوں سے خدا مجھ کو بچائے
سو جائے کوئی ان پہ تو پھر اٹھ نہیں سکتا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        May God protect me from these soft beds; once asleep in them getting up again is impossible.’
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مکڑے نے کہا دل میں سنی بات جو اس کی
پھانسوں اسے کس طرح یہ کم بخت ہے دانا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The spider spoke to itself on hearing this talk: ‘How to trap it? This wretched fellow is clever.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="31">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سو کام خوشامد سے نکلتے ہیں جہاں میں
دیکھو جسے دنیا میں خوشامد کا ہے بندا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Many desires are fulfilled with flattery in the world; all in the world are enslaved with flattery.’
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ سوچ کے مکھی سے کہا اس نے بڑی بی !
اللہ نے بخشا ہے بڑا آپ کو رتبا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Thinking this the spider spoke to the fly thus! ’Madam, God has bestowed great honours on you!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="35">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہوتی ہے اسے آپ کی صورت سے محبت
ہو جس نے کبھی ایک نظر آپ کو دیکھا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Everyone loves your beautiful face; even if someone sees you for the first time.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="37">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آنکھیں ہیں کہ ہیرے کی چمکتی ہوئی کنیاں
سر آپ کا اللہ نے کلغی سے سجایا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your eyes look like clusters of glittering diamonds. God has adorned your beautiful head with a plume.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="39">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ حسن، یہ پوشاک، یہ خوبی، یہ صفائی
پھر اس پہ قیامت ہے یہ اڑتے ہوئے گانا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This beauty, this dress, this elegance, this neatness! And all this is very much enhanced by singing in flight.’
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="41">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مکھی نے سنی جب یہ خوشامد تو پسیجی
بولی کہ نہیں آپ سے مجھ کو کوئی کھٹکا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The fly was touched by this flattery and spoke: ‘I do not fear you any more.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="43">
      <Text Language="Original">
        انکار کی عادت کو سمجھتی ہوں برا میں
سچ یہ ہے کہ دل توڑنا اچھا نہیں ہوتا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I hate the habit of declining requests; disappointing somebody is bad indeed.’
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="45">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ بات کہی اور اڑی اپنی جگہ سے
پاس آئی تو مکڑے نے اچھل کر اسے پکڑا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Saying this it flew from its place when it got close the spider snapped it.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="47">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بھوکا تھا کئی روز سے اب ہاتھ جو آئی
آرام سے گھر بیٹھ کے مکھی کو اڑایا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The spider had been starving for many days. The fly provided a good leisurely meal.
[Translated by M.A.K.Khalil]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>