<Poem ID="16" Name="ایک نوجوان کے نام" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="04" SectionName="منظومات">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ترے صوفے ہیں افرنگی، ترے قالیں ہیں ایرانی 
لہو مجھ کو رلاتی ہے جوانوں کی تن آسانی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        TO A YOUNG MAN
Thy sofas are from Europe, thy carpets from Iran; this slothful opulence evokes my sigh of pity.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        امارت کیا، شکوہ خسروی بھی ہو تو کیا حاصل
نہ زور حیدری تجھ میں، نہ استغنائے سلمانی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        استغنائے سلمانی: حضرت سلمان (رضی اللہ) جیسی بے نیازی اور ہر قسم کی محتاجی سے بالا ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In vain if thou possessest Khusroe’s imperial pomp, if thou dost not possess prowess or contentment.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہ ڈھونڈ اس چیز کو تہذیب حاضر کی تجلی میں 
کہ پایا میں نے استغنا میں معراج مسلمانی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Seek not thy joy or greatness in the glitter of Western life, for in contentment lies a Muslim’s joy and greatness.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عقابی روح جب بیدار ہوتی ہے جوانوں میں 
نظر آتی ہے اس کو اپنی منزل آسمانوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When an eagle’s spirit awakens in youthful hearts, it sees its luminous goal beyond the starry heavens.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہ ہو نومید، نومیدی زوال علم و عرفاں ہے 
امید مرد مومن ہے خدا کے راز دانوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Despair not, for despair is the decline of knowledge and gnosis: the Hope of a Believer is among the confidants of God.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہیں تیرا نشیمن قصر سلطانی کے گنبد پر 
تو شاہیں ہے، بسیرا کر پہاڑوں کی چٹانوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Thy abode is not on the dome of a royal palace; thou art an eagle and shouldst live on the rocks of mountains.
[Translated by Naim Siddiqui]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>