<Poem ID="48" Name="کنار راوی" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="1a" SectionName="حصہ اول">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سکوت شام میں محو سرود ہے راوی
نہ پوچھ مجھ سے جو ہے کیفیت مرے دل کی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ON THE BANKS OF THE RAVI
In the evening's serenity the Ravi melodious is: Do not ask me what the condition of my heart is.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پیام سجدے کا یہ زیر و بم ہوا مجھ کو
جہاں تمام سواد حرم ہوا مجھ کو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This became message of prostration’s rise and fall to me; the whole world became precincts of the Haram to me.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سر کنارہ آب رواں کھڑا ہوں میں
خبر نہیں مجھے لیکن کہاں کھڑا ہوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I am standing at the bank of the running water; however, I do not know where I am standing.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شراب سرخ سے رنگیں ہوا ہے دامن شام
لیے ہے پیر فلک دست رعشہ دار میں جام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The red wine has coloured the skirt of the evening. The aged sky is holding wine cup in its trembling hand.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عدم کو قافلہ روز تیز گام چلا
شفق نہیں ہے، یہ سورج کے پھول ہیں گویا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The day's fast moving caravan is advancing to its end. The evening's twilight is the sun's flower so to say.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کھڑے ہیں دور وہ عظمت فزائے تنہائی
منار خواب گہ شہسوار چغتائی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In the distance those solitary structures are standing; they are the minarets of the Mughal emperors' tombs.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فسانہء ستم انقلاب ہے یہ محل
کوئی زمان سلف کی کتاب ہے یہ محل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This place is the tale of revolution’s tyranny. This place is some book of the bygone age.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مقام کیا ہے سرود خموش ہے گویا
شجر، یہ انجمن بے خروش ہے گویا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This place is a silent orchestra so to say; not trees! But it is a serene assembly so to say.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رواں ہے سینہء دریا پہ اک سفینہ تیز
ہوا ہے موج سے ملاح جس کا گرم ستیز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A fast moving boat is sailing on its surface; whose sailor is fighting fiercely with the waves.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سبک روی میں ہے مثل نگاہ یہ کشتی
نکل کے حلقہ حد نظر سے دور گئی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This boat is in fast speed like the sight; getting out of sight, it has gone far away.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جہاز زندگی آدمی رواں ہے یونہی
ابد کے بحر میں پیدا یونہی، نہاں ہے یونہی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The ship of Man’s life is sailing in the same way: it is present as well as hidden in eternity’s sea.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شکست سے یہ کبھی آشنا نہیں ہوتا
نظر سے چھپتا ہے لیکن فنا نہیں ہوتا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It never gets acquainted with defeat; it is concealed from sight but is not effaced!
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>