<Poem ID="11" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="02" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہزار خوف ہو لیکن زباں ہو دل کی رفیق 
یہی رہا ہے ازل سے قلندروں کا طریق
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A host of peril though you face, yet your tongue with heart ally: From times antique and hoar Qalandars on this mode rely.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہجوم کیوں ہے زیادہ شراب خانے میں 
فقط یہ بات کہ پیر مغاں ہے مرد خلیق
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        پير مغاں: شراب فروش۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Men congregate in numbers large in the mart where wine is sold: For polite and courteous seems the Head of Mart, the Magian Old.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        علاج ضعف یقیں ان سے ہو نہیں سکتا 
غریب اگرچہ ہیں رازی کے نکتہ ہائے دقیق
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        نکتہ ہائے دقيق: باریک اور عجیب و غریب نقطے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Though the points by Razi touched may be subtle and profound; yet against infirm belief no cure in them is ever found.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مرید سادہ تو رو رو کے ہو گیا تائب 
خدا کرے کہ ملے شیخ کو بھی یہ توفیق
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The disciple blind shed copious tears, of sinful life he felt contrite. May God aid the shaykh as well to feel ashamed and do the right!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اسی طلسم کہن میں اسیر ہے آدم 
بغل میں اس کی ہیں اب تک بتان عہد عتیق
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        بتان عہد عتيق: پرانا زمانہ ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Man is bound still hand and foot in chains by this talisman old: For idols of the age of past still men within their armpits hold.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مرے لیے تو ہے اقرار باللساں بھی بہت 
ہزار شکر کہ ملا ہیں صاحب تصدیق
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اقرار باللساں: زبانی اقرار۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Enough for me that I affirm with tongue alone my faith and creed: A thousand thanks for mullah’s claim that he with heart avows, indeed.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اگر ہو عشق تو ہے کفر بھی مسلمانی 
نہ ہو تو مرد مسلماں بھی کافر و زندیق
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        زنديق: بے دین، ملحد۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        As good as Muslim’s true belief, if blessed with Love, unfaith is eke: Bereft of Love a Muslim true is no better than Zindiq.
[Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>