<Poem ID="02" Name="حقیقت حسن" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="2a" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خدا سے حسن نے اک روز یہ سوال کیا
جہاں میں کیوں نہ مجھے تو نے لازوال کیا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE REALITY OF BEAUTY
Beauty one day put this question to God: Why did you not make me eternal in the world?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ملا جواب کہ تصویر خانہ ہے دنیا
شب دراز عدم کا فسانہ ہے دنیا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The answer was that the world is like a picture gallery. The world is the story of the long night of annihilation.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہوئی ہے رنگ تغیر سے جب نمود اس کی
وہی حسیں ہے حقیقت زوال ہے جس کی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        As the nature of change is the basis of its display; only that is beautiful whose reality is decline.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کہیں قریب تھا، یہ گفتگو قمر نے سنی
فلک پہ عام ہوئی، اختر سحر نے سنی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اختر سحر: صبح کا تارا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The moon was somewhere near and it heard this conversation; it became well-known in the heaven, the morning star heard.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سحر نے تارے سے سن کر سنائی شبنم کو
فلک کی بات بتا دی زمیں کے محرم کو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Having heard from the star the morning related it to the dew, it exposed the celestial world’s secret to earth’s confidante.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بھر آئے پھول کے آنسو پیام شبنم سے
کلی کا ننھا سا دل خون ہو گیا غم سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The flower’s eye started weeping from the dew’s message; the flower bud’s little heart was injured by this sorrow.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چمن سے روتا ہوا موسم بہار گیا
شباب سیر کو آیا تھا، سوگوار گیا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The spring weeping from the garden departed: Youth had come for amusement, sad it departed.
[Translated by Dr M A K Khalil]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>