<Poem ID="19" Name="رام" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لبریز ہے شراب حقیقت سے جام ہند 
سب فلسفی ہیں خطہء مغرب کے رام ہند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        RAMA
Overflowing with the wine of Truth is the cup of India. All philosophers of the Western world have acknowledged India.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ ہندیوں کے فکر فلک رس کا ہے اثر 
رفعت میں آسماں سے بھی اونچا ہے بام ہند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        فکر فلک رس: آسمان پر پہنچنے والا خیال ۔
بام ہند: ہند کی چھت، مراد ہے ہمالیہ پہاڑ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It is the result of the elegant thinking of Indians that higher than the sky is the position of India.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اس دیس میں ہوئے ہیں ہزاروں ملک سرشت 
مشہور جن کے دم سے ہے دنیا میں نام ہند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ملک سرشت: فرشتہ خصلت۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This country has had many people of angelic disposition; on whose account world renowned is the name of India.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے رام کے وجود پہ ہندوستاں کو ناز 
اہل نظر سمجھتے ہیں اس کو امام ہند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        India is proud of the existence of Rama. Spiritual people consider him prelate of India.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اعجاز اس چراغ ہدایت کا ہے یہی 
روشن تر از سحر ہے زمانے میں شام ہند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        روشن تر از سحر: صبح سے زیادہ روشن۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This alone is the miracle of this light of righteousness that brighter than world’s morning is the evening of India.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تلوار کا دھنی تھا، شجاعت میں فرد تھا 
پاکیزگی میں، جوش محبت میں فرد تھا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He was expert in sword craft, was unique in bravery; was matchless in piety and in the enthusiasm of love.
(Translated by M.A.K. Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>