<Poem ID="20" Name="زمانہ" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="04" SectionName="منظومات">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        محرمانہ قریب تر ہے نمود جس کی، اسی کا مشتاق ہے زمانہ 
جو تھا نہیں ہے، جو ہے نہ ہو گا، یہی ہے اک حرف
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        TIME
What was; has faded: what is; is fading: but of these words few can tell the worth; time still is gaping with expectation of what is nearest its hour of birth.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مری صراحی سے قطرہ قطرہ نئے حوادث ٹپک رہے ہیں 
میں اپنی تسبیح روز و شب کا شمار کرتا ہوں دانہ دانہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        New tidings slowly come drop by drop from my pitcher gurgling of time’s new sights, as I count over the beads strung out on my threaded rosary of days and nights.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہر ایک سے آشنا ہوں، لیکن جدا جدا رسم و راہ میری 
کسی کا راکب، کسی کا مرکب، کسی کو عبرت کا تازیانہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        With each man friendly, with each I vary, and have a new part at my command: To one the rider, to one the courser, to one the whiplash of reprimand.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہ تھا اگر تو شریک محفل، قصور میرا ہے یا کہ تیرا 
مرا طریقہ نہیں کہ رکھ لوں کسی کی خاطر مےء شبانہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If in the circle you were not numbered, was it your own fault or mine? To humour no-one am I accustomed to keep untasted the midnight wine!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مرے خم و پیچ کو نجومی کی آنکھ پہچانتی نہیں ہے 
ہدف سے بیگانہ تیرا اس کا، نظر نہیں جس کی عارفانہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        No planet-gazer can ever see through my winding mazes; for when the eye that aims it sees by no lights from Heaven, the arrow wavers and glances by.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شفق نہیں مغربی افق پر یہ جوئے خوں ہے، یہ جوئے خوں ہے! 
طلوع فردا کا منتظر رہ کہ دوش و امروز ہے فسانہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        That is no dawn at the Western skyline – it is a bloodbath, that ruddy glow! Await tomorrow; our yesterday and today are legends of long ago.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وہ فکر گستاخ جس نے عریاں کیا ہے فطرت کی طاقتوں کو 
اس کی بیتاب بجلیوں سے خطر میں ہے اس کا آشیانہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        From Nature’s forces their reckless science has stripped the garments away, until at last its own nesting-place is scorched by the restless lightning it cannot still:
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہوائیں ان کی، فضائیں ان کی، سمندر ان کے، جہاز ان کے 
گرہ بھنور کی کھلے تو کیونکر، بھنور ہے تقدیر کا بہانہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        To them the trade-wind belongs, the sky-way, to them the ocean, to them the ship: It shall not serve them to calm the whirlpool by which their fate holds them in its grip!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جہان نو ہو رہا ہے پیدا، وہ عالم پیر مر رہا ہے 
جسے فرنگی مقامروں نے بنا دیا ہے قمار خانہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        But now a new world is being born, while this old one sinks out of sight of men, this world the gamblers of Europe turned into nothing else than a gambling-den.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہوا ہے گو تند و تیز لیکن چراغ اپنا جلا رہا ہے 
وہ مرد درویش جس کو حق نے دیے ہیں انداز خسروانہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        That man will still keep his lantern burning, however tempests blow strong and cold, whose soul is centred on high, whose temper the Lord has cast in the royal mould.
(Translated by V.G. Kiernan)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>