<Poem ID="45" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="02" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رہا نہ حلقہ صوفی میں سوز مشتاقی 
فسانہ ہائے کرامات رہ گئے باقی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        To Lover’s glowing fire and flame the mystic order has no claim: They don’t discourse or talk of aught save wonders by their elders wrought.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خراب کوشک سلطان و خانقاہ فقیر 
فغاں کہ تخت و مصلی کمال زراقی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        زراقي: مکر و فن۔ 
کوشک: محل، دربار۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Alas! The throne as well as the mat, alike are full of guile and craft: Both royal hall and Holy Shrine have lost their essence fine.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کرے گی داور محشر کو شرمسار اک روز 
کتاب صوفی و ملا کی سادہ اوراقی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        داور محشر: روز حساب، قیامت کے دن۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The scrolls of Sufis and mullah may put them to shame on Judgment Day before the Throne of Judge Supreme for being empty in extreme.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہ چینی و عربی وہ، نہ رومی و شامی 
سما سکا نہ دو عالم میں مرد آفاقی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مرد آفاقي : دنیا کی نسبت سے آزاد۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        How can this world or next contain the man not bound to one domain? The East or West is not his home, not tied to Syrian Land or Rome.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مے شبانہ کی مستی تو ہو چکی، لیکن 
کھٹک رہا ہے دلوں میں کرشمہ ساقی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Intoxication due to nightly wine, no doubt, by now, is one decline, but saki’s glance still pricks the heart, like a swift and piercing dart.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چمن میں تلخ نوائی مری گوارا کر 
کہ زہر بھی کبھی کرتا ہے کار تریاقی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ترياقي: زہر کی دوا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My bitter notes with patience hark, that I utter in this park: Bear it in mind that passion too oft can work like elixir true.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عزیز تر ہے متاع امیر و سلطاں سے 
وہ شعر جس میں ہو بجلی کا سوز و براقی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        براقي: چمک، تب و تاب۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        More dear and precious song replete with lightning’s dazzling flash and heat than coffers full of yellow gold that mighty kings and chiefs do hold.
(Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>