<Poem ID="06" Name="" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="2b" SectionName="غزلیات 2">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مثال پرتو مے، طوف جام کرتے ہیں 
یہی نماز ادا صبح و شام کرتے ہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        رتو مے: شراب کے جلوے کی طرح۔ مثال
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        We circumambulate the wine cup like the wine's reflection; we are offering this prayer from morning till evening.
(Our daily prayers are only ritual in nature. They resemble circumambulation of the wine cup rather that of the wine. Similarly our circumambulation of the Holy Ka'bah does not make us close to God which the Holy Ka'bah represents.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خصوصیت نہیں کچھ اس میں اے کلیم تری 
شجر حجر بھی خدا سے کلام کرتے ہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        حجر: درخت اور پتھر۔ شجر،
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You are not singular in this O Kalim; trees and stones are also talking with God.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نیا جہاں کوئی اے شمع ڈھونڈیے کہ یہاں
ستم کش تپش ناتمام کرتے ہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O Candle! Search for a new world, because here* we are enduring tyrannies of the incomplete Love.
(Allusion to the verses of the Holy Qur'an which give this information, e.g. 62:1 and 64:1. This means that the Love of and approach to God is universally present in the nature of all His creation, even in inanimate objects.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بھلی ہے ہم نفسو اس چمن میں خاموشی 
کہ خوشنوائوں کو پابند دام کرتے ہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O Companions! Silence in this garden is good, as the melodious ones are kept in cages here.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        غرض نشاط ہے شغل شراب سے جن کی 
حلال چیز کو گویا حرام کرتے ہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Those whose purpose is pleasure from wine; are changing the lawful into the unlawful. 
(This verse refers to the two kinds of wine. One is the wine of the Love of God, which is not only lawful but essential for the fulfillment of the potentials of human life. The other one is the ordinary wine which people drink for pleasure, which is not only unlawful, but dulls those potentials.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بھلا نبھے گی تری ہم سے کیونکر اے واعظ! 
کہ ہم تو رسم محبت کو عام کرتے ہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        How can you and we reconcile, O preacher, as we are making the custom of Love universal!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        الہی سحر ہے پیران خرقہ پوش میں کیا! 
کہ اک نظر سے جوانوں کو رام کرتے ہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O God! What magic is concealed in the saints, clad in rags! That they subdue the youth with a single glance.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میں ان کی محفل عشرت سے کانپ جاتا ہوں 
جو گھر کو پھونک کے دنیا میں نام کرتے ہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I shudder at the pleasures of their assemblies; who are getting fame by destroying their homes.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہرے رہو وطن مازنی کے میدانو! 
جہاز پر سے تمھیں ہم سلام کرتے ہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مازني: اٹلی کا محب وطن راہنما جسے 1870 میں قید کر دیا اور وہ قید ہی میں مر گیا۔ یہ شعر غالبا بحری جہاز میں سفر کرتے ہوئے اٹلی کے میدانوں کو دیکھنے پر لکھے گئے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        May the meadows of the motherland* be ever flourishing; we are saluting you from the ship sailing away. 
(This expresses Allamah Iqbal's patriotism at the time of his departure from India. *The word Maazni, however, has been translated differently by Maulana Ghulam Rasool Mehar as quoted above with Urdu translation.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جو بے نماز کبھی پڑھتے ہیں نماز اقبال 
بلا کے دیر سے مجھ کو امام کرتے ہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When those un-accustomed to prayers assemble for one, Iqbal; calling me back from temple they make me their Imam.
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>