<Poem ID="38" Name="سرگزشت آدم" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="1a" SectionName="حصہ اول">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سنے کوئی مری غربت کی داستاں مجھ سے
بھلایا قصہ پیمان اولیں میں نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        پيمان اوليں: پہلا عہد، مراد ہے روز ازل۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE STORY OF MAN
Someone should hear the tale of my emigration.* I ignored the story of the primeval covenant** 
* Allusion to the Holy Qur’an 2:30-34, which describes the creation of Adam (A.S.) and his spouse and their transfer to the earth. **Allusion to the Holy Qur’an 3:81. This verse describes the pledge of the prophets to support every prophet of God, not to disregard the prophets who were to appear in the future, not to consider themselves exclusive custodians of the true Faith, and not to oppose the Truth. The pledge of a prophet is binding on his Ummah. However, the human race has betrayed this trust throughout its history except a few righteous people who believed in and testified to the Truth and the message of God as brought by the successive prophets.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لگی نہ میری طبیعت ریاض جنت میں
پیا شعور کا جب جام آتشیں میں نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جام آتشيں: تیز شراب کا پیالہ ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I did not feel attachment to the garden of Paradise, when I drank the fiery cup of Intellection.*
* The process of comprehension of all things as taught by God and is the criterion for Man's distinction from other of God's creation such as angels. Endowed with such a faculty Man was sent to the earth to populate it and maintain its order and beauty as created by God. According to the Holy Qur'an the emigration of at Adam A.S. was not a punishment but a responsibility bestowed by God on him for which he had been prepared and pre ordained.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رہی حقیقت عالم کی جستجو مجھ کو
دکھایا اوج خیال فلک نشیں میں نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        آسمان تک پہنچنے والا خیال۔ خيال فلک نشيں:
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I remained in pursuit of the Truth of the universe. I exhibited the excellence of elegant thoughts.
(Search for knowledge has been an inseparable part of Man's nature since his creation.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ملا مزاج تغیر پسند کچھ ایسا
کیا قرار نہ زیر فلک کہیں میں نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تغير پسند: بدلنے والا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I got such a change-loving temperament that I did not settle anywhere under the sky.* 
* Allusion to the constantly wandering nature of the human race throughout history. It also refers to the constantly changing thought of Man.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نکالا کعبے سے پتھر کی مورتوں کو کبھی
کبھی بتوں کو بنایا حرم نشیں میں نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Sometimes I removed the stone idols from the Ka'bah. Sometimes I established the idols in the Haram.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کبھی میں ذوق تکلم میں طور پر پہنچا
چھپایا نور ازل زیر آستیں میں نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Sometimes I arrived at Toor in my desire to speak and I concealed the Eternal Light up my sleeve.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کبھی صلیب پہ اپنوں نے مجھ کو لٹکایا
کیا فلک کو سفر، چھوڑ کر زمیں میں نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Sometimes I was nailed to the cross by my own clan. I rose to the Celestial world leaving the earth.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کبھی میں غار حرا میں چھپا رہا برسوں
دیا جہاں کو کبھی جام آخریں میں نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Sometimes I remained hidden in Cave of Hira for years. Sometimes I gave the world the last cup of Divine wine.*
* Allusion to the Last message of God to Man contained in the Holy Qur'an.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سنایا ہند میں آ کر سرود ربانی
پسند کی کبھی یوناں کی سر زمیں میں نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        سرود رباني: مراد ہے اللہ کا پیغام۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Coming to India I played the Divine Orchestra.* Sometimes I chose the land of Greece.
* Allusion to the large number of pious persons who preached Tawhid of God and that of mankind in India.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دیار ہند نے جس دم مری صدا نہ سنی
بسایا خطہء جاپان و ملک چیں میں نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When the people of India paid no heed to my call, I populated the countries of China and Japan.*
* Allusion to the persecution of Buddhists by the idol worshipping, caste-ridden and Brahman-dominated Hindu society, on account of which Buddhism which stood of Tawhid-i-Insaniyat and a caste less society all but disappeared from India. Buddhists migrated to and settled in far off places, including China and Japan.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بنایا ذروں کی ترکیب سے کبھی عالم
خلاف معنی تعلیم اہل دیں میں نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Sometimes I created the universe by combining elements; I did this against the meanings of priests' preaching.* 
* Allusion to the cosmology and astronomy as evolved in Europe during the Renaissance period. The findings of astronomy were considered heretic by the Roman Catholic Church under the influence of the Greek cosmology which had entered Christian thought and had assumed the position of being a part of the Christian religion.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لہو سے لال کیا سینکڑوں زمینوں کو
جہاں میں چھیڑ کے پیکار عقل و دیں میں نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        پيکار عقل و ديں: عقل اور دین کی جنگ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I stained hundreds of lands with blood when I started the war between Intellect and religion.* 
* Allusion to the persecution and bloodshed in the Christendom, due to the differences in belief with the Roman Catholic Church during and after the Reformation.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سمجھ میں آئی حقیقت نہ جب ستاروں کی
اسی خیال میں راتیں گزار دیں میں نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When I could not understand the reality of stars, I passed sleepless nights in this contemplation.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ڈرا سکیں نہ کلیسا کی مجھ کو تلواریں
سکھایا مسئلہ گردش زمیں میں نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The swords of the Church could not frighten me when I taught the theory of earth's revolution.*
* Allusion to Galileo, the famous Italian scientist who presented the theory of the spherical nature of the earth and its revolution round the sun as opposed to the Greek philosophy which taught the earth to be flat and the center of the universe. The Christian Church was so much influenced by Greek thought that they considered Greek philosophy to be part of the Christian faith. Hence, they declared Galileo a heretic.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کشش کا راز ہویدا کیا زمانے پر
لگا کے آئنہ عقل دور بیں میں نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ہويدا: ظاہر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I demonstrated the gravity's secret to the world using the far-sighted Intellect's mirror.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="31">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کیا اسیر شعاعوں کو، برق مضطر کو
بنادی غیرت جنت یہ سر زمیں میں نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I arrested radiations and the restless electricity. I made the earth the source of envy to Paradise.
(Allusion to the achievements of modern science and technology.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مگر خبر نہ ملی آہ! راز ہستی کی
کیا خرد سے جہاں کو تہ نگیں میں نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تہ نگيں: تسخیر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Ah! But I could not reach the Existence' secrets, though I made the world beautiful with my Intellect.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="35">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہوئی جو چشم مظاہر پرست وا آخر
تو پایا خانہء دل میں اسے مکیں میں نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مظاہر پرست: قدرت کے مظاہر کو پوجنے والے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When my materialistic eye opened I found Him lodged in my own heart.
(Translated by Dr. M.A.K. Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>