<Poem ID="07" Name="" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3b" SectionName="غزلیات 3">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تہ دام بھی غزل آشنا رہے طائران چمن تو کیا 
جو فغاں دلوں میں تڑپ رہی تھی، نوائے زیر لبی رہی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        نوائے زير لبي: وہ گانا جو لبوں تک نہ آیا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        No wonder if the garden birds remained fond of poetry even under the net; the lament fluttering in hearts as silent song remained.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ترا جلوہ کچھ بھی تسلی دل ناصبور نہ کر سکا 
وہ گریہ سحری رہا، وہی آہ نیم شبی رہی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Thy Effulgence could not satisfy the restless heart at all; the same dawn’s lament remained, the same midnight sighs remained.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہ خدا رہا نہ صنم رہے، نہ رقیب دیر حرم رہے 
نہ رہی کہیں اسد اللہی، نہ کہیں ابولہبی رہی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Neither God, nor idols nor the rivals of temple and the Haram remained.
Neither Ali’s prowess nor Abi Lahab’s infidelity remained.
(This is a sad commentary on the disappearance of religion and the Love of God from the present day Man and the goals of his life.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مرا ساز اگرچہ ستم رسیدئہ زخمہ ہائے عجم رہا 
وہ شہید ذوق وفا ہوں میں کہ نوا مری عربی رہی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Though my orchestra remained oppressed by Ajam’s plectrum; I am that martyr in fidelity’s cause whose song ever Arabic remained!
(Allama Iqbal was one of those reformers who tried to remove the effect of non-Islamic thoughts and ideologies (Greek, Zoroastrian, Chinese, Hindu) from Islamic thinking. This verse refers to this and says that in spite of the deep influence of non-Islamic ideologies on Islam he has continued to keep his thinking purely Islamic.)
[Translated by Dr M A K Khalil]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>