<Poem ID="34" Name="تصویر درد" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="1a" SectionName="حصہ اول">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہیں منت کش تاب شنیدن داستاں میری
خموشی گفتگو ہے بے زبانی ہے زباں میری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        منت کش تاب شنيدن: سننے کی طاقت کا احسان اٹھانے والی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My story is not indebted to the patience of being heard. My silence is my talk, my speechlessness is my speech.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ دستور زباں بندی ہے کیسا تیری محفل میں
یہاں تو بات کرنے کو ترستی ہے زباں میری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Why does this custom of silencing exist in your assembly? My tongue is tantalized to talk in this assembly.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اٹھائے کچھ ورق لالے نے، کچھ نرگس نے، کچھ گل نے
چمن میں ہر طرف بکھری ہوئی ہے داستاں میری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Some leaves were picked up by the tulip, some by the narcissus, some by the rose. My story is scattered around everywhere in the garden.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اڑالی قمریوں نے، طوطیوں نے، عندلبوں نے
چمن والوں نے مل کر لوٹ لی طرز فغاں میری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The turtle-doves, parrots, and nightingales pilfered away; the garden's denizens jointly robbed away my plaintive way.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ٹپک اے شمع آنسو بن کے پروانے کی آنکھوں سے
سراپا درد ہوں حسرت بھری ہے داستاں میری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O Candle! Drip like tears from the eye of the moth; head to foot pathos I am, full of longing is my story.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        الہی! پھر مزا کیا ہے یہاں دنیا میں رہنے کا
حیات جاوداں میری، نہ مرگ ناگہاں میری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        حيات جاوداں: ہمیشہ کی زندگی۔ 
مرگ ناگہاں: اچانک موت۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O God! What is the pleasure of living so in this world? Neither the eternal life, nor the sudden death is mine.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مرا رونا نہیں، رونا ہے یہ سارے گلستاں کا
وہ گل ہوں میں، خزاں ہر گل کی ہے گویا خزاں میری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This is not only my wailing, but is that of the entire garden; I am a rose, to me every rose' autumn is my autumn.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دریں حسرت سرا عمریست افسون جرس دارم
ز فیض دل تپیدنہا خروش بے نفس دارم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میری ذات تو ایک انتباہ کرنے والی گھنٹی کی طرح سے ہے اس لیے کہ جب تڑپتا ہوں تو اس کا اظہار بھی پورے جوش و خروش کے ساتھ اپنے اشعار میں کرتا ہوں، لیکن افسوس یہ ہے کہ انتباہ کے باوجود میری آہ و زاری پر کوئی کان نہیں دھرتا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ‘In this grief-stricken land, in life-long spell of the caravan's bell I am. From the palpitating heart's bounties the silent clamor I have.’
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ریاض دہر میں نا آشنائے بزم عشرت ہوں
خوشی روتی ہے جس کو، میں وہ محروم مسرت ہوں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In the world's garden unaware of pleasant company I am. Whom happiness still mourns, that hapless person I am.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مری بگڑی ہوئی تقدیر کو روتی ہے گویائی
میں حرف زیر لب، شرمندہء گوش سماعت ہوں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        حرف زير لب: جو بات اتنی آہستہ کہی جائے کہ سنائی نہ دے۔ 
شرمندہء گوش سماعت: جو بات کان تک نہ پہنچے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Speech itself sheds tears at my ill luck; silent word, longing for an eager ear I am.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پریشاں ہوں میں مشت خاک، لیکن کچھ نہیں کھلتا
سکندر ہوں کہ آئینہ ہوں یا گرد کدورت ہوں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I am a mere handful of scattered dust but I do not know whether Alexander or a mirror or just dust and scum I am.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ سب کچھ ہے مگر ہستی مری مقصد ہے قدرت کا
سراپا نور ہو جس کی حقیقت، میں وہ ظلمت ہوں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Despite all this my existence is the Divine Purpose; embodiment of light is whose reality, that darkness I am.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خزینہ ہوں، چھپایا مجھ کو مشت خاک صحرا نے
کسی کیا خبر ہے میں کہاں ہوں کس کی دولت ہوں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I am a treasure, concealed in the wilderness dust; no one knows where I am, or whose wealth I am?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نظر میری نہیں ممنون سیر عرصہء ہستی
میں وہ چھوٹی سی دنیا ہوں کہ آپ اپنی ولایت ہوں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ممنون: احسان مند۔ 
سير عرصہء ہستي: زندگی کے میدان کی سیر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My insight is not obligated to the stroll of existence that small world I am whose sovereign myself I am.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہ صہاہوں نہ ساقی ہوں نہ مستی ہوں نہ پیمانہ
میں اس میخا نہء ہستی میں ہر شے کی حقیقت ہوں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        صہبا: شراب۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Neither wine, nor cup-bearer, nor ecstasy, nor goblet I am; but the truth of everything in the existence' tavern I am.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="31">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مجھے راز دو عالم دل کا آئینہ دکھاتا ہے
وہی کہتا ہوں جو کچھ سامنے آنکھوں کے آتا ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My heart’s mirror shows me both worlds’ secrets; I relate exactly what I witness before my eyes.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عطا ایسا بیاں مجھ کو ہوا رنگیں بیانوں میں
کہ بام عرش کے طائر ہیں میرے ہم زبانوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I am bestowed with such speech among the elegant speakers that the birds of the Arsh’s roof are concordant with me.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="35">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اثر یہ بھی ہے اک میرے جنون فتنہ ساماں کا
مرا آ ئینہ دل ہے قضا کے راز دانوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جنون فتنہ ساماں: وہ دیوانگی جو فتنے اٹھائے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This also is an effect of my tumultuous love that my heart’s mirrors are Destiny’s confidante.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="37">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رلاتا ہے ترا نظارہ اے ہندوستاں! مجھ کو
کہ عبرت خیز ہے تیرا فسانہ سب فسانوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your spectacle makes me shed tears, O India! Your tales are admonitory among all the tales.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="39">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دیا رونا مجھے ایسا کہ سب کچھ دے دیا گویا
لکھا کلک ازل نے مجھ کو تیرے نوحہ خوانوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Conferring the wailing on me is like conferring everything; since eternity Destiny’s pen has put me where all your mourners are.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="41">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نشان برگ گل تک بھی نہ چھوڑ اس باغ میں گلچیں
تری قسمت سے رزم آرائیاں ہیں باغبانوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        رزم آرائياں: لڑائی کے لیے صفیں باندھنا ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O gardener do not leave even the rose-petals’ trace in this garden! By your misfortune war preparations are afoot among the gardeners.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="43">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چھپاکر آستیں میں بجلیاں رکھی ہیں گردوں نے
عنادل باغ کے غافل نہ بیٹھیں آشیانوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        عنادل:عندلیب کی جمع، بلبلیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The sky has kept thunderbolts concealed up its sleeve; garden’s nightingales should not slumber in their nests.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="45">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سن اے غافل صدا میری، یہ ایسی چیز ہے جس کو
وظیفہ جان کر پڑھتے ہیں طائر بوستانوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Listen to my call, O imprudent one! This is something which the birds in gardens are reciting like the daily prayers.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="47">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وطن کی فکر کر ناداں مصیبت آنے والی ہے
تری بربادیوں کے مشورے ہیں آسمانوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Think of the homeland, O ignorant one! Hard times are coming; conspiracies for your destruction are afoot in the heavens.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="49">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ذرا دیکھ اس کو جو کچھ ہو رہا ہے، ہونے والا ہے
دھرا کیا ہے بھلا عہد کہن کی داستانوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Pay attention to what is happening and what is going to happen; what good there is in repeating the tales of the old glories?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="51">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ خاموشی کہاں تک؟ لذت فریاد پیدا کر
زمیں پر تو ہو اور تیری صدا ہو آسمانوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        How long will you remain silent? Create taste for complaint! You should be on the earth, so your cries be in the heavens!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="53">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہ سمجھو گے تو مٹ جائو گے اے ہندوستاں والو
تمھاری داستاں تک بھی نہ ہو گی داستانوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You will be annihilated if you do not understand O people of India! Even your tales will disappear from the world’s chronicles. (Isn’t it more relevant for Muslims of today’s Pakistan than it was for Indian Muslims about a century ago?)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="55">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہی آئین قدرت ہے، یہی اسلوب فطرت ہے
جو ہے راہ عمل میں گام زن، محبوب فطرت ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اسلوب فطرت: قدرت کا دستور۔ 
گام زن: چلنے والا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This is the law of Nature, this is the order of Nature; those who tread dynamism’s path, are the darlings of Nature.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="57">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہویدا آج اپنے زخم پنہاں کر کے چھوڑوں گا
لہو رو رو کے محفل کو گلستاں کر کے چھوڑوں گا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ہويدا: ظاہر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I will surely exhibit all my hidden wounds today; I will surely change assembly to a garden with blood-mixed tears.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="59">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جلانا ہے مجھے ہر شمع دل کو سوز پنہاں سے
تری تاریک راتوں میں چراغاں کر کے چھوڑں گا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I have to light every heart’s candle with hidden pathos; I will surely create bright illumination in your darkness.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="61">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مگر غنچوں کی صورت ہوں دل درد آشنا پیدا
چمن میں مشت خاک اپنی پریشاں کر کے چھوڑں گا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        So that love-cognizant hearts be created like rose-buds; I will surely scatter around my handful of dust in the garden.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="63">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پرونا ایک ہی تسبیح میں ان بکھرے دانوں کو
جو مشکل ہے، تو اس مشکل کو آساں کر کے چھوڑوں گا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If stringing these scattered pearls in a single rosary is difficult, I will surely make this difficult task easy.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="65">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مجھے اے ہم نشیں رہنے دے شغل سینہ کاوی میں
کہ میں داغ محبت کو نمایاں کر کے چھوڑوں گا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O Companion! Leave me alone in the soul-searching effort as I will surely exhibit this mark of the ardent Love.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="67">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دکھا دوں گا جہاں کو جو مر ی آنکھوں نے دیکھا ہے
تجھے بھی صورت آئینہ حیراں کر کے چھوڑوں گا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I will show the world what my eyes have seen; I will surely make you also bewildered like a mirror.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="69">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جو ہے پردوں میں پنہاں، چشم بینا دیکھ لیتی ہے
زمانے کی طبیعت کا تقاضا دیکھ لیتی ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The discerning eye sees every thing covered in veils; it does see the exigencies of the nature of times.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="71">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کیا رفعت کی لذت سے نہ دل کو آشنا تو نے
گزاری عمر پستی میں مثال نقش پا تو نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مثال نقش پا: پاؤں کے نشان کی طرح یعنی پست۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You have not acquainted your heart with pleasure of dignity. You have passed your entire life in humility like foot-prints.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="73">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رہا دل بستہء محفل، مگر اپنی نگاہوں کو
کیا بیرون محفل سے نہ حیرت آشنا تو نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        دل بستہء محفل: محفل کا شیدائی۔ 
حيرت آشنا: حیرانی سے آشنائی رکھنے والا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You always remained entangled inside the assembly, but have not acquainted yourself with the world outside the assembly.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="75">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فدا کرتا رہا دل کو حسنیوں کی ادائوں پر
مگر دیکھی نہ اس آئینے میں اپنی ادا تو نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You have continued loving the charm of material beauties, but you have never seen your own elegance in this mirror.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="77">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تعصب چھوڑ ناداں! دہر کے آئینہ خانے میں
یہ تصویریں ہیں تیری جن کو سمجھا ہے برا تو نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Give up prejudice O imprudent one! In the world's glass housel they are your own pictures which you have taken as evil ones.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="79">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سراپا نالہ بیداد سوز زندگی ہو جا
سپند آسا گرہ میں باندھ رکھی ہے صدا تو نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        سپند آسا: حرمل کے دانے کی طرح کا جڑی بوٹی کا ایک بیج۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Become embodiment of the wail of tyranny of life's pathos! You have concealed sound in your pocket like the rue seed.
(Rue: This is a perennial evergreen European shrub, (Ruta graveolens, Family Rutaceae). Its seeds when roasted crack and jump. The metaphor is used for a person who is restless in pursuing a just cause.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="81">
      <Text Language="Original">
        صفائے دل کو کیا آرائش رنگ تعلق سے
کف آئینہ پر باندھی ہے او ناداں حنا تو نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Clarity of heart has nothing to do with external decorations O imprudent one! You have applied myrtle to mirror's palm.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="83">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زمیں کیا آسماں بھی تیری کج بینی پہ روتا ہے
غضب ہے سطر قرآں کو چلیپا کر دیا تو نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        چليپا: سولی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Not only the earth even the sky is bewailing your imprudence. It is outrageous that you have twisted the Qur'an's lines!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="85">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زباں سے گر کیا توحید کا دعوی تو کیا حاصل
بنایا ہے بت پندار کو اپنا خدا تو نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        بت پندار: تصوّر کا بت یعنی تصوّر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        To what purpose is your claim to monotheism! You have made the idol of self conceit your deity.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="87">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کنویں میں تو نے یوسف کو جو دیکھا بھی تو کیا دیکھا
ارے غافل! جو مطلق تھا مقید کر دیا تو نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مقيد: قید کیا ہوا۔
مطلق: پوری طرح آزاد۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What did you see even if you saw Yusuf in the well? O imprudent one! You have made the Absolute confined.
(This is an allusion to the Holy Qur'an 12:19. The traveler in the caravan who saw Yusuf A.S. saw him as a man, perhaps as a source of profit by sale on account of being extraordinarily handsome. However, he failed to recognize his greatness as a prophet of God, which is the highest stage to which a human being can rise. By extending the analogy ‘Allamah Iqbal means that we see only the ritual part in religion and do not comprehend religion's higher values, and by doing so we have reduced the absolute Truth of the Holy Qur’an to mere rituals.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="89">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہوس بالائے منبر ہے تجھے رنگیں بیانی کی
نصیحت بھی تری صورت ہے اک افسانہ خوانی کی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You are greedy of flowery style even at the pulpit. Your advice also is a form of story telling.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="91">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دکھا وہ حسن عالم سوز اپنی چشم پرنم کو
جو تڑپاتا ہے پروانے کو، رلواتا ہے شبنم کو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Show that universally illuminating Beauty to your weeping eye, which renders the moth highly agitated, which makes the dew weep like eye.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="93">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نرا نظارہ ہی اے بوالہوس مقصد نہیں اس کا
بنایا ہے کسی نے کچھ سمجھ کر چشم آدم کو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        بوالہوس: ہوس میں الجھا ہوا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Mere seeing is not its purpose O greedy one! Some One has made the human eye with some purpose.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="95">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اگر دیکھا بھی اس نے سارے عالم کو تو کیا دیکھا
نظر آئی نہ کچھ اپنی حقیقت جام سے جم کو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Even if he viewed the whole world, what did he see? Jam could not see his own reality in the wine cup.
(Jam: This is the abbreviation for the name of a famous Persian monarch, Jamshid who is believed to have possessed a wine cup in which he could see the whole world.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="97">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شجر ہے فرقہ آرائی، تعصب ہے ثمر اس کا
یہ وہ پھل ہے کہ جنت سے نکلواتا ہے آدم کو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Sectarianism is the tree, prejudice is its fruit. This fruit caused expulsion of A’dam (A.S.) from Paradise.
(This is an allusion to the Holy Qur'an 2:35-39. Iblis misguided A’dam A.S. to eat the forbidden fruit on account of his jealousy and prejudice against him. This prejudice of Iblis brought about the descent of A’dam A.S. from Paradise to earth, which is sometimes described as a punishment, based on the biblical story.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="99">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہ اٹھا جذبہء خورشید سے اک بر گ گل تک بھی
یہ رفعت کی تمنا ہے کہ لے اڑتی ہے شبنم کو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Not even a single rose-petal could rise by sun's attraction. It is the longing for elegance which raises the dew.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="101">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پھرا کرتے نہیں مجروح الفت فکر درماں میں
یہ زخمی آپ کر لیتے ہیں پیدا اپنے مرہم کو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مجروح الفت: محبت کے زخمی۔ 
فکر درماں: علاج کی فکر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Those wounded by Love do not wander in search of cure. These wounded ones themselves create their own cure.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="103">
      <Text Language="Original">
        محبت کے شرر سے دل سراپا نور ہوتا ہے
ذرا سے بیج سے پیدا ریاض طور ہوتا ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The heart gets complete illumination by the spark of Love. The Toor's flower bed is raised from the Love's small seed.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="105">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دوا ہر دکھ کی ہے مجروح تیغ آرزو رہنا
علاج زخم ہے آزاد احسان رفو رہنا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        آزاد احسان رفو: زخم سلوانے کا احسان نہ لینا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Every malady's cure is to remain wounded with Longing's sword. Wound's remedy is to remain free from obligation to stitching.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="107">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شراب بے خودی سے تا فلک پرواز ہے میری
شکت رنگ سے سیکھا ہے میں نے بن کے بو رہنا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        With the Bekhudi's wine up to the celestial world is my flight. From disappearance of colour I have learnt to remain fragrance.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="109">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تھمے کیا دیدئہ گریاں وطن کی نوحہ خوانی میں
عبادت چشم شاعر کی ہے ہر دم با وضو رہنا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="111">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بنائیں کیا سمجھ کر شاخ گل پر آشیاں اپنا
چمن میں آہ! کیا رہنا جو ہو بے آبرو رہنا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        To what purpose should we make our nest in the rose-branch? Ah! How can we live with constant disgrace in the garden?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="113">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جو تو سمجھے تو آزادی ہے پوشیدہ محبت میں
غلامی ہے اسیر امتیاز ماو تو رہنا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اسير امتياز ماو تو: ما و تو کے فرق کا قیدی، ایک دوسرے میں فرق کرنے والا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If you understand, independence is veiled in Love. Slavery is to remain imprisoned in the net of schism.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="115">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ استغنا ہے، پانی میں نگوں رکھتا ہے ساغر کو
تجھے بھی چاہیے مثل حباب آبجو رہنا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        استغنا: بے پروائی ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Contentment is what keeps the cup submerged in water. You should also remain like the bubble in the stream.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="117">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہ رہ اپنوں سے بے پروا، اسی میں خیر ہے تیری
اگر منظور ہے دنیا میں او بیگانہ خو رہنا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It is best for you not to remain indifferent to yours own O apathetic person! If you want to remain alive in the world.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="119">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شراب روح پرور ہے محبت نوع انساں کی
سکھایا اس نے مجھ کو مست بے جام و سبو رہنا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Soul-invigorating wine is the Love of the human race; it has taught me to remain ecstatic without the wine cup and the pitcher.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="121">
      <Text Language="Original">
        محبت ہی سے پائی ہے شفا بیمار قوموں نے
کیا ہے اپنے بخت خفتہ کو بیدار قوموں نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        بخت خفتہ: سوئی ہوئی قسمت۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Sick nations have been cured only through Love. Nations have warded off their adversity through Love.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="123">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بیابان محبت دشت غربت بھی، وطن بھی ہے
یہ ویرانہ قفس بھی، آشیانہ بھی، چمن بھی ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        دشت غربت: بے وطنی کا صحرا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The expanse of Love is at once foreign land and homeland; this wilderness is the cage, the nest, as well as the garden.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="125">
      <Text Language="Original">
        محبت ہی وہ منزل ہے کہ منزل بھی ہے، صحرا بھی
جرس بھی، کارواں بھی، راہبر بھی، راہزن بھی ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Love is the only stage which is the stage as well as the wilderness; it is the bell, the caravan, the leader as well as the robber.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="127">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مرض کہتے ہیں سب اس کو، یہ ہے لیکن مرض ایسا
چھپا جس میں علاج گردش چرخ کہن بھی ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Everybody calls it an illness, but it is such an illness in which the cure for all ills and misfortunes is concealed.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="129">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جلانا دل کا ہے گویا سراپا نور ہو جانا
یہ پروانہ جو سوزاں ہو تو شمع انجمن بھی ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The heart's pathos in a way is to become embodiment of Light; if this moth burns it is also the assembly's candle.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="131">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وہی اک حسن ہے، لیکن نظر آتا ہے ہر شے میں
یہ شیریں بھی ہے گویا بیستوں بھی، کوہکن بھی ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Beauty is just one but appears in everything; it is Shirin, the sky, as well as the mountain digger (Farhad is called here the mountain digger).
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="133">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اجاڑا ہے تمیز ملت و آئیں نے قوموں کو
مرے اہل وطن کے دل میں کچھ فکر وطن بھی ہے؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Distinction of sects and governments has destroyed nations. Is there any concern for the homeland in my compatriot's hearts?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="135">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سکوت آموز طول داستان درد ہے ورنہ
زباں بھی ہے ہمارے منہ میں اور تاب سخن بھی ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        سکوت آموز: خاموشی سکھانے والا، چپ کرا دینے والا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Prolonging the tale of my woes calls for silence, otherwise the tongue in my mouth as well as the ability to speak is.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="137">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نمیگردید کوتہ رشتہء معنی رہا کر دم
حکایت بود بے پایاں، بخاموشی ادا کر دم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مضمون کا سلسلہ مختصر نہ ہوتا تھا اس لیے میں نے اسے چھوڑ دیا، یہ ایسا بیان تھا جو لامحدود تھی، لہذا اس کے بغیر اور کوئی چارہ نہ تھا کہ خاموشی اختیار کر لوں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ‘Take not this meaningful tale as related by me is the story was endless, but related with silence is.’
[Translated by Dr M A K Khalil]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>