<Poem ID="17" Name="" BookID="08" BookName="زبورِعجم" SectionID="02" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہوس ہنوز تماشا گر جہانداری است
دگر چہ فتنہ پس پردہ ہای زنگاری است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Greed is acting still his play this world to dominate; what new turbulence, I pray, behind Heaven’s veil doth wait?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زمان زمان شکند آنچہ می تراشد عقل
بیا کہ عشق مسلمان و عقل زناری است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Now and now Mind breaketh through what idols it designed; come, for Love believeth true and infidel is Mind.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        امیر قافلہ ئی سخت کوش و پیہم کوش
کہ در قبیلۂ ما حیدری ز کراری است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Thou’rt the Leader of the train; then labour fiercely still; in our tribe, he rule doth gain who hath a warrior’s will.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تو چشم بستی و گفتی کہ این جہان خوٍابست
گشای چشم کہ این خواب خواب بیداری است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Thou hast closed thine eyes, and said, ‘The world’s a dream, no less’: Ope thine eyes; this dream-abed is all of wakefulness.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بخلوت انجمنی آفرین کہ فطرت عشق
یکی شناس و تماشا پسند بسیاری است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In thy solitude, alone, create a company: Love, that’s made to know the One, the many loves to see.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تپید یک دم و کردند زیب فتراکش
خوشا نصیب غزالی کہ زخم او کاری است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        But an instant quivered be ere to the saddle bound – fortunate gazelle, to he so singled out to wound!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بباغ و راغ گہر ہای نغمہ می پاشم
گران متاع و چہ ارزان ز کند بازاری است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In the garden and the mead I sow my jeweled air; precious goods, yet cheap indeed when there are none to hear.
(Translated by A.J. Arberry.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>