<Poem ID="14" Name="در حضور رسالت مآب" BookID="10" BookName="پس چہ بائد کرد" SectionID="01" SectionName="پس چہ بائد کرد">
  <Para Name="شب سہ اپریل 1936 کہ در دارالاقبال بہوپال بودم سید احمد خان را در خواب دیدم - فرمودند کہ از علالت خویش در حضور رسالت مآب عرض کن">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے تو ما بیچارگان را ساز و برگ
وا رہان این قوم را از ترس مرگ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تین اپریل 1936 کی شب جب میں دارالاقبال بھوپال میں تھا؛ میں نے خواب میں سید احمد خان کو دیکھا۔ انہوں نے مجھے فرمایا کہ اپنی بیماری کے بارہ میں حضور رسالت مآب (صلعم) سے عرض کر۔ 

آپ (صلعم) ہم بے چارہ لوگوں کی متاع ہیں؛ اس قوم (مسلم) کو موت کے خوف سے رہائی دلائیے ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        TO THE HOLY PROPHET S.A.W.
On the night of 3 April 1936, while I was staying in Dar al-Iqbal, Bhopal for rest and treatment I saw in a dream1Sayyid Ahmad Khan (on whom be God’s mercy). He advised me to place before the Holy Prophet the state of my health.

O you who are helper of helpless people like us, free this nation from the fear of death.

(Fear of death: Iqbal feels that this is the basic malady which destroys the moral strength of man; it is found when men are oriented towards this world and are unmindful of the next world. To be truly creative, one must cultivate indifference to death which in any case is inevitable.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سوختی لات و منات کہنہ را 
تازہ کردی کائنات کہنہ را
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        آپ (صلعم) نے پرانے لات و منات جلا دیے ؛ آپ (صلعم) نے قدیم دنیا کو جدید رنگ عطا فرمایا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You burnt down ancient idols and renewed the old universe.
(Ancient idols: Old social and economic order, old loyalties to others than God.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        در جہان ذکر و فکر انس و جان
تو صلوت صبح تو بانگ اذان
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        انسانوں اور جنوں کے جہان ذکر و فکر میں آپ (صلعم) صبح کی نماز ہیں، آپ (صلعم) بانگ آذان ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In this world where men and genii are engaged in meditation and devotion, you are the morning prayer and the call to prayer.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لذت سوز و سرور از لا الہ
در شب اندیشہ نور از لا الہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        سوز و سرور کی لذت لا الہ سے ہے؛ اندیشوں کی (تاریک) رات کو لا الہ کا نور روشن کرتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        La ilah is the essence of ardour and ecstasy; it sheds light in the dark night of doubts.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نے خدا ہا ساختیم از گاو و خر
نے حضور کاہنان افکندہ سر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        نہ ہم نے گائے اور گدھے کی پوجا کی؛ نہ کاہنوں کے سامنے اپنا سر جھکایا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        We did not make gods of cows and asses, nor did we bow our heads before soothsayers;
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نے سجودی پیش معبودان پیر
نے طواف کوشک سلطان و میر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        نہ پرانے خداؤں کو سجدہ کیا؛ نہ پادشاہوں اور امرا کے محلات کا طواف کیا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        We did not prostrate ourselves before ancient gods, nor did we walk in adoration round the palaces of kings and nobles;
(It was due to the revolutionary teaching of the Prophet that man was freed from bondage to other-than God.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        این ہمہ از لطف بی پایان تست
فکر ما پروردۂ احسان تست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        یہ سب آپ (صلعم) کے لطف بے پایاں کے طفیل ہے؛ ہمارے فکر نے آپ (صلعم) کے احسان سے پرورش پائی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This is all the result of your benevolence, our thought has been nourished by your kindness.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ذکر تو سرمایۂ ذوق و سرور
قوم را دارد بہ فقر اندر غیور
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        آپ (صلعم) کا ذکر ذوق و سرور (روحانیت) کا سرمایہ ہے؛ اس لیے قوم فکر میں غیور ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Our remembrance of you is the source of delight and rapture, and keeps the nation jealous of its honour even in poverty.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے مقام و منزل ہر راہرو
جذب تو اندر دل ہر راہرو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        آپ (صلعم) ہر سالک کے لیے مقام بھی ہیں اور منزل بھی ؛ ہر راہرو کے دل میں آپ (صلعم) ہی کا جذب ہے (جو اسے کشاں کشاں لیے جا رہا ہے)۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You are the goal of every wayfarer, the ideal that everyone aspires to attain.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ساز ما بی صوت گردید آنچنان
زخمہ بر رگھای او آید گران
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ہمارا ساز (حیات) اس طرح سے بے آواز ہو گیا ہے؛ کہ اسے اپنے تاروں پر مضراب کا لگانا بھی گراں گذرتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        We are a defunct musical instrument whose chords do not respond to the plectrum any longer.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        در عجم گردیدم و ہم در عرب
مصطفی نایاب و ارزان بولہب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میں عجم میں بھی پھرا ہوں اور عرب میں بھی ، بو لہب زیادہ ہیں اور آپ (صلعم) کے رنگ میں رنگے ہوئے لوگ نایاب ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I have wandered through lands, Arab and non-Arab, Bu Lahab is everywhere, Mustafa (S.A.W.) nowhere.
(Mustafa, the Chosen One, the Holy Prophet Muhammad (S.A.W.). Bu Lahab, lit. the father of flame, title given by the Qur’an to one of the Prophet’s uncles, who opposed his mission tooth and nail and, therefore, stands as a symbol of untruth and falsehood in Muslim literature, opposed to truth.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        این مسلمان زادۂ روشن دماغ
ظلمت آباد ضمیرش بی چراغ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        یہ روشن دماغ مسلمان زادہ اس کے ضمیر کی اندھیر نگری چراغ کے بغیر ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The so-called enlightened Muslim has no lamp to illumine the darkness of his heart. (Think of contemporary enlightened moderates.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        در جوانے نرم و نازک چون حریر
آرزو در سینۂ او زود میر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        یہ جوانی میں ریشم کی طرح نرم و نازک ہے؛ اس کے سینے میں کوئی مستقل آرزو نہیں پلتی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Even in his youth he is soft like silk, the desires in his heart are short-lived.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        این غلام ابن غلام ابن غلام
حریت اندیشۂ او را حرام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس غلام ابن غلام ابن غلام پر آزادی کی سوچ حرام ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He is a slave, son of a slave, son of a slave, who dare not think of freedom;
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مکتب از وی جذبۂ دین در ربود
از وجودش این قدر دانم کہ بود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جدید تعلیم نے اس سے دین کا جذبہ چھین لیا ہے؛ اس کے وجود کے متعلق میں اتنا جانتا ہوں کہ وہ کبھی تھا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The school has drained him of love for religion; all I can say about him is that he existed at one time;
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="31">
      <Text Language="Original">
        این ز خود بیگانہ این مست فرنگ
نان جو می خواہد از دست فرنگ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        یہ نوجوان اپنے آپ سے نا آشنا ہے اور افکار فرنگ میں مست ہے؛ یہ صرف اتنا چاہتا ہے کہ فرنگیوں سے اسے جو کی روٹی مل جائے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Forgetful of himself and enamoured of the West, he begs bread of barley from the hands of the Franks.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نان خرید این فاقہ کش با جان پاک
داد ما را نالہ ھای سوز ناک
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس فاقہ کش نے اپنی جان پاک دے کر روٹی خریدی؛ اس کے اس طرز عمل نے ہمیں دردناک نالوں پر مجبور کر دیا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This hungry man bartered away his soul for a piece of bread and caused us great grief thereby.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="35">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دانہ چین مانند مرغان سرا ست
از فضای نیلگون ناآشناست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        یہ پالتو پرندوں کی طرح (دوسروں کے ہاتھ سے) دانہ چگتا ہے اور فضائے نیلگوں کی پہنائیوں سے ناآشنا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He picks up grain from the ground like domestic birds and is unaware of the blue expanse of space.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="37">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آتش افرنگیان بگداختش
یعنی این دوزخ دگرگون ساختش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        فرنگیوں کی آگ نے اسے پگھلا دیا ہے؛ اس دوزخ نے اس کا حلیہ بگاڑ دیا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The fire of the Franks has melted him: this hell has totally transformed him.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="39">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شیخ مکتب کم سواد و کم نظر
از مقام او نداد او را خبر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        سکول کا استاد نالائق اور کم نظر ہے؛ اس نے اسے اس کے مقام سے آگاہ نہیں کیا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The teacher, lacking intellectual equipment and insight, did not inform him of his real stature.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="41">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مومن و از رمز مرگ آگاہ نیست
در دلش لا غالب الا اﷲ نیست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مومن ہے اور موت کی رمز سے آگاہ نہیں؛ اس کا دل لا غالب الا ﷲ سے خالی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He is a believer and yet unaware of the secret of Death. His heart does not believe in the truth that none is supreme except Allah.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="43">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تا دل او در میان سینہ مرد
می نیندیشد مگر از خواب و خورد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        چونکہ اس کے سینے کے اندر دل مر چکا ہے؛ اس لیے اسے کھانے اور سونے کے علاوہ اور کچھ سوجھتا نہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        As his heart has died in his breast, He does not think of anything except food and sleep.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="45">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بہر یک نان نشتر "لا و نعم"
منت صد کس برای یک شکم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ایک روٹی کی خاطر 'ہاں ' اور ' نہ' کے نشتر کھاتا ہے؛ ایک پیٹ کے لیے سینکڑوں انسانوں کی خوشامد کرتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        For one piece of bread, he bears the sting of yes and no, for a day’s meal he begs favours from a hundred persons.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="47">
      <Text Language="Original">
        از فرنگی می خرد لات و منات
مومن و اندیشہ او سومنات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        یہ فرنگی سے لات و منات خریدتا ہے؛ ہے مومن مگر اس کا دماغ سومنات بنا ہوا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He buys false gods from the Frank, though he is a believer, his mind is an idol-temple.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="49">
      <Text Language="Original">
        "قم باذنے" گوی و او را زندہ کن
در دلش "اﷲ ہو" را زندہ کن
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ' اٹھ میرے حکم سے' فرما کر اسے زندہ کر دیں؛ اس کے دل کو اللہ ہو سے زندگی عطا کر دیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Say: Get up at my order and quicken, revive in his heart the cry: Allah is He,
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="51">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ما ہمہ افسونی تہذیب غرب
کشتۂ افرنگیان بی حرب و ضرب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ہم سب مغرب کی تہذیب کے سحر زدہ ہیں؛ ہمیں افرنگیوں نے بغیر جدال و قتال کے قتل کر دیا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        We are all under the spell of Western culture, and are martyrs at the altar of the Franks.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="53">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تو از آن قومی کہ جام او شکست
وا نما یک بندہ اﷲ مست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        آپ (صلعم) کی زیر قیادت عربوں نے ان کا جام توڑا تھا؛ اس دور میں بھی ایک بندہء اللہ مست ظاہر کیجیے ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        From that nation whose cup is now broken, produce a single man who is God-intoxicated.
(Iqbal has repeated this idea in several of his books… he advises the new generation to do its best in seeking the right type of dervish who can help people in transforming the pattern of their life and the mode of their thought.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="55">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تا مسلمان باز بیند خویش را
از جہانے برگزیند خویش را
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تاکہ مسلمان پھر اپنے آپ کو پہچان لے پھر اپنے آپ کو پہچان لے اور سارے جہان سے برگزیدہ ہو جائے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        So that the Muslim should learn to see himself again and look upon himself as the cream of the whole world.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="57">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شہسوارا ! یک نفس در کش عنان
حرف من آسان نیاید بر زبان
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اے شہسوار ! ایک لمحے کے لیے اپنے گھوڑے کو روکیے؛ الفاظ آسانی سے میری زبان پر نہیں آ رہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O rider, rein in your horse for a moment; I cannot easily find words to express my mind.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="59">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آرزو آید کہ ناید تا بہ لب
می نگردد شوق محکوم ادب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        (میں سوچ رہا ہوں کہ) آرزو کو لب پر لاؤں یا نہ لاؤں ؛ میرا شوق حد ادب سے بڑھتا جا رہا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Should I give expression to my desire or not? Love is not restrained by etiquette;
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="61">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آن بگوید لب گشا اے دردمند
این بگوید چشم بگشا لب ببند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        آرزو کہتی ہے کہ لب کھول ؛ شوق کہتا ہے لب بند رکھ اور آنکھ کھول (اور آپ (صلعم)کے جمال کا نظارہ کر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Love says: O grieved one, open your lips; etiquette says: Open your eyes and keep your mouth shut.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="63">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گرد تو گردد حریم کائنات
از تو خواہم یک نگاہ التفات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کائنات آپ (صلعم) کے حریم ناز کا طواف کرتی ہے ؛ میں آپ (صلعم) کی ایک نگاہ التفات کا بھکاری ہوں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The whole universe revolves round you. I entreat a look of mercy from you.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="65">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ذکر و فکر و علم و عرفانم توئی
کشتی و دریا و طوفانم توئی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میرا ذکر و فکر اور علم و عرفان آپ (صلعم) ہی ہیں؛ میری کشتی بھی آپ (صلعم) ہیں، دریا بھی اور طوفان بھی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You are my dhikr and fikr, my knowledge and gnosis; you are my boat, river and storm.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="67">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آہوی زار و زبون و ناتوان
کس بہ فتراکم نبست اندر جہان
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میں ایک زار و زبوں اور نا تواں آہو ہوں؛ دنیا میں مجھے کسی نے اپنے فتراک میں نہیں باندھا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Not even a lean, frail and weak deer could anybody tie to my saddle-strap.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="69">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے پناہ من حریم کوی تو
من بہ امیدی رمیدم سوی تو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میں اس امید پر آپ (صلعم) کی طرف دوڑتا چلا آ رہا ہوں کہ آپ (صلعم) کے کوچے کے حریم میں مجھے پناہ مل جائے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My shelter is the sanctuary of your street: I turn towards you with a hopeful heart.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="71">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آن نوا در سینہ پروردن کجا
وز دمی صد غنچہ وا کردن کجا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اپنے سینے کے اندر نوا کی پرورش کرنا اور اپنی ایک پھونک سے سینکڑوں غنچوں (قلوب) کو کھلا دینا ، یہ بات کہاں ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        No longer am I able to nourish song in the breast and open a hundred buds with a single breath.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="73">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نغمۂ من در گلوی من شکست
شعلہ ئی از سینہ ام بیرون نجست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میرا نغمہ میرے گلے میں ٹوٹ گیا ہے؛ شعلہ میرے سینے سے باہر نہیں لپکا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My song has broken in my throat; the flame no longer comes out of my breast.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="75">
      <Text Language="Original">
        در نفس سوز جگر باقی نماند
لطف قرآن سحر باقی نماند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میری آواز میں سوز جگر باقی نہیں رہا؛ صبح کی تلاوت کا مزہ جاتا رہا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My words have lost their fervour and I have ceased to enjoy my morning recitation of the Quran.
(These lines refer to the malady from which Iqbal was suffering during the last days of his life. His vocal chord was badly affected as a result of which he could not sneak and hence was unable to recite the Qur’an in a loud melodious voice as he used to do.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="77">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نالہ ئے کو می نگنجد در ضمیر
تا کجا در سینہ ام ماند اسیر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        وہ نالہ جو میرے ضمیر کے اندر نہیں سماتا ؛ کب تک میرے سینے میں مقید رہے گا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        How could songs remain confined within my breast; songs that could hardly be contained in the mind.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="79">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یک فضای بیکران میبایدش
وسعت نہ آسمان میبایدش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اسے ایک فضائے بیکراں چاہیے؛ اسے نو آسمان کی وسعت چاہیے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        They need a limitless expanse; the whole breadth of nine heavens.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="81">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آہ زان دردی کہ در جان و تن است
گوشۂ چشم تو داروی من است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ہائے وہ درد جو میرے جان و تن میں ہے؛ اس کا علاج صرف آپ (صلعم) کا گوشہء چشم ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Ah! The pain that afflicts my body and soul, a look from your eyes is my remedy.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="83">
      <Text Language="Original">
        در نسازد با دواہا جان زار 
تلخ و بویش بر مشامم ناگوار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میری جان زار دواؤں کو پسند نہیں کرتی ؛ ان کا ذائقہ تلخ اور بو ناگوار ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        These medicines no longer agree with this weak soul of mine: Their bitter taste and smell are unbearable.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="85">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کار این بیمار نتوان برد پیش
من چو طفلان نالم از داروی خویش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس بیمار کی بیماری کم نہیں ہوتی؛ (کیونکہ) میں بچوں کی طرح اپنی دوا سے نالاں رہتا ہوں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My condition cannot be improved by these medicines: At the very sight of them I cry like a child.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="87">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تلخی او را فریبم از شکر
خندہ ہا در لب بدوزد چارہ گر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        دوائی کی کڑواہٹ کو چینی ملا کر فریب دیتا ہوں؛ طبیب میری اس حرکت پر اپنی مسکراہٹ کو چھپاتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I deceive myself by sugar-coating them, the physicians laugh at me in their sleeves.
(These lines refer to Iqbal’s utter helplessness and disgust at continued illness and the use of bitter dozes of medicine which is Iqbal put it, are a challenge to man’s fine tastes.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="89">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چون بصیری از تو میخواہم گشود
تا بمن باز آید آن روزی کہ بود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میں بھی بصیری کی طرح آپ (صلعم) سے شفا کا خواہاں ہوں؛ تاکہ میرے گذشتہ (صحت مند) دن واپس آ جائیں ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I seek relief from you as did Busairi and pray that old days may come back again.
(Busairi, an Arab poet whose poem in praise of the Prophet is very famous and is known as Qasidah Burdah. It is related that the poet had an attack of paralysis during which be wrote this poem. He is said to have recovered miraculously.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="91">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مہر تو بر عاصیان افزونتر است
در خطا بخشی چو مہر مادر است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        گناہ گاروں پر آپ (صلعم) کی شفقت زیادہ ہوتی ہے؛ اور خطائیں معاف کرنے میں آپ (صلعم) کی شفقت ماں کی شفقت کی مانند ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your kindness to sinners is great: It is forgiving like a mother’s love.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="93">
      <Text Language="Original">
        با پرستاران شب دارم ستیز
باز روغن در چراغ من بریز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میرا مقابلہ رات کے پرستاروں سے ہے؛ میرے چراغ میں اور روغن ڈال دیجیے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I am battling against the worshippers of darkness, replenish my lamp with oil.
Lovers of night: (worshippers of darkness) refers to people who stand for untruth, falsehood, kufr. To fight the worshippers of night it is necessary to dispel darkness through light. But the light from his (i.e. Iqbal’s) lamp is very dim due to lack of oil. ‘Oil’ stands for material as well as spiritual resources.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="95">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے وجود تو جہان را نو بھار
پرتو خود را دریغ از من مدار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        آپ (صلعم) کا وجود مبارک جہاں کے لیے نو بہار ہے؛ اپنے عکس جمال سے مجھے محروم نہ رکھیے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your existence lends lustre to the world; do not deny my soul a reflection from it.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="97">
      <Text Language="Original">
        "خود بدانی قدر تن از جان بود
قدر جان از پرتو جانان بود"
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        آپ (صلعم) جانتے ہیں کہ بدن کی قدر جان سے ہے؛ اور جان کی قدر محبوب کے عکس جمال سے ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You know that value of the body is due to soul, and the value of the soul is due to the reflection of the Beloved!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="رومی">
    <Verse ID="99">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تا ز غیر اﷲ ندارم ہیچ امید
یا مرا شمشیر گردان یا کلید
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کیونکہ میں غیر اللہ سے کوئی امید نہیں رکھتا ؛ اس لیے مجھے یا شمشیر بنا دیجیے، یا کلید۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I have no hope from other-than-God; make of me either a sword or a key.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="101">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فکر من در فہم دین چالاک و چست
تخم کرداری ز خاک من نرست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میرا فکر دین کے فہم میں تیز اور چست ہے؛ (لیکن) میری خاک بدن سے عمل کا بیج نہیں پھوٹتا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I am quick in understanding the significance of religion; the seed of action, however, has never sprouted out of my dust.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="103">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تیشہ ام را تیز تر گردان کہ من
محنتی دارم فزون از کوہکن
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میرے تیشے کو اور تیز کر دیجیے کیونکہ مجھے فرہاد سے زیادہ محبت در پیش ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Sharpen my axe all the more, for I have a task greater than that of Farhad.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="105">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مومنم، از خویشتن کافر نیم
بر فسانم زن کہ بد گوھر نیم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میں صاحب ایمان ہوں کافر نہیں ہوں؛ مجھے سان پر لگایئے ، میں اصل فولاد کی شمشیر ہوں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I am a believer and I do not deny myself; test me on the touchstone, you will not find me false metal.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="107">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گرچہ کشت عمر من بیحاصل است
چیزکی دارم کہ نام او دل است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اگرچہ میری عمر کی کھیتی بے حاصل ہے؛ مگر میں ایک چھوٹی سی چیز رکھتا ہوں جس کا نام دل ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Although the field of my life has remained barren, yet I possess a tiny thing called ‘heart’.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="109">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دارمش پوشیدہ از چشم جہان
کز سم شبدیز تو دارد نشان
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میں نے اسے لوگوں کی نظر سے پنہاں رکھا ہوا ہے؛ کیونکہ اس پر آپ (صلعم) کے اسپ مشکیں کے سم کا نشان موجود ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I keep it hidden from the eye of the people, for it bears the marks of your horse’s hoof.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="111">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بندہ ئی را کو نخواہد ساز و برگ
زندگانی بی حضور خواجہ مرگ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        یہ بندہ جو دینوی ساز و سامان کا خواہاں نہیں؛ آقا (صلعم) کی حضوری کے بغیر زندگی موت کے برابر ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        For a slave who does not seek material means life without you is as good as death.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="113">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے کہ دادی کرد را سوز عرب
بندۂ خود را حضور خود طلب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        آپ (صلعم) نے کردوں کو عربوں کا سوز عطا فرمایا؛ اپنے اس (ہندی) غلام کو بھی اپنے حضور میں طلب فرمائیے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You blessed a Kurd with fluency in the Arabic tongue, call your slave into your presence:
(It is related that a Kurd had great love for the Prophet One day be felt grieved at being unacquainted with Arabic, the language of his beloved. How could he claim, he thought, to love the Prophet when he could not speak to him in his own language? Next day he was miraculously granted know-ledge of Arabic.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="115">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بندہ ئی چون لالہ داغی در جگر
دوستانش از غم او بی خبر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        یہ بندہ اپنے جگر میں گل لالہ سا داغ رکھتا ہے؛ اس کے دوست اس کے غم سے بے خبر ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A slave who bears like the tulip a mark on his heart, which his friends are unaware of.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="117">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بندہ ئی اندر جھان نالان چو نے
تفتہ جان از نغمہ ہای پی بہ پے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        یہ بندہ دنیا میں نے کی مانند نالاں رہتا ہے؛ پے بہ پے نغموں نے اس کی جان کو جلا دیا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A slave who weeps like a reed, his soul almost burnt through constant songs.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="119">
      <Text Language="Original">
        در بیابان مثل چوب نیم سوز
کاروان بگذشت و من سوزم ہنوز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میں بیابان میں پڑی نیم جلی لکڑی کی مانند ہوں؛ کاروان جا چکا ہے ، اور میں ابھی تک جل رہا ہوں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I am like a half-burnt piece of wood in the desert, the caravan has passed on, and I am still burning.
(When a caravan stays at some place for the night, people light fire. Burning wood thus symbolises the presence of a caravan. Next day when the caravan moves away, the burning wood reminds other people coming after-wards that some caravan had camped there.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="121">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اندرین دشت و دری پہناوری
بو کہ آید کاروانے دیگری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میں اس وسیع و عریض بیاباں میں پڑا جل رہا ہوں؛ اس امید پر کہ شاید ایک اور کاروان آ جائے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In this vast world perhaps another caravan one day appear.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="123">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جان ز مہجوری بنالد در بدن
نالۂ من واے من اے واے من!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میرے بدن میں میری جان ہجر کی وجہ سے فریاد کناں ہے؛ یہ (بے اثر) نالہ! افسوس ، صد افسوس۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My soul, afflicted with separation, cries within me: O my lament! Ah me! Ah me!
(Translated by B A Dar)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>