<Poem ID="07" Name="ایک پہاڑ اور گلہری" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="1a" SectionName="حصہ اول">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کوئی پہاڑ یہ کہتا تھا اک گلہری سے
تجھے ہو شرم تو پانی میں جا کے ڈوب مرے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A MOUNTAIN AND A SQUIRREL
A mountain was saying this to a squirrel: ‘Commit suicide if you have self-respect.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ذرا سی چیز ہے، اس پر غرور، کیا کہنا
یہ عقل اور یہ سمجھ، یہ شعور، کیا کہنا!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You are insignificant, still so arrogant, how strange! You are neither wise, nor intelligent! Not even shrewd!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خدا کی شان ہے ناچیز چیز بن بیٹھیں
جو بے شعور ہوں یوں باتمیز بن بیٹھیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It is strange when the insignificant pose as important! When the stupid ones like you pose as intelligent!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تری بساط ہے کیا میری شان کے آگے
زمیں ہے پست مری آن بان کے آگے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You are no match in comparison with my splendour; even the earth is low compared with my splendour.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جو بات مجھ میں ہے، تجھ کو وہ ہے نصیب کہاں
بھلا پہاڑ کہاں جانور غریب کہاں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The grandeur of mine does not fall to your lot; the poor animal cannot equal the great mountain!’
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کہا یہ سن کے گلہری نے، منہ سنبھال ذرا
یہ کچی باتیں ہیں دل سے انھیں نکال ذرا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        On hearing this, the squirrel said: ‘Hold your tongue! These are immature thoughts; expel them from your heart!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جو میں بڑی نہیں تیری طرح تو کیا پروا
نہیں ہے تو بھی تو آخر مری طرح چھوٹا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I do not care if I am not large like you! You are not a pretty little thing like me.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہر ایک چیز سے پیدا خدا کی قدرت ہے
کوئی بڑا، کوئی چھوٹا، یہ اس کی حکمت ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Everything shows the Omni-potence of God; some large, some small, is the wisdom of God.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بڑا جہان میں تجھ کو بنا دیا اس نے
مجھے درخت پہ چڑھنا سکھا دیا اس نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He has created you large in the world and He has taught me climbing large trees.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        قدم اٹھانے کی طاقت نہیں ذرا تجھ میں
نری بڑائی ہے، خوبی ہے اور کیا تجھ میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You are unable to walk a single step. Only large size! What other greatness have you?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جو تو بڑا ہے تو مجھ سا ہنر دکھا مجھ کو
یہ چھالیا ہی ذرا توڑ کر دکھا مجھ کو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If you are large show me some of the skills I have; show me how you break this beetle nut as I can.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہیں ہے چیز نکمی کوئی زمانے میں
کوئی برا نہیں قدرت کے کارخانے میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Nothing is useless in this world. Nothing is bad in God's creation.
[Translated by M.A.K.Khalil]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>