<Poem ID="07" Name="فلسفہ غم" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="میاں فضل حسین صاحب بیرسٹرایٹ لاء لاہور کے نام">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گو سراپا کیف عشرت ہے شراب زندگی
اشک بھی رکھتا ہے دامن میں سحاب زندگی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE PHILOSOPHY OF GRIEF
Though the wine of life is the embodiment of pleasure; the cloud of life carries tears also in its skirt.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        موج غم پر رقص کرتا ہے حباب زندگی
ہے 'الم' کا سورہ بھی جزو کتاب زندگی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The bubble of life dances on the wave of grief; ‘Alam’s’ Surah* is also part of the Book of Life.
(Allusion to the Holy Qur’an: 94: 5-6.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ایک بھی پتی اگر کم ہو تو وہ گل ہی نہیں
جو خزاں نادیدہ ہو بلبل، وہ بلبل ہی نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        By losing even a single petal the rose ceases to be rose; if the nightingale is unaware of autumn it ceases to be nightingale.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آرزو کے خون سے رنگیں ہے دل کی داستاں
نغمہ انسانیت کامل نہیں غیر از فغاں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The heart’s story is coloured with Longing’s blood; the human music is incomplete without lament’s cry.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دیدہ بینا میں داغ غم چراغ سینہ ہے 
روح کو سامان زینت آہ کا آئینہ ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        For the discerning eye the grief’s scar is insight; for the soul sigh’s mirror is beauty’s accompaniment.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حادثات غم سے ہے انساں کی فطرت کو کمال
غازہ ہے آئینہء دل کے لیے گرد ملال
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Incidents of grief give perfection to human nature; the dust of anguish is rouge for the heart’s mirror.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        غم جوانی کو جگا دیتا ہے لطف خواب سے
ساز یہ بیدار ہوتا ہے اسی مضراب سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Youth is awakened from sleep’s pleasure by grief; this orchestra wakes up with this plectrum alone.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        طائر دل کے لیے غم شہپر پرواز ہے
راز ہے انساں کا دل غم انکشاف راز ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        For the heart’s bird grief is the strongest feather. The human heart is a secret whose disclosure is grief.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        غم نہیں غم، روح کا اک نغمہء خاموش ہے
جو سرود بربط ہستی سے ہم آغوش ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Grief is not distress, but is the soul’s silent song, which is locked in the embrace of existence’ harp.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شام جس کی آشنائے نالہء 'یا رب' نہیں
جلوہ پیرا جس کی شب میں اشک کے کوکب نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Whose night is not acquainted with ‘Ya Rab’s’* plaint! Whose night does not manifest the stars of tears!
(This expression is used by true believers in the hour of their distress and trial.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جس کا جام دل شکست غم سے ہے ناآشنا
جو سدا مست شراب عیش و عشرت ہی رہا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Whose heart’s cup does not know breaking with grief! Who always remained ecstatic with pleasure and exhilaration!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہاتھ جس گلچیں کا ہے محفوظ نوک خار سے
عشق جس کا بے خبر ہے ہجر کے آزار سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The gardener whose hand is safe from thorn’s tip; whose love is unaware of the pathos of separation.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کلفت غم گرچہ اس کے روز و شب سے دور ہے
زندگی کا راز اس کی آنکھ سے مستور ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Though grief’s affliction is far from his life; the secret of life is concealed from his eyes.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے کہ نظم دہر کا ادراک ہے حاصل تجھے
کیوں نہ آساں ہو غم و اندوہ کی منزل تجھے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O the one with comprehension of life’s affairs! Why should not grief and sorrow be easy for you?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے ابد کے نسخہ دیرینہ کی تمہید عشق
عقل انسانی ہے فانی، زندہء جاوید عشق
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Love is the introduction to the Eternity’s old treatise; human intellect is mortal but Love is eternally alive.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="31">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عشق کے خورشید سے شام اجل شرمندہ ہے
عشق سوز زندگی ہے، تا ابد پائندہ ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The evening of death is no match to the sun of Love. Love is the warmth of life and lasts till eternity.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رخصت محبوب کا مقصد فنا ہوتا اگر 
جوش الفت بھی دل عاشق سے کر جاتا سفر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If annihilation had been intended for the departed beloved; Love’s zeal would have also departed from the Lover’s heart.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="35">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عشق کچھ محبوب کے مرنے سے مر جاتا نہیں
روح میں غم بن کے رہتا ہے، مگر جاتا نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Love does not die by the beloved’s death; it stays in the soul as grief but does not die.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="37">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے بقائے عشق سے پیدا بقا محبوب کی
زندگانی ہے عدم ناآشنا محبوب کی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Lover’s immortality is the beloved’s immortality; the beloved’s life is unacquainted with mortality.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="39">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آتی ہے ندی جبین کوہ سے گاتی ہوئی
آسماں کے طائروں کو نغمہ سکھلاتی ہوئی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The spring comes singing from the mountain top teaching the art of singing to the birds of the sky.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="41">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آئنہ روشن ہے اس کا صورت رخسار حور
گر کے وادی کی چٹانوں پر یہ ہو جاتا ہے چور
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Its mirror is bright like the Houri’s cheek, but falling on valley’s rocks it is shattered.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="43">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہر جو تھی، اس کے گوہر پیارے پیارے بن گئے
یعنی اس افتاد سے پانی کے تارے بن گئے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The river’s pearls ever more beautiful became; that is by this fall they water’s stars became.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="45">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جوئے سیماب رواں پھٹ کر پریشاں ہو گئی
مضطرب بوندوں کی اک دنیا نمایاں ہو گئی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The river of flowing mercury spread and became scattered; a whole entire world of restless drops became manifest;
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="47">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہجر، ان قطروں کو لیکن وصل کی تعلیم ہے
دو قدم پر پھر وہی جو مثل تار سیم ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        But separation is the training for reunion to those drops, after a while the same river is running like a silver string.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="49">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ایک اصلیت میں ہے نہر روان زندگی
گر کے رفعت سے ہجوم نوع انساں بن گئی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The flowing river of life is of the same origin; falling from high it became the concourse of humanity.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="51">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پستی عالم میں ملنے کو جدا ہوتے ہیں ہم
عارضی فرقت کو دائم جان کر روتے ہیں ہم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In the depths of this world we part to reunite, but we cry considering temporary parting as permanent.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="53">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مرنے والے مرتے ہیں لیکن فنا ہوتے نہیں
یہ حقیقت میں کبھی ہم سے جدا ہوتے نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Though the dead do die they do not perish; really they do not get separated from us.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="55">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عقل جس دم دہر کی آفات میں محصور ہو
یا جوانی کی اندھیری رات میں مستور ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When Intellect be surrounded in worldly calamities, or when it be besieged in the dreary night of youth;
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="57">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دامن دل بن گیا ہو رزم گاہ خیر و شر
راہ کی ظلمت سے ہو مشکل سوئے منزل سفر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When the heart’s skirt be the battle field of good and evil; when journey to the goal be difficult in road’s darkness;
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="59">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خضر ہمت ہو گیا ہو آرزو سے گوشہ گیر
فکر جب عاجز ہو اور خاموش آواز ضمیر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When the Khizar of courage may be resigned from longing; when Intellect be helpless and conscience a silent voice;
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="61">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وادی ہستی میں کوئی ہم سفر تک بھی نہ ہو
جادہ دکھلانے کو جگنو کا شرر تک بھی نہ ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When not a single fellow-traveler be in the vale of life; when not even fire-fly’s spark to show the way there be.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="63">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مرنے والوں کی جبیں روشن ہے اس ظلمات میں
جس طرح تارے چمکتے ہیں اندھیری رات میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The foreheads of the dead brighten up in this darkness as stars are shining in the darkness of the night.
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>