<Poem ID="41" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="02" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ڈھونڈ رہا ہے فرنگ عیش جہاں کا دوام 
وائے تمنائے خام، وائے تمنائے خام!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The West seeks to make life a perpetual feast; a wish in vain, in vain, in vain!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پیر حرم نے کہا سن کے مری روئداد 
پختہ ہے تیری فغاں، اب نہ اسے دل میں تھام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Aware of my state, my spiritual guide assures me; thy ecstasy has reached the plenitude of its power.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تھا ارنی گو کلیم، میں ارنی گو نہیں 
اس کو تقاضا روا، مجھ پہ تقاضا حرام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Moses asked for a Divine glimpse, but I do not: The demand was right for him; but is forbidden for me.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گرچہ ہے افشائے راز، اہل نظر کی فغاں 
ہو نہیں سکتا کبھی شیوہ رندانہ عام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The plaint of the men of God betrays a suppressed secret; but the ways of the men of God are not meant for all.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حلقہ صوفی میں ذکر، بے نم و بے سوز و ساز
میں بھی رہا تشنہ کام، تو بھی رہا تشنہ کام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Zikr in the Sufis’ circle was devoid of ecstasy, I remained unsatisfied, and so was everyone.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عشق تری انتہا، عشق مری انتہا 
تو بھی ابھی ناتمام، میں بھی ابھی ناتمام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Love is thy goal, and mine, too, but both are so far novices on the path of love.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آہ کہ کھویا گیا تجھ سے فقیری کا راز 
ورنہ ہے مال فقیر سلطنت روم و شام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Alas! Thou hast betrayed the secret of a faqir, though a faqir has wealth more than a king of men. 
(Translated by Naim Siddiqui)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>