<Poem ID="50" Name="نکتہ توحید" BookID="03" BookName="ضربِ کلیم" SectionID="01" SectionName="اسلام اور مسلمان">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بیاں میں نکتہ توحید آ تو سکتا ہے 
ترے دماغ میں بت خانہ ہو تو کیا کہیے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        UNITY OF GOD
The subtle point in God's Oneness hid with ease in words we can explain, but what about your mind unsound that brims with myths and idols vain?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وہ رمز شوق کہ پوشیدہ لاالہ میں ہے 
طریق شیخ فقیہانہ ہو تو کیا کہیے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Elder of the Shrine has traits that smack of Jurist's faith and creed; much thirst for view 'No god but He', among his fellows cannot breed.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سرور جو حق و باطل کی کارزار میں ہے 
تو حرب و ضرب سے بیگانہ ہو تو کیا کہیے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        None can appraise the glee one gets, when war is on 'twixt good and bad; he who can't inflict deadly blows and strokes in war is never glad.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جہاں میں بندہ حر کے مشاہدات ہیں کیا 
تری نگاہ غلامانہ ہو تو کیا کہیے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Observations made by free born men in world with marvels so replete to those who own the glance of thralls none can such wonders 'fore them repeat.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مقام فقر ہے کتنا بلند شاہی سے 
روش کسی کی گدایانہ ہو تو کیا کہیے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A Darvesh holds a loftier rank than a monarch who wears a crown; there is no cure for such a man, who, like paupers, has sunk down.
(Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>