<Poem ID="14" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="01" SectionName="حصہ اول">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اپنی جولاں گاہ زیر آسماں سمجھا تھا میں 
آب و گل کے کھیل کو اپنا جہاں سمجھا تھا میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        آب و گل: پانی اور مٹی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Methought my racing field lay under the skies; this plaything of water and clay, I regarded as my world.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بے حجابی سے تری ٹوٹا نگاہوں کا طلسم 
اک ردائے نیلگوں کو آسماں سمجھا تھا میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ردائے نیلگوں: نیلی چادر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Thy unveiling broke the spell of searching glances; I mistook this blue vault for Heaven.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کارواں تھک کر فضا کے پیچ و خم میں رہ گیا 
مہروماہ و مشتری کو ہم عناں سمجھا تھا میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Sun, the Moon, the Stars, methought, would keep me company, fatigued; they dropped out in the twists and turns of space:
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عشق کی اک جست نے طے کر دیا قصہ تمام 
اس زمین و آسماں کو بے کراں سمجھا تھا میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        بے کراں: کنارے کے بغیر، لا محدود۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        One leap by Love ended all the pother, I fondly imagined, the earth and sky were boundless.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کہہ گئیں راز محبت پردہ دار یہاے شوق 
تھی فغاں وہ بھی جسے ضبط فغاں سمجھا تھا میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My silent secrecies of love were but effusions in disguise; what I had believed to be restraint, betrayed my passion even more.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تھی کسی درماندہ رہرو کی صداے درد ناک 
جس کو آواز رحیل کارواں سمجھا تھا میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        آواز رحیل کارواں: قافلے کی روانگی کا اعلان۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What I esteemed as the clarion call of the caravan was but the plaintive cry of a traveller, weary and forlorn.
(Translated by S.A. Rahman)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>