<Poem ID="13" Name="" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="1b" SectionName="غزلیات 1">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مجنوں نے شہر چھوڑا تو صحرا بھی چھوڑ دے
نظارے کی ہوس ہو تو لیلی بھی چھوڑ دے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Majnun abandoned habitation, you should abandon wilderness also; if there be ambition for Sight, you should abandon Lailah also.
(Majn’on gave up living in human habitations and started roaming about in the wilderness. The Lover of God is advised to abandon wilderness also. This is so because it is immaterial for a Lover of God whether he lives in habitations or in the wilderness as God is independent of space and time and is omni-present. The Lover will find Him anywhere and everywhere provided his Love is selfless and sincere.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        واعظ! کمال ترک سے ملتی ہے یاں مراد
دنیا جو چھوڑ دی ہے تو عقبی بھی چھوڑ دے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O preacher! Perfection of abandonment attains the objective, as you have abandoned the world, abandon the Hereafter also.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تقلید کی روش سے تو بہتر ہے خودکشی
رستہ بھی ڈھونڈ، خضر کا سودا بھی چھوڑ دے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Suicide is better than the way of taqlid; seek your own path, abandon the love of Khizar also. 
(Taqlid: Literally it means following the accepted path. In ‘Allamah Iqbal’s terminology it means blind following of traditions. Khizar (A.S.): He is believed to guide the wayfarers who have gone astray.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مانند خامہ تیری زباں پر ہے حرف غیر
بیگانہ شے پہ نازش بے جا بھی چھوڑ دے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Like the pen the un-Islamic message is on your tongue; abandon unjustified pride in the un-Islamic objects also.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لطف کلام کیا جو نہ ہو دل میں درد عشق
بسمل نہیں ہے تو تو تڑپنا بھی چھوڑ دے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Theology is no pleasure if heart does not have Love’s pathos; if you are not the Wounded, you should abandon fluttering also.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شبنم کی طرح پھولوں پہ رو، اور چمن سے چل
اس باغ میں قیام کا سودا بھی چھوڑ دے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Weep like the dew on flowers and leave the garden; abandon the desire of staying in this garden also.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے عاشقی میں رسم الگ سب سے بیٹھنا
بت خانہ بھی، حرم بھی، کلیسا بھی چھوڑ دے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The custom of Love is abandonment of all; abandon temple, mosque, and church also.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سوداگری نہیں، یہ عبادت خدا کی ہے
اے بے خبر! جزا کی تمنا بھی چھوڑ دے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This is not business, this is ibadat of God! O ignorant one, abandon the longing for reward also.
(Ibadat: This is wrongly understood to mean ‘worship’ and formal prayers and the latter are considered to be the climax of piety. This word is derived from the root abd, which literally means a ‘slave’ or ‘servant’. In the Holy Qur’an abd designates the nature, status and destiny of Man, that he is a slave of God and is neither Divine nor has any share in the Powers and Rights of God. According to this his destiny is Abdiyat, obudiyat, or bondage. He is required to be a perfect servant or ‘abd’. In Persian and Urdu ‘abdiyat’ is more commonly used than obudiyat. Bandah and bandagi are the Persian equivalents of abd and obudiyat respectively. Ibadat really means obedience with absolute self-surrender and humility. It includes worship, reverence, and prayer but is really comprised of honesty and sincerity to God in all phases and departments of life. The second line of this verse means that only the Love of God should be the motive force for a Mu’min’s virtuous actions. It is not a trade in which one offers his merchandise and expects a reward as its price. Only that piety is acceptable to God which is performed without the desire for sawab.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اچھا ہے دل کے ساتھ رہے پاسبان عقل
لیکن کبھی کبھی اسے تنہا بھی چھوڑ دے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It is good to guard Intuition with Intellect, but sometimes you should let it go alone also.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جینا وہ کیا جو ہو نفس غیر پر مدار
شہرت کی زندگی کا بھروسا بھی چھوڑ دے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What life is that which is dependent on others? Abandon dependence on the life of fame also.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شوخی سی ہے سوال مکرر میں اے کلیم!
شرط رضا یہ ہے کہ تقاضا بھی چھوڑ دے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Repeated request is a kind of boldness! O Kalim the condition for approbation is to abandon urging also.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        واعظ ثبوت لائے جو مے کے جواز میں
اقبال کو یہ ضد ہے کہ پینا بھی چھوڑ دے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        As the preacher brought proof in support of wine, Iqbal insists that he should abandon drinking also.
(It is not clear whether the proof is meant for the virtues of abstention from drinking or that of drinking. In either case the verse shows strong doubts in the mind of Allamah Iqbal about the sincerity of the half-baked Ulama.)
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>