<Poem ID="22" Name="قندہار و زیارت خرقہ مبارک" BookID="10" BookName="پس چہ بائد کرد" SectionID="01" SectionName="پس چہ بائد کرد">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        قندہار آن کشور مینو سواد
اہل دل را خاک او خاک مراد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        SEEING PROPHET’S GARB AT QANDHAR
Qandhar, that place of paradisiac charm, its dust the heart’s desire of men of heart.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رنگ ہا، بوہا، ہواہا، آب ہا
آب ہا تابندہ چون سیماب ہا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        These hues, scents, waters! These waters glittering like mercury!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لالہ ھا در خلوت کہسار ہا
نارھا یخ بستہ اندر نارہا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Tulips in the coign of the mountains; fires frozen within pomegranates.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کوی آن شہر است ما را کوی دوست
ساربان بر بند محمل سوی دوست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Its streets the streets of the friend for us, O camel-driver, set the litter for the beautiful one.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        می سرایم دیگر از یاران نجد
از نوائی، ناقہ را آرم بہ وجد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I sing again of the mates of Najd and bring the dromedary into ecstasy with my chant.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="غزل">
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        از دیر مغان آیم بی گردش صہباست
در منزل لا بودم از بادہ الا مست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Az I come from the temple of Magians intoxicated with the passing of wine. I was inebriate with the wine of Illa (Affirmation) in the state of La (Negation).
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دانم کہ نگاہ او ظرف ہمہ کس بیند
کرد است مرا ساقی از عشوہ و ایما مست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I know his eyes perceives the capacity of every person, the saqi has made me ecstatic by his blandishment and beckoning.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وقت است کہ بگشایم میخانۂ رومی باز
پیران حرم دیدم در صحن کلیسا مست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It is time I should again open the tavern of Rumi.I have seen the custodian of the Harem intoxicated in the churchyard.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        این کار حکیمی نیست دامان کلیمی گیر
صد بندۂ ساحل مست یک بندہ دریا مست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It is not the work of a philosopher, catch hold of the hem of a Moses, who conversed with God. A hundred persons enrapt with the shore and but one tipsy with the river.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دل را بہ چمن بردم از باد چمن افسرد
میرد بخیابانہا این لالۂ صحرا مست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I took my heart to the garden where it became numb with the breeze it dies in a park, this tulip stimulated by the desert.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        از حرف دلاویزش اسرار حرم پیدا
دی کافرکی دیدم در وادی بطحا مست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        From his delightful words, the secrets of the Harem shine out. I saw a mini-infidel yesterday intoxicated in the valley of Bat’ha;
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سینا است کہ فاران است یارب چہ مقام است این
ہر ذرہ خاک من چشمی است تماشا مست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Is this Sinai or Faran? O God, what is this place? Each particle of my dust is an eye lost in beholding.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خرقۂ آن "برزخ لایبغیان"
دیدمش در نکتۂ "لی خرقتان"
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The garment of that Interstise that cannot be crossed; I behold in his saying: For me two garbs: Continence and Jihad.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دین او آئین او تفسیر کل
در جبین او خط تقدیر کل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Both his Faith and system expositions of the whole; on his forehead inscribed the destiny of all.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عقل را او صاحب اسرار کرد
عشق را او تیغ جوھر دار کرد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Intellect made him knower of secrets and love a matchless sword.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="31">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کاروان شوق را او منزل است
ما ہمہ یک مشت خاکیم او دل است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He is the destination of the caravan of ardour, we are but a pinch of dust and he the heart thereof.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آشکارا دیدنش اسرای ماست
در ضمیرش مسجد اقصای ماست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        To see his outside is our Asra, and in his inner self is our Aqsa.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="35">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آمد از پیراہن او بوی او
داد ما را نعرہ اﷲ ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        From his garment I sensed his perfume; he gave us the shout of Allah-hu.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="37">
      <Text Language="Original">
        با دل من شوق بی پروا چہ کرد
بادۂ پر زور با مینا چہ کرد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What did my reckless love do to my heart? Whatever tempestuous wine to the flask.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="39">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رقصد اندر سینہ از زور جنون
تا ز راہ دیدہ میآید برون
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It leapt in the breast because of wild rapture till it rushed out of the eyes.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="41">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گفت "من جبریلم و نور مبین"
پیش ازین او را ندیدم اینچنین
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It said: I am Gabriel and radiant light; I never saw him like this before.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="43">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شعر رومی خواند و خندید و گریست
یا رب این دیوانۂ فرزانہ کیست؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It recited lines from Rumi, laughed and wept, O God! Who is this Sage gone wild?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="45">
      <Text Language="Original">
        در حرم با من سخن زندانہ گفت
از می و مغ زادہ و پیمانہ گفت
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It talked to me so volubly in the sanctuary, talking of wine, Magian pages and wine cups.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="47">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گفتمش این حرف بیباکانہ چیست
لب فرو بند این مقام خامشی ست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I asked it what audacious words these be; close your lips for this is a solemn occasion.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="49">
      <Text Language="Original">
        من ز خون خویش پروردم ترا
صاحب آہ سحر کردم ترا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I have nurtured you with by blood and made you fit for raising a morning sigh.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="51">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بازیاب این نکتہ را اے نکتہ رس
عشق مردان ضبط احوال است و بس
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Note again this point you who understand, the love of disciplined lovers is naught but restraint.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="53">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گفت عقل و ہوش آزار دل است
مستی و وارفتگی کار دل است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It said: Reason and restraint are a blight for the heart, ecstasy and frenzy are its nature.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="55">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نعرہ ہا زد تا فتاد اندر سجود
شعلۂ آواز او بود او نبود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It raised shouts upon shouts till it fell into prostration; there was only the flame of its voice but itself no more!
(Translated by B A Dar)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>