<Poem ID="19" Name="کرمک شبتاب" BookID="07" BookName="پیامِ مشرق" SectionID="02" SectionName="افکار">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یک ذرہ بی مایہ متاع نفس اندوخت
شوق این قدرش سوخت کہ پروانگی آموخت
پہنای شب افروخت
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE GLOW-WORM
A tiny atom found itself a living thing by chance. Aquiver with life’s ardour it began a moth-like dance, and set aglow the night’s expanse.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        واماندہ شعاعی کہ گرہ خورد و شرر شد
از سوز حیاتست کہ کارش ہمہ زر شد
دارای نظر شد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A dormant sunbeam re-awoke and shot up with a dash. The alchemy of life converted it to gold from trash came vision to it in a flash.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پروانۂ بیتاب کہ ہر سو تک و پو کرد
بر شمع چنان سوخت کہ خود را ہمہ او کرد
ترک من و تو کرد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A restlessly aflutter moth was bold enough to dart into the candle’s flame, became one with its fiery heart, and ceased to be a thing apart.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یا اخترکی ماہ مبینی بہ کمینی
نزدیک تر آمد بتماشای زمینی
از چرخ برینے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A moon-faced starlet, living in its isolated bower, came out of it in order to look closer at the lower planet than from its high tower.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یا ماہ تنک ضو کہ بیک جلوہ تمام است
ماہی کہ برو منت خورشید حرام است
آزاد مقام است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A gently beaming moonlet told itself that it would owe its light no longer to the bounty of the sun, and so wherever it likes it can go.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے کرمک شب تاب سراپای تو نور است
پرواز تو یک سلسلۂ غیب و حضور است
آئین ظہور است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O glow-worm, your whole body is made of the stuff of light. A sequence of its intermittent flashes is your flight – thus flit things in and out of sight.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        در تیرہ شبان مشعل مرغان شب استی
آن سوز چہ سوز است کہ در تاب و تب استی
گرم طلب استی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You are a torch for birds that in the evening fly to rest; but what and whence this restless passion burning in your breast, which keeps you in unceasing quest?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مائیم کہ مانند تو از خاک دمیدیم
دیدیم تپیدیم، ندیدیم تپیدیم
جائی نرسیدیم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Like you we entered into this world by earth’s dusty door. We saw and tossed about; we did not see, and tossed about the more. O never did we reach the shore.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گویم سخن پختہ و پروردہ و تہ دار
از منزل گم گشتہ مگو پای برہ دار
این جلوہ نگہ دار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I speak from ripe experience and true is what I say, don’t think of lost horizons and be steadfast on your way: Keep shining like this while you may. 
(Translated by M. Hadi Husain)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>