<Poem ID="11" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="01" SectionName="حصہ اول">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تجھے یاد کیا نہیں ہے مرے دل کا وہ زمانہ 
وہ ادب گہ محبت، وہ نگہ کا تازیانہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Have You forgotten then my heart of old, that college of Love, that whip that bright eyes hold?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ بتان عصر حاضر کہ بنے ہیں مدرسے میں 
نہ ادائے کافرانہ، نہ تراش آزرانہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The school-bred demi-goddesses of this age lack the carved grace of the old pagan mold!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہیں اس کھلی فضا میں کوئی گوشہء فراغت 
یہ جہاں عجب جہاں ہے، نہ قفس نہ آشیانہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This is a strange world, neither cage nor nest, with no calm nook in all its spacious fold.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رگ تاک منتظر ہے تری بارش کرم کی 
کہ عجم کے مے کدوں میں نہ رہی مے مغانہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The vine awaits Your bounteous rain: no more is the Magian wine in Persia’s taverns sold.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مرے ہم صفیر اسے بھی اثر بہار سمجھے 
انھیں کیا خبر کہ کیا ہے یہ نوائے عاشقانہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My comrades thought my song were of spring’s kindling: How should they know what in Love’s notes is told?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مرے خاک و خوں سے تونے یہ جہاں کیا ہے پیدا 
صلہ شہید کیا ہے، تب و تاب جاودانہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تب و تاب جاودانہ: ہمیشہ رہنے والی چمک دمک۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Out of my flesh and blood You made this earth; its quenchless fever the martyr’s crown of gold.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تری بندہ پروری سے مرے دن گزر رہے ہیں 
نہ گلہ ہے دوستوں کا، نہ شکایت زمانہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My days supported by Your alms, I do not complain against my friends, or the times scold.
(Translated by Victor Kiernan)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>