<Poem ID="21" Name="حدی" BookID="07" BookName="پیامِ مشرق" SectionID="02" SectionName="افکار">
  <Para Name="نغمۂ ساربان حجاز">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ناقۂ سیار من
آہوے تاتار من
درہم و دینار من
اندک و بسیار من
دولت بیدار من
تیزترک گام زن منزل ما دور نیست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        SONG OF THE HIJAZI CAMEL-DRIVER
My fleet-footed dromedary, my doe of the Tartar country, O my riches, O my money, O my entire patrimony, O my fortune, O my plenty! Quicken your pace just a little; journey’s end is not far off.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دلکش و زیباستی
شاہد رعناستی
روکش حوراستی
غیرت لیلاستی
دختر صحراستی
تیزترک گام زن منزل ما دور نیست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O you bright and beautiful thing, you are lovely, you are charming, O you houri of my dreaming, you, the Layla of whom bards sing, you, the desert’s sprightly offspring! Quicken your pace just a little; journey’s end is not far off.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        در تپش آفتاب
غوطہ زنے در سراب
ہم بہ شب ماہتاب
تند روی چون شہاب
چشم تو نادیدہ خواب
تیزترک گام زن منزل ما دور نیست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When the sun of noontide blazes, you dive into clear mirages; and in moonlit nights’ bright reaches you flash as a comet flashes with an eye that never closes! Quicken your pace just a little; journey’s end is not far off.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لکہ ابر روان
کشتی بی بادبان
مثل خضر راہ دان
بر تو سبک ہر گران
لخت دل ساربان
تیزترک گام زن منزل ما دور نیست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Like the clouds a constant roamer; sailless boat with sand for river; born path-knower like a Khizr, carrier who does not murmur, darling of the camel-driver! Quicken your pace just a little; journey’s end is not far off.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سوز تو اندر زمام
ساز تو اندر خرام
بی خورش و تشنہ کام
پا بہ سفر صبح و شام
خستہ شوی از مقام
تیزترک گام زن منزل ما دور نیست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In your rein is stimulation; travel is your inspiration; with a very scanty ration, you are night and day in motion, never resting at one station! Quicken your pace just a little; journey’s end is not far off.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="31">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شام تو اندر یمن
صبح تو اندر قرن
ریگ درشت وطن
پای ترا یاسمن
اے چو غزال ختن
تیزترک گام زن منزل ما دور نیست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If at dusk you are in Yaman, then at dawn you are in Qaran. Rough sand of your native region is to your feet soft like jasmine. O you fleet gazelle of Khotan! Quicken your pace just a little; journey’s end is not far off.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="37">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مہ ز سفر پا کشید
در پس تل آرمید
صبح ز مشرق دمید
جامۂ شب بر درید
باد بیابان وزید
تیزترک گام زن منزل ما دور نیست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Now the moon, her journey over, goes into her sand hill shelter, dawns a new day, so much brighter than the moon for all her splendour. Blows the desert wind of summer! Quicken your pace just a little; journey’s end is not far off.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="43">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نغمۂ من دلگشای
زیر و بمش جانفرای
قافلہ ہا را درای
فتنہ ربا فتنہ زای
اے بہ حرم چہرہ سای
تیزترک گام زن منزل ما دور نیست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Lively is the song that I sing; lively, but full of foreboding – for the caravan a warning that the hour has struck for starting. Kisser of the Haram’s paving! Quicken your pace just a little; journey’s end is not far off.
(Translated by M. Hadi Husain)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>