<Poem ID="01" Name="بحق دل بند و راہ مصطفی رو" BookID="11" BookName="ارمغانِ حجاز" SectionID="03" SectionName="حضور ملت">
  <Para Name="(01)">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بہ منزل کوش مانند مہ نو
درین نیلی فضا ہر دم فزون شو
مقام خویش اگر خواہی درین دیر
بحق دل بند و راہ مصطفی رو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        للہ تعالے سے دل لگا اور حضور اکرم (صلعم) کی اتباع کر۔ 

نئے چاند کی مانند منزل تک پہنچنے کی کوشش کر؛ اس فضائے نیلگوں میں ہر دم بڑھتا جا۔
اگر تو بتخانہ (ءدنیا) میں اپنا مقام پانا چاہتا ہے؛ تو اللہ تعالے سے دل لگا اور حضور اکرم (صلعم) کی اتباع کر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Tie your heart with Allah Ta’ala and follow the Holy Prophet (S.A.W.).

Be nearer to the aim like a moon new; seek the higher heights with efforts anew.
A place in this lane if you wish to make; make a tie with God in the Prophet’s wake.*
* Basic ideas Seek a tete-a-tete with God in the Prophet’s wake. The ultimate aim of each faithful (without distinction of cast and creed) is tete-a-tete with God or the Wisal-i-Ilahi, for which Raza-j-Ilahi is a must. The Namaz, Roza and Zikr are the necessary vehicles through which we strive to achieve the ultimate aim of Visal-j-llahi. (Tete.a-tete of God is more appropriate than union here). Raza-i-Ilahi, means) pleasure of God.)
[Translated by Qazi Ahdul Kabir]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(02)">
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چو موج از بحر خود بالیدہ ام من
بخود مثل گہر پیچیدہ ام من
از آن نمرود با من سر گران است
بہ تعمیر حرم کوشیدہ ام من
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میں موج کی مانند اپنے سمندر سے اٹھا ہوں؛ اور موتی کی مانند اپنی نشو و نما پر متوجہ رہا ہوں۔
 نمرود اس لیے مجھ سے ناراض ہے ؛ کہ میں حرم کی تعمیر میں کوشاں ہوں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My self’s own sea gave a rise to me; it sharpen’d my wits like pearls in sea.
On me that ‘Nimrod’ is boiling with rage; I’m trying to build up ‘Harem’s’ image.
(Bakhud paecheedgan; According to a contemporary scholar it means to fortify and cultivate one’s own self; strong thing of one’s own ego. I also understand its meanings are self seeing (though literal meanings are self-writhing’s Self coiling viz, the philosophers and other thinkers.)
[Translated by Qazi Ahdul Kabir]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(03)">
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بیا ساقی بگردان ساتگین را
بیفشان بر دو گیتی آستین را
حقیقت را بہ رندی فاش کردند
کہ ملا کم شناسد رمز دین را
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ساقی ! اٹھ اور جام مے آگے بڑھا؛ دونوں جہانوں پر اپنا دامن جھاڑ دے۔
(اس دور میں) مجھ جیسے رند پر حقیقت فاش کی گئی ہے؛ کیونکہ ملّا راز دین سمجھنے سے قاصر ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Come O’ bearer* and move the cup of Wine**; and leave the worlds both under long veils line***.
He raised all the curtains before this sot; the codes of His Path the ‘Mullah’ knew not.
* Bearer means Iqbal’s own preceptor and religious guide. **Wine among mystics of Indo-Pakistan and Persia is the terminology used for spiritual guidance. The mystics of East are wont to talk in esoterics to avoid an air of pride and boasts. ***I have added long veils line (after leave the worlds both) to convery the true sense of this Persian phrase. Iqbal clarifies this sense in line 3 of this quatrain. (viz. curtains of pride, pomp and show, criticism, jealousy etc. common with entire mankind).
[Translated by Qazi Ahdul Kabir]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(04)">
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بیا ساقی نقاب از رخ برافکن
چکید از چشم من خون دل من
بہ آن لحنی کہ نہ شرقی نہ غربی است
نوائی از مقام لاتخف زن
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ساقی ! اٹھ اپنے چہرے سے نقاب اٹھا (اور دیکھ) ؛ میرے دل کا خون میری آنکھوں سے ٹپک رہا ہے۔
اور مقام سے اس لے میں؛ نوا ریز ہو ، جو نہ شرقی ہے ، نہ غربی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Aur moqam ‘la-takhaf’ sey iss la’ey mein; nawa-raiz ho, jo nah Sharqi hai, nah Gharbi.] 
Come O’ bearer and raise the veils aside; cause my heart’s blood’ dripping from the eyes side.
From a tone which gives no East or. West trace; send a ‘no fear note’ from the ‘no fear place.’*
* Send a ‘La takhaf’ note from its place, was the best literal translation (La-takhaf means – fear not) as it was addressed to Moses by God.)
[Translated by Qazi Ahdul Kabir]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(05)">
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        برون از سینہ کش تکبیر خود را
بخاک خویش زن اکسیر خود را
خودی را گیر و محکم گیر و خوش زی
مدہ در دست کس تقدیر خود را
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اپنے سینہ سے (نعرہء) تکبیر باہر نکال (زبان پر لا) ؛ اور اپنی (اس) اکسیر کو اپنی خاک پر ڈال۔ 
خودی کو پکڑ ، مضبوطی سے پکڑ اور خوش رہ ؛ اپنی تقدیر کسی اور کے ہاتھ میں نہ دے (خود اپنی تقدیر بن)۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Raise from thy bosom a ‘Call of God Great’; hit thy own exir on thy dusty fate.
Gaurd thy ego ever, lead a life nice; to none give thy luck at any great price.*
* ‘From thy own dust (dusty fate) make thy own nexir’: A call of God Great; viz. Takbir of Arabic.
[Translated by Qazi Ahdul Kabir]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(06)">
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مسلمان از خودی مرد تمام است
بخاکش تا خودی میرد غلام است
اگر خود را متاع خویش دانی
نگہ را جز بخود بستن حرام است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مسلمان ، خودی (کے استحکام) سے انسان کامل بنتا ہے؛ اس کے بدن میں خودی مر جائے، تو وہ غلام ہے۔ 
اگر تو اپنے آپ کو اپنی متاع جانے ؛ (تو یہ نکتہ سمجھ جائے کہ) اپنے علاوہ کسی اور پر توجہ مرکوز کرنا حرام ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Agar tou apney aap ko apni mata’a jaaney; (tou yeh noktah samajh jaa’ey keh) apney allawah kissi aur per tawajoh markooz karna haraam hai.]
From self a Muslim is man perfect; he is slave when it dies in heart in fact.
If you take thy ‘self’, ‘a priceless’ lot; to look save Thee is a tabood thought.
[Translated by Qazi Ahdul Kabir]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(07)">
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مسلمانان کہ خود را فاش دیدند
بہ ہر دریا چو گوھر آرمیدند
اگر از خود رمیدند اندرین دیر
بجان تو کہ مرگ خود خریدند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        وہ مسلمان جنہوں نے اپنے آپ کو پوری طرح دیکھ لیا؛ وہ ہر دریائے (مصیبت) میں گوہر کی مانند پر سکون رہے ۔
لیکن اگر وہ اس بتخانہ (ء دہر) میں اپنے آپ سے گریزاں رہیں؛ تو تیری جان کی قسم ! انہوں نے (اپنے ہاتھوں ) اپنی موت خریدی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        As long the Muslim, in self can peep; like pearls they rest in the oceans deep.
From ego if you ran in this fane; your own death you buy for life’s bargain.*
* Basic thought: Thus the Ego’s price he forgot when he took his own life with own hands then.)
[Translated by Qazi Ahdul Kabir]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(08)">
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گشودم پردہء از روی تقدیر
مشو نومید و راہ مصطفی گیر
اگر باور نداری آنچہ گفتم
ز دین بگریز و مرگ کافری میر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میں نے تقدیر کے چہرے سے پردہ اٹھا دیا ہے ؛ نا امید نہ ہو اور حضور اکرم (صلعم) کی راہ اختیار کر۔
لیکن اگر تجھے میری بات کا اعتبار نہیں؛ تو اسلام چھوڑ اور کافر کی موت مر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The veils of thy fortune lo! I ope; take the Prophet’s path give up no hope.
If you believe not whatever I say; give up the faith and die in Kafir’s way.
[Translated by Qazi Ahdul Kabir]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(09)">
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بہ ترکان بستہ درہا را گشادند 
بنای مصریان محکم نھادند
تو ہم دستی بدامان خودی زن
کہ بے او ملک و دین کس را ندادند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ترکوں کے لیے بند دروازے کھول دیے گئے؛ مصریوں کی بنیاد مستحکم کر دی گئی۔
تو بھی خودی کا دامن پکڑ ؛ اس کے بغیر (کبھی ) کسی کو ملک و دین نہیں ملا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Now all the shut doors for Turks are ope; the Egypt’s base would be firm I hope.
You give a rap too at the Ego’s door; none knew without it his faith and land’s lore1
* The poet is explaining the condition of Turks during 1922 AD., when they were surrounded all over by difficulties and so the Egyptians slater on. ‘Land’ and ‘Fold’; country and faith.)
[Translated by Qazi Ahdul Kabir]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(10)">
    <Verse ID="37">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہر آن قومی کہ می ریزد بہارش 
نسازد جز بہ بوہای رمیدہ
ز خاکش لالہ می روید ولیکن
قبائے دارد از رنگ پریدہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ہر (زوال پذیر) قوم، جس کی بہار جا چکی ہو ؛ انہی خوشبوؤں کو سینے سے لگائے رکھتی ہے جو ختم ہو چکی ہے۔
اس خاک سے (گل) لالہ اگتا تو ہے، مگر ، اس کی قبائے (سرخ) کا رنگ اڑا ہوا ہوتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A nation whose spring falls to decay; she always craves for the good old days.
A poppy grows though from her dusty gems; it also takes a gown of fading stems.*
* Here poppy means a young man (of that nation), when every young man of a nation falls a prey to disappointment and makes no efforts for his revival. As such the nations can regain their lost prestige by efforts alone.) 
[Translated by Qazi Ahdul Kabir]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(11)">
    <Verse ID="41">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خدا آن ملتی را سروری داد
کہ تقدیرش بدست خویش بنوشت
بہ آن ملت سروکاری ندارد
کہ دہقانش برای دیگران کشت
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        للہ تعالے صرف اسی قوم کو سرداری عطا فرماتے ہیں ؛ جو خود اپنے ہاتھ سے اپنی تقدیر لکھتی ہے۔
اللہ تعالے ایسی قوم سے کوئی سروکار نہیں رکھتے؛ جس کا دہقان دوسروں کے لیے کھیتی بوتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        God gave that nation a sway o’er lands; who shaped her fortunes with her hands.
With that nation he keeps no links; whose farmer tills for other’s drinks. 
[Translated by Qazi Ahdul Kabir]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(12)">
    <Verse ID="43">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ز رازی حکمت قرآن بیاموز
چراغی از چراغ او بر افروز
ولی این نکتہ را از من فرا گیر
کہ نتوان زیستن بے مستی و سوز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        (بے شک) رازی سے قرآن پاک کی حکمت سیکھ؛ اس کے چراغ سے اپنا چراغ جلا۔
لیکن مجھ سے یہ نکتہ سمجھ لے؛ کہ مستی ء سوز (عشق) کے بغیر زندہ نہیں رہا جا سکتا ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        From Razi thus learn the Quran’s insight; from his lamp he lit up his own lamp’s light.
But a point from me you must learn hence; that can’t be life, lacking flame and trance*.
* No life is life without the Prophet’s flame of love burning in his heart.
[Translated by Qazi Ahdul Kabir]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>