<Poem ID="05" Name="" BookID="11" BookName="ارمغانِ حجاز" SectionID="04" SectionName="حضور عالم انسانیت">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دجود است اینکہ بینی یا نمود است
حکیم ما چہ مشکلہا گشود است
کتابی بر فن غواص بنوشت
ولیکن در دل دریا نبود است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        یہ عالم جو تو دیکھ رہا ہے (حقیقی) وجود رکھتا ہے یا صرف یوں دکھائی دیتا ہے، ہمارے مغربی فلسفہ نے کیا مشکلات پیدا کر رکھی ہیں۔
اس نے غوّاصی کے فن پر کتاب تو لکھ دی ، مگر اسے دریا کے اندر جانا نصیب نہیں ہوا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This being* would last or just a passing show, the wise could not solve this knotty tie so. 
He wrote a book though ‘on diving in sea’, to his heart’s sea ah! he could never see! 
* It is difficult to convey the true sense of ‘beeni’. If it conveys an opposite sense of Namud’ then its meaning is truth. Iqbal has not used beena (Conscious, having insight, a seeing being) here, still Wajud-i-beeni means conscious being. We enjoy both the meanings. If it means truth, then translation of line 2 gives a correct sense. Line 1 means: What we see would last, or a passing show, this being is a truth or just a false show.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بہ ضرب تیشہ بشکن بیستون را
کہ فرصت اندک و گردون دو رنگ است
حکیمان را درین اندیشہ بگذار
شرر از تیشہ خیزد یا ز سنگ است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تیشے کی ضرب سے بے ستوں پہاڑ توڑ ڈال؛ کیونکہ فرصت کم ہے اور حالات کا کچھ اعتبار نہیں۔ 
فلسفیوں کو اسی سوچ میں پڑا رہنے دے کہ چنگاری تیشہ سے نکلتی ہے یا پتھر سے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        With battle axe smite the Bistoon Mountain, the time is short trust on sky too in vain. 
Leave the wise men thus in their headaches own, did the spark raised from the axe or from stone?*
* Farhad had taken a pledge with the King of Persia to dig a canal from Baistoon Mountain against which the King pledged to marry his daughter (princess) with him. There was a long controversy amongst Persian historians, poets or phillosophers whether Farhad was killed by his own axe or from a stone rolling from the mountain top. The readers would find a hint of that controversy in the above mentioned quatrain (twin couplet).
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        منہ از کف چراغ رزو را
بدست ور مقام ہای و ہو را
مشو در چار سوی این جھان گم
بخود باز و بشکن چار سو را
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        امید کا چراغ ہاتھ سے نہ چھوڑ (امید قائم رکھ) اور ہا و ہو (عشق الہی ) کا مقام حاصل کر۔
اس جہان کے چہار اطراف (حدود) میں گم نہ ہو جا، بلکہ اپنے آپ میں آ اور ان حدود کو توڑ ڈال ( ان سے ورا نکل جا)۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Keep the crave’s lamp burning ever in heart, get the place where the uproars start. 
Do not get lost in the world’s four nooks, break the four nooks, and turn to self’s look.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دل دریا سکون بیگانہ از تست
بہ جیبش گوھر یکدانہ از تست
تو اے موج اضطراب خود نگہدار
کہ دریا را متاع خانہ از تست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اے موج! دریا کے دل کے اندر تجھی سے طلاطم ہے، تیرے ہی باعث اس کی جیب میں قیمتی موتی ہے۔
 تو اپنا اضطراب قائم رکھ، کیونکہ دریا کے گھر کی پونجی تیری وجہ سے ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O heart’s sea! No peace yet known to thee, the gloss of gems here, due to my glee.
O wave! Thus guard thy own restive thrill, the noise of storms thus, due to thy will. 
(The literal translation of line 4 is as follows: To sea, the whole asset is thy own home’s wealth, makes no sense if written in English. Here the meaning of ‘Mata-i-Khana’ is legacy.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دو گیتی را بخود باید کشیدن
نباید از حضور خود رمیدن
بہ نور دوش بین امروز خود را
ز دوش امروز را نتوان ربودن
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اپنے آپ سے بھاگنا نہیں چاہئے ، بلکہ دونوں جہانوں کو اپنی طرف کھینچنا چاہئے۔
اپنے ماضی کی روشنی میں اپنا حال دیکھ ؛ حال کو ماضی سے الگ نہیں کیا جا سکتا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        To both the worlds win with efforts and zeal, from thee never run for thy own self’s weal. 
From light of past see the light of to day, to day you cant cut off from the last day.*
* Rabudan: To pounce upon and run away. Here it means to separate, keep apart, detach.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بہ ما اے لالہ خود را وانمودی
نقاب از چہرہ زیبا گشودی
ترا چون بر دمیدی لالہ گفتند
بہ شاخ اندر چسان بودی چہ بودی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اے گل لالہ! تو نے اپنے خوبصورت چہرے سے نقاب اٹھا کر اپنے آپ کو ہم پر ظاہر کیا ہے۔
جب تو شاخ سے پھوٹا تو تجھے لالہ کہا گیا، مگر (یہ بتا کہ) جب تو شاخ کے اندر تھا، اس وقت کیا تھا ، کیسا تھا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You show us O Poppy! Thy self’s own trace, and turned the hid mask of thy charming face.
I call you poppy when you show thy face, in branch what you looked? Where was thy trace?*
* It is up to the readers to infer their own conclusions of the philosophical points referred to here being not within the field of the translator. Here Iqbal has left a feeler to the believers of pantheism, theism and panentheism.)
[Translated by Q A Kabir]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>