<Poem ID="13" Name="بندگی نامہ" BookID="08" BookName="زبورِعجم" SectionID="03" SectionName="گلشن راز جدید">
  <Para Name="بسم اﷲ الرحمن الرحیم">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گفت با یزدان مہ گیتی فروز
تاب من شب را کند مانند روز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        چاند جو جہان کو روشن کرتا ہے ، اس نے اللہ تعالے کی جناب میں عرض کیا۔ میری چاندنی رات کو دن بنا دیتی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Moon that illuminates earth submitted to Allah; my light turns the night into day.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یاد ایامی کہ بی لیل و نہار
خفتہ بودم در ضمیر روزگار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        وہ بھی کیا بے لیل و نہار وقت تھا، جب میں زمانے کے ضمیر میں سویا ہوا تھا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I remember the time when there was no night or day; I was deep asleep in the conscience of time.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کوکبے اندر سواد من نبود
گردشے اندر نہاد من نبود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میرے جلو میں کوئ ستارہ نہ تھا، مجھے ابھی گردش عطا نہیں ہوئ تھی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        There was no star in my attendence; revolutionary movement was not in my nature.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نے ز نورم دشت و در آئینہ پوش
نے بہ دریا از جمال من خروش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        نہ میرے نور سے دشت ودر آئینہ پوش تھے اور نہ میرے جمال سے سمندر میں جوار بھاٹا اٹھتا تھا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When desert and human abode was not lit by my light; oceans had no restlessness (tides) because of (the attraction of my megnatic) beauty.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آہ زین نیرنگ و افسون وجود
واے زین تابانی و ذوق نمود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مجھے اپنی اس نیرنگی اور طلسم وجود پر افسوس ہے، میں اپنی اس تابانی اور اظہار ذات پر سخت متاسف ہوں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Alas! This was changed by the magic spell of being; I regret my brightness and urge for manifestation.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تافتن از آفتاب آموختم
خاکدانی مردہ ئی افروختم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میں نے آفتاب سے چمکنا سیکھا ، اس مردہ جہان کو (اپنی چاندنی سے) چمکا دیا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I learnt shining from the Sun; and lightened the dead Earth.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خاکدانی با فروغ و بی فراغ
چہرۂ او از غلامی داغ داغ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        یہ خاکدان روشن تو ہے مگر اس میں آسودگی نہیں، کیونکہ اس کا چہرہ غلامی سے داغدار ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Earth is lit (by me) but it has no joy or solace; its face has pimples of slavery.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آدم او صورت ماہی بہ شست
آدمی یزدان کشی آدم پرست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        یہاں ہر شخص کے گلے میں مچھلی کی مانند کانٹا پھنسا ہوا ہے، یہاں کے لوگ خدا کو بھول چکے ہیں اور آدمیوں کی پرستش کرتے ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Everyone on earth has a hook stuck in his throat like a fish; mankind has forgotten God and worships human beings.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تا اسیر آب و گل کردی مرا
از طواف او خجل کردی مرا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        آپ نے مجھے آب وگل کا اسیر کر کے ، اس زمین کے طواف سے شرمسار کیا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        By bounding me to soil and water, made me ashamed of revolving around it.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        این جہان از نور جان آگاہ نیست
این جہان شایان مہر و ماہ نیست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        یہ جہان روح کے نور سے آگاہ نہیں، اس لیے سورج اور چاند کی شان کے شایاں نہیں ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This world is not aware of the light of the soul; it does not deserve Sun and Moon.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        در فضاے نیلگون او را بہل
رشتۂ ما نوریان از وے گسل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اسے نیلگوں فضا میں دکھیل دیں، اور ہم نوریوں کا رشتہ اس سے منقطع کر دیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Push this Earth into blue sky; cut its link with celestial beings like us.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یا مرا از خدمت او واگذار
یا ز خاکش آدم دیگر بیار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        یا مجھے اس کی خدمت سے فارغ کر دیں، اور یا اس جہان کی خاک سے نیا آدم پیدا کریں ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Either relieve me (of duty) of serving it; or create a new Adam out of its soil.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چشم بیدارم کبود و کور بہ
اے خدا این خاکدان بی نور بہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میری بیدار آنکھ اندھی اور بے کور ہی بہتر ہے ، اس خاکدان کو (میری) روشنی کے بغیر ہی رہنے دیں ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My eye was better blind and lightless; leave this earthly abode without my light.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        از غلامی دل بمیرد در بدن
از غلامی روح گردد بار تن
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        غلامی میں بدن کے اندر دل مر جاتا ہے، غلامی میں روح بدن کے لیے بوجھ بن جاتی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In servitude heart dies inside the body; the soul becomes burden for the body.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        از غلامی ضعف پیری در شباب
از غلامی شیر غاب افکندہ ناب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        غلامی جوان کو بوڑھوں کی مانند کمزور کر دیتی ہے، غلامی میں شیر بیشہ کے دانت جھڑ جاتے ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Slavery renders the young weak like the old; in slavery the (fiercefully young) lion sheds his teeth.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="31">
      <Text Language="Original">
        از غلامی بزم ملت فرد فرد
این و آن با این و آن اندر نبرد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        غلامی میں ملّت ٹکڑے ٹکڑے ہو جاتی ہے، ایک گروہ دوسرے گروہ سے لڑتا رہتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In slavery a nation is fragmented; and its individuals fight with each other.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آن یکی اندر سجود این در قیام
کاروبارش چون صلوة بی امام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ایک سجدے میں ہوتا ہے تو دوسرا قیام میں ، ملّت کا کام ایسے ہوتا ہے، جیسے امام کے بغیر نماز۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        One group prostrates and the other stands up; life is like praying without prayer leader.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="35">
      <Text Language="Original">
        در فتد ھر فرد با فردی دگر
ہر زمان ہر فرد را دردی دگر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ہر شخص دوسرے سے الجھتا ہے، ہر شخص نئی راگنی الاپتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Everyone quarrels with other; everyone complains of some problem all the time.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="37">
      <Text Language="Original">
        از غلامی مرد حق زنار بند
از غلامی گوہرش ناارجمند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        غلامی میں اللہ تعالے کا بندہ بھی (بت پرستی کا) زنّار پہن لیتا ہے، غلام کی قیمتی متاع کو بھی کوئ نہیں پوچھتا ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In slavery the man of God becomes idol worshiper; slavery turns his precious potentialities worthless.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="39">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شاخ او بی مہرگان عریان ز برگ
نیست اندر جان او جز بیم مرگ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس کے درخت کی شاخ بغیر خزاں کے پتّوں سے عریاں ہوتی ہے، اور اسے ہر دم موت کا خوف لگا رہتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Branches of his tree shed leaves without (autumn); he has no life as he is afraid of death every moment.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="41">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کور ذوق و نیش را دانستہ نوش
مردہ ئی بی مرگ و نعش خود بدوش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        وہ اتنا کور ذوق ہو جاتا ہے کہ زہر کو شہد سمجھتا ہے، بغیر موت کے مر جاتا ہے اور اپنی نعش ابپنے کندھے پر اٹھاے پھرتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He becomes so clueless that he takes poison as honey; dead without death and carrying his dead body on his shoulders.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="43">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آبروے زندگی در باختہ
چون خران با کاہ و جو در ساختہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        وہ زندگی کی آبرو گنوا بیٹھتا ہے، اور گدھوں کی طرح گھاس اور جو پر مطمئن ہو جاتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He has lost the dignity of life; like a donkey he is satisfied with hay and barley.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="45">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ممکنش بنگر محال او نگر
رفت و بود ماہ و سال او نگر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس کا ممکن اور محال دیکھ ، اس کی حرکت اور زمانہ ملاحظہ کر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Observe his possible and impossible; watch his sense of time (and space).
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="47">
      <Text Language="Original">
        روزھا در ماتم یکدیگرند
در خرام از ریگ ساعت کمترند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس کے دن ایک دوسرے کے ماتم میں ہیں، اور اس کے دنوں کی رفتار ریگ ساعت سے بھی سست ہے۔ (ساعت ریگ وہ آلہ تھا جس سے پرانے وقتوں کا شمار کیا جاتا تھا)
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        His days mourn each other (in state of perpetual mourning); speed of his movement (endeavour) is slower than sand-clock.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="49">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شورہ بوم از نیش کژدم خار خار
مور او اژدر گز و عقرب شکار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        شور زمین جو بچھّو کے ڈنک سے خار خار ہو چکی ہو، جس کی چیونٹی ، اژ دھا کو کاٹتی اور بچھّو کا شکار کرتی ہو۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The soil of which has turned like thorns (brackish) because of stinging by scorpions; where ants hunt dragons and prey scorpions.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="51">
      <Text Language="Original">
        صرصر او آتش دوزخ نژاد
زورق ابلیس را باد مراد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جس کی باد صرصر میں آتش دوزخ کی گرمی ہو، جو ابلیس کی کشتی کے لیے باد موافق ہو۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Its wind has heat of Hell; that acts as tail wind only for Devil’s barge.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="53">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آتشے اندر ہوا غلطیدہ ئی
شعلہ ئی در شعلہ ئی پیچیدہ ئی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جس کی ہوا آگ برساتی ہو اور اس کے اندر شعلے بھڑکتے ہوں ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        There is fire in its swirling wind; flames flare up, intermingle and multiply.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="55">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آتشے از دود پیچان تلخ پوش
آتشے تندر غو و دریا خروش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جس کی آگ اٹھتے ہوے دھوغیں میں اور تلخی پیدا کر رہی ہو، جس کی آگ میں بجلی کی کڑک اور سمندر کا جوش و خروش ہو۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Fire that has grown bitter due to its swirling smoke, the fire which roars like thunder and rages like (rough) sea.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="57">
      <Text Language="Original">
        در کنارش مارہا اندر ستیز
مارہا با کفچہ ہای زھر ریز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جس کے کنارے پر زہریلے پھنوں والے سانپ آپس میں لڑ رہے ہوں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        On its banks poisonous snakes fight each other like cobras with their hoods full of poison.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="59">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شعلہ اش گیرندہ چون کلب عقور
ہولناک و زندہ سوز و مردہ نور
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جس کا شعلہ ہولناک، زندہ سوز ، اوپر سے بند اور کاٹنے والے کتّے کی طرح لپٹ جانے والا ہو۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Its flames pounce like a dog that bites; extremely frightening, burn them alive and extinguish the light of their life.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="61">
      <Text Language="Original">
        در چنین دشت بلا صد روزگار
خوشتر از محکومی یک دم شمار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ایسے دشت بلا میں کئی صدیاں گزارنا ، غلامی کی ایک گھڑی سے بہتر ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Spending centuries in such horrifying desert is better than a moment of slavery. (Translated by Bashir Ahmad Dar)
In these introductory lines (verses) Allamah has enumerated a long list of slavery-related curses that exist in this world; as observed and described by moon; the nearest celestial body to the planet Earth. The beauty of this description lies in the last of the thirty-one verses wherein he says that living in such horrifying world for centuries is better than a moment spent in slavery۔ 
It is because of the fact that slavery is one-word for a long list of afflictions to which human beings could be subjected, e.g. inequalities, injustice, discrimination, exploitation, cruelties, brutalities and so on. The ugliest aspect of this is that all these happen to human beings at the hands of fellow human beings.
This is two-way denial of human dignity. On one hand those human beings who enslave others try to trespass the exclusive domain of the God, and on the other, those who submit to servitude (slavery) are guilty of not believing in the capabilities bestowed upon the best of the creations of the Creator.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>