<Poem ID="44" Name="داغ" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="1a" SectionName="حصہ اول">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عظمت غالب ہے اک مدت سے پیوند زمیں
مہدی مجروح ہے شہر خموشاں کا مکیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        NAWAB MIRZA KHAN DAGH
The grandeur of Ghalib has remained buried since long; Mahdi Majrooh* is the cemetery's resident since long.
* Mir Mahdi Majrooh, Dehalvi; an eminent poet of India.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        توڑ ڈالی موت نے غربت میں مینائے امیر
چشم محفل میں ہے اب تک کیف صہبائے امیر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Death broke the decanter of Amir* in a strange country’ the assembly's eye still has the ecstasy of the wine of Amir.
* Munshi Amir Ahmad and Amir Ahmad Minaeyi Lakhhnavi; eminent poets of India.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آج لیکن ہمنوا! سارا چمن ماتم میں ہے
شمع روشن بجھ گئی، بزم سخن ماتم میں ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        However, today O Companion! The whole garden is mourning! Lighted candle is extinguished, literary assembly is mourning!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بلبل دلی نے باندھا اس چمن میں آشیاں
ہم نوا ہیں سب عنادل باغ ہستی کے جہاں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Delhi's nightingale made its nest in such a garden; where all the world's nightingales are singing in a chorus.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چل بسا داغ آہ! میت اس کی زیب دوش ہے
آخری شاعر جہان آباد کا خاموش ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Ah Dagh has gone! His bier is on our shoulders. The last poet of Jahanabad is finally silent.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اب کہاں وہ بانکپن، وہ شوخی طرز بیاں
آگ تھی کافور پیری میں جوانی کی نہاں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Gone is that smartness! Gone is that humor of style! The fire of youth was veiled in the old age's camphor.* 
* Camphor is characterized with coolness. This verse is a very artistic expression of the fact that Dagh's thinking was a judicious mixture of the fervor of youth tempered with the coolness of mature age.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تھی زبان داغ پر جو آرزو ہر دل میں ہے
لیلی معنی وہاں بے پردہ، یاں محمل میں ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Every heart has the longing which the language of Dagh had; this Lailah was unveiled there, she is behind the veil here.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اب صبا سے کون پوچھے گا سکوت گل کا راز
کون سمجھے گا چمن میں نالہ بلبل کا راز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Who will ask zephyr now the secret of silence of the rose? Who in the garden will understand the secret of nightingale's wailing?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تھی حقیقت سے نہ غفلت فکر کی پرواز میں
آنکھ طائر کی نشیمن پر رہی پرواز میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In his elegant imagination he was not unaware of reality: The bird's eye remained focused on the nest even in flight.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اور دکھلائیں گے مضموں کی ہمیں باریکیاں
اپنے فکر نکتہ آرا کی فلک پیمائیاں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Others will show us the subtleties of linguistic thought; the elevated elegance of the sagacity of their thought.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تلخی دوراں کے نقشے کھینچ کر رلوائیں گے
یا تخیل کی نئی دنیا ہمیں دکھلائیں گے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        They will make us cry painting the picture of time's vicissitudes; or will show us the new world of their imagination.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اس چمن میں ہوں گے پیدا بلبل شیراز بھی
سینکڑوں ساحر بھی ہوں گے، صاحب اعجاز بھی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Nightingales of Shiraz also will be born in this garden; there will be hundreds of magicians and masters of miracles.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اٹھیں گے آزر ہزاروں شعر کے بت خانے سے
مے پلائیں گے نئے ساقی نئے پیمانے سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Thousands of Azar’s will rise from the temple of poetry. The new cup-bearers will serve wine from the new goblets.
(Azar: Father of Ibrahim A.S. famous for making stone idols.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لکھی جائیں گی کتاب دل کی تفسیریں بہت
ہوں گی اے خواب جوانی! تیری تعبیریں بہت
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Many commentaries of the book of Love will be written; there will be many interpretations of the youths' dreams.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہوبہو کھینچے گا لیکن عشق کی تصویر کون ؟
اٹھ گیا ناوک فگن، مارے گا دل پر تیر کون ؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        However, who will draw the exact picture of Love? The master having departed; who will enchant the heart?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="31">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اشک کے دانے زمین شعر میں بوتا ہوں میں
تو بھی رو اے خاک دلی! داغ کو روتا ہوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I am sowing the seeds of tears in the soil of verse. You also cry O Delhi's soil! I am crying for Dagh!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے جہان آباد، اے سرمایہ بزم سخن
ہوگیا پھر آج پامال خزاں تیرا چمن
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Ah! O the Ka'bah of the literateur's religion; your garden has been ruined by autumn today.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="35">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وہ گل رنگیں ترا رخصت مثال بو ہوا
آہ! خالی داغ سے کاشانہ و اردو ہوا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        That colourful rose of yours has departed like fragrance; that is, the abode of Urdu has become deprived of Dagh.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="37">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تھی نہ شاید کچھ کشش ایسی وطن کی خاک میں
وہ مہ کامل ہوا پنہاں دکن کی خاک میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Perhaps not much attraction was in the homeland's soil; that full moon has set in the soil of the Dakkan.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="39">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اٹھ گئے ساقی جو تھے، میخانہ خالی رہ گیا
یادگار بزم دہلی ایک حالی رہ گیا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The cup-bearers have left; the tavern has become deserted; only Hali the memorable personality of Delhi's assembly has been left.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="41">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آرزو کو خون رلواتی ہے بیداد اجل
مارتا ہے تیر تاریکی میں صیاد اجل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The tyranny of death makes longing shed tears of blood; the archer of death shoots out arrows in the dark.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="43">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کھل نہیں سکتی شکایت کے لیے لیکن زباں
ہے خزاں کا رنگ بھی وجہ قیام گلستاں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        However, the tongue cannot open in complaint; autumn's style is also a prelude to garden's existence.* 
* This and the next verse are very artistic expression of logic and coherence in the working of the universe. Life without death is tasteless as the spring without autumn is tasteless.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="45">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ایک ہی قانون عالم گیر کے ہیں سب اثر
بوے گل کا باغ سے، گلچیں کا دنیا سے سفر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The one universal law creates all such results: Exit of fragrance from the garden, that of the gardener from the world
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>