<Poem ID="08" Name="دل" BookID="11" BookName="ارمغانِ حجاز" SectionID="04" SectionName="حضور عالم انسانیت">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دل ن بحر است کو ساحل نورزد
نہنگ از ہیبت موجش بلرزد
از ن سیلی کہ صد ہامون بگیرد
فلک با یک حباب او نیرزد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        دل وہ سمندر ہے جو ساحل نہیں رکھتا ، اس کی موجوں کی ہیبت سے مگر مچھ بھی ڈرتے ہیں۔
 اس کے اندر وہ سیلاب اٹھتے ہیں جو سینکڑوں بیابانوں کو اپنی گرفت میں لے لیتے ہیں، آسمان تو اس کے (سیلاب کے ) ایک بلبلے کے برابر ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The heart is a sea which likes no shore, a shark too shivers from his wave’s roar.
Like tempest which takes jungles of rubble, the whole sky’s worth, not alike his bubble.
(Here nahang (alligator) is probably the Satan… Iqbal has explained different states of heart: Sometimes a huge sea in which the whole cosmos can be contained. As such his heart is not a mere lump of flesh which beats in bosom. It is a place in which God himself likes to live when He loves a man.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دل ما تش و تن موج دودش 
تپید دمبدم ساز وجودش 
بہ ذکر نیم شب جمعیت او
چو سیمابی کہ بندو چوب عودش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ہمارا دل آگ ہے اور بدن اس کے دھوئیں کی موج، مسلسل تڑپ اس (دل) کے وجود کا ساز ہے۔ 
ذکر نیم شب سے دل کی تربیت ہے، جیسے پارہ کو عود کی لکڑی ساکن کر دیتی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My heart is a fire, a smoke my frame, my being’s harp burns with a constant flame.
From mid night prayers the heart gets a calm, like mercury* closed in aloe- wood balm.@
* The mercury was killed (to make calx) in aloe wood in old days. Aloe wood is called ood (Ud) in Arabic and Persian. (It also means lute or harp). It gives a sweet smelling fragrance when it burns. @ Balm: ointment that which gives peace of mind or consolation.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زمانہ کار او را میبرد پیش
کہ مرد خود نگہدار است درویش
ہمین فقر است و سلطانی کہ دل را
نگہ داری چو دریا گوہر خویش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        زمانہ (خود) اس کے کام کو آگے بڑھاتا ہے، کیونکہ خود دار شخص مرد درویش ہے۔ 
یہی فقر ہے اور یہی سلطانی کہ تو دل کی اس طرح حفاظت کرے جیسے دریا اپنے گوہر کی حفاظت کرتا ہے،
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        His help the world seeks like his slave own, since he guarded self with saintly tone.
This is faqr and kingship which guards the heart, as sea guards pearls like a best work of art.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہ نیروی خودی را زمودی
نہ بند از دست و پای خود گشودی
خرد زنجیر بودی دمے را
اگر در سینۂ او دل نبودے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اگر آدمی کے سینے میں دل نہ ہوتا ، تو نہ وہ اپنی خودی کی قوّت آزماتا؛ 
اور نہ اپنے ہاتھ پاؤں کے بند کھولتا، بلکہ خرد زنجیر بن کر اسے جکڑے ہوتی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Ego’s power he did not try, his hands and feet too opened no tie.
The wisdom to man is sometimes a chain, if he had no heart* to check and restrain.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تو میگوئی کہ دل از خاک و خون است
گرفتار طلسم کاف و نون است
دل ما گرچہ اندر سینۂ ماست
ولیکن از جھان ما برون است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تو کہتا ہے کہ دل خاک و خون سے پیدا ہوتا ہے، اور یہ (بھی) طلسم کن میں گرفتار ہے۔ 
(نہیں یہ بات نہیں) اگرچہ ہمارا دل ہمارے سینہ میں ہے، مگر وہ ہماری دنیا سے ماورا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You say the heart is the Khak and Khoon, a work of magic of Kaf and Nun.* 
My heart is though in the bosom of mine, it is yet beyond the pale of world thine.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جہان مھر و مہ زناری اوست
گشاد ھر گرہ از زاری اوست
پیامی دہ ز من ہندوستان را
غلام، زاد از بیداری اوست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        یہ کائنات دل کی غلام ہے، دل کے سوز گریہ سے ہر مشکل آسان ہو جاتی ہے۔
میری طرف سے ہندوستان کو یہ پیغام پہنچا دو، کہ غلام دل کی بیداری سے آزادی حاصل کرتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The world of Sun and Moon, slave of his thread, each tie will be ope from tears lie can shed.
To ‘Hind’ please convey a message of me, when a slave is wide awake he is free.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        من و تو کشت یزدان، حاصل است این
عروس زندگی را محمل است این
غبار راہ شد دانای اسرار
نپنداری کہ عقل است این، دل است این
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میں اور تو اللہ تعالے کی کھیتی ہیں ، دل اس کی پیداوار ہے، یہی عروس زندگی کا محمل ہے۔
غبار راہ (انسان) دانائے اسرار ہے، عقل کی وجہ سے نہیں ، بلکہ دل کے باعث۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        We are God’s harvest its yield is heart, for life’s bride, it is the lady cart!
He told the ‘dust of path’ His Secret Acts, was it due to wisdom or heart’s own tacts?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گہی جویندۂ حسن غریبے 
خطیبی منبر او از صلیبی
گہی سلطان با خیل و سپاہی
ولی از دولت خود بے نصیبی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کبھی یہ حسن یکتا کا طلبگار ہوتا ہے، کبھی ایسا خطیب ، صلیب جس کا منبر ہو۔ 
کبھی صاحب لاؤ لشکر سلطان ، لیکن اپنی دولت سے کنارہ کش۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        To that rare beauty my heart seeks again, to speaker* whose pulpit was ‘cross’ and slain.
To the King* often with lancers and force, to wealth who never touched at any course.
* Speaker: Refers to Mansoor Hallaj. TheKing: Sultan Noor-ud-Din Zangi. Sultan N D Zangi raised his banner for Jehad and fought vigorously for 28 years during his reign, from 541 A.H. to 569 A.H. He was victorious in every battle he fought. He ammassed no wealth except the dust of his face during fighting which he had collected in a hand-kerchief. He left a will that when he will be lowered in grave that dust should be rubbed at his face. His will was fulfilled in like manner.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جہان دل، جہان رنگ و بو نیست
درو پست و بلند و کاخ و کو نیست 
زمین و سمان و چار سو نیست
درین عالم بجز اللہ ہو نیست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        یہ رنگ و جو کی دنیا ، دل کی دنیا نہیں ، دل کی دنیا میں پستی و بلندی ہے نہ محل و کوچہ۔ 
نہ وہاں زمین و آسمان ہیں ، نہ چہار اطراف ، اس جہان میں سوائے اللہ تعالے کے اور کچھ نہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The heart’s world is not world of pomp ‘an show, no lanes and doors, there nor homes high and low.
Neither earth and sky nor the four nooks too, there is none in this world save ‘Allah hoo’.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="37">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نگہ دید و خرد پیمانہ ورد
کہ پیماید جھان چار سو را
می شامی کہ دل کردند نامش
بخویش اندر کشید این رنگ و بو را
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        نگاہ نے (جہان) کا مشاہدہ کیا اور خرد پیمانہ لے آئ ، کہ اس چہار اطراف کے جہان کی پیمائش کرے۔
مگر وہ مئے کش ، جسے دل کہتے ہیں ، اس جہان رنگ و بو کو (ایک ہی جام میں ) پی گیا،
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The glance brought eyes and wisdom a tape band, to measure four sides and all the world’s land. 
Who drinks the whole wines whom we named heart, who sucks within it all beauties of art.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="41">
      <Text Language="Original">
        محبت چیست تاثیر نگاہی است
چہ شیرین زخمی از تیر نگاہی است
بہ صید دل روی، ترکش بینداز
کہ این نخچیر، نخچیر نگاہی است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        محبت کیا ہے، تاثیر نگاہ؛ یہ تیر نگاہ کا لگایا ہوا کیسا شیریں زخم ہے۔
دل کے شکار کو جا رہا ہے، تو ترکش پھینک دے، کہ یہ شکار نگاہ کا شکار ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What is the love? An impact of glance, which gives a sweet prick of the eye’s lance.
If you seek heart’s hand? Throw quiver and bow, this game is the game of glance and eye brow?
[Translated by Q A Kabir]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>