<Poem ID="05" Name="" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3b" SectionName="غزلیات 3">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پھر باد بہار آئی، اقبال غزل خواں ہو 
غنچہ ہے اگر گل ہو، گل ہے تو گلستاں ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The spring breeze is flowing again start singing, O Iqbal; if you are a bud be the flower, if a flower the garden become.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تو خاک کی مٹھی ہے، اجزا کی حرارت سے 
برہم ہو، پریشاں ہو، وسعت میں بیاباں ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You are a handful of dust, with the warmth of the components wander around, scatter about and wilderness in extent become.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تو جنس محبت ہے، قیمت ہے گراں تیری 
کم مایہ ہیں سوداگر، اس دیس میں ارزاں ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کم مایہ : غریب؛ کم مال والے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You belong to the essence of Love; you are invaluable; the purchasers are indigent, low priced in this country become.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کیوں ساز کے پردے میں مستور ہو لے تیری
تو نغمہ رنگیں ہے، ہر گوش پہ عریاں ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Why should your tunes be veiled in the guitar’s frets? You are an ornamented song, evident to every ear become.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے رہرو فرزانہ! رستے میں اگر تیرے 
گلشن ہے تو شبنم ہو، صحرا ہے تو طوفاں ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        رہرو فرزانہ: عقلمند مسافر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O wise traveler! If in your path you encounter the garden become dew, if wilderness the storm become.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ساماں کی محبت میں مضمر ہے تن آسانی
مقصد ہے اگر منزل، غارت گر ساماں ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Indulgence is concealed in the love of opulence; if you aim at the destination, destroyer of opulence become.
[Translated by M.A.K.Khalil]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>