<Poem ID="23" Name="عبدالقادر کے نام" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="2a" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اٹھ کہ ظلمت ہوئی پیدا افق خاور پر 
بزم میں شعلہ نوائی سے اجالا کر دیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        خاور: مشرق۔
شعلہ نوائي: ایسے نغمے گانا جن سے شعلے نکل رہے ہوں، یعنی تڑپانے والے نغمے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Rise, as darkness has appeared on the eastern horizon! We should light up the assemblage with blazing songs.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ایک فریاد ہے مانند سپند اپنی بساط 
اسی ہنگامے سے محفل تہ و بالا کر دیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Our capacity is only a cry of lament like the wild rue.* We should overturn the assemblage with this same uproar.
(Sipand or Wild Rue: The property of the rue seed of cracking and jumping when put in fire is referred to here as an expression of distress and lament as well as the restlessness produced by them.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اہل محفل کو دکھا دیں اثر صیقل عشق 
سنگ امروز کو آئینہ فردا کر دیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        We should show the assemblage the effect of Love’s polish. We should convert the stone of today into the mirror* of tomorrow.
* This refers to the technology of glass making, ultimately making mirrors, whose starting material is a base material like silicates in stones and soil. This hemistich means that we should convert the youth of today, who are inert and useless like stones, into the mirrors of tomorrow.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جلوہ یوسف گم گشتہ دکھا کر ان کو 
تپش آمادہ تر از خون زلیخا کر دیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تپش آمادہ: تڑپانے کے لیے بیتاب اور بیقرار۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        By showing them the effulgence of the lost Yusuf; we should make them more agitation-prone than Zalaykha’s blood.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اس چمن کو سبق آئین نمو کا دے کر 
قطرہ شبنم بے مایہ کو دریا کر دیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        آئين نمو کا: پھلنے پھولنے کا قانون۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        By giving the lesson of the law of growth to this garden; we should turn the insignificant drop of dew into the ocean.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رخت جاں بت کدہء چیں سے اٹھا لیں اپنا
سب کو محو رخ سعدی و سلیمی کر دیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        We should lift our dearest chattel from the China's temple.* We should fascinate all with the face of Sa'di and Sulaima.**
* This is a part of the often repeated message of Allamah Iqbal that Muslims should return to Islam for guidance in knowledge and for inspiration for noble deeds. The mention of China is a delicate reference to the Hadith that one should acquire knowledge even if it is in China. **It was a tradition in pre Islamic Arabic poetry to write poems about their beloveds. However, the identity of the beloved was not revealed and she was represented by one of the several legendary beauties of the Arab folk lore, such as Salmah, Sulaima, Lubnah, Lailah etc.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دیکھ! یثرب میں ہوا ناقہ لیلی بیکار 
قیس کو آرزوئے نو سے شناسا کر دیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Look! The Lailah's she camel became useless in Yathrib; we should make Qais acquainted with the new Longing.
(With the advent of Islam old values in literature, including poetry, changed… Instead of Lailah and her she camel, God and Holy Prophet S.A.W. became the objects of Love and they were referred to metaphorically as Lailah. Allamah Iqbal has used this metaphor often.).
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بادہ دیرینہ ہو اور گرم ہو ایسا کہ گداز 
جگر شیشہ و پیمانہ و مینا کر دیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        بادہ ديرينہ: پرانی شراب ، مراد ہے اسلام۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The wine should be mature and so hot that with it we should soften the heart of the glass, the goblet, and the decanter.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گرم رکھتا تھا ہمیں سردی مغرب میں جو داغ 
چیر کر سینہ اسے وقف تماشا کر دیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The grief which kept us warm in the cold of the West; opening up the breast we should make it public.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شمع کی طرح جییں بزم گہ عالم میں 
خود جلیں، دیدہ اغیار کو بینا کر دیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ديدہ اغيار: دوسروں کی آنکھیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In the world's congregation we should live like the candle; we should burn ourselves and open up the rivals' eyes.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہر چہ در دل گذرد وقف زباں دارد شمع 
سوختن نیست خیالے کہ نہاں دارد شمع
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        شمع کے دل پر جو کچھ گز رتا ہے، وہ اسے زبان پر لے آتی ہے؛ جینا کوئی خیال نہیں جسے شمع چھپا کر رکھ سکے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ‘The candle reveals whatever passes through the heart; burning is not the thought which the candle conceals’. 
(Translated by Dr. M.A.K. Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>