<Poem ID="05" Name="" BookID="03" BookName="ضربِ کلیم" SectionID="06" SectionName="محراب گل افغان کے افکار">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ مدرسہ یہ کھیل یہ غوغائے روارو 
اس عیش فراواں میں ہے ہر لحظہ غم نو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In school the noise of games, debates, great stir and animation prevail; this abundant joy e'ery moment breeds new griefs and naught else can avail.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وہ علم نہیں، زہر ہے احرار کے حق میں 
جس علم کا حاصل ہے جہاں میں دو کف جو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        دو کف جو: دو مٹھی جو۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        For men of free and noble birth such knowledge is a venom dread, which makes them earn some barley corn to fill their bellies with its bread.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ناداں ! ادب و فلسفہ کچھ چیز نہیں ہے 
اسباب ہنر کے لیے لازم ہے تگ و دو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تگ و دو: کوشش، محنت۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O fool, great wisdom and book lore have not much worth nor carry weight: To learn a useful art one must put in much strife and struggle great.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فطرت کے نوامیس پہ غالب ہے ہنر مند 
شام اس کی ہے مانند سحر صاحب پرتو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        نوامیس: ناموس کی جمع؛ مراد ہے قانون، قاعدے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A man of skill controls the working of Nature, his nights are brighter than mornings.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وہ صاحب فن چاہے تو فن کی برکت سے 
ٹپکے بدن مہر سے شبنم کی طرح ضو!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ضو: روشنی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If such a craftsman likes, with ease, by dint of skill and magic art, like dew, can make from mass of Sun, the rays of light proceed and dart.
[Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>