<Poem ID="06" Name="" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="1b" SectionName="غزلیات 1">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        انوکھی وضع ہے، سارے زمانے سے نرالے ہیں
یہ عاشق کون سی بستی کے یا رب رہنے والے ہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Unusual in state, distinct from the whole world they are; O Lord! Inhabitants of which habitation these Lovers are?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        علاج درد میں بھی درد کی لذت پہ مرتا ہوں
جو تھے چھالوں میں کانٹے، نوک سوزن سے نکالے ہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Even during pathos's cure I desperately love pathos; blisters' thorns have been extracted with needle's point.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پھلا پھولا رہے یا رب! چمن میری امیدوں کا
جگر کا خون دے دے کر یہ بوٹے میں نے پالے ہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O Lord, the garden of my hopes may remain prosperous I have raised these plants watering them with my blood.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رلاتی ہے مجھے راتوں کو خاموشی ستاروں کی
نرالا عشق ہے میرا، نرالے میرے نالے ہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The stars' silence at night makes me weep: Strange my Love is, strange my Laments are.
* Reference to the Holy Qur'an 2:164 and 3: 190 as well as 2:219-20 (in part) will help appreciating the thought expressed in this verse.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہ پوچھو مجھ سے لذت خانماں برباد رہنے کی
نشیمن سینکڑوں میں نے بنا کر پھونک ڈالے ہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Do not ask me of the pleasure of remaining destitute; hundreds of nests have been made and destroyed by me.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہیں بیگانگی اچھی رفیق راہ منزل سے
ٹھہر جا اے شرر، ہم بھی تو آخر مٹنے والے ہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Being a stranger to the journey's companion is not good, O spark! Wait, after all we are also going to disappear.*
* A spark is an ephemeral phenomenon, but the spark of Divine Love in the Lover's heart is not ephemeral and does not part with its companion till the end of the life's journey.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        امید حور نے سب کچھ سکھا رکھا ہے واعظ کو
یہ حضرت دیکھنے میں سیدھے سادے، بھولے بھالے ہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Expectation for the houri has taught everything to the preacher; only in appearance simple and straight forward these people are.
(This is sarcasm on the half-baked ‘Ulema who give literal interpretation of religious thought and miss it’s inner or real meaning.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مرے اشعار اے اقبال کیوں پیارے نہ ہوں مجھ کو
مرے ٹوٹے ہوئے دل کے یہ درد انگیز نالے ہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Why should not my verses be dear to me, O Iqbal; these the painful laments of my heart are.
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>