<Poem ID="25" Name="خردہ" BookID="07" BookName="پیامِ مشرق" SectionID="04" SectionName="نقش فرنگ">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        می خورد ھر ذرہ ما پیچ و تاب
محشری در ھر دم ما مضمر است
با سکندر خضر در ظلمات گفت
مرگ مشکل، زندگی مشکل تر است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Agony in every atom of our being, every breath of us a rising from the dead.
To Sikandar lost amidst the Land of Darkness, ‘Hard is Death, but Life is harder’, Khizar said. 
(Translated by R.A. Nicholson)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دردانہ ادا شناس دریاست
از گردش آسیا چہ داند؟
کلک را نالہ از تہی مغزی است
قلم سرمہ را صریری نیست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        قلم کا رونا اس کی تہی مغزی (بے عقلی) کے باعث ہے؛ (ورنہ ) قلم سرمہ آواز پیدا نہیں کرتا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The pearl is used to the ways of the sea. What can it know about the millstone that grind grain? 
The reed-pen, being hollow, makes a noise; the pencil, being solid lead, makes none.
(Translated by M. Hadi Husain)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        منم کہ طوف حرم کردہ ام بتی بہ کنار
منم کہ پیش بتان نعرہ ہای ہو زدہ ام
دلم ہنوز تقاضای جستجو دارد
قدم بجادۂ باریک تر ز مو زدہ ام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میں وہ ہوں جس نے بغل میں بت لیے حرم کا طواف کیا ؛ میں وہ ہوں جس نے بتوں سامنے نعرہ ء ہو بلند کیا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I am one who has walked around the Harem with an idol under my arms. I am one who has shouted Allah’s name when idols were in front of me.
My heart still wants that I should go on seeking, though I have set foot on a path thinner than a hair.
(Translated by M. Hadi Husain)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گل گفت کہ عیش نو بہاری خوشتر
یک صبح چمن ز روزگاری خوشتر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        پھول نے کہا کہ نو بہار کا عیش کیا خوب ہے؛ چمن کی ایک صبح ساری دنیا سے بہتر ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Sweet is the time of Spring, the red Rose cried; sweeter an hour here than an age outside;
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زان پیش کہ کس ترا بدستار زند
مردن بکنار شاخساری خوشتر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        پیشتر اس کے کہ کوئی تجھے اپنی دستار میں آویزاں کر لے؛ شاخسار پر مر جانا ہی بہتر ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Before some lover plucks you for his cap, sweetest to die in this green garden’s lap.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سخن گو طفلک و برنا و پیر است
سخن را سالی و ماہی نباشد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        بچہ، جوان اور بوڑھا سب بات کرتے ہیں ؛ سخن کے لیے مہ و سال (عمر) کی کوئی قید نہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The poet is child, youth and old man all in one; distinctions of age are unknown to poetry.
(Translated by M. Hadi Husain)
(Translated by V.G. Kiernan)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چشم را بینائی افزاید سہ چیز
سبزہ و آب روان و روی خوش
کالبد، را فربہی می آورد
جامۂ قز جان بی غم، بوی خوش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تین چیزیں بینائی میں اضافہ کرتی ہیں؛ سبزہ، آب رواں اور خوبصورت چہرہ۔ 
بدن کو (بھی تین چیزیں ) فربہ کرتی ہیں؛ ریشمی کپڑا، بے فکری اور خوشبو۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Three things make your vision better: Greenery, running water and fair faces.
Three things tend to make you fatter: Silk robes, good smells and a carefree heart. 
(Translated by M. Hadi Husain)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے برادر من ترا از زندگی دادم نشان
خواب را مرگ سبک دان مرگ را خواب گران
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اے برادر ! میں تجھے زندگی کا راز بتاتا ہوں ؛ نیند کو سبک موت سمجھ اور موت کو خواب گراں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Of Life, O brother, I give thee a token to hold and keep; sleep is a lighter death, and Death a heavier sleep. 
(Translated by R.A. Nicholson)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        طاقت عفو در تو نیست اگر
خیز و با دشمنان در آ بہ ستیز
سینہ را کارگاہ کینہ ساز
سرکہ در انگبین خویش مریز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اگر تجھ میں معاف کر دینے کا حوصلہ نہیں؛ تو اٹھ اور دشمنوں سے برسر پیکار ہو۔ 
مگر اپنے سینے کو کینے کی کارگاہ (فیکٹری) نہ بنا؛ (اپنی زندگی کے) شہد میں سرکہ نہ ملا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If you do not possess the power to forgive, go; get to grips with those who have wronged you.
Do not nurse hatred in your heart. O do not make your honey sour by mixing vinegar with it. 
(Translated by M. Hadi Husain)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        از نزاکت ہای طبع موشکاف او مپرس
کز دم بادی زجاج شاعر ما بشکند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس کی طبع ء موشگاف کی نزاکتوں کے بارے میں نہ پوچھ، ہمارے شاعر کا شیشہ ہوا کے جھونکے سے ٹوٹ جاتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Do not speak to me of his sensitive, fine mind, our poet’s crystal breaks at a mere breath of wind.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="31">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کی تواند گفت شرح کارزار زندگی
"می پرد رنگش حبابی چون بدریا بشکند"
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        وہ کیسے زندگی کے کارزار کی وضاحت کر سکتا ہے، (اس کا تو یہ حال ہے کہ) 'دریا میں بلبلہ ٹوٹے تو اس کا رنگ اڑ جاتا ہے'۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Of life’s grim war how can he ever tell the tale, when at the sight of a burst bubble he turns pale?
(Translated by M. Hadi Husain)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        در جھان مانند جوی کوہسار 
از نشیب و ہم فراز آگاہ شو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In this world either be a hill-stream, which observes heights and depressions in its course;
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="35">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یا مثال سیل بی زنہار خیز
فارغ از پست و بلند راہ شو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Or be a headlong flood, which just ignores heights and depressions as it rushes on.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="37">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ایکہ گل چیدی منال از نیش خار
خار ھم می روید از باد بھار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O you who plucked a rose, do not complain about the thorn, for like the rose the thorn is born of the spring breeze.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="39">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مزن وسمہ بر ریش و ابروی خویش
جوانے ز دزدیدن سال نیست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اپنی ریش اور آبرو پر وسمہ نہ لگا؛ سال چرا کر جوانی قائم نہیء رکھی جا سکتی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Do not apply a hair-dye to your eyebrows and your beard, for you cannot get back your youth by stealing years from time. 
(Translated by M. Hadi Husain)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="41">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ندارد کار با دون ہمتان عشق
تذرو مردہ را شاہین نگیرد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کم ہمت لوگوں سے عشق کوئی سروکار نہیں رکھتا؛ شاہین، مردہ تدرو کا شکار نہیں کرتا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Love has no use for those who do not dare. To catch dead birds an eagle does not care.
(Translated by M Hadi Husain)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="43">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نقد شاعر در خور بازار نیست
نان بہ سیم نسترن نتوان خرید
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        شاعر کی متاع بازار میں لائے جانے کے قابل نہیں، گل نسترن کی چاندی سے روٹی نہیں خریدی جا سکتی ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The poet’s product is not saleable. The silver of a white rose will not buy you bread.
(Translated by M. Hadi Husain)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="45">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چہ خوش بودی اگر مرد نکویی
ز بند باستان آزاد رفتی
اگر تقلید بودی شیوۂ خوب
پیمبر ھم رہ اجداد رفتی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کیا اچھا ہوتا کہ اگر نیک خو مرد ؛ گزرے ہوئے لوگوں کے بندھنوں سے آزاد رہ کر زندگی بسر کرتا ہے۔ 
اگر تقلید اچھی بات ہوتی؛ تو ہمارے رسول پاک (صلعم) بھی ابا و اجداد کا راستہ اختیار کرتے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        How nice a thing it were if every traveler who wants to travel far and fast could go free from the trammels of the past.
If blind conformity were good, the Prophet himself would have gone the way of Arabs in an earlier day. 
(Translated by M. Hadi Husain)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>