<Poem ID="26" Name="تصوف" BookID="03" BookName="ضربِ کلیم" SectionID="01" SectionName="اسلام اور مسلمان">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ حکمت ملکوتی، یہ علم لاہوتی 
حرم کے درد کا درماں نہیں تو کچھ بھی نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ملکوتي: فرشتوں کی دنیا؛ مراد ہے پاکیزہ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        MYSTICISM
If angelic art and celestial lore the ills of Muslims can not cure, worthless they are and of no use, of fact so true you must be sure.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ ذکر نیم شبی، یہ مراقبے، یہ سرور 
تری خودی کے نگہباں نہیں تو کچھ بھی نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ذکر نيم شبي: آدھی رات کی عبادت۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your reveries deep and rapture sweet, your worship at the midst of night, if fail to keep a watch on Self, are useless quite and have value slight.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ عقل، جو مہ و پرویں کا کھیلتی ہے شکار 
شریک شورش پنہاں نہیں تو کچھ بھی نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مہ و پرويں: چاند اور ستارے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The intellect can cast its noose on the Pleiades and the Moon if heart is b'reft of love for God, it is not a worthy gift and boon.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خرد نے کہہ بھی دیا 'لاالہ' تو کیا حاصل 
دل و نگاہ مسلماں نہیں تو کچھ بھی نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If wit incites a man to say ‘No God but He’ it brings no gain; it has no worth at all I think, unless affirmed by heart and brain.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عجب نہیں کہ پریشاں ہے گفتگو میری 
فروغ صبح پریشاں نہیں تو کچھ بھی نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        No wonder great that my discourse with distraction unbound is fraught if it won't spread like rays of morn, it means such talk has value naught.
(Written in Riaz Manzil; residence of Sir Raas Masood, Bhopal.)
(Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>