<Poem ID="36" Name="چاند" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="1a" SectionName="حصہ اول">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میرے ویرانے سے کوسوں دور ہے تیرا وطن
ہے مگر دریائے دل تیری کشش سے موجزن
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE MOON
Though miles away from my abode is your homeland; tumultuous like the sea is my heart with your attraction.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        قصد کس محفل کا ہے؟ آتا ہے کس محفل سے تو؟
زرد رو شاید ہوا رنج رہ منزل سے تو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Where do you intend to go? From where are you coming? Perhaps you have become pale from the journey's hardships.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آفرنیش میں سراپا نور، ظلمت ہوں میں
اس سیہ روزی پہ لیکن تیرا ہم قسمت ہوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In creation you are embodiment of light, of darkness I am; in spite of this misfortune akin to you in destiny I am.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آہ، میں جلتا ہوں سوز اشتیاق دید سے
تو سراپا سوز داغ منت خورشید سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Ah! Ablaze I am from the heat of longing for God's Sight; embodiment of pathos are you from obligation of sun's sight.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ایک حلقے پر اگر قائم تری رفتار ہے
میری گردش بھی مثال گردش پرکار ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If your motion established in an orbit is; my motion also like that of a compass is.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زندگی کی رہ میں سرگرداں ہے تو، حیراں ہوں میں
تو فروزاں محفل ہستی میں ہے، سوزاں ہوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You are diligently pursuing your life's path, so am I! You are lighted in existence' assembly, so alight am I.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میں رہ منزل میں ہوں، تو بھی رہ منزل میں ہے
تیری محفل میں جو خاموشی ہے، میرے دل میں ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In the midst of my journey I am, in the midst of your journey you are. Similar to the silence of my heart, silent in your assembly you are.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تو طلب خو ہے تو میرا بھی یہی دستور ہے
چاندنی ہے نور تیرا، عشق میرا نور ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A seeker you are and the same custom is mine. Moon light is your light, Love is the light mine.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        انجمن ہے ایک میری بھی جہاں رہتا ہوں میں
بزم میں اپنی اگر یکتا ہے تو، تنہا ہوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In the world of my residence with an assembly I also am; if unique in your assembly you are, unique like you I am.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مہر کا پرتو ترے حق میں ہے پیغام اجل
محو کر دیتا ہے مجھ کو جلوئہ حسن ازل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The light of the sun as the message of death to you is; annihilated in the Eternal Beauty's effulgence my heart is.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پھر بھی اے ماہ مبیں! میں اور ہوں تو اور ہے
درد جس پہلو میں اٹھتا ہو وہ پہلو اور ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Still, O shining moon! I am different, you are different; the bosoms which are afflicted by the pathos are different.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گرچہ میں ظلمت سراپا ہوں، سراپا نور تو
سینکڑوں منزل ہے ذوق آگہی سے دور تو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Though the embodiment of darkness I am, embodiment of light you are. Hundreds of stages away from the taste of Intellect you are.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جو مری ہستی کا مقصد ہے، مجھے معلوم ہے
یہ چمک وہ ہے، جبیں جس سے تری محروم ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I know what the purpose of my existence is. This is the luster of which your forehead devoid is
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>