<Poem ID="56" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="02" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کھو نہ جا اس سحروشام میں اے صاحب ہوش!
اک جہاں اور بھی ہے جس میں نہ فردا ہے نہ دوش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        دوش: گزرا ہوا کل۔
فردا: آنے والا کل۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In the maze of eve and morn, O man awake, do not be lost: Another world there yet exists that has no future or the past.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کس کو معلوم ہے ہنگامہ فردا کا مقام 
مسجد و مکتب و میخانہ ہیں مدت سے خموش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        None knows that tumult’s worth and price which hidden lies in future’s womb: The mosque, the school and tavern too since long are silent like a tomb.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میں نے پایا ہے اسے اشک سحر گاہی میں 
جس در ناب سے خالی ہے صدف کی آغوش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اشک سحر گاہي: صبح سویرے اللہ کی یاد میں آنسو بہانا۔ 
در ناب: نایاب موتی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In tears shed at early morn is found the gem unique and best, the gem, whose like is never held, by mother shell within its breast.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نئی تہذیب تکلف کے سوا کچھ بھی نہیں 
چہرہ روشن ہو تو کیا حاجت گلگونہ فروش!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        گلگونہ فروش: ابٹن، مراد ہے سرخی پاؤڈر بیچنے والا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Culture New is nothing else save glamour false and show, indeed: If the face be fair and bright, rouge vendors aid it does not need.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        صاحب ساز کو لازم ہے کہ غافل نہ رہے 
گاہے گاہے غلط آہنگ بھی ہوتا ہے سروش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Much care and caution must he take, who sets the music of a song: For oft the Voice Unseen inspires such airs as jarring are and wrong.
(Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>