<Poem ID="04" Name="حکمت کلیمی" BookID="10" BookName="پس چہ بائد کرد" SectionID="01" SectionName="پس چہ بائد کرد">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تا نبوت حکم حق جاری کند
پشت پا بر حکم سلطان میزند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جب نبوّت اللہ تعالے کو حکم جاری کرتی ہے؛ تو بادشاہ کے حکم کو ٹھکرا دیتی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE WISDOM OF MOSES
As the prophet establishes God’s decrees, he repudiates Caesar’s law.
(Iqbal here brings into sharp contrast God’s Will and king’s will, keeping in mind perhaps the well-known saying of Christ: Render unto Caeser what is Caesar’s and render unto God what is God’s. Iqbal feels that it is not possible for one to be loyal to God’s will and yet to accept and follow the lead of ordinary mundane rulers.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        در نگاہش قصر سلطان کہنہ دیر
غیرت او بر نتابد حکم غیر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس کی نگاہ میں بادشاہ کا محل ایک پرانا بتخانہ ہے، اس کی غیرت غیر اللہ کا حکم برداشت نہیں کرتی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In his eyes the royal palace is like an old idol-temple; his sense of honour makes him disobey the order of the other-than-God.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پختہ سازد صحبتش ہر خام را
تازہ غوغائی دھد ایام را
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        نبی (صلعم) کی صحبت ہر خام (شخصیت ) کو پختہ کر دیتی ہے، وہ زمانے کو نئے ہنگامے عطا کرتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The imperfect become perfect through association with him. He gives a new tumult to the age.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        درس او "اﷲ بس باقی ہوس"
تا نیفتد مرد حق در بند کس
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        وہ 'اللہ بس، باقی ہوس' کا سبق دیتا ہے تاکہ اللہ تعالے کے بندے کسی اور کے دام میں نہ پھنسیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        His message is that Allah is sufficient and all else is meaningless, so that the man of truth does not fall into anybody’s snare.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        از نم او آتش اندر شاخ تاک
در کف خاک از دم او جان پاک
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس کے نم سے انگور کی شاخ میں آگ بھر جاتی ہے اور اس کے دم سے خاک (بدن) کے اندر پاک روح پیدا ہو جاتی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        His moisture imparts fire to the vine’s twig and his breath gives life to this handful of earth.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        معنی جبریل و قرآن است او
فطرة اﷲ را نگہبان است او
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        نبی (صلعم) کی زندگی (پیغام) جبریل و قرآن پاک کا عملی نمونہ ہے، وہ فطرت اللہ (دین فطرت) کا نگہبان ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He is the meaning of Gabriel and the Quran, and he is the custodian of God’s Law*.
* Qur’anic verse (xxx. 30): ‘So set thy face for religion, being upright, the nature made by Allah in which He has created man.’ Allah’s Nature, as the Qur’anic verse signifies, stands for Islam to which the Prophet is commissioned to give practical and concrete shape.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حکمتش برتر ز عقل ذوفنون
از ضمیرش امتی آید برون
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس کی حکمت عقل چالاک سے برتر ہے، اس کے ضمیر سے (نئی) امت وجود میں آتی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        His wisdom is superior to artful Reason, his spirit gives birth to a people (ummah).
(It appears that, according to Iqbal, the hikmat (wisdom) of the Prophet is not qualitatively different from reason only it is much higher than the latter.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حکمرانی بی نیاز از تخت و تاج
بی کلاہ و بی سپاہ و بی خراج
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        وہ ایسا حکمران ہے ، جو تاج و تخت سے بے نیاز ہے، نہ وہ کلّاہ رکھتا ہے، نہ سپاہ اور نہ کسی سے خراج وصول کرتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He is a ruler disinterested in throne and crown: sans crown, sans army, sans tribute.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        از نگاہش فرودین خیزد ز دی
درد ہر خم تلخ تر گردد ز می
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس کی نگاہ خزاں کو بہار میں تبدیل کر دیتی ہے، اس کی شراب (تعلیم) ہر خم کی تلچھٹ کو اور زیادہ نشہ آور بنا دیتی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        His look transforms autumn into spring, and through him the dregs of every pitcher become stronger than the wine.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اندر آہ صبحگاہ او حیات
تازہ از صبح نمودش کائنات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس کی آہ سحر گاہی میں نئی زندگی ہے، اس کی صبح نمود کائنات کو تازگی عطا کرتی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In his morning-lamentation lies life and the universe is renewed by the morning of his manifestation.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بحر و بر از زور طوفانش خراب
در نگاہ او پیام انقلاب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس کے طوفان کے زور میں سمندر اور خشکی ڈوب جاتے ہيں؛ اس کی نگاہ میں انقلاب کا پیغام ہوتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The sea and the earth are devastated by the intensity of his deluge, and in his eyes there is a message of revolution.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        درس "لا خوف علیہم" می دہد
تا دلے در سینۂ آدم نہد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        وہ انہیں لا خوف علیہم کا درس دیتا ہے، تاکہ آدم کے سینہ کے اندر دل مضبوط ہو۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He teaches the lesson of they have no fear; he puts a heart into the breast of man.
(Qur’anic verse (x. 62): ‘Now surely the friends of Allah have no fear, nor do they grieve.’)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عزم و تسلیم و رضا آموزدش
در جہان مثل چراغ افروزدش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        وہ اسے عزم ، فرمانبرداری اور راضی برضا رہنا سکھا کر دنیا میں چراغ کی مانند روشن کر دیتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He teaches man determination, submission (to the will of God) and willing acquiescence; and makes him radiant in the world like a lamp.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        من نمیدانم چہ افسون می کند
روح را در تن دگرگون می کند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میں نہیں جانتا کہ وہ کیا افسوں پھونکتا ہے جس سے بدن کے اندر جو روح ہے وہ کچھ اور ہو جاتی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I do not know what magic he practises, but he totally transforms the soul in the body.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        صحبت او ہر خزف را در کند
حکمت او ہر تہی را پر کند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس کیصحبت ہر سنگریزے کو موتی بنا دیتی ہے اور اس کی حکمت ہر ایک کا دامن بھر دیتی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In his society a piece of clay becomes a pearl; and his wisdom gives abundance to the deficient.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="31">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بندۂ درماندہ را گوید کہ خیز
ہر کہن معبود را کن ریز ریز"
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        و ہ گرے ہوئے غلام سے کہتا ہے : 'اٹھ اور ہر پرانے معبد کو ریزہ ریزہ کر دے'۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He says to the downtrodden slave: Arise and break into pieces every ancient
deity.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مرد حق افسون این دیر کہن
از دو حرف "ربی الاعلی" شکن
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اے بندہ حق ! ربی الاعلی کے دو الفاظ سے اس پرانے بتخانہ (دنیا) کا جادو توڑ دے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O man of God, break the spell of this old world with these words: God is the highest of all.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="35">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فقر خواہی از تہی دستی منال
عافیت در حال و نے در جاہ و مال
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        فقر چاہتا ہے کہ تو افلاس کی فریاد نہ کر؛ سکون قلب کی کیفیت پر منحصر ہے، اس کا تعلق جاہ و مال سے نہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If you wish to gain faqr, don’t complain of poverty; well-being depends on one’s attitude and not on rank and wealth.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="37">
      <Text Language="Original">
        صدق و اخلاص و نیاز و سوز و درد
نے زر و سیم و قماش سرخ و زرد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        صدق، اخلاص ، نیازمندی اور سوز و درد (سکوں لاتے ہیں) نہ کہ سونا چاندی اور سرخ و زرد (ریشمی) کپڑے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Truthfulness, sincerity, submissiveness, ardour and sympathy these are needed and not gold or silver, nor red and yellow coins.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="39">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بگذر از کاوس و کی اے زندہ مرد 
طوف خود کن گرد ایوانی مگرد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اے زندہ مرد! کیکاؤس اور کیقباد جیسے بادشاہوں کے محلات کا طواف کرنے کی بجائے اپنا طواف کر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O living man, avoid these kings and nobles, walk around your own self and not around the palaces.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="41">
      <Text Language="Original">
        از مقام خویش دور افتادہ ئی
کرگسی کم کن کہ شاہین زادہ ئی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تو اپنے مقام سے دور جا پڑا ہے، تو شاہینوں کی اولاد ہے کرگسوں جیسے کام نہ کر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Thou hast fallen away from thy true station, thou art born of a falcon, do not follow the ways of vultures.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="43">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مرغک اندر شاخسار بوستان
بر مراد خویش بندد آشیان
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        پرندہ بھی باغ کے درخت کی ٹہنیوں پر اپنی مرضی کے مطابق اپنا آشیانہ بناتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A bird in a garden grove builds his nest to his own liking.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="45">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تو کہ داری فکرت گردون مسیر
خویش را از مرغکی کمتر مگیر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تیری سوچ کی پرواز آسمانوں تک ہے؛ تو اپنے آپ کو پرندے سے کم تر نہ سمجھ ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Thou who hast a heaven-traversing imagination should not think thyself inferior to a bird.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="47">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دیگر این نہ آسمان تعمیر کن
بر مراد خود جہان تعمیر کن
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ان نو آسمانوں کو دوبارہ تعمیر کر۔ اس دنیا کو اپنی مرضی کے مطابق بنا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Rebuild these nine heavens and refashion this world according to thy own desire.
(According to Lisan aI-’Arab, the word ‘seven’ was used by the Arabs to denote multiplicity. Iqbal’s use of ‘nine’ instead of ‘seven’ does not seem to be a departure from the classical tradition; it may have been used to conform, not of course exactly, to the latest scientific research.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="49">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چون فنا اندر رضای حق شود
بندۂ مومن قضای حق شود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جب بندہء مومن اپنے آپ کو رضائے الہی میں گم کر دیتا ہے تو وہ قضائے الہی بن جاتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When he gets annihilated in God’s will, the man of faith becomes God’ decree.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="51">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چار سوی با فضای نیلگون
از ضمیر پاک او آید برون
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        پھر یہ جہان چار سو اور یہ فضائے نیلگوں اس کے ضمیر پاک کے اندر سے نئی صورت میں باہر آتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The four dimensions along with the blue heavens are born out of his pure bosom.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="53">
      <Text Language="Original">
        در رضای حق فنا شو چون سلف
گوہر خود را برون آر از صدف
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اپنے آباء کی طرح اللہ تعالے کی رضا میں گم ہو کر صدف سے اپنے موتی کو باہر نکال۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Annihilate thyself in the will of God like thy forefathers; bring out thy pearl out of the oyster.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="55">
      <Text Language="Original">
        در ظلام این جہان سنگ و خشت
چشم خود روشن کن از نور سرشت
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس جہان سنگ و خشت کی تاریکی میں اپنی پاک طینت کے نور سے روشن کر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In the darkness of this world of stone and bricks, illumine thy eyes with the light of thy nature.
(Light of nature: Nur-i sirisht, the natural simplicity and righteousness of man, the basic nature (fitrat Allah) on which God created man.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="57">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تا نگیری از جلال حق نصیب
ہم نیابی از جمال حق نصیب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جب تک تو اللہ تعالے کے جلال سے حصّہ نہ پائے گا، اس کے جمال سے بھی بہرہ اندوز نہ ہو سکے گا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Unless thou takest thy share of the majesty of God, thou canst not enjoy Divine Beauty.
(Majesty (jalal) and beauty (jamal) are the two antithetical but complementary aspects of God’s Essence. The former indicates might, wrath, awfulness, while the latter stands for beauty, mercy and loving-kindness.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="59">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ابتدای عشق و مستی قاہری است
انتہای عشق و مستی دلبری است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        عشق و مستی کی ابتدا قاہری (سختی) اور انتہا دلبری (محبوبی) ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The beginning of love and ecstasy is majesty (qahiri); the end of love and ecstasy is beauty (dilbari).
(Dilbari, lit, art of heart-ravishing, heart-captivating, while qahiri, lit, is conquering power, might. These two terms like jamal and jalal, khalwat and jalwat form two complementary aspects of a higher synthesis.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="61">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مرد مومن از کمالات وجود
او وجود و غیر او ہر شی نمود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مرد مومن کمالات وجود (کے شاہکاروں میں) سے ہے۔ وہ وجود (حقیقی ) ہے، باقی ہر شے صرف (وجود) نظر آتی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The man of faith is a symbol of perfect existence: he alone is real; all else is mere appearance.
(According to pantheistic mystics, wujud (being), as such, belongs to God alone; all else is devoid of wujud and if they possess it, it is only as a reflection (zill). Here Iqbal asserts that man alone has independent existence and enjoys fullness of being. By wujud, Iqbal means strong and rich personality.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="63">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گر بگیرد سوز و تاب از لاالہ
جز بکام او نگردد مھر و مہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اگر مومن لاالہ سے حرارت اور چمک پا لے تو سورج اور چاند (یہ کائنات) اسی کے مقصد کی تکمیل کے لیے گردش کرتے ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If he gains ardour and zeal from There is no deity (but God), the Sun and Moon will revolve only at his bidding.
(Translated by Jamil Naqvi)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>