<Poem ID="48" Name="شعاع آفتاب" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        صبح جب میری نگہ سودائی نظارہ تھی 
آسماں پر اک شعاع آفتاب آوارہ تھی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE SUN’S RAY
At the dawn when my eye was enjoying the panorama I saw that a ray of the sun was wandering about.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میں نے پوچھا اس کرن سے اے سراپا اضطراب! 
تیری جان ناشکیبا میں ہے کیسا اضطراب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ناشکيبا: بے صبر، بے چین، بے قرار۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I asked the ray, ‘O head to foot restlessness! What kind of restlessness your impatient life has!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تو کوئی چھوٹی سی بجلی ہے کہ جس کو آسماں 
کر رہا ہے خرمن اقوام کی خاطر جواں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Are you a small little lightning, which the sky is nurturing to fall on the harvest of nations.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ تڑپ ہے یا ازل سے تیری خو ہے، کیا ہے یہ 
رقص ہے، آوارگی ہے، جستجو ہے، کیا ہے یہ؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Is this a flash, or your eternal nature, what is it? Is it a dance? Wandering? Seeking what is it?’
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خفتہ ہنگامے ہیں میری ہستی خاموش میں 
پرورش پائی ہے میں نے صبح کی آغوش میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ‘A sea of tumults is asleep in my silent life; my existence has been nurtured by the morning’s breeze.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مضطرب ہر دم مری تقدیر رکھتی ہے مجھے 
جستجو میں لذت تنویر رکھتی ہے مجھے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My destiny keeps me constantly restless. Taste for enlightenment keeps me busy in seeking.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        برق آتش خو نہیں، فطرت میں گو ناری ہوں میں 
مہر عالم تاب کا پیغام بیداری ہوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I am not fire-brand lightning, though by nature fire I am. Message of awakening from the world-illuminating sun I am!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سرمہ بن کر چشم انساں میں سما جائوں گی میں 
رات نے جو کچھ چھپا رکھا تھا، دکھلائوں گی میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Becoming collyrium I shall enter the human eye; whatever night had hidden I shall show to the eye.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تیرے مستوں میں کوئی جویائے ہشیاری بھی ہے 
سونے والوں میں کسی کو ذوق بیداری بھی ہے؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Among your ecstatics is there any seeker of prudence also? Among the sleeping people is anyone with taste of awakening also?’
(Translated by Dr. M.A.K. Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>