<Poem ID="29" Name="" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="04" SectionName="ظریفانہ">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مسجد تو بنا دی شب بھر میں ایماں کی حرارت والوں نے 
من اپنا پرانا پاپی ہے، برسوں میں نمازی بن نہ سکا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Though the mosque was built overnight by the believers’ our heart being old sinner for years devout could not be.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کیا خوب امیر فیصل کو سنوسی نے پیغام دیا 
تو نام و نسب کا حجازی ہے پر دل کا حجازی بن نہ سکا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What a beautiful message did Sanosi give to King Faisal: By descent you Hijazi are, but in heart Hijazi could no be.
(Sanosi: A member of the Brotherhood founded in 1837 in North Africa by Muéammad Ibn ‘Ali al-Sanosi (d. 1859), an Algerian Muslim leader.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تر آنکھیں تو ہو جاتی ہیں، پر کیا لذت اس رونے میں 
جب خون جگر کی آمیزش سے اشک پیازی بن نہ سکا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Though eyes become wet there is no pleasure is in this weeping; if by mixture of affliction’s blood tears pink could not be.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اقبال بڑا اپدیشک ہے من باتوں میں موہ لیتا ہے 
گفتارکا یہ غازی تو بنا،کردار کا غازی بن نہ سکا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اپديشک: اچھا واعظ۔ اچھا مشیر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Iqbal is a good advisor, fascinates the heart in moments; he did become hero in talk, but one in deeds he could not be.
This marks the end of poetic works chosen from Bang-e-Dara, wherein Iqbal focused more in expressing his grief and pain, with only passing remarks about causes and remedies. This changed markedly with the passage of time.
[Translated by Dr M A K Khalil]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>