<Poem ID="13" Name="عا شق ہر جائی" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="2a" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="(1)">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے عجب مجموعہء اضداد اے اقبال تو
رونق ہنگامہء محفل بھی ہے، تنہا بھی ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مجموعہء اضداد: ایسے اوصاف کا مجموعہ جو ایک دوسرے کی ضد ہوں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE UNFAITHFUL LOVER
O Iqbal! You are a strange mixture of opposites; you are the elegance of assembly’s crowd as well as alone.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تیرے ہنگاموں سے اے دیوانہ رنگیں نوا!
زینت گلشن بھی ہے، آرائش صحرا بھی ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O lunatic with colorful song! Your struggles and efforts are the garden’s beauty as well as wilderness’ adornment.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہم نشیں تاروں کا ہے تو رفعت پرواز سے
اے زمیں فرسا، قدم تیرا فلک پیما بھی ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        زميں فرسا: زمین پر چلنے پھرنے والا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You are the associate of stars due to your flight’s elegance: O land traveler your steps also traverse the sky.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عین شغل میں پیشانی ہے تیری سجدہ ریز
کچھ ترے مسلک میں رنگ مشرب مینا بھی ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your forehead is in prostration in the midst of preoccupation with wine; in your system are some colours of the system of goblets also.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مثل بوئے گل لباس رنگ سے عریاں ہے تو
ہے تو حکمت آفریں، لیکن تجھے سودا بھی ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Like flower’s fragrance you are devoid of colour’s dress; though you are a creator of wisdom you are also insane.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جانب منزل رواں بے نقش پا مانند موج
اور پھر افتادہ مثل ساحل دریا بھی ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مانند موج: لہر کی طرح۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Like waves you are running to the destination without foot-prints; and then you are also left behind like the sea-shore. 
(This means that though you claim to pursue the path of the Love of God, which ultimately leads to Fana Fi-Allah you are also involved in the love of material objects of the universe, including human beings. Is this not anomalous?)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حسن نسوانی ہے بجلی تیری فطرت کے لیے
پھر عجب یہ ہے کہ تیرا عشق بے پروا بھی ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Female beauty has the effect of electricity for your nature; and strangely enough your loves are unconventional also.
(As you have ‘Ishq-i-Majazi’, including ‘Husn i Niswan’ or female beauty you really do not follow the customs of fidelity.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تیری ہستی کا ہے آئین تفنن پر مدار
تو کبھی ایک آستانے پر جبیں فرسا بھی ہے ؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تفنن: گوناگوئی۔ 
جبيں فرسا: پیشانی گھسنے والی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your existence depends on the amusement’s law: Are you prostrating only at a single door step?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے حسینوں میں وفا نا آشنا تیرا خطاب
اے تلون کیش! تو مشہور بھی، رسوا بھی ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تلون کيش: وہ شخص جو اپنے انداز بدلتا رہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Among the beautiful you are famous for infidelity O fickle-minded! You are famous as well as infamous.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لے کے آیا ہے جہاں میں عادت سیماب تو
تیری بے تابی کے صدقے، ہے عجب بے تاب تو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You have come into the world with mercury’s nature; your restlessness is lovable, you are very restless.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(2)">
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عشق کی آشفتگی نے کر دیا صحرا جسے
مشت خاک ایسی نہاں زیر قبا رکھتا ہوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        آشفتگي: پریشانی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What the disturbance of love has turned into wilderness; I keep that handful of dust concealed under the cloak.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہیں ہزاروں اس کے پہلو، رنگ ہر پہلو کا اور
سینے میں ہیرا کوئی ترشا ہوا رکھتا ہوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It has thousands of facets, each of a different colour; I keep such a multi-faceted diamond in my breast.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دل نہیں شاعر کا، ہے کیفیتوں کی رستخیز
کیا خبر تجھ کو درون سینہ کیا رکھتا ہوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        رستخيز: قیامت۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The poet’s heart is but intoxication’s toil and hustle: What do you know, what I keep inside my breast!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آرزو ہر کیفیت میں اک نئے جلوے کی ہے
مضطرب ہوں، دل سکوں نا آشنا رکھتا ہوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In every intoxication of Love there is a new effulgence of Longing; I am restless, I have a heart unacquainted with rest.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گو حسین تازہ ہے ہر لحظہ مقصود نظر
حسن سے مضبوط پیمان وفا رکھتا ہوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Though a new beauty every moment is the sight’s object, I have a firm covenant of fidelity with the Beauty.
(Though I love the beauty of every new object of the material universe I possess the everlasting Love of God in my heart.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="31">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بے نیازی سے ہے پیدا میری فطرت کا نیاز
سوز و ساز جستجو مثل صبا رکھتا ہوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Beniazi has created my nature’s Niaz; I keep the struggle for the Longing like the zephyr.
(Beniazi (freedom from need, which is an attribute of God) has created the opposite nature of ‘niaz’ (or being in need) in me. This needfulness has created the longing for the Sight of God, which is my strongest need and for which I am wandering around like zephyr. This thought extends to the next two verses.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        موجب تسکیں تماشائے شرار جستہ اے
ہو نہیں سکتا کہ دل برق آشنا رکھتا ہوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        شرار جستہ: تڑپ کر اچھلنے والی چنگاری۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The spectacle of a single flying spark cannot be assuasive as I have a thunderous heart.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="35">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہر تقاضا عشق کی فطرت کا ہو جس سے خموش
آہ! وہ کامل تجلی مدعا رکھتا ہوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What may fulfill every demand of the nature of Love Ah! Attainment of that perfect effulgence is my aim.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="37">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جستجو کل کی لیے پھرتی ہے اجزا میں مجھے
حسن بے پایاں ہے، درد لادوا رکھتا ہوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The search for the Whole misguides me into its parts. The Beauty is boundless, I have the incurable pathos.
(According to the theory of ‘Wahdat al Shuhood’ God is the Whole or Real Being and has a real Existence while the material objects of the universe are merely the reflections of this Being. In my search for God I am temporarily misguided to the objects of the material world. However, my objective is always kept in view which guides me back to the right path.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="39">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زندگی الفت کی درد انجامیوں سے ہے مری
عشق کو آزاد دستور وفا رکھتا ہوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        درد انجاميوں: وہ کیفیت جس کی انتہا درد ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My life depends upon Love's extreme compassion, but I keep the Love free of customs of fidelity. 
(For the reasons mentioned in note above, though I appreciate and love the material objects of the universe I keep that love free of the custom of fidelity. This guides me away from them and towards the object of my real Love, i.e. God.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="41">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سچ اگر پوچھے تو افلاس تخیل ہے وفا
دل میں ہر دم اک نیا محشر بپا رکھتا ہوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        افلاس تخيل: خیال کی ناداری۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The truth is that lack of imagination produces fidelity;* I have a new Resurrection Day ever fresh in my heart.
(People practice fidelity in their love for material objects, like human beings, because of their lack of power of imagination on account of which they do not realize that the material objects do not have a real existence and are merely reflections of the Divine Beauty.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="43">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فیض ساقی شبنم آسا، ظرف دل دریا طلب
تشنہء دائم ہوں آتش زیر پا رکھتا ہوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        شبنم آسا: شبنم کی مانند۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        By creating me He created His own critic; as a picture, I have complaint against my Painter.
(Allusion to the anomaly that though Man has been created by God he always criticizes his Creator.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="45">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مجھ کو پیدا کر کے اپنا نکتہ چیں پیدا کیا
نقش ہوں، اپنے مصور سے گلا رکھتا ہوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If the Beauty was so short lived in existence' assembly; why then do I keep such a boundless imagination?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="47">
      <Text Language="Original">
        محفل ہستی میں جب ایسا تنک جلوہ تھا حسن
پھر تخیل کس لیے لا انتہا رکھتا ہوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Cup bearer's bounty is like dew, heart's capacity demands oceans; I am always thirsty, I have a burning fire under my foot.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="49">
      <Text Language="Original">
        در بیابان طلب پیوستہ می کوشیم ما
موج بحریم و شکست خویش بر دوشیم ما
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میں تو تلاش و جستجو کے صحرا میں مسلسل جد و جہد میں مصروف ہوں اور سمندر کی موجوں کی طرح اپنی شکست کا سامان خود اپنے کندھوں پر اٹھائے پھرتا ہوں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I am constantly struggling in the Longing's wilderness; I am the ocean's wave, I carry my destruction on my shoulder.
(This is an extremely beautiful metaphor. The ocean waves harbour their destruction in their existence, which occurs when they reach the shore. Similarly, my creation and existence as a human being harbour the potential for my destruction on reaching the life's end.)
(Translated by Dr. M.A.K. Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>