<Poem ID="04" Name="" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="1b" SectionName="غزلیات 1">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لائوں وہ تنکے کہیں سے آشیانے کے لیے
بجلیاں بے تاب ہوں جن کو جلانے کے لیے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I should procure such straws for my nest from somewhere for burning which the lightning may be restless.
(One should be prepared to sacrifice everything in the Love of God.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وائے ناکامی، فلک نے تاک کر توڑا اسے
میں نے جس ڈالی کو تاڑا آشیانے کے لیے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Alas! O despair! The sky broke it down intently; whichever branch I selected for my nest.
(Under the influence of Greek cosmology the sky was considered to control human destiny throughout the ancient world. In particular it was believed to bring ill luck. Though this belief no longer exists the expression still continues in Urdu and Persian literature.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آنکھ مل جاتی ہے ہفتاد و دو ملت سے تری
ایک پیمانہ ترا سارے زمانے کے لیے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You are contending with the seventy two nations; one goblet of yours suits the whole world best.*
*Allusion to the Hadith of the Holy Prophet S.A.W. that the Muslim Ummah would be divided into seventy two sects. However, this verse reminds Muslims that the Holy Qur’an has been sent down to guide the entire world and unite the whole mankind into a super national society and State. So the Muslims, who are its first recipients and custodians, should keep their own brotherhood intact instead of being divided into seventy-two mutually contending sects.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دل میں کوئی اس طرح کی آرزو پیدا کروں
لوٹ جائے آسماں میرے مٹانے کے لیے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I should create some such longing in my heart; so the sky may turn around to annihilate me best.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جمع کر خرمن تو پہلے دانہ دانہ چن کے تو
آ ہی نکلے گی کوئی بجلی جلانے کے لیے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Collect your harvest first by picking it grain by grain; some thunderbolt will surely come out to annihilate it. 
(Verses 4 and 5 mean that the highest felicity for a Lover of God is to sacrifice all his hard-earned worldly possessions in His cause.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پاس تھا ناکامی صیاد کا اے ہم صفیر
ورنہ میں، اور اڑ کے آتا ایک دانے کے لیے!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ہم صفير: ہم آواز ، ہم نوا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I had regard for the failure of the hunter, O friend; otherwise, why could I come over flying for one grain?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اس چمن میں مرغ دل گائے نہ آزادی کا گیت
آہ یہ گلشن نہیں ایسے ترانے کے لیے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The heart should not sing freedom's song in this garden. Ah! This garden is not suitable for such odes!
(Translated by Dr. M.A.K. Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>