<Poem ID="01" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="01" SectionName="حصہ اول">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میری نوائے شوق سے شور حریم ذات میں 
غلغلہ ہائے الاماں بت کدئہ صفات میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ذات: باری تعالے کی ہستی ، وجود مطلق۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A blaze is raging near His Throne by my strains that burn like flames; the cries of ‘Mercy!’ rise aloft from the Temple of His Names.

Blaze: Conflagration. His Throne: The precincts of the Absolute Being or Harim-i-Zat, the original word in the text. Strains: Songs. Aloft: On high. Temple of His Names: The Temple of His attributes.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حور و فرشتہ ہیں اسیر میرے تخیلات میں 
میری نگاہ سے خلل تیری تجلیات میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Houris and angels, all alike, my soaring thought can keep in hold: The moulds in which Thou dost reveal get ruffled by my glances bold.

Moulds: Shapes i.e., the different aspects in which God displays Himself. 
Ruffled: Disturbed
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گرچہ ہے میری جستجو دیر و حرم کی نقش بند 
میری فغاں سے رستخیز کعبہ و سومنات میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        نقش بند: نقش باندھنے والا، نقّاش۔ 
رستخیز: قیامت۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In my search and quest for Thee Cloisters and Kirks I did design, but my groans and woeful wails can shake the founds of Fane and Shrine.

Cloister: a place of religious retirement, a sanctuary. Kirk: Scotch equivalent for church. Founds: Foundations. Pane: Temple. Shrine: Sanctuary.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گاہ مری نگاہ تیز چیر گئی دل وجود 
گاہ الجھ کے رہ گئی میرے توہمات میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        There were times when my vision sharp pierced the heart and core of Life: Time again, fell short of mark by mine inner doubts and strife. 
Mark: Target.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تو نے یہ کیا غضب کیا، مجھ کو بھی فاش کر دیا 
میں ہی تو اک راز تھا سینہء کائنات میں!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I was the only secret veil’d in Nature’s Womb in Latent form: When I was brought to light for show, what wondrous act Thou didst perform!

Womb: Uterus, the organ in which the young of mammals are developed and kept till birth, the word in the poem is Sina-i-Kainat. Latent: Hidden.
(Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>