<Poem ID="44" Name="" BookID="08" BookName="زبورِعجم" SectionID="02" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بیا کہ خاوریان نقش تازہ ئی بستند
دگر مرو بطواف بتی کہ بشکستند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Come! The Asiatic man has created a new plan: Go not, pilgrimage to make to the idol that he brake.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چہ جلوہ ایست کہ دلہا بلذت نگہی
ز خاک راہ مثال شرارہ بر جستند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What is this epiphany that men’s hearts, rejoiced to see, from the ashes of the way gladly leap, like sparks at play?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کجاست منزل تورانیان شہر آشوب
کہ سینہ ہای خود از تیزی نفس خستند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        To attain what far abode strive the Turks upon the road, that their bosom fluttereth with the quickness of their breath?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تو ہم بذوق خودی رس کہ صاحبان طریق
بریدہ از ہمہ عالم بخویش پیوستند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Strive thou, selfhood’s joy to know: They who on this journey go shatter every worldly chain that they may to self attain.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بچشم مردہ دلان کائنات زندانی است
دو جام بادہ کشیدند و از جہان رستند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Men whose hearts are dead and cold as a cell this world behold; with two cups to fill their head, from the whole of life they fled.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        غلام ہمت بیدار آن سوارانم
ستارہ را بہ سنان سفتہ در گرہ بستند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I will ever be the slave of those horsemen bold and brave who, with spear uplifted, far ride, to pierce and thread a star.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فرشتہ را دگر آن فرصت سجود کجاست
کہ نوریان بتماشای خاکیان مستند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Angels lack the season now prostrate to their Lord to bow; creatures of pure light, for they rapturous gaze on men of clay!
(Translated by A.J. Arberry)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>