<Poem ID="22" Name="قطرۂ آب" BookID="07" BookName="پیامِ مشرق" SectionID="02" SectionName="افکار">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مرا معنی تازہ ئی مدعاست
اگر گفتہ را باز گویم رواست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE RAINDROP AND THE SEA
I quote what someone else has said, but wish to make a new point with its aid.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یکی قطرہ باران ز ابری چکید
خجل شد چو پہنای دریا بدید
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ‘A raindrop fell into the sea. And awed by its expanse, it thought:
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کہ جائی کہ دریاست من کیستم؟
گر او ہست حقا کہ من نیستم"
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        By God, I am a mere nonentity beside the sea. If it exists, then surely I do not.’
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ولیکن ز دریا برآمد خروش
ز شرم تنک مایگی رو مپوش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        There came out of the sea a sound, loud and profound, as of a voice, and it declaimed: ‘You do not have to be ashamed of being small and feel so sad.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تماشای شام و سحر دیدہ ئی
چمن دیدہ ئی دشت و در دیدہ ئی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        For all your smallness, you have had experiences which were great. You have watched dawn and evening alternate. You have seen orchard, plain and glade.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بہ برگ گیاہی بہ دوش سحاب
درخشیدی از پرتو آفتاب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Suspended on a blade of grass or a cloud-flake, you have reflected the sun’s rays.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گہی ھمدم تشنہ کامان راغ
گہی محرم سینہ چاکان باغ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        There have been days on which it fell to you to slake the thirst of desert shrubs. Again, there were days when you soothed the pain in the rent bosom of a rose.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گہی خفتہ در تاک و طاقت گداز
گہی خفتہ در خاک بی سوز و ساز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        At times you slumbered in the vine to wake up as a potent liquid – wine. At other times abed in dust, you made mere mud.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ز موج سبک سیر من زادہ ئی
ز من زادہ ئی در من افتادہ ئی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It was out of my waves that you arose. Born of me, you come back to me, come back to be a part of me.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بیاسای در خلوت سینہ ام
چو جوھر درخش اندر آئینہ ام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Now rest in my broad breast, and make my mirror gleam with one more beam of light.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گہر شو در آغوش قلزم بزی
فروزان تر از ماہ و انجم بزی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Become a pearl and be lodged in the depths of me – My moon, my star, as bright as those of the sky are.’ 
(Translated by M. Hadi Husain)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>