<Poem ID="10" Name="وطنیت" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="یعنی وطن بحیثیت ایک سیاسی تصور کے">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اس دور میں مے اور ہے، جام اور ہے جم اور 
ساقی نے بنا کی روش لطف و ستم اور
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        NATIONALISM (Nation as a political concept)
In this age the wine, the cup, even Jam is different. The cup-bearer started different ways of grace and tyranny.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مسلم نے بھی تعمیر کیا اپنا حرم اور 
تہذیب کے آزر نے ترشوائے صنم اور
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Muslim also constructed a different Haram of his own; the Azar of civilization made different idols of his own.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ان تازہ خداوں میں بڑا سب سے وطن ہے
جو پیرہن اس کا ہے، وہ مذہب کا کفن ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        پيرہن: لباس۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Country is the biggest among these new gods! What is its shirt is the shroud of Din.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ بت کہ تراشیدہء تہذیب نوی ہے 
غارت گر کاشانہء دین نبوی ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تراشيدہء تہذيب نوي: نئی تہذیب کا تراشا ہوا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This idol which is the product of the new civilization is the plunderer of the structure of the Holy Prophet’s (S.A.W.) Deen.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بازو ترا توحید کی قوت سے قوی ہے 
اسلام ترا دیس ہے، تو مصطفوی ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your arm is enforced with the strength of the Divine Unity. You are the followers of Mustafa (S.A.W.), your country is Islam.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نظارہ دیرینہ زمانے کو دکھا دے 
اے مصطفوی خاک میں اس بت کو ملا دے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        نظارہ ديرينہ: پرانا نظارہ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You should show the old panorama to the world, O Mustafa’s follower! You should destroy this idol.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہو قید مقامی تو نتیجہ ہے تباہی 
رہ بحر میں آزاد وطن صورت ماہی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        قيد مقامي: زمین کے چھوٹے چھوٹے حصّوں میں قید۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The limitation to country results in destruction; live like the fish in the ocean free from country.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے ترک وطن سنت محبوب الہی 
دے تو بھی نبوت کی صداقت پہ گواہی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Renouncing the country is the way of the God’s Beloved;* you should also testify to the Prophethood’s Truth by similar action.
* Allusion to the emigration of the Holy Prophet (S.A.W.) to Madinah.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گفتار سیاست میں وطن اور ہی کچھ ہے 
ارشاد نبوت میں وطن اور ہی کچھ ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In political parlance country is something different. In Prophet’s command country is something different.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اقوام جہاں میں ہے رقابت تو اسی سے 
تسخیر ہے مقصود تجارت تو اسی سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        رقابت: دشمنی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The antagonism among world’s nations is created by this alone; subjugation as the goal of commerce is created by this alone.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خالی ہے صداقت سے سیاست تو اسی سے 
کمزور کا گھر ہوتا ہے غارت تو اسی سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Politics have become bereft of sincerity is by this alone; the destruction of the home of the weak is by this alone.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اقوام میں مخلوق خدا بٹتی ہے اس سے 
قومیت اسلام کے جڑ کٹتی ہے اس سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        God’s creation is unjustly divided among nations by it; the Islamic concept of nationality is uprooted by it. 
(Translated by M.A.K. Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>