<Poem ID="04" Name="سوامی رام تیرتھ" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="2a" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہم بغل دریا سے ہے اے قطرہ بے تاب تو
پہلے گوہر تھا، بنا اب گوہر نایاب تو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        SWAMY RAM TIRATH
O Impatient drop! You are in the bosom of the sea; you were a pearl earlier, now you are an invaluable pearl.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آہ کھولا کس ادا سے تو نے راز رنگ و بو
میں ابھی تک ہوں اسیر امتیاز رنگ و بو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Ah! How gracefully you opened the secrets of life; I am still a prisoner of the discriminations of life.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مٹ کے غوغا زندگی کا شورش محشر بنا
یہ شرارہ بجھ کے آتش خانہ آزر بنا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The life’s clamour on destruction became the Last Day’s tumult; the spark on being extinguished became Azar’s fire temple. 
(Azar: Father of Ibrahim A.S. was a master sculptor and idol maker in Chaldea. Though he was not connected with the pre-Islamic fire temples of Iran this expression confers special excellence, in the material sense, on fire temples.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نفی ہستی اک کرشمہ ہے دل آگاہ کا
'لا' کے دریا میں نہاں موتی ہے 'الااللہ' کا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The denial of Existence is the Love’s gesture of the informed heart; in the river of La is concealed the pearl of Illallah.
(This alludes to the Kalimah-i-Tawhid. The first part of theKalimah, ‘La’ is the negation and denial of everything except God and is the prelude to the second partIllallah which is what the Kalimah accepts and testifies.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چشم نابینا سے مخفی معنی انجام ہے
تھم گئی جس دم تڑپ، سیماب سیم خام ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The meaning of the end is hidden from the unsightful eye: Mercury is only raw silver, when its restlessness stops.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        توڑ دیتا ہے بت ہستی کو ابراہیم عشق
ہوش کا دارو ہے گویا مستی تسنیم عشق
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Ibrahim of Love is the destroyer of the idol of existence. The ecstasy of Tasnim* of Love is the cure of awareness.
(This verse is highly mystical. Tasnâm is one of the streams of Paradise. Ecstasy denotes perfection of Love and the ecstasy produced by the water of Tasnâm is the perfection of the Love of God. This perfection is the cure for the awareness which is an impediment to ecstasy resulting from the Love of God.
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>