<Poem ID="17" Name="انسان" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="2a" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        قدرت کا عجیب یہ ستم ہے!
انسان کو راز جو بنایا
راز اس کی نگاہ سے چھپایا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        MANKIND
What an ingenious tyranny of Nature it is! Man has been made a seeker of the Secret; The Secret has been concealed from his eyes.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بے تاب ہے ذوق آگہی کا
کھلتا نہیں بھید زندگی کا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The taste for awareness is restless; the secret of life is not un raveled.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حیرت آغاز و انتہا ہے
آئینے کے گھر میں اور کیا ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Amazing is the alpha and omega of life*: What else is there in the mirror's house?
(Alpha and Omega: Alpha is the first letter of the Greek alphabet. This word is also used for the brightest star in a constellation. Omega is the last letter of the Greek alphabet. The phrase is used for the most important person or entity, e.g. The New Testament, The Book of Revelations of Saint John the Divine, Chapter 1:8, in which Issa A.S. is supposed to have said to Saint John in his dream ‘I am Alpha and Omega, the beginning and the ending.’ In this verse Allamah uses this phrase to show the intrinsic value and elegance of Man, and also the miraculous way in which he was created by God.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے گرم خرام موج دریا
دریا سوئے سجر جادہ پیما
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The river stream is moving fast; the river is moving towards the ocean.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بادل کو ہوا اڑا رہی ہے
شانوں پہ اٹھائے لا رہی ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The wind is blowing the cloud: Is bringing the cloud on its shoulders.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تارے مست شراب تقدیر
زندان فلک میں پا بہ زنجیر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Stars are intoxicated with destiny's wine; they are chained in the prison of the sky.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خورشید، وہ عابد سحر خیز
لانے والا پیام بر خیز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The sun, that early rising devotee, that carrier of the message of ‘rise’!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مغرب کی پہاڑیوں میں چھپ کر
پیتا ہے مے شفق کا ساغر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Concealed in the hills of the west is drinking wine in twilight's goblet.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لذت گیر وجود ہر شے
سر مست مے نمود ہر شے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Everything is enjoying its existence; it is intoxicated with manifestation's wine.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کوئی نہیں غم گسار انساں
کیا تلخ ہے روزگار انساں!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        None is sympathetic with Man! How bitter is the life of Man!
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>