<Poem ID="52" Name="کفر واسلام" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="تضمین بر شعر میررضی دانش">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ایک دن اقبال نے پوچھا کلیم طور سے 
اے کہ تیرے نقش پا سے وادی سینا چمن
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        INFIDELITY AND ISLAM
One day Iqbal questioned the Kalim of Toor: ‘O You whose foot-prints converted the Valley of Sinai into a garden!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آتش نمرود ہے اب تک جہاں میں شعلہ ریز 
ہوگیا آنکھوں سے پنہاں کیوں ترا سوز کہن
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The fire of Namrud* is still ablaze in the world; why your Love’s old fire has been hidden from the eye’?
* Though the Holy Qur’an does not say so it is universally believed in Islamic literature that Namrud was the king who ordered that Ibrahim A.S. be thrown into the fire).
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تھا جواب صاحب سینا کہ مسلم ہے اگر 
چھوڑ کر غائب کو تو حاضر کا شیدائی نہ بن
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The reply of Sinai’s Master was: ‘If you are a Muslim, leaving the Invisible do not become the lover of the visible.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ذوق حاضر ہے تو پھر لازم ہے ایمان خلیل 
ورنہ خاکستر ہے تیری زندگی کا پیرہن
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If you have taste for the visible you need the Faith of Khalil; otherwise ashes are the adornments of your life.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے اگر دیوانہء غائب تو کچھ پروا نہ کر 
منتظر رہ وادی فاراں میں ہو کر خیمہ زن
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If you are Lover of the Invisible do not care at all; set your lamp in the Valley of Faran and remain waiting.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عارضی ہے شان حاضر، سطوت غائب مدام
اس صداقت کو محبت سے ہے ربط جان و تن
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The visible’s glory is temporary; the Invisibile’s Majesty is permanent. This Truth has the body-and-soul connection with Love.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شعلہ نمرود ہے روشن زمانے میں تو کیا 
شمع خود رامی گدازد درمیان انجمن 
نور ما چوں آتش سنگ از نظر پنہاں خوش است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What if the flame of Namrud is alight in the world?
The candle melts itself in the midst of the assembly; my light like the stone’s spark is better if concealed.’
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>