<Poem ID="03" Name="در فن تعمیر مردان آزاد" BookID="08" BookName="زبورِعجم" SectionID="04" SectionName="در بیان فنون لطیفۂ غلامان">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یک زمان با رفتگان صحبت گزین
صنعت آزاد مردان ہم ببین
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ایک لمحہ کے لیے گزرے ہوؤں کی صحبت اختیار کر اور آزاد مردوں کا فن بھی دیکھ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ON THE ARCHITECTURE OF FREE MEN
A slave, a follower shy of new ideas, is satisfied with status quo and he ceases to be a creative being. On the other hand, a freeman is never satisfied with the world he inherits. He wants change; constantly endeavours for improvement. He is an embodiment of creativity. In the last part of Bandgi Namah Allamah showed a glimpse of free man to draw contrast between him and slave.
Spare a moment for the company of those who have passed away; see the art (works) of free men.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خیز و کار ایبک و سوری نگر
وا نما چشمی اگر داری جگر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اگر تیرے اندر حوصلہ ہے تو اپنی آنکھ کھول، اٹھ اور قطب الدین ایبک اور شیر شاہ سوری کے کرشمے دیکھ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Open your eyes and see at miracles performed by Qutbuddin Aibek and Sher Shah Suri, if you have the heart.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خویش را از خود برون آوردہ اند
این چنین خود را تماشا کردہ اند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        انہوں نے تعمیرات میں اپنے آپ کو ظاہر کر کے خود اپنا نظّارہ کیا ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The displayed their inner selves through construction (creativity) and then sought satisfaction by looking at their own creations (through eyes of others).
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سنگہا با سنگہا پیوستہ اند
روزگاری را بہ آنی بستہ اند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        انہوں نے پتّھر کو پتّھر سے وابستہ کر کے پورے عہد کو ایک لمحہ میں مقید کر دیا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        By arranging stones along stones; they captured eternity in a moment.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دیدن او پختہ تر سازد ترا
در جھان دیگر اندازد ترا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ان تعمیرات کو دیکھنا تمہاری شخصیت کو پختہ تر بناتا، اور تمہیں ایک اور جہان میں لے جاتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Watching their creations (works) strengthens your personality; it takes you to another world.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نقش سوی نقشگر می آورد
از ضمیر او خبر می آورد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        فن اپنے فنکار کی طرف لے جاتا ہے اور اس کے ذہن رسا کا پتہ دیتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Art (symbol) takes you towards artist (creator); provides access into artist’s mind.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہمت مردانہ و طبع بلند
در دل سنگ این دو لعل ارجمند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ان عمارتوں کو دیکھنے سے ان کے پتّھر وں میں، ہمّت مردانہ اور طبع بلند کے دو قیمتی موتی نظر آتے ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Pearls of sustained manly effort and noble nature can be seen in the stones these buildings (creations).
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سجدہ گاہ کیست این از من مپرس
بی خبر روداد جان از تن مپرس
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مجھ سے نہ پوچھ یہ شاہکار کس کا سجدہ گاہ ہیں ، بے خبر! روح کے احوال کو بدن کیا بتا سکتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Don’t ask me whose place of worship these masterpieces become; O ignorant! Body cannot describe the tale of spirit.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        واے من از خویشتن اندر حجاب
از فرات زندگی ناخوردہ آب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        افسوس ہے مجھ پر کہ میں اپنے آپ سے حجاب میں ہوں، (اپنے آپ کو ظاہر نہیں کر سکا) میں نے زندگی کے دریا سے پانی نہیں پیا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Woe me! I am hidden from myself (I have not been able to discover myself); I have yet to drink from the stream of life.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        واے من از بیخ و بن بر کندہ ئی
از مقام خویش دور افکندہ ئی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        افسوس مجھ پر کہ میں نے اپنی بنیادیں کھود دی ہیں، اور اپنے مقام سے دور جا پڑا ہوں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Woe me! I regret digging (demolishing) my foundations; and I have fallen away from my (distinguished) position.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        محکمی ہا از یقین محکم است
واے من شاخ یقینم بی نم است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        استحکام ، یقیں محکم ہی سے حاصل ہوتا ہے، افسوس کہ میری شاخ یقیں سوکھ چکی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Stability accrues from strong faith; regretfully the branch of my faith has gone dry (has died).
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        در من آن نیروی الا اﷲ نیست
سجدہ ام شایان این درگاہ نیست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میرے اندر الا الہ کی قوّت نہیں، میرا سجدہ اس درگاہ کے لائق نہيں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I lack the strength of illallah (of the true faith, that there is no god except Allah); so my prostration is not worth this high shrine.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یک نظر آن گوھر نابی نگر
تاج را در زیر مہتابی نگر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ایک نظر اس گوہر نایاب کو دیکھ، تاج محل کا چاندنی رات میں نظّارہ کر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Have a glance at this rare jewel; look at Taj Mahal in moonlit night.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مرمرش ز آب روان گردندہ تر
یک دم آنجا از ابد پایندہ تر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس کا سنگ مرمرآب رواں سے بھی زیادہ تیز رو ہے (اس پر نظر نہیں ٹھہرتی) وہاں کا ایک لمحہ ابد سے پائندہ تر ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Its marble is shinier that the running (spring) water (it is difficult to focus on its dazzle); a moment of his world is longer than eternity.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عشق مردان سر خود را گفتہ است
سنگ را با نوک مژگان سفتہ است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        (اس عمارت کے ذریعے ) عشق مرداں نے اپنا بھید کہا ہے، (گویا ) پتھروں کو پلکوں کی نوک سے پرو دیا ہے ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The secret of True Love has been expressed (through their works); as if stone slabs have been laced (arranged) with the help of eyelashes.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="31">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عشق مردان پاک و رنگین چون بہشت
می گشاید نغمہ ہا از سنگ و خشت
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        عشق مرداں بہشت کی مانند پاک اور رنگیں ہے، وہ سنگ و خشت سے نغمے پیدا کر لیتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        True Love is clean and colourful like heavens; it produces songs with (the help of) stones and bricks.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عشق مردان نقد خوبان را عیار
حسن را ھم پردہ در ہم پردہ دار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        عشق مرداں محبوبوں ( کے جمال ) کی قیمت کا معیار ہے، وہ حسن کے چہرے سے پردہ بھی اٹھاتا ہے اور حسن کی حفاظت بھی کرتا ہے۔ (پردہ در اور پردہ دار)
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        True Love is reflection (criterion) of the beauty; he (lover) reveals the beauty and then guards it.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="35">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہمت او آنسوی گردون گذشت
از جہان چند و چون بیرون گذشت
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس کی ہمّت افلاک سے آگے بڑھ جاتی ہے، وہ اس جہان چندوچوں سے باہر نکل جاتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        His perseverance takes him beyond heavens; his world (endeavours) cross the barriers of ifs and buts.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="37">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زانکہ در گفتن نیاید آنچہ دید
از ضمیر خود نقابی بر کشید
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کیونکہ جو کچھ وہ دیکھتا ہے وہ الفاظ میں نہیں سماتا، اس لیے وہ اپنے اندرون سے نقاب اٹھا دیتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Whatever he sees cannot be described in words; so (without uttering a world) he exposes beauty of his inner-self.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="39">
      <Text Language="Original">
        از محبت جذبہ ہا گردد بلند
ارج می گیرد ازو ناارجمند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        محبت سے جذبات میں بلندی پیدا ہوتی ہے، یہ بے قدر و قیمت کی قیمت بڑھا دیتی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        True Love elevates the passions (to new heights); because of that the worthless becomes precious.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="41">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بی محبت زندگی ماتم ھمہ
کاروبارش زشت و نامحکم ھمہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        محبت کے بغیر زندگی سر تا پا ماتم ہے، اس کا سارا کاروبار قبیح و نا پختہ ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Without True Love life is eternal wailing; its entire affairs are rendered corrupt and unstable.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="43">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عشق صیقل می زند فرہنگ را
جوہر آئینہ بخشد سنگ را
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        عشق ، عقل کو چمکا دیتا ہے، وہ پتھّر کو آئینے کی طرح شفاف بنا دیتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        True Love sharpens the common sense; it imparts shining glaze to the (rough surface) of stone.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="45">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اھل دل را سینۂ سینا دہد
با ھنرمندان ید بیضا دہد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        عشق سے اہل دل کا سینہ جلوہ گاہ سینا بن جاتا ہے، وہ ہنرمند وں کو یدبیضا عطا کرتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        True Love turns the heart into Mount Sinai; it gives brightness to the hand of the artist (like that Mose’s hand; he starts performing miracles).\
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="47">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پیش او ہر ممکن و موجود مات
جملہ عالم تلخ و او شاخ نبات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        عشق کے سامنے تمام ممکنات و موجودات ہیچ ہیں، ساری دنیا تلخ ہے اور صرف عشق مصری کی ڈلی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        All realities and possibilities become ordinary in True Love; entire world is bitter (in taste); only True Love is sweet like sugar cube.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="49">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گرمی افکار ما از نار اوست
آفریدن جان دمیدن کار اوست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ہمارے افکار کی گرمی آتش عشق سے ہے، پیدا کرنا اور اس میں روح پھونکنا عشق ہی کا کام ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Fire of True Love (transmits) warmth into the thinking; True Love moulds a body (out of dust) and then grants it soul (life).
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="51">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عشق مور و مرغ و آدم را بس است
عشق تنہا ہر دو عالم را بس است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        چیوئٹی، پرندے اور انسان سب کے لیے عشق کافی ہے، 'اکیلا عشق دونوں جہانوں کے لیے بس ہے'۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        True Love is sufficient for insects, birds and humans; True Love alone is better than two worlds (this and the world hereafter).
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="53">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دلبری بی قاہری جادوگری است
دلبری با قاہری پیغمبری است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        دلبری (جمال) بغیر قاہری (جلال) کے (محض) جادوگری ہے، دلبری قاہری کے ساتھ ہو تو پیغمبری ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Love without power (to captivate) is magic (illusion, deception); Love with power is prophecy.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="55">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہر دو را در کار ہا آمیخت عشق
عالمی در عالمی انگیخت عشق
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        عشق اپنے کاموں میں ان دونوں کو ملا دیتا ہے، اور اس طرح اس جہان کے اندر ایک نیا جہان پیدا کرتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        True Love combines the two (characteristics) into one; and then creates a new world in this ancient world.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>