<Poem ID="15" Name="نوائے غم" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="2a" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زندگانی ہے مری مثل رباب خاموش
جس کی ہر رنگ کے نغموں سے ہے لبریز آغوش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE SONG OF GRIEF
My life is similar to that of the silent violin; the lap of which is full of all kinds of melodies.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بربط کون و مکاں جس کی خموشی پہ نثار
جس کے ہر تار میں ہیں سینکڑوں نغموں کے مزار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The harp of the universe is sacrificed on whose silence; every string of which is the grave of hundreds of melodies.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        محشرستان نوا کا ہے امیں جس کا سکوت
اور منت کش ہنگامہ نہیں جس کا سکوت
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The silence of which is the custodian of music's perfection, and the silence of which is not obligated to any uproar.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آہ! امید محبت کی بر آئی نہ کبھی
چوٹ مضراب کی اس ساز نے کھائی نہ کبھی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Ah! The hope of my Love was never fulfilled: this instrument was never hit by the plectrum.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مگر آتی ہے نسیم چمن طور کبھی
سمت گردوں سے ہوائے نفس حور کبھی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        But sometimes the zephyr of the garden of Toor flows and sometimes the breeze of Houri’s breath from the sky.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چھیڑ آہستہ سے دیتی ہے مرا تار حیات
جس سے ہوتی ہے رہا روح گرفتار حیات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Which gently touches the string of my life; and frees the imprisoned soul of my life.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نغمہ یاس کی دھیمی سی صدا اٹھتی ہے
اشک کے قافلے کو بانگ درا اٹھتی ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The gentle sound of the music of despair rises; the clarion's call for the caravan of tears rises.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جس طرح رفعت شبنم ہے مذاق رم سے
میری فطرت کی بلندی ہے نوائے غم سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Just as dew's elegance depends upon the taste for racing; the elegance of my nature depends upon grief's melodies!
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>