<Poem ID="29" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="02" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        افلاک سے آتا ہے نالوں کا جواب آخر 
کرتے ہیں خطاب آخر، اٹھتے ہیں حجاب آخر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        From the heavens comes an answer to our long cries at last: the heavens break their silence, the curtains rise at last!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        احوال محبت میں کچھ فرق نہیں ایسا 
سوز و تب و تاب اول، سوزو تب و تاب آخر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Little of change love’s fortunes inherit: born in anguish and fire, in fire and anguish its end it buys at last.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میں تجھ کو بتاتا ہوں، تقدیر امم کیا ہے 
شمشیر و سناں اول، طاوس و رباب آخر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The destiny of nations I chart for you: At first the sword and spear; the zither’s, the lute’s soft sighs at last.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میخانہ یورپ کے دستور نرالے ہیں 
لاتے ہیں سرور اول، دیتے ہیں شراب آخر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Outlandish are the customs that Europe’s tavern knows! It steeps men first in pleasure, the wine supplies at last.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کیا دبدبہ نادر، کیا شوکت تیموری 
ہو جاتے ہیں سب دفتر غرق م ے ناب آخر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Be it the awe of Nadir, be it the glory of a Tamerlane: At last all exploits are drowned in a barrel of wine.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خلوت کی گھڑی گزری، جلوت کی گھڑی آئی 
چھٹنے کو ہے بجلی سے آغوش سحاب آخر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The cloistered hour is over, the arena’s hour begins; the lightning comes to asunder those cloudy skies at last!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تھا ضبط بہت مشکل اس سیل معانی کا 
کہہ ڈالے قلندر نے اسرار کتاب آخر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It was too hard to withhold the flood of these truths, at last the Qalandar revealed the secrets of the Book. 
(Translated by M.D. Taseer)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>