<Poem ID="03" Name="" BookID="11" BookName="ارمغانِ حجاز" SectionID="05" SectionName="بہ یاران طریق">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سجودی وری دارا و جم را
مکن اے بیخبر رسوا حرم را
مبر پیش فرنگی حاجت خویش
ز طاق دل فرو ریز این صنم را
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تو دارا و جم (جیسے پادشاہوں) کے سامنے سجدہ کرتا ہے، اے بیخبر! حرم کو رسوا نہ کر۔
اپنی حاجت فرنگی کے سامنے نہ لے جا، اس بت کو اپنے دل کے طاقچہ سے نیچے گرا دے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You are bowing head to ‘Dara’ and ‘Jam’, O fool tarnish not the honour of ‘harm’.
Take not thy needs to Anglian’s door; drop these idols from heart’s inner core.
Dara: Darius. Jam: A title of old Kings of Persia. Jam’s throne; when used with throne it means ‘Solomon’.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شیندم بیتکی از مرد پیری
کہن فرزانۂ روشن ضمیری
اگر خود را بناداری نگہ داشت
دو گیتی را بگیردن فقیری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میں نے ایک دانا اور روشن ضمیر پیر کہن سے یہ شعر سنا تھا: 
جو فقیر ناداری میں خود داری اختیار کرتا ہے ، وہ دونوں جہانوں کا مالک بن جاتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I heard a nice verse from a man old, a wise man great with conscience of gold.
If he guards the self in want and need, that darvesh can win both worlds in deed.
A conscience of gold: Having brilliant qualities of head and heart.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہان اندر دو حرفی سر کار است
مقام عشق منبر نیست، دار است
براہیمان ز نمرودان نترسند
کہ عود خام را تش عیار است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کام کی بات دو حرفوں میں پوشیدہ ہے ، عشق کا مقام منبر نہیں، دار ہے۔
ابراہیم، نمرود سے نہیں ڈرتے، کیونکہ عود خام کے لیے آگ کسوٹی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The being’s secret hids in two words of sage, on cross the love lies and never on stage. 
The Abrams feared not at Nimrod’s behest, to raw aloewood the fire is a test. 
It is one of the best poems of Iqbal, being full of sparkling similies of wits. The being’s secret; viz the secret of success.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہان اندر دو حرفی سر کار است
مقام عشق منبر نیست، دار است
براہیمان ز نمرودان نترسند
کہ عود خام را تش عیار است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اے گل لالہ ! تو کسی سے ہمدردی کا خواہاں نہ ہو، میری طرح (صرف) اپنے آپ سے دوستی رکھ؛
جو بھی ہوا آئے ، اس کے سامنے سینہ کھول دے (نئے علوم سے فائدہ اٹھا) ، مگر اپنے پرانے داغ (محبت) کا خیال رکھ (کہیں وہ ضائع نہ ہو جاے)۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        From none seek not O poppy a solace, like me seek friendship with self’s inner base. 
To every wind blowing make the heart ope, watch the old scar and keep a good hope. 
(The old scar: The scar of love’s flame; self’s inner base; heart.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ز پیری یاد دارم این دو اندرز
نباید جز بجان خویشتن زیست
گریز از پیش ن مرد فرودست
کہ جان خود گرو کرد و بہ تن زیست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مجھے ایک پیر مرد کی دو نصیحتیں یاد ہیں، ایک یہ کہ اپنی جان ہی سے زندہ رہا جا سکتا ہے۔
دوسری یہ کہ اس بے ہمت انسان سے دور رہ ، جس نے اپنی جان گروی رکھ دی اور صرف تن (کی آسائش) کس لیے زندہ رہا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Two worlds of old man I keep in mind still, that a man is alive from one’s own will.
Shun that mean man who made no life’s goal, for body who lived and pawned his soul.
(Andurz: Advice, a will, a maxim. Frodast: Weak, bumble, of low birth.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بہ ساحل گفت موج بیقراری
بہ فرعونی کنم خود را عیاری
گہی بر خویش می پیچم چو ماری
گہی رقصم بہ ذوق انتظاری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        موج بیقرار نے ساحل سے کہا، میں کسی فرعون سے اپنی ہمت آزماتی ہے۔
کبھی (غصّہ سے) سانپ کی طرح پیچ و تاب کھاتی ہوں ، اور کبھی ذوق انتظار میں رقص کرتی ہوں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A restive wave said once to a coast, I test my might on a Pharoah’s boast.
I coil around self often like snake, oft I dance for a ‘waiting’ taste sake.
(Restive wave: An allusion to ‘Momin’. Coast: An allusion to impractical man, given to theorizing.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اگر اینب و جاہی از فرنگ است
جبین خود منہ جز بر در او
سرین را ھم بچوبش دہ کہ خر
حقی دارد بہ خر پالان گر او
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اگر تیری یہ شان و مرتبہ فرنگی کے سبب سے ہے، تو اسی کے دروازے پر سجدہ ریز ہو۔
 لیکن اپنے سرین بھی اس کے ڈنڈے کے حوالے کر، کیونکہ آخر پالان گر اپنے گدھے پر کچھ حق بھی رکھتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If this pomp and show the Anglian boon, bow not thy forehead save at his shoon. 
Get kicks of his stick at thy ass too, a right on the ass of saddlers’ pooh.
(Anglians: Adj of Anglia (England) of the angles, their culture, dialect etc. Shoon: (archaic or dial) of shoe. Pooh (poo) (slang): An exclamation of disdain, hate or impatience.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فرنگی را دلی زیر نگین نیست
متاع او ہمہ ملک است دین نیست
خداوندی کہ در طوف حریمش
صد ابلیس است و یک روح الامین نیست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کسی دل پر فرنگی کی حکومت نہیں، اس کا اثاثہ صرف ممالک ہیں، دین نہیں۔
وہ ایسا خدا ہے جس کی بارگاہ کے طواف میں، سینکڑوں ابلیس تو ہیں، مگر روح الامین ایک بھی نہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        To Anglians thus the hearts do not own, they own only lands, to faith they disown. 
O God during rounds of thy sacred place, I saw hundred Satans not the Gabe’s face.
(The Gabe: A diminutive noun of the Gabrial, one of the seven arch angels of the God.) 
(Translated by Q A Kabir)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>