<Poem ID="10" Name="" BookID="03" BookName="ضربِ کلیم" SectionID="06" SectionName="محراب گل افغان کے افکار">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وہی جواں ہے قبیلے کی آنکھ کا تارا 
شباب جس کا ہے بے داغ، ضرب ہے کاری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        That youth is held in high esteem by all the members of his tribe, whose prime of life is pure and chaste, dread blows to him we can ascribe.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اگر ہو جنگ تو شیران غاب سے بڑھ کر 
اگر ہو صلح تو رعنا غزال تاتاری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        غاب: جنگل۔ 
رعنا: دل کو موہ لینے والا خوبصورت ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In days of war he can surpass tile ferocious lions of the wood when peace prevails in every place, like Tartar deer is fine and good.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عجب نہیں ہے اگر اس کا سوز ہے ہمہ سوز 
کہ نیستاں کے لیے بس ہے ایک چنگاری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        نیستاں: سرکنڈوں کا جنگل۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        There is no wonder, if his glow may set the things around afire to burn the bed of reeds one spark is 'nough that from the flame does spire.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خدا نے اس کو دیا ہے شکوہ سلطانی 
کہ اس کے فقر میں ہے حیدری و کراری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کرار: بار بار حملہ کرنے والا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        God Mighty has endowed him with a monarch's grandeur, pomp and show his brand of Faqr has virtues such that shone on Haider's valorous brow.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نگاہ کم سے نہ دیکھ اس کی بے کلاہی کو 
یہ بے کلاہ ہے سرمایہ کلہ داری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Do not look down upon the youth, if his head is devoid of gear: This lad can claim close kinship with those kings who crowns on heads do wear.
[Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>