<Poem ID="34" Name="حور وشاعر" BookID="07" BookName="پیامِ مشرق" SectionID="02" SectionName="افکار">
  <Para Name="در جواب نظم گوتہ موسوم بہ حور و شاعر" />
  <Para Name="حور">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہ بہ بادہ میل داری نہ بہ من نظر گشائے
عجب اینکہ تو ندانی رہ و رسم آشنائے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE HOURI AND THE POET
The Houri: You are not attracted to wine, and you do not look at me: How surprising that you do not know the art of mixing!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہمہ ساز جستجوئی ہمہ سوز آرزوئے
نفسی کہ میگدازی غزلی کہ می سرائے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It is but a tune of quest, a flame of desire, your sigh, your song.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بہ نوای آفریدی چہ جہان دلگشائے
کہ ارم بہ چشم آید چو طلسم سیمیائے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        With your song you have made such a lovely world that paradise itself appears to me to be some conjurer’s trick.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="شاعر">
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دل رھروان فریبی بہ کلام نیش داری
مگر اینکہ لذت او نرسد بہ نوک خاری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Poet: You charm travelers’ hearts with pointed talk except that, in the pleasure it gives, one cannot compare it with the sharp thorn.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چکنم کہ فطرت من بہ مقام در نسازد
دل ناصبور دارم چو صبا بہ لالہ زاری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What can I do, for by nature I am not someone who can live for long in one place! My heart is restless, like the west wind in a field of tulips.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چو نظر قرار گیرد بہ نگار خوبروئے
تپد آن زمان دل من پی خوبتر نگاری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The moment my eyes light upon a pretty face, my heart begins to long for one prettier still.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ز شرر ستارہ جویم ز ستارہ آفتابی
سر منزلی ندارم کہ بمیرم از قراری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In the spark I seek a star, in the star a sun: I have no wish for a destination, for if I stop I die.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چو ز بادۂ بہاری قدحی کشیدہ خیزم
غزلی دگر سرایم بہ ہوای نوبہاری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When I get up, having drunk a cup of wine matured by one spring, I begin to sing another verse, and long for yet another spring.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        طلبم نہایت آن کہ نہایتی ندارد
بہ نگاہ ناشکیبی بہ دل امیدواری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I seek the end of what has no end – with a restless eye, and hope in my heart.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دل عاشقان بمیرد بہ بہشت جاودانی
نہ نوای دردمندی نہ غمی نہ غمگساری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The lover’s heart dies in an eternal heaven – in it no afflicted soul cries, there is no sorrow, and no one to drive sorrow away!
(Translated by Mustansir Mir)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>