<Poem ID="39" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="02" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تازہ پھر دانش حاضر نے کیا سحر قدیم 
گزر اس عہد میں ممکن نہیں بے چوب کلیم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The magic old to life is brought by means of present science and thought: The path of life cannot be trod without the aid of Moses’ Rod.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عقل عیار ہے، سو بھیس بنا لیتی ہے 
عشق بے چارہ نہ ملا ہے نہ زاہد نہ حکیم!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The mind is skilful in artful tasks, and can assume a hundred masks: Poor helpless Love that knows no guise ain’t mullah, hermit or too wise.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عیش منزل ہے غریبان محبت پہ حرام 
سب مسافر ہیں، بظاہر نظر آتے ہیں مقیم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Forbid the rest of lodge and bed to those who road of Love do tread: Like travelers they always roam, though they seem to stay at home.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے گراں سیر غم راحلہ و زاد سے تو 
کوہ و دریا سے گزر سکتے ہیں مانند نسیم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Concern for journey’s food and steed, like burden great, retards your speed: Of this dead weight, if one be free, like breeze can cross the mount and sea.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مرد درویش کا سرمایہ ہے آزادی و مرگ 
ہے کسی اور کی خاطر یہ نصاب زر و سیم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        No wealth is owned by dervish free; at call of death he yields with glee: He has not either gold or land; of him no one can tithe demand.
(Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>