<Poem ID="11" Name="ایک حاجی مدینے کے راستے میں" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        قافلہ لوٹا گیا صحرا میں اور منزل ہے دور 
اس بیاباں یعنی بحر خشک کا ساحل ہے دور
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A PILGRIM ON HIS WAY TO MADINAH
The caravan has been robbed in wilderness and the destination is far; the coast of this desolation that is this dry ocean is far.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہم سفر میرے شکار دشنہء رہزن ہوئے 
بچ گئے جو، ہو کے بے دل سوئے بیت اللہ پھرے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        دشنہ: خنجر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My fellow travelers became victims of the robbers’ dagger; the remaining ones turned back to Makkah in frustration.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اس بخاری نوجواں نے کس خوشی سے جان دی ! 
موت کے زہراب میں پائی ہے اس نے زندگی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        زہراب: زہر بھرا پیالہ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        How willingly this young man from Bukhara gave his life! In the poison of death he has found the taste of life!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خنجر رہزن اسے گویا ہلال عید تھا 
'ہائے یثرب' دل میں، لب پر نعرہ توحید تھا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The robber’s dagger was the Eid’s crescent to him. ‘Ah Yathrib’ was within heart, Tawhid’s slogan was on the lips.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خوف کہتا ہے کہ یثرب کی طرف تنہا نہ چل 
شوق کہتا ہے کہ تو مسلم ہے، بے باکانہ چل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Fear says, ‘Do not travel alone towards Yathrib’; Longing says, ‘You are a Muslim, travel fearlessly’.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بے زیارت سوئے بیت اللہ پھر جاوں گا کیا 
عاشقوں کو روز محشر منہ نہ دکھلاوں گا کیا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Would I return to Makkah without paying homage? Would I not appear confidently before Lovers on the Judgment Day?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خوف جاں رکھتا نہیں کچھ دشت پیمائے حجاز 
ہجرت مدفون یثرب میں یہی مخفی ہے راز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        : وہ پاک ذات جو مدینہ میں دفن ہے، مراد ہے محمد مصطفے (صلعم) مدفون يثرب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The traveler through Hijaz’ wilderness has no fear for life; this secret is hidden in the emigration of the Holy Prophet.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گو سلامت محمل شامی کی ہمراہی میں ہے 
عشق کی لذت مگر خطروں کے جاں کاہی میں ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        محمل شامي: غلاف کعبہ لانے والا وہ قافلہ جو شام سے آتا ہے۔ 
جاں کاہي: محنت۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Thought safety is in the companionship of the Syrian litter.* Pleasure of Love is in the heart-breaking affliction of danger.
(Allusion to the custom of a State caravan proceeding from Damascus in Syria to Makkah Mu’azzamah for Haj in which safety was ensured.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آہ! یہ عقل زیاں اندیش کیا چالاک ہے 
اور تاثر آدمی کا کس قدر بے باک ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Ah! How clever this timid Intellect is! And the brave man’s feeling how fearless is!
(Translated by Dr. M.A.K. Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>