<Poem ID="34" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="02" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جب عشق سکھاتا ہے آداب خود آگاہی 
کھلتے ہیں غلاموں پر اسرار شہنشاہی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When through the Love man conscious grows of respect self-awareness needs, though in chains, he learns at once the regal mode and kingly deeds.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عطار ہو، رومی ہو، رازی ہو، غزالی ہو 
کچھ ہاتھ نہیں آتا بے آہ سحر گاہی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Like Rumi, Attar, Ghazzali and Razi, one may be mystic great or wise, but none can reach his goal and aim without the help of morning sighs.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نومید نہ ہو ان سے اے رہبر فرزانہ! 
کم کوش تو ہیں لیکن بے ذوق نہیں راہی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        فرزانہ: عقلمند، دانا۔ 
کم کوش: کم کوشش کرنے والا ، تن آسان۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        No need for leaders sage and great to lose all hope of Muslim true: Though amiss this pilgrim be, yet can burn on fire like rue.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے طائر لاہوتی! اس رزق سے موت اچھی 
جس رزق سے آتی ہو پرواز میں کوتاہی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        طائر لاہوتی: تصوّف میں آخری منزل لا ہوت ہے، یعنی وہ مقام جہاں اللہ تعالے کے سوا اور کچھ نہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O Bird, that yearn to merge with God*, you must keep this truth in sight; to suffer death is nobler far than bread that clogs your upward flight.

* Contrary to the translation, Iqbal’s phrase simply means the bird that flies to the Throne of God.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دارا و سکندر سے وہ مرد فقیر اولی 
ہو جس کی فقیری میں بوئے اسد اللہی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A person poor and destitute, who walks in steps of God’s Lion bold, is more exalt’d than monarchs great: He spurns the worldly wealth and gold.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آئین جوانمردں، حق گوئی و بے باکی 
اللہ کے شیروں کو آتی نہیں روباہی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        روباہی: لومڑی جیسی عادت، چالاکی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Men bold and firm uphold the truth and let no fears assail their hearts: No doubt, the mighty Lions of God know no tricks and know no arts.
(Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>