<Poem ID="21" Name="مسولینی" BookID="03" BookName="ضربِ کلیم" SectionID="05" SectionName="سیاست مشرق و مغرب">
  <Para Name="اپنے مشرقي اور مغربي حريفوں سے">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کیا زمانے سے نرالا ہے مسولینی کا جرم! 
بے محل بگڑا ہے معصومان یورپ کا مزاج
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        MUSSOLINI (to his Eastern and western adversaries)
Does crime of Mussolini seem so odd to age, without cause all the chaste are put to rage?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میں پھٹکتا ہوں تو چھلنی کو برا لگتا ہے کیوں 
ہیں سبھی تہذیب کے اوزار ! تو چھلنی، میں چھاج
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Why does pot feel offence, if kettle has a blot, our culture same – I kettle and you pot?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میرے سودائے ملوکیت کو ٹھکراتے ہو تم 
تم نے کیا توڑے نہیں کمزور قوموں کے زجاج؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        زجاج: شیشے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My craze for Empire makes you sneer and frown, but walls of weak states, you too have brought down.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ عجائب شعبدے کس کی ملوکیت کے ہیں 
راجدھانی ہے، مگر باقی نہ راجا ہے نہ راج
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Whose monarchy such wondrous tricks does own. The royal seat exists, no king or crown?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آل سیزر چوب نے کی آبیاری میں رہے 
اور تم دنیا کے بنجر بھی نہ چھوڑو بے خراج!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The sons of Caesar watered reedy sands; you did not leave untaxed barren lands.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تم نے لوٹے بے نوا صحرا نشینوں کے خیام 
تم نے لوٹی کشت دہقاں، تم نے لوٹے تخت و تاج
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کشت دہقاں: کسان کی فصل۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You pillaged tents of nomads, who little own ravaged peasant's crops, looted throne and crown.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پردہ تہذیب میں غارت گری، آدم کشی 
کل روا رکھی تھی تم نے، میں روا رکھتا ہوں آج
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You plundered, slaughtered in culture's way, you did it previous day' I do today. (Written in August in Shish Mehal, Bhopal)
(Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>