<Poem ID="18" Name="خاتمہ" BookID="11" BookName="ارمغانِ حجاز" SectionID="03" SectionName="حضور ملت">
  <Para Name="(1)">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہ از ساقی نہ از پیمانہ گفتم
حدیث عشق بیباکانہ گفتم
شنیدم نچہ از پاکان امت
ترا با شوخے رندانہ گفتم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میں نے (شاعروں کی مانند) نہ ساقی کی بات کی ہے، نہ پ یمانے کی؛ میں نے تو عشق کی بات کی ہے اور وہ بھی بے کرانہ انداز میں۔
جو کچھ میں نے امت کے پاکباز بزرگوں سے سنا تھا ؛ وہ شوخیء رندانہ سے کہہ دیا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE FINISH
I talk not of bearer nor of bowl hence; this love theme, I say in a frank parlance. 
From Holies of Ummah what e’er I hold; in their own frank style to thee I have told. 
(Here Iqbal’s setting of words is so wonderful that it was difficult to convey that sweet lush (of words) to the readers. According to Webster’s Collegeate Dictionary ‘Parlance’ means language, a style or manner of speaking or writing as Military parlance. However, the archaic words (old use) are allowed to be used in poetry for special purposes only.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(2)">
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بخود باز او دامان دلے گیر
درون سینہ خود منزلی گیر
بدہ این کشت را خونابۂ خویش
فشاندم دانہ من تو حاصلی گیر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ہے تو اپنے آپ کی طرف واپس آ اپنے دل کا دامن تھام لے؛ اور اپنے ہی سینے کو اپنی منزل بنا۔
اب اپنے (دل کی) کھیتی کو اپنے خون سے سینچ ؛ دانہ میں نے بکھیر دیا ہے، اب پیداوار تو سمیٹ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Back to ego turn, and back to heart look; make the self’s own place in thy bosom nook.
Treat this tillage with moist of blood and tear. Eat the harvest thus, I throw my seeds here.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(3)">
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حرم جز قبلہ قلب و نظر نیست
طواف او طواف بام و در نیست
میان ما و بیت اللہ رمزیست
کہ جبریل امین را ھم خبر نیست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        حرم تو قلب و نظر کا قبلہ ہے؛ اس کا طواف محض مکان کا طواف نہیں۔
ہمارے اور بیت اللہ شریف کے درمیان جو راز ہے ؛ اس سے جبریل امین (علیہ) بھی با خبر نہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        For heart and eyes course, the ‘Harem’ is the aim; its round is not the round of door’an roof’s frame.
In us and God’s House there hids a hint so; which Gabe, the Trustee may not even know.
[Translated by Qazi Ahdul Kabir]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>