<Poem ID="41" Name="صبح کا ستارہ" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="1a" SectionName="حصہ اول">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لطف ہمسایگی شمس و قمر کو چھوڑوں
اور اس خدمت پیغام سحر کو چھوڑوں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE MORNING STAR –VENUS
Should I abandon the pleasure of sun's and moon's company? And should I abandon this service of conveying dawn's message?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میرے حق میں تو نہیں تاروں کی بستی اچھی
اس بلندی سے زمیں والوں کی پستی اچھی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        For me the height of the world of stars is not good; for me lowliness of earth's denizens is better than this height.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آسماں کیا، عدم آباد وطن ہے میرا
صبح کا دامن صد چاک کفن ہے میرا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What is the sky? Is the uninhabited homeland of mine? The tattered skirt of the morning is my shroud?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میری قسمت میں ہے ہر روز کا مرنا جینا
ساقی موت کے ہاتھوں سے صبوحی پینا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My destiny is dying and being born every day. Drinking morning draft of wine from the hand of death's cup-bearer.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہ یہ خدمت، نہ یہ عزت، نہ یہ رفعت اچھی
اس گھڑی بھر کے چمکنے سے تو ظلمت اچھی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This service, this honor, this elegance is not good; darkness is better than this ephemeral illumination.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میری قدرت میں جو ہوتا، تو نہ اختر بنتا
قعر دریا میں چمکتا ہوا گوہر بنتا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If I had the power, I would have never become a planet. I would have become the shining pearl in the ocean's depth.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        واں بھی موجوں کی کشاکش سے جو دل گھبراتا
چھوڑ کر بحر کہیں زیب گلو ہو جاتا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        There also if I would have become weary of the waves' struggle; leaving the ocean I would have become some neck's decoration.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے چمکنے میں مزا حسن کا زیور بن کر
زینت تاج سر بانوئے قیصر بن کر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The pleasure of brightness is in being some beauty's ornament; in being the ornament of the crown of the princess of Caesar.
Caesar: This is the generic title of the emperors of the Roman Empire. They are proverbial for their immense power and wealth of that time.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ایک پتھر کے جو ٹکڑے کا نصیبا جاگا
خاتم دست سلیماں کا نگیں بن کے رہا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        As the fortune of a piece of stone gained ascendancy; it did not stop short of being jewel of Sulaiman's ring.
* Sulaiman A.S. a true prophet is also famous for his wealth, power and glory. The signet ring refers to the stone of his ring which was an emblem of his sovereignty. This verse shows that a mere piece of stone gained elegance by being the stone of the ring of a man.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ایسی چنروں کا مگر دہر میں ہے کام شکست
ہے گہر ہائے گراں مایہ کا انجام شکست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        But breaking is the end of such things in the world. Breaking is the end of the invaluable pearls.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زندگی وہ ہے کہ جو ہو نہ شناسائے اجل
کیا وہ جینا ہے کہ ہو جس میں تقاضائے اجل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Real life is the one which is not acquainted with death. What good is the life in which there is demand of death?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے یہ انجام اگر زینت عالم ہو کر
کیوں نہ گر جائو ں کسی پھول پہ شبنم ہو کر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If this is the end of being the decoration of the universe: Why should I not fall as dew on some flower?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کسی پیشانی کے افشاں کے ستاروں میں رہوں
کس مظلوم کی آہوں کے شراروں میں رہوں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I should live as shining specks in the decoration of someone's forehead; I should live in the sparks of some oppressed person's sighs.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اشک بن کر سرمژگاں سے اٹک جائوں میں
کیوں نہ اس بیوی کی آنکھوں سے ٹپک جائوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        As tear I be entangled in the eye lashes of someone: Why should I not drip from the eyes of that lady?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جس کا شوہر ہو رواں، ہو کے زرہ میں مستور
سوئے میدان وغا، حب وطن سے مجبور
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Whose husband, clad in the chains armour is departing to battlefield, compelled by the love of the homeland!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="31">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یاس و امید کا نظارہ جو دکھلاتی ہو
جس کی خاموشی سے تقریر بھی شرماتی ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Who may be exhibiting hope and despair's spectacle; whose silence may be putting speech to embarrassment?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جس کو شوہر کی رضا تاب شکیبائی دے
اور نگاہوں کو حیا طاقت گویائی دے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        To whom pleasing the husband may give the strength for patience and to whose eyes' modesty may give the power to speak.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="35">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زرد، رخصت کی گھڑی، عارض گلگوں ہو جائے
کشش حسن غم ہجر سے افزوں ہو جائے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Whose rosy cheeks at departure's time may be turned pale; attraction of whose beauty by separation's sorrow may be enhanced.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="37">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لاکھ وہ ضبط کرے پر میں ٹپک ہی جائوں
ساغر دیدئہ پرنم سے چھلک ہی جائوں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        However hard she may control but still I may drip; I may spill over from the cup of the tearful eye.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="39">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خاک میں مل کے حیات ابدی پا جائوں
عشق کا سوز زمانے کو دکھاتا جائوں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        After mixing with dust I may get eternal life and departing, I may show warmth of Love to the world.
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>