<Poem ID="37" Name="جوی آب" BookID="07" BookName="پیامِ مشرق" SectionID="02" SectionName="افکار">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بنگر کہ جوی آب چہ مستانہ میرود
مانند کہکشان بگریبان مرغزار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE STREAM
Behold the stream! How merrily it flows right through the meadow, like the Milky Way!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        در خواب ناز بود بہ گہوارۂ سحاب
وا کرد چشم شوق بہ آغوش کوہسار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ’Twas sound asleep in the cradle of the clouds; opened its wondering eye in the lap of the mountains.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        از سنگریزہ نغمہ گشاید خرام او
سیمای او چو آینہ بیرنگ و بی غبار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        From the pebbles its graceful motion music strikes; its brows chaste and unsullied like the mirror!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زی بحر بیکرانہ چہ مستانہ میرود
در خود یگانہ از ہمہ بیگانہ میرود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Towards the shoreless ocean how merrily it flows; linked with itself, unlinked with all, it flows.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        در راہ او بھار پریخانہ آفرید
نرگس دمید و لالہ دمید و سمن دمید
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Around its track spring fashioned a fairyland: Narcissus bloomed, and tulip, and Jessamine.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گل عشوہ داد و گفت یکی پیش ما بایست
خندید غنچہ و سر دامان او کشید
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The rose said temptingly: Stay with us here awhile; the rose-bud laughed and pulled the helm of its skirt.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نا آشنای جلوہ فروشان سبز پوش
صحرا برید و سینۂ کوہ و کمر درید
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Unmindful of these green-robed beauty-vendors, it cleft the desert and rent the breast of hill and dale.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زی بحر بیکرانہ چہ مستانہ میرود
در خود یگانہ از ہمہ بیگانہ میرود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Towards the shoreless ocean how merrily it flows; linked with itself, unlinked with all, it flows.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        صد جوی دشت و مرغ و کہستان و باغ و راغ
گفتند اے بسیط زمین با تو سازگار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A hundred brooks from woods and meadows, from vales and gardens and villas cried: ‘O thou with whom accords the earth’s expanse!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ما را کہ راہ از تنک آبی نبردہ ایم
از دستبرد ریگ بیابان نگاہ دار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Stricken with drought, we have fallen by the way; protect us from the pillage of the sandy waste!’
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وا کردہ سینہ را بہ ہوا ہای شرق و غرب
در بر گرفتہ ہمسفران زبون و زار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It opened its breast to the winds of the East and the West, clasping its weak and wailing fellow travelers.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زی بحر بیکرانہ چہ مستانہ میرود
با صد ھزار گوھر یکدانہ میرود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Towards the shoreless ocean how merrily it flows; with a hundred thousand matchless pearls it flows.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دریای پر خروش ز بند و شکن گذشت
از تنگنای وادی و کوہ و دمن گذشت
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The surging river went over dam dyke, went over the narrow gorge of valley, hill and glen,
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یکسان چو سیل کردہ نشیب و فراز را
از کاخ شاہ و بارہ ہ کشت و چمن گذشت
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Made one, like a torrent, each hollow and eminence, went over the king’s palace and rampart and field and orchard.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بیتاب و تند و تیز و جگر سوز و بیقرار
در ہر زمان بہ تازہ رسید از کہن گذشت
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Passionate and fierce and sharp, restless and heart-inflaming each time it arrived at the New and went beyond the Old.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="31">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زی بحر بیکرانہ چہ مستانہ میرود
در خود یگانہ از ہمہ بیگانہ میرود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Towards the shoreless ocean how merrily it flows; linked with itself, unlinked with all, it flows.
(Translated by Prof. Hamid Ahmad Khan)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>