<Poem ID="41" Name="پنچاب کے پیرزادوں سے" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="04" SectionName="منظومات">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حاضر ہوا میں شیخ مجدد کی لحد پر 
وہ خاک کہ ہے زیر فلک مطلع انوار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مطلع انوار:نورانی تجلّیوں کے ظہور کی جگہ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        TO THE PUNJAB PIRS
I stood by the Reformer's tomb: that dust whence here below an orient splendour breaks;
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اس خاک کے ذروں سے ہیں شرمندہ ستارے 
اس خاک میں پوشیدہ ہے وہ صاحب اسرار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Dust before whose least speck stars hang their heads, dust shrouding that high knower of things unknown.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گردن نہ جھکی جس کی جہانگیر کے آگے 
جس کے نفس گرم سے ہے گرمی احرار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Who to Jehangir would not bend his neck, whose ardent breath fans every free heart’s ardour?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وہ ہند میں سرمایہء ملت کا نگہباں 
اللہ نے بر وقت کیا جس کو خبردار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Whom Allah sent in season to keep watch in India on the treasure-house of Islam.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کی عرض یہ میں نے کہ عطا فقر ہو مجھ کو 
آنکھیں مری بینا ہیں، و لیکن نہیں بیدار!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I craved the saints' gift, other-worldliness for my eyes saw, yet dimly. Answer came:
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آئی یہ صدا سلسلہء فقر ہوا بند 
ہیں اہل نظر کشور پنجاب سے بیزار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Closed is the long roll of the saints; this Land of the Five Rivers stinks in good men's nostrils.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عارف کا ٹھکانا نہیں وہ خطہ کہ جس میں 
پیدا کلہ فقر سے ہو طرئہ دستار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        God's people have no portion in that country where lordly tassel sprouts from monkish cap.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        باقی کلہ فقر سے تھا ولولہء حق 
طروں نے چڑھایا نشہء 'خدمت سرکار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        That cap bred passionate faith, this tassel breeds passion for playing pander to Government.' 
(Translated by V G Kiernan)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>