<Poem ID="38" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="02" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ پیران کلیسا و حرم، اے وائے مجبوری! 
صلہ ان کی کدوی کاوش کا ہے سینوں کی بے نوری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Alas! The mullah and the priest, conduct their sermons so that despite their efforts great, the hearts of listeners fail to glow.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یقیں پیدا کر اے ناداں! یقیں سے ہاتھ آتی ہے 
وہ درویشی، کہ جس کے سامنے جھکتی ہے فغفوری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O fellow stupid, get firm belief, for faith upon you can bestow: Dervishhood of such lofty brand ’fore which the mighty monarchs bow.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کبھی حیرت، کبھی مستی، کبھی آہ سحرگاہی 
بدلتا ہے ہزاروں رنگ میرا درد مہجوری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Disunion’s ache that I do feel a thousand hues and garbs can don: To rapture and surprise converts, anon to sighs of early morn.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حد ادراک سے باہر ہیں باتیں عشق و مستی کی 
سمجھ میں اس قدر آیا کہ دل کی موت ہے، دوری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Secrets of love and passion strong transcend the ken of earthy breed: This much alone I learnt that death of heart disunion means indeed.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وہ اپنے حسن کی مستی سے ہیں مجبور پیدائی 
مری آنکھوں کی بینائی میں ہیں اسباب مستوری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Fair with His own Beauty drunk is impelled to cast the Veil aside: The reasons of His remaining hid within my own dim sight abide.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کوئی تقدیر کی منطق سمجھ سکتا نہیں ورنہ 
نہ تھے ترکان عثمانی سے کم ترکان تیموری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The rules that govern the Turn of Fate no one can ever understand, else the heirs to Tamerlane were brave like those of Turkish Land.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فقیران حرم کے ہاتھ اقبال آگیا کیونکر 
میسر میرو سلطاں کو نہیں شاہین کافوری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        How have the beggars of the Shrine brought Iqbal within their fold, though monarchs great and princes strong a falcon white can’t get in hold? 
(Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>