<Poem ID="06" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="01" SectionName="حصہ اول">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پریشاں ہوکے میری خاک آخر دل نہ بن جائے 
جو مشکل اب ہے یارب پھر وہی مشکل نہ بن جائے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My scattered dust charged with Love the shape of heart may take at last: O God, the grief that bowed me then, may press me down as in the past!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہ کر دیں مجھ کو مجبور نوا فردوس میں حوریں 
مرا سوز دروں پھر گرمی محفل نہ بن جائے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Maids of Eden by their charm may arouse my urge for song: The flame of Love that burns in me, may fire the zeal of Celestial Throng!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کبھی چھوڑی ہوئی منزل بھی یاد آتی ہے راہی کو 
کھٹک سی ہے، جو سینے میں، غم منزل نہ بن جائے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The pilgrim’s mind can dwell at times on spots and stages left behind: My heed for spots and places crossed, from the Quest may turn my mind!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بنایا عشق نے دریائے ناپیدا کراں مجھ کو 
یہ میری خود نگہداری مرا ساحل نہ بن جائے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ناپیدا کراں: جس کا کنارہ نظر نہ آئے ۔
خود نگہداری: اپنے آپ کو نگاہ میں رکھنا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        By the mighty force of Love I am turned to Boundless Deep: I fear that my self-regard, me, for aye, on shore may keep!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کہیں اس عالم بے رنگ و بو میں بھی طلب میری 
وہی افسانہ دنبالہ محمل نہ بن جائے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        دنبالہ: پشت ّ پیچھے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My hectic search for aim and end, in life that smell and hue doth lack, may get renown like lover’s tale, who riding went on litter’s track!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عروج آدم خاکی سے انجم سہمے جاتے ہیں 
کہ یہ ٹوٹا ہوا تارا مہ کامل نہ بن جائے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The rise of clay-born man hath smit the hosts of heaven with utter fright: They dread that this fallen star to moon may wax with fuller light.
(Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>