<Poem ID="12" Name="" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="1b" SectionName="غزلیات 1">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سختیاں کرتا ہوں دل پر، غیر سے غافل ہوں میں
ہائے کیا اچھی کہی ظالم ہوں میں، جاہل ہوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I bear hardships on myself, I am unconcerned with others. Alas! How strange, I am the oppressor, I am the ignorant. 
(This is the kind of sarcastic remark people make on the material losses and sufferings of the true Lovers of God.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میں جبھی تک تھا کہ تیری جلوہ پیرائی نہ تھی
جو نمود حق سے مٹ جاتا ہے وہ باطل ہوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I existed only till the time Thy Splendor appeared, I am the falsehood which is annihilated by the Truth.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        علم کے دریا سے نکلے غوطہ زن گوہر بدست
وائے محرومی! خزف چین لب ساحل ہوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        From the knowledge’s sea divers came out with pearls in hand. Alas, O deprivation! A mere pebble collector on the sea shore I am.*
(Allusion to the transfer of Adam (A.S.) from Paradise to the earth on account of his negligence in obeying the Command of God.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے مری ذلت ہی کچھ میری شرافت کی دلیل
جس کی غفلت کو ملک روتے ہیں وہ غافل ہوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My disgrace itself is the demonstration of my nobility; I am the negligence which the angels ardently desire.
(The whole purpose of the Creation of the universe was to create Man, who is the master-piece of the creation, and the master-piece of the human elegance is the person of the Holy Prophet S.A.W. There is a Hadith to the effect that God would not have created the universe if He had not intended to create the Holy Prophet S.A.W.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بزم ہستی! اپنی آرائش پہ تو نازاں نہ ہو
تو تو اک تصویر ہے محفل کی اور محفل ہوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O the existence’ assemblage! Be not proud of your beauty. You are a mere picture of the assemblage, I am the assemblage.
(Allusion to the constant search of Man to know himself.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ڈھونڈتا پھرتا ہوں اے اقبال اپنے آپ کو
آپ ہی گویا مسافر، آپ ہی منزل ہوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O Iqbal! I am in constant search for myself; I am the traveler as well as the destination.
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>