<Poem ID="15" Name="رات اور شاعر" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="رات">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کیوں میری چاندنی میں پھرتا ہے تو پریشاں 
خاموش صورت گل، مانند بو پریشاں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE NIGHT AND THE POET
NIGHT:
Why in my light are you roaming about perturbed; silent like the rose, like the fragrance perturbed?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تاروں کے موتیوں کا شاید ہے جوہری تو 
مچھلی ہے کوئی میرے دریائے نور کی تو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Perhaps you are the jeweler of the star’s pearls; perhaps you are some fish of the river of my light.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یا تو مری جبیں کا تارا گرا ہوا ہے 
رفعت کو چھوڑ کر جو بستی میں جا بسا ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        رفعت: بلندی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Or you are a star fallen from my forehead; which, leaving eminence has adopted habitation in humility.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خاموش ہو گیا ہے تار رباب ہستی 
ہے میرے آئنے میں تصویر خواب ہستی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Quiet has become the string of the harp of life. In my mirror is the picture of the dream of life.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دریا کی تہ میں چشم گرادب سو گئی ہے 
ساحل سے لگ کے موج بے تاب سو گئی ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        چشم گرداب: بھنور کی آنکھ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        At the bottom of the river the whirlpool’s eye is asleep’ by the river bank the restless wave has fallen asleep.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بستی زمیں کی کیسی ہنگامہ آفریں ہے 
یوں سو گئی ہے جیسے آباد ہی نہیں ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        How tumultuous the habitation of the earth is; has fallen asleep as if it not even inhabited is.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شاعر کا دل ہے لیکن ناآشنا سکوں سے 
آزاد رہ گیا تو کیونکر مرے فسوں سے؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        But the poet’s heart is unacquainted with peace. How did you remain free from my enchantment?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="شاعر">
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میں ترے چاند کی کھیتی میں گہر بوتا ہوں 
چھپ کے انسانوں سے مانند سحر روتا ہوں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        گہر: موتی ، مراد ہے آنسو۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        POET:
I am sowing pearls in the fields of your moon; hiding from people I weep like the dawn.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دن کی شورش میں نکلتے ہوئے گھبراتے ہیں 
عزلت شب میں مرے اشک ٹپک جاتے ہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        عزلت شب: رات کی تنہائی ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Being shy of coming out in the day’s commotion; my tears start dripping in the night’s seclusion.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مجھ میں فریاد جو پنہاں ہے، سناوں کس کو 
تپش شوق کا نظارہ دکھاوں کس کو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        پنہاں: چھپا ہوا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        To whom should I relate the lament concealed in me? To whom should I show the scene of the heat of Love1?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        برق ایمن مرے سینے پہ پڑی روتی ہے 
دیکھنے والی ہے جو آنکھ، کہاں سوتی ہے!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Aiman’s lightning is lying on my breast and weeping; where the eye which has insight is sleeping?
(Aiman: The Valley of Mount Toor where Mosa A.S. saw the Effulgence of God in the form of lightning.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        صفت شمع لحد مردہ ہے محفل میری 
آہ، اے رات! بڑی دور ہے منزل میری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        صفت شمع لحد: قبر پر بجھے ہوئے چراغ کی طرح۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My congregation is dead like the grave’s candle, Ah! O night my destination is very far.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عہد حاضر کی ہوا راس نہیں ہے اس کو 
اپنے نقصان کا احساس نہیں ہے اس کا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The present day conditions are not amenable to it; there is no perception of its own loss in it.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ضبط پیغام محبت سے جو گھبراتا ہوں 
تیرے تابندہ ستاروں کو سنا جاتا ہوں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When I become tired of the restraint of Love’s message; coming here I relate them to your shining states!
[Translated by Dr M A K Khalil]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>