<Poem ID="06" Name="لا الہ الا اﷲ" BookID="10" BookName="پس چہ بائد کرد" SectionID="01" SectionName="پس چہ بائد کرد">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نکتہ ئی میگویم از مردان حال
امتان را "لا" جلال "الا" جمال
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میں صاحب حال بزرگوں کی بات بتاتا ہوں ، امتوں کے لیے لا جلال ہے اور الا جمال (لا سے غیر اللہ کی نفی ہے اور الا میں اللہ تعالے کے سامنے جھک جانا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I tell thee a significant point known only to the people of ecstasy: For nations, negation expresses power, affirmation expresses beauty.	 
(People of ecstasy, mardan-i-hal: Persons who pass through different states in their spiritual experiences. This phrase stands here for people engaged in dynamic activity in contrast to mardan-i-hal, people who only talk and do nothing. Jalal: Power. Jamal: Beauty.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لا و الا احتساب کائنات
لا و الا فتح باب کائنات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        لا و الا سے کائنات کا احتساب ہے ، لا و الا سے کائنات (کی برکتوں) کا دروازہ کھلتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Negation and affirmation together signify control of the universe: They are the keys to the doors of the universe.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہر دو تقدیر جہان کاف و نون
حرکت از لا زاید از الا سکون
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ان دونوں ( الفاظ ) سے اس جہان کن کی تقدیر بنتی ہے، لا سے حرکت میں اضافہ ہوتا ہے اور الا سے سکون میں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Both are the destiny of this world of Becoming. Movement is born out of negation, stationary state, out of affirmation.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تا نہ رمز لاالہ آید بدست
بند غیر اﷲ را نتوان شکست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جب تک لاالہ کا نکتہ ہاتھ نہ آئے غیر اللہ کے بند توڑے نہیں جا سکتے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Unless the secret of negation is grasped, the bonds of the other-than-God cannot be broken.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        در جہان آغاز کار از حرف لاست
این نخستین منزل مرد خداست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        دنیا میں کام کا آغاز لا سے ہے، یہ مرد خدا کی پہلی منزل ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The beginning of every work in the world is with the word of negation: It is the first stage of the man of God.	 
(In Darb-i-Kalim, Allamah says: In the universe, negation is the beginning; affirmation the end.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ملتے کز سوز او یک دم تپید
از گل خود خویش را باز آفرید
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        وہ ملّت جو ایک لمحہ کے لیے لا کے سوز میں تڑپی اس نے اپنی مٹی سے اپنے آپ کو (از سر نو ) پیدا کر لیا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A nation which burns itself in its heat for a moment recreates itself out of its own ashes.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پیش غیر اﷲ "لا" گفتن حیات
تازہ از ہنگامۂ او کائنات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        غیر اللہ کے سامنے لا کہنا زندگی ہے، اسی کے ہنگامے سے کائنات میں تازگی پیدا ہوتی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        To say No to the other-than-God is Life: The universe is ever renewed by its tumult.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        از جنونش ہر گریبان چاک نیست
در خور این شعلہ ہر خاشاک نیست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        لا کے جنوں سے ہر (ایک کا) گریباں چاک نہیں ، ہر خاشاک اس شعلے کے لائق نہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Not every person is affected by its madness; not every haystack is fit to catch its fire.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جذبۂ او در دل یک زندہ مرد
می کند صد رہ نشین را رہ نورد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس کا جذبہ ایک زندہ مرد کے دل میں پیدا ہوتا ہے اور وہ سینکڑوں رہ نشینوں کو (منزل کی جانب) گامزن کر دیتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When this ecstasy affects the heart of a living person, he makes sluggards sitting on the roadside to move on swiftly.
(Sluggards, rah-nashin: wayside beggars, sitting and doing nothing. Rah-naward: He who is on the way, going somewhere, indicating movement, progress towards the goal.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بندہ را با خواجہ خواہی در ستیز
تخم "لا" در مشت خاک او بریز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تو غلام کو آقا کے خلاف لڑانا چاہتا ہے تو اس کی مشت خاک میں لا کا بیج بو دے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Dost thou wish the servant to fight the master (for his rights)? Then sow the seed of No in his handful of dust.	 
(Iqbal coined the word khwajgi to express the idea behind ‘capitalism’. It was first used in Rumuz-i-Bekhudi. Capitalism has cast many a charming idol: race, nationalism, church, state, civilization, and colour.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہر کرا این سوز باشد در جگر
ہولش از ہول قیامت بیشتر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جس شخص کے جگر میں اس کا سوز ہو گا اس کی ہیبت قیامت کی ہیبت سے بڑھ کر ہو گی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Whoever has this burning ardour in his heart	is more awe-inspiring than the Doomsday.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لا مقام ضربہای پی بہ پی
این غو رعد است نے آواز نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        لا ضرب ہائے پے بہ پے کا مقام ہے، یہ بجلی کی کڑک ہے، بانسری کی آواز نہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        No is a succession of violent blows; it is the rumbling of thunder, not the piping tune of a flute.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ضرب او ہر "بود" را سازد "نبود"
تا برون آئی ز گرداب وجود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس کی ضرب ہر موجود کو مٹا دیتی ہے تاکہ تو موجود کے بھنور سے باہر آ جائے (لا موجود الا اﷲ)۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Its blow changes every being into non-being, so that thou comest out of the whirlpool of Existence.
(The point Iqbal wishes to emphasise here is that one who follows Tawhid in spirit feels everything besides himself and God as of no value and hence insignificant and unreal. One must, however, guard here against a misconception. Iqbal’s normal position is that the world of matter is real and not illusory.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        با تو میگویم ز ایام عرب
تا بدانی پختہ و خام عرب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میں تمہیں عرب کی تاریخ بتاتا ہوں تاکہ اس کے پختہ اور خام ایّام سے آگاہ ہو۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I relate to thee the history of the Arabs that thou may know its good and bad aspects.
(Literally, so that you may know what is ripe and unripe in (the history of) the Arabs.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ریز ریز از ضرب او لات و منات
در جہات آزاد از بند جہات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس کی ضرب سے (سب) لات و منات ریزہ ریزہ ہو گئے اور وہ قوم (جہان) جہات کے اندر رہتی ہوئی بھی جہات کی بندشوں سے آزاد ہو گئی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Their strokes broke Lat and Manat into pieces; confined within dimensions, they yet lived free of all bonds.	 
(Lat and Manat: Two idols, among many, which the Arabs worshipped. Here they stand for objects and persons other than God, to whom people pay homage.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="31">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہر قبای کہنہ چاک از دست او
قیصر و کسری ھلاک از دست او
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس کے ہاتھوں ہر پرانی قبا چاک ہوئی، اس نے قیصر و کسری ( کی سلطنتوں ) کو خاک میں ملا دیا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Every old garment was torn off by them; Chosroes and Caesars met their doom at their hands.	 
(Chosroe was the title of Persian monarchs and Caesar, of Roman emperors. Qaisar and Kisra are used as symbols of imperialism.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گاہ دشت از برق و بارانش بدرد
گاہ بحر از زور طوفانش بدرد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کبھی اس کی برق و باراں نے صحرا کو ہلا دیا اور کبھی اس کے زور طوفاں نے سمندر کو جھنجوڑ دیا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        At times deserts were overrun by their thunder showers; at other times seas were churned by their storms.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="35">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عالمی در آتش او مثل خس
این ہمہ ہنگامہ "لا" بود و بس
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جملہ عالم اس کی آگ کے سامنے خس کی مانند تھا، یہ سارا لا ہی کا ہنگامہ تھا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The whole world, no more than a straw, was set afire by them: It was all a manifestation of No.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="37">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اندرین دیر کہن پیھم تپید
تا جھانی تازہ ئی آمد پدید
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        وہ اس پرانے بتخانے میں مسلسل تڑپے یہاں تک کہ ایک نیا جہان ظاہر ہو گیا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        They were constantly astir until out of this old world they brought forth a new one into existence.
(Jahan-e-Taza: New World. According to Allamah the New World means a world in accordance with the basic principles of Islam and is most relevant to the contemporary situation.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="39">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بانگ حق از صبح خیزیہای اوست
ہر چہ ہست از تخم ریزیہای اوست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس کی صبح خیزی سے بانگ حق بلند ہوئی ، جو کچھ بھی ہمیں نظر آتا ہے ان ہی کے بوئے ہوئے بیج ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The invitation to the truth (the call to prayer) is the result of their early rising; whatever exists is the outcome of their sowing (of seed).	 
(Rising early in the morning: It stands for intense devotion to God. Sowing of seed is to prepare the field for cultivation. The first line signifies that the ideal man is in constant touch with God from Whom be gets inspiration, as a result of which he tries to establish the rule of God’s laws on this earth.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="41">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اینکہ شمع لالہ روشن کردہ اند
از کنار جوی او آوردہ اند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        یہ جو اس دور میں گل لالہ (تازہ علوم) کی شمع روشن کی گئی ہے یہ پودا ان ہی کی جوئے آب کے کنارے سے لایا گیا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The lamp of the tulip that has been lit up was brought from the banks of their river.
(Iqbal refers to the tremendous creative work done by the Arabs in the fields of science and art. All that is visible in this world, of civilization, of knowledge, art and skill, is the result of their creative activity. It was they who sowed the seed and we in the present age are witnessing and enjoying the fruit of their labours. Modern sciences and arts are a continuation of what the Arabs achieved in their days.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="43">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لوح دل از نقش غیر اﷲ شست
از کف خاکش دو صد ہنگامہ رست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جب عربوں نے اپنے دل سے غیر اللہ کا نقش دھو دیا تو ان کی کف خاک سے سینکڑوں ہنگامے اٹھ کھڑے ہوئے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        They erased from the tablet of their heart the	impress of the other-than-God; hundreds of new worlds therefore came into being at their hands.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="45">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہمچنان بینی کہ در دور فرنگ
بندگی با خواجگی آمد بہ جنگ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس طرح تو نے دیکھا کہ فرنگیوں کے دور میں بھی غلامی نے آقائی سے جنگ کی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You will similarly see that in the period of Western dominance capital and labour have come to blows.	 
(Daur-i-Farang: Period of European domination, both political and intellectual. Iqbal seems to imply that the class struggle, strife between capital and labour, is the result of this age which is secular in nature, divorced from religious background.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="47">
      <Text Language="Original">
        روس را قلب و جگر گردیدہ خون
از ضمیرش حرف "لا" آمد برون
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جب روس کا قلب و جگر خون ہو گیا تو اس کے ضمیر سے لا کا لفظ اٹھ کھڑا ہوا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        As the heart of Russia was sorely afflicted, the word No came out of the depths of her being.
(Depth of being: The word used by Iqbal, damir, signifies conscience, heart, and hence inner recesses of mind. This is a peculiar use of the word in Iqbal. The Qur’an says (xli. 53): ‘We will show them Our signs in the outer world and in the inner world (of self).’ The actual word used is anfus which the mystics regard as a region where they receive illumination and hence are able to arrive at the truth, mentioned in the above Qur’anic verse. This region of mystic experience may be called qalb (mentioned in the Qur’an, xxxii. 7-9) about which Iqbal says: ‘It is, according to the Qur’an, something which ‘sees’, and its reports, if properly interpreted, are never false’ (Reconstruction). In Javid Namah, Allamah says: ‘If you possess the spirit of a true Muslim, look into your heart and the Qur’an, a hundred new worlds lie in its verses, whole centuries are involved in its moments.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="49">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آن نظام کہنہ را برہم زد است
تیز نیشی بر رگ عالم زد است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس نے اپنا پرانا نظام درہم برہم کر دیا ہے اور جہان کی رگ حیات پر تیز نشتر لگایا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        She has upset the old order and applied a sharp scalpel to the veins of the world.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="51">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کردہ ام اندر مقاماتش نگہ
لا سلاطین، لا کلیسا، لا الہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میں نے اس ( انقلاب) کے مقامات پر نظر ڈالی ہے، اس نے پہلے سلاطین پھر کلیسا اور آخر میں اللہ تعالے کی نفی کی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I have closely observed her position which is: no kings, no church, no deity.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="53">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فکر او در تند باد "لا" بماند
مرکب خود را سوی "الا" نراند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس کا فکر لا کی تیز آندھی ہی میں رہا ، اس نے اپنی سواری کا رخ الا کی طرف نہ موڑا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Her thought has remained tied to the wind-storm of negation, and has not marched towards the affirmative ‘but’.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="55">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آیدش روزی کہ از زور جنون
خویش را زین تند باد آرد برون
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ایک دن آئے گا جب وہ زور جنوں سے اپنے آپ کو اس آندھی سے نکال دے گا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Maybe a day will come when through force of ecstasy she may extricate herself from this whirlwind.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="57">
      <Text Language="Original">
        در مقام "لا" نیاساید حیات
سوی الا می خرامد کائنات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کیونکہ زندگی لا کے مقام میں آسودگی نہیں پاتی ، کائنات خود بخود الا کی طرف چل نکلتی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Life does not rest at the station of Negation, the universe moves on towards ‘but’.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="59">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لا و الا ساز و برگ امتان
نفی بی اثبات مرگ امتان
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        قوموں کا آسمان لا اور الا دونوں ہیں، اثبات کے بغیر نفی میں قوموں کی موت ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Negation and affirmation both are necessary for the nations: Negation without affirmation is their death.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="61">
      <Text Language="Original">
        در محبت پختہ کی گردد خلیل
تا نگردد لا سوی الا دلیل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        خلیل ا لّہ کی محبت میں کیسے پختہ ہو سکتا ہے، جب تک لا اس کی راہنمائی الا اﷲ کی جانب نہ کرے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        How can Khalil (friend) be ripe in love unless negation guides him towards affirmation?
(Reference is to the life of Prophet Abraham (A.S.). See the Qur’an, vi 76-80 where Abraham’s experience of ‘the kingdom of the heavens and the earth’ is described, involving denial of all false gods and attaining certainty by affirming his complete submission to Him ‘Who originated the heavens and the earth’, and he was not of the polytheists.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="63">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے کہ اندر حجرہ ہا سازی سخن
نعرہ لا پیش نمرودی بزن
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        (اے صوفی!) تو جو حجرے کے اندر بیٹھ کر باتیں بناتا ہے، (باہر نکل اور) نمرود کے سامنے لا کا نعرہ لگا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O you, who indulge in debate in your closet, raise the cry of negation before a Nimrod. 
(Here Nimrod stands for any haughty ruler whose authority is not based on consent and who rules autocratically.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="65">
      <Text Language="Original">
        این کہ می بینی نیرزد با دو جو
از جلال لا الہ آگاہ شو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        یہ جو کچھ تو دیکھتا ہے اس کی قیمت دو جو کے برابر بھی نہیں ، لا الہ کے جلال سے آگاہ ہو۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What you see around you is not worth two grains of barley, be acquainted with the might of there is no deity.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="67">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہر کہ اندر دست او شمشیر لاست
جملہ موجودات را فرمانرواست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جس کے ہاتھ میں لا کی شمشیر ہے وہ ساری موجودات کا فرمانروا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He who has the sword of negation in his hands is the ruler of all the universe.	
(Translated by Bashir Ahmad Dar)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>