<Poem ID="23" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="02" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تری نگاہ فرومایہ، ہاتھ ہے کوتاہ 
ترا گنہ کہ نخیل بلند کا ہے گناہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        نگاہ فرومايہ: ایسی نگاہ جو دور رس نہ ہو۔ 
نخيل: کھجور کے درخت۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Thy vision and thy hands are chained, earth-bound, is it thy nature’s fault, or of the thought too high?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گلا تو گھونٹ دیا اہل مدرسہ نے ترا 
کہاں سے آئے صدا 'لا الہ الا اللہ'
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The schoolmen have strangled thy nascent soul, and stifled the voice of passionate faith in thee.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خودی میں گم ہے خدائی، تلاش کر غافل! 
یہی ہے تیرے لیے اب صلاح کار کی راہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Absorb thyself in selfhood, seek the path of God, this is the only way for thee to find freedom.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حدیث دل کسی درویش بے گلیم سے پوچھ 
خدا کرے تجھے تیرے مقام سے آگاہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Ask an unclad dervish what the heart doth say, may God show thee thy place in the world of men.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        برہنہ سر ہے تو عزم بلند پیدا کر 
یہاں فقط سر شاہیں کے واسطے ہے کلاہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If bare-headed, have a towering will, the crown is not for thee, but for the eagle alone.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہ ہے ستارے کی گردش، نہ بازی افلاک 
خودی کی موت ہے تیرا زوال نعمت و جاہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When thou losest selfhood, thou losest power, too; blame not the stars and fate for thy fall.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اٹھا میں مدرسہ و خانقاہ سے غم ناک 
نہ زندگی، نہ محبت، نہ معرفت، نہ نگاہ!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Monasteries and schools left me sad and dejected no life and no love; no vision and no knowledge.
(Translated by Naim Siddiqui)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>