<Poem ID="11" Name="ماں کا خواب" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="1a" SectionName="حصہ اول">
  <Para>
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میں سوئی جو اک شب تو دیکھا یہ خواب
بڑھا اور جس سے مرا اضطراب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A MOTHER'S DREAM
As I slept one night I saw this dream, which further increased my vexation.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ دیکھا کہ میں جا رہی ہوں کہیں
اندھیرا ہے اور راہ ملتی نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I dreamt I was going somewhere on the way; dark it was and impossible to find the way.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لرزتا تھا ڈر سے مرا بال بال
قدم کا تھا دہشت سے اٹھنا محال
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Trembling all over with fear I was, difficult to take even a step with fear was.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جو کچھ حوصلہ پا کے آگے بڑھی
تو دیکھا قطار ایک لڑکوں کی تھی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        With some courage as I forward moved, I saw some boys as lined in nice array.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زمرد سی پوشاک پہنے ہوئے
دیے سب کے ہاتھوں میں جلتے ہوئے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Dressed in emerald-like raiment they were, carrying lighted lamps in their hands they were.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وہ چپ چاپ تھے آگے پیچھے رواں
خدا جانے جانا تھا ان کو کہاں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        They were going quietly behind each other; no one knew where they were to go.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اسی سوچ میں تھی کہ میرا پسر
مجھے اس جماعت میں آیا نظر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Involved in this thought was I, when in this troupe my son saw I.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وہ پیچھے تھا اور تیز چلتا نہ تھا
دیا اس کے ہاتھوں میں جلتا نہ تھا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He was walking at the back, and was not walking fast. The lamp he had in his hand was not lighted.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کہا میں نے پہچان کر، میری جاں!
مجھے چھوڑ کر آ گئے تم کہاں!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Recognizing him I said ‘O My dear! Where have you come leaving me there?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جدائی میں رہتی ہوں میں بے قرار
پروتی ہوں ہر روز اشکوں کے ہار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Restless due to separation I am; weeping every day for ever I am.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہ پروا ہماری ذرا تم نے کی
گئے چھوڑ، اچھی وفا تم نے کی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You did not care even a little for me! What loyalty you showed, you left me’!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جو بچے نے دیکھا مرا پیچ و تاب
دیا اس نے منہ پھیر کر یوں جواب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        As the child saw the distress in me, he replied thus; turning around to me.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رلاتی ہے تجھ کو جدائی مری
نہیں اس میں کچھ بھی بھلائی مری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ‘The separation from me makes you cry, not least little good does this to me.’
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ کہہ کر وہ کچھ دیر تک چپ رہا
دیا پھر دکھا کر یہ کہنے لگا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He remained quiet for a while after talking; showing me the lamp then he started talking.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سمجھتی ہے تو ہو گیا کیا اسے؟
ترے آنسوئوں نے بجھایا اسے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ‘Do you understand what happened to this? Your tears have extinguished this’!
[Translated by M.A.K.Khalil]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>