<Poem ID="30" Name="دل" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="1a" SectionName="حصہ اول">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        قصہ دار و رسن بازی طفلانہ دل
التجائے 'ارنی' سرخی افسانہء دل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        بازي طفلانہ: بچوں کا کھیل۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Tales of gallows and crucifixion are mere child's play for the Heart. The request of Arini* is only the title of the story of the Heart.
* This alludes to the several verses of the Holy Qur’an in which the desire of Musa (A.S) to see God has been mentioned, especially 7:143, in which this word occurs.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یا رب اس ساغر لبریز کی مے کیا ہو گی
جاوہ ملک بقا ہے خط پیمانہ دل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جادہ ملک بقا: ہمیشہ کی زندگی کا راستہ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O Lord! How powerful the full cup of that wine would be? The Way to eternity is each single line on the measuring cup of the Heart.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ابر رحمت تھا کہ تھی عشق کی بجلی یا رب
جل گئی مزرع ہستی تو اگا دانہء دل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مزرع: کھیتی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O Lord! Was it the cloud of mercy or the thunderbolt of Love, when the life's crop got burned down, sprouted the seed of the Heart.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حسن کا گنج گراں مایہ تجھے مل جاتا
تو نے فرہاد! نہ کھودا کبھی ویرانہ دل!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        گنج گراں: بے بہا خزانہ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You would have got the Beauty's bountiful treasure, O Farhad*! You never dug into the ruins of the Heart.
* Lover of Shirin in the Persian epic of love titled Khusro Wa Shirin by Hakim Abu Muhammad Ilyas Jamal al-Din).
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عرش کا ہے کبھی کعبے کا ہے دھوکا اس پر
کس کی منزل ہے الہی! مرا کاشانہ دل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Now it looks like the ‘Arsh ’, now like the Ka'bah. O God! Whose lodging is the abode of my Heart.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اس کو اپنا ہے جنوں اور مجھے سودا اپنا
دل کسی اور کا دیوانہ، میں دیوانہء دل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It has its own junoon* and I have my own sawda;* the Heart loves someone else and I love the Heart.
* Junoon and Sawda: Both are Arabic words and mean insanity; used in Urdu and Persian for the extreme love in which the lover loses his logic and behaves like a lunatic.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تو سمجھتا نہیں اے زاہد ناداں اس کو
رشک صد سجدہ ہے اک لغزش مستانہء دل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You do not comprehend this, O simple hearted ascetic! Envy of a thousand prostrations is one slip of the Heart.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خاک کے ڈھیر کو اکسیر بنا دیتی ہے
وہ اثر رکھتی ہے خاکستر پروانہ دل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        خاک کے ڈھير: مراد ہے انسان۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It changes the heap of earth into elixir; such is the power of the ashes of the Heart.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عشق کے دام میں پھنس کر یہ رہا ہوتا ہے
برق گرتی ہے تو یہ نخل ہرا ہوتا ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        نخل: پودا، درخت۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It gains freedom after being caught in the net of Love; on being thunder-struck greens up the tree of the Heart
(Translated by Dr. M.A.K. Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>