<Poem ID="11" Name="" BookID="08" BookName="زبورِعجم" SectionID="02" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لالہ این چمن آلودۂ رنگ است ہنوز
سپر از دست مینداز کہ جنگ است ہنوز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The tulip of this meadowland is yet all flecked with hue; cast not the shield out of thy hand, for battle flares anew.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فتنہ ئی را کہ دو صد فتنہ با آغوشش بود
دختری ہست کہ در مہد فرنگ است ہنوز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A tumult, in whose swelling breast two hundred tumults wait that maiden is who dwells caressed in Europe’s cradle yet.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے کہ آسودہ نشینی لب ساحل بر خیز
کہ ترا کار بگرداب و نہنگ است ہنوز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O thou who sittest at thy ease beside the shore, arise! The whirlpool roars across the seas, the shark in menace lies.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        از سر تیشہ گذشتن ز خردمندی نیست
اے بسا لعل کہ اندر دل سنگ است ہنوز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        No part of wisdom ’tis, I trow, the trusty axe to shun; within the rock’s heart, even now, are rubies to be won.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        باش تا پردہ گشایم ز مقام دگری
چہ دہم شرح نواہا کہ بچنگ است ہنوز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Await! And I will raise the veil, that other songs may thrill; what should I of such music tell the lute concealeth still?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نقش پرداز جھان چون بجنونم نگریست
گفت ویرانہ بسودای تو تنگ است ہنوز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When the world’s wondrous Artist viewed the madness in my brain, he cried, ‘Too mighty swells thy mood, this ruin to contain!’
(Translated by A.J. Arberry.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>