<Poem ID="25" Name="مسلم" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہر نفس اقبال تیرا آہ میں مستور ہے 
سینہ سوزاں ترا فریاد سے معمور ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE MUSLIM
O Iqbal! Every breath of yours is veiled in sighs; your burning breast is filled with complaint.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نغمہ امید تیری بربط دل میں نہیں 
ہم سمجھتے ہیں یہ لیلی تیرے محمل میں نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The song of hope does not exist in the harp of your heart; we think this Lailah does not exist in your camel-litter.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گوش آواز سرود رفتہ کا جویا ترا 
اور دل ہنگامہء حاضر سے بے پروا ترا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your ear is the seeker of the sound of bygone lyre and your heart is unconcerned with today’s affairs.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        قصہ گل ہم نوایان چمن سنتے نہیں 
اہل محفل تیرا پیغام کہن سنتے نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your garden companions do not listen to the tale of roses; the assembly’s people do not listen to your old message.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے درائے کاروان خفتہ پا! خاموش رہ 
ہے بہت یاس آفریں تیری صدا خاموش رہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O bell of the sleeping caravan! Be quiet your call is very frustrating! Be quiet.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زندہ پھر وہ محفل دیرینہ ہو سکتی نہیں 
شمع سے روشن شب دوشینہ ہوسکتی نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        That old assembly cannot be brought back to life. The yesternight cannot be illuminated with candle.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہم نشیں! مسلم ہوں میں، توحید کا حامل ہوں میں 
اس صداقت پر ازل سے شاہد عادل ہوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O Companion! I am a Muslim, I am the harbinger of Tawhid; since eternity I am the sincere testifier of this Truth.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نبض موجودات میں پیدا حرارت اس سے ہے 
اور مسلم کے تخیل میں جسارت اس سے ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The warmth in the pulse of the universe is from this and the courage in the Muslim’s thought is from this.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حق نے عالم اس صداقت کے لیے پیدا کیا
اور مجھے اس کی حفاظت کے لیے پیدا کیا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        God created the universe for this Truth and created me for its guardianship.
(Allusion to the Holy Qur’an 51:56. True service to God implies firm belief in His Tawhid and other attributes, not only in words but by affirmation with the heart and by deeds in His cause and in the service of humanity as is required by the Holy Qur’an.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دہر میں غارت گر باطل پرستی میں ہوا 
حق تو یہ ہے حافظ ناموس ہستی میں ہوا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I became the destroyer of false worship in the world; the truth is that I became the protector of Existence’ honour.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میری ہستی پیرہن عریانی عالم کی ہے 
میرے مٹ جانے سے رسوائی بنی آدم کی ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My life is the cover for the world’s nakedness; my destruction is the disgrace of the human race.
(Allamah Iqbal sincerely believed that the decline and fall of the Muslim world to its present abject state is the cause of the ethical and moral degeneration of the whole human race. This, in its turn, is the cause of the evils in the present day world.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        قسمت عالم کا مسلم کوکب تابندہ ہے 
جس کی تابانی سے افسون سحر شرمندہ ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Muslim is the shining star of the universe’s destiny; the spell of the morning by whose brilliance is shy.
(These two verses show the supremacy of Man in the creation of God. According to Allamah Iqbal’s concept of Khudi Man reaches perfection and the zenith of his spiritual progress by complete submission to God, which is what Islam is.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آشکارا ہیں مری آنکھوں پہ اسرار حیات 
کہہ نہیں سکتے مجھے نومید پیکار حیات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The secrets of life are open to my eyes; I cannot be considered lacking hope in the battle of life.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کب ڈرا سکتا ہے غم کا عارضی منظر مجھے 
ہے بھروسا اپنی ملت کے مقدر پر مجھے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        How can the transient scene of grief frighten me! Confidence in destiny of my Millat strengthens me.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یاس کے عنصر سے ہے آزاد میرا روزگار 
فتح کامل کی خبر دتیا ہے جوش کارزار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My world is free of the component of despair; the zeal for battle gives the news of complete victory.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="31">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہاں یہ سچ ہے چشم بر عہد کہن رہتا ہوں میں 
اہل محفل سے پرانی داستاں کہتا ہوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Yes, it is true I keep my eye on the old times; I relate the old story to the assembly’s audience.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یاد عہد رفتہ میری خاک کو اکسیر ہے 
میرا ماضی میرے استقبال کی تفسیر ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Memory of the past age is the elixir for my life; my past is the interpretation of my future.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="35">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سامنے رکھتا ہوں اس دور نشاط افزا کو میں 
دیکھتا ہوں دوش کے آئینے میں فردا کو میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I keep that pleasurable period before me; I see the tomorrow in the mirror of today.
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>