<Poem ID="27" Name="شفاخانہ حجاز" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اک پیشوائے قوم نے اقبال سے کہا 
کھلنے کو جدہ میں ہے شفاخانہ حجاز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE HOSPITAL OF HIJAZ
A leader of the nation once said to Iqbal: ‘A hospital is about to open in Jeddah for Hijaz.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہوتا ہے تیری خاک کا ہر ذرہ بے قرار 
سنتا ہے تو کسی سے جو افسانہ حجاز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Every speck of your dust becomes restless as you hear from somebody the tale of Hijaz.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دست جنوں کو اپنے بڑھا جیب کی طرف 
مشہور تو جہاں میں ہے دیوانہ حجاز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Move your hand of Love towards your pocket; you are world famous as the lover of Hijaz.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دارالشفا حوالی لبطحا میں چاہیے 
نبض مریض پنجہ عیسی میں چاہیے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The hospital in the suburbs of Battha* is needed in the hands of Issa the patient’s pulse is needed.’
(*This is another name of Makkah Mu‘azzamah.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میں نے کہا کہ موت کے پردے میں ہے حیات 
پوشیدہ جس طرح ہو حقیقت مجاز میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I said ‘Life lies in the veil of death as the Truth lies veiled in metaphors.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تلخابہ اجل میں جو عاشق کو مل گیا 
پایا نہ خضر نے مے عمر دراز میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What the Lover has obtained in the position of death; Khizar could not obtain in the wine of eternal life.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اوروں کو دیں حضور! یہ پیغام زندگی 
میں موت ڈھونڈتا ہوں زمین حجاز میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Sir, convey this message of life to others; I am searching for death in the land of Hijaz.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آئے ہیں آپ لے کے شفا کا پیام کیا 
رکھتے ہیں اہل درد مسیحا سے کام کیا!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Why have you brought the message of cure? What concern do Lovers have with the Masiha.* 
(*Allusion to Issa A.S. and his miracle of bringing the dead to life.
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>