<Poem ID="10" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="02" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دل سوز سے خالی ہے، نگہ پاک نہیں ہے 
پھر اس میں عجب کیا کہ تو بے باک نہیں ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Of passion’s glow your heart is blank; your glances are not chaste and frank: To wonder at then there is naught that bold and dauntless you are not.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے ذوق تجلی بھی اسی خاک میں پنہاں 
غافل! تو نرا صاحب ادراک نہیں ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        صاحب ادراک: اشارہ ہے مشہور عام حدیث کی طرف جس میں کہا گیا 'اگر تو نہ ہو تا تو میں اسمانوں کو پیدا نہ کرتا'۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A longing strong for God’s display is also hid in self-same clay: O heedless man, let this be known, brains alone you do not own.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وہ آنکھ کہ ہے سرم ہ افرنگ سے روشن 
پرکار و سخن ساز ہے، نم ناک نہیں ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The eye whose light and luster rest on collyrium brought from West: Is full of art, conceit and show, it gets not wet at others’ woe.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کیا صوفی و ملا کو خبر میرے جنوں کی 
ان کا سر دامن بھی ابھی چاک نہیں ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        How can the priest and monk assess the height of craze that I possess? Still sound the hems of robes they wear, which have no rifts and know no tear.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کب تک رہے محکومی انجم میں مری خاک 
یا میں نہیں، یا گردش افلاک نہیں ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        How long the stars shall hold their sway on fate of man, sprung from clay? Either bereft of life I drop, or the Wheel of Fate must stop.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بجلی ہوں، نظر کوہ و بیاباں پہ ہے مری 
میرے لیے شایاں خس و خاشاک نہیں ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Lightning I am and keep my eye on waste and hill that reach the sky: Heaps of straw and mounds of dust, too low they are, avoid I must.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عالم ہے فقط مومن جاں باز کی میراث 
مومن نہیں جو صاحب لولاک نہیں ہے!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        That godly man gets world’s bequest, who risks his life in ceaseless quest: That man no Faith can claim at all, who lives not up to Prophet’s call.
[Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>