<Poem ID="13" Name="" BookID="11" BookName="ارمغانِ حجاز" SectionID="02" SectionName="حضور رسالت">
  <Para Name="(1)">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تو ہم آن می بگیر از ساغر دوست
کہ باشی تا ابد اندر بر دوست
سجودی نیست اے عبدالعزیز این 
بروبم از مژہ خاک در دوست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اے عبدالعزیز (ابن سعود) تو بھی ساغر دوست سے وہ شراب عشق پی؛ تاکہ تو ہمیشہ محبوب کے پہلو میں رہے۔
 میں یہاں سجدہ نہیں کر رہا؛ بلکہ در دوست (صلعم) کی خاک اپنی پلکوں سے صاف کر رہا ہوں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You too take the wine from friend’s cup warm; to be for ever in the friend’s arm.
No bows are these O, ‘Aziz of Arab land’; from eyelash I’m dusting my friend’s door sand.*

* In Arabic and Persian ‘Arab’ is pronounced as A-rb; Arab and ‘urb means ‘Arabs’ living in towns who keep a good breed of horses.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(2)">
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تو سلطان حجازی من فقیرم
ولی در کشور معنی امیرم
جہانی کو ز تخم لاالہ رست
بیا بنگر بہ آغوش ضمیرم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        (اے ابن سعود!) تو حجاز کا سلطان ہے اور میں ایک فقیر ہوں؛ (ہوں فقیر) مگر ولایت معنی کا امیر ہوں۔ 
آ، میرے آغوش ضمیر میں وہ جہان دیکھ ؛ جو لاالہ کے بیج سے پیدا ہوا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A poor man I’m, you hold the ‘Arab’s reign; I hold a king’s place in meaning’s domain.
A world which grew up from ‘Lailah’s’ seed; its root are quite deep in my faith and creed.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(3)">
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سراپا درد درمان ناپذیرم
نپنداری زبون و زار و پیرم
ہنوزم در کمانی میتوان راند
ز کیش ملتی افتادہ پیرم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اگرچہ میں سراپا درد ہوں اور درد بھی ایسا جو لا علاج ہے (درد محبت کی طرف اشارہ ہے) ؛ مگر تو یہ گمان نہ کر کہ میں زار و زبون و ضعیف ہوں۔ 
ابھی مجھے کو ان میں رکھ کر چلایا جا سکتا ہے ؛ میں ملت (ہی) کے ترکش سے گرا ہوا تیر ہوں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A look of pain I’m and see no cure quick; I boast not but weep being old, weak and sick. 
I’m lost arrow though, put in nation’s bow; use me again if the nation thinks so.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(4)">
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بیا باھم در آویزیم و رقصیم
ز گیتی دل بر انگیزیم و رقصیم
یکی اندر حریم کوچہء دوست
ز چشمان اشک خون ریزیم و رقصیم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        آ، ہم باہم مل کر رقص کریں ؛ دنیا سے دل اٹھا لیں اور رقص کریں۔
کوئے محبوب (صلعم) کے حریم میں ؛ آنکھوں سے خون کے آنسو بہائیں اور رقص کریں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Let us join hands to dance in his flame; leave the world whole and dance for his name.
For a short while in the sweet beau’s lane; we dance* till the tears make the blood’s rain. 

* It is a well known term used by all the past mystics and as well as by Iqbal. In mystic’s esoterics or arcane signs it means ‘frenzy’ in their beloved Prophet’s love. As such ‘raqs-i-tan’ (dance of booy) means dedication of one’s body for the cause of the Prophet and Allah). Raqs-i.-jan’ means dance of soul.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(5)">
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ترا اندر بیابانی مقام است
کہ شامش چون سحر آئینہ فام است
بہرجائی کہ خواہی خیمہ گستر
طناب از دیگران جستن حرام است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تیرا مقام ایسے صحرا میں ہے؛ جس کی شام بھی صبح کی مانند روشن و شفاف ہے۔
جہاں چاہے اپنا خیمہ لگا؛ (مگر اتنا خیال رکھ کہ) دوسروں سے طناب مانگنا (یعنی فرنگیوں کا سہارا ڈھونڈنا حرام ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You hold a high place in the desert’s land; whose eyes are bright like a mirror house grand. 
Where e’er you wish you may pitch up the tents; but ban a feast there if the tent chords are lent.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(6)">
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مسلمانیم و آزاد از مکانیم
برون از حلقہء نہ آسمانیم
بما آموختند آن سجدہ کز وی 
بہای ھر خداوندی بدانیم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ہم مسلمان قید مکاں سے آزاد ہیں ؛ ہم نو آسمانوں کے حلقہ سے باہر ہیں۔
ہمیں ایسا سجدہ سکھایا گیا ہے؛ جس سے ہم ہر خداوند (معبود باطل) کی قیمت پہچان جاتے ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Being Muslims we make no home and false ties; from a circle aloof, we are nine skies. 
He taught us a kowtow from which we know; the price of each god to whom the men how. 

In East it is a sort of humble way to address oneself as a poor dervesh, as a poor Soov, a sinner. It does not mean actually drunk. It is just an etiquette to address one’s self in an humble way.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(7)">
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ز افرنگی صنم بیگانہ تو شو
کہ پیمانش نمی ارزد بیک جو
نگاہی وام کن از چشم فاروق
قدم بیباک نہ در عالم نو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        فرنگی بت سے لا تعلق ہو جا ؛ اس کے عہد و پیمان کی قیمت ایک جو کے برابر بھی نہیں۔ 
فاروق اعظم (رضی اللہ ) سے نگاہ قرض لے؛ اور ایک نئے جہان میں بے باکی سے قدم رکھ (اہل مغرب پر اعتبار نہ کر ، بلکہ اپنا نیا جہان پیدا کر)۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        To Anglian idols pay not a heed; the worth of her bonds is not a malt’s seed. 
From the Farooq’s bold eyes borrow a glance; make a fearless jump in the new age hence. 
(Translated by Q A Kabir)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>