<Poem ID="36" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="02" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہ ہو طغیان مشتاقی تو میں رہتا نہیں باقی 
کہ میری زندگی کیا ہے، یہی طغیان مشتاقی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Devoid of passion’s roar I can exist no more: What else can be this life but passion strong and strife?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مجھے فطرت نوا پر پے بہ پے مجبور کرتی ہے 
ابھی محفل میں ہے شاید کوئی درد آشنا باقی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My essence endlessly impels my minstrelsy: Some may in throng be still, who feels for others’ ill.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وہ آتش آج بھی تیرا نشیمن پھونک سکتی ہے 
طلب صادق نہ ہو تیری تو پھر کیا شکوئہ ساقی!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Love’s flame can still set fire to lodge and goods entire: If thirst be not aflame, wherefore the saki blame?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہ کر افرنگ کا اندازہ اس کی تابناکی سے 
کہ بجلی کے چراغوں سے ہے اس جوہر کی براقی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your judgment of the West on glamour must not rest: Its essence seems so bright by means of electric light.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دلوں میں ولولے آفاق گیری کے نہیں اٹھتے 
نگاہوں میں اگر پیدا نہ ہو انداز آفاقی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The thoughts of world conquest can never shape in breast, if blessed not be your gaze with world-wide wont and ways.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خزاں میں بھی کب آسکتا تھا میں صیاد کی زد میں 
مری غماز تھی شاخ نشیمن کی کم اوراقی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I, even in winter drear, fell not in hunter’s snare: My nest’s branches bare drew the hunter’s stare.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        الٹ جائیں گی تدبیریں، بدل جائیں گی تقدیریں 
حقیقت ہے، نہیں میرے تخیل کی یہ خلاقی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Their plans shall end in smoke, miscarry the destined stroke: This fact with truth is fraught, no fiction of my thought.
(Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>