<Poem ID="32" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="02" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اعجاز ہے کسی کا یا گردش زمانہ! 
ٹوٹا ہے ایشیا میں سحر فرنگیانہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This wonder by some glance is wrought, or Fortune’s wheel has come full round: At last the Frankish charm has been broken by the East by which in past was bound.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تعمیر آشیاں سے میں نے یہ راز پایا 
اہل نوا کے حق میں بجلی ہے آشیانہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        By the building of my nest, this secret hid was brought to view that for the bards that sing and chant the choice of nest is bolt from blue.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ بندگی خدائی، وہ بندگی گدائی 
یا بندہ خدا بن یا بندہ زمانہ!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If slave to God, you grow divine, if slave to world a beggar mean: You are the master of your fate, so make the choice the two between.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        غافل نہ ہو خودی سے، کر اپنی پاسبانی 
شاید کسی حرم کا تو بھی ہے آستانہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Of selfhood heedless never be, your gaze to self always confine: Who knows, you mat anon become the threshold of some sacred shrine.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے لا الہ کے وارث! باقی نہیں ہے تجھ میں 
گفتار دلبرانہ، کردار قاہرانہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O heir to creed no god but He, in you I see no sign or trace of mighty deeds that terror strike; your talk devoid of charm and grace.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تیری نگاہ سے دل سینوں میں کانپتے تھے 
کھویا گیا ہے تیرا جذب قلندرانہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your glances bold would strike the heart with awe, though sheathed within the breast: Alas! a qalandar’s fervent zeal in you is dead and is at rest.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        راز حرم سے شاید اقبال باخبر ہے 
ہیں اس کی گفتگو کے انداز محرمانہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Of Sanctuary’s secret hid Iqbal perhaps is well aware: His speech and song display alike a confidential moder.
[Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>