<Poem ID="39" Name="غلام قادر رہیلہ" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رہیلہ کس قدر ظالم، جفا جو، کینہ پرور تھا
نکالیں شاہ تیموری کی آنکھیں نوک خنجر سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        How cruel, tyrant and vindictive the Ruhilah was? He blinded the Mughal Emperor with the point of his dagger.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دیا اہل حرم کو رقص کا فرماں ستم گر نے
یہ انداز ستم کچھ کم نہ تھا آثار محشر سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        آثار محشر: قیامت کی نشانیاں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The tyrant ordered members of the royal household to dance. This tyranny was no less than the Judgment Day’s signal.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بھلا تعمیل اس فرمان غیرت کش کی ممکن تھی! 
شہنشاہی حرم کی نازنینان سمن بر سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        سمن بر: چنبیلی جیسے جسم والی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        For the delicate ladies of the royal household it was utterly impossible to comply with this shameless order.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بنایا آہ! سامان طرب بیدرد نے ان کو 
نہاں تھا حسن جن کا چشم مہر و ماہ و اختر سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        سامان طرب: عیش و نشاط کا سرمایہ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Ah! The merciless one made them the means of pleasure; whose beauty had been veiled from sun’s, moon’s and stars.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لرزتے تھے دل نازک، قدم مجبور جنبش تھے 
رواں دریائے خوں، شہزادیوں کے دیدئہ تر سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The feeble hearts were throbbing, the feet were forced to move; a river of blood was flowing from the wet eyes of the princesses.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یونہی کچھ دیر تک محو نظر آنکھیں رہیں اس کی 
کیا گھبرا کے پھر آزاد سر کو بار مغفر سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مغفر: لڑائی میں سر پر پہننے والی فولادی ٹوپی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        For some time his eyes remained thus absorbed in seeing; in confusion he freed his head from the load of Mighfar.
(Mighfar: This is the head covering worn under the helmet. It is also used as a helmet.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کمر سے، اٹھ کے تیغ جاں ستاں، آتش فشاں کھولی 
سبق آموز تابانی ہوں انجم جس کے جوہر سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He untied the deadly, fire-spitting sword from the waist; whose sharpness was a source of luminescence to the stars.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رکھا خنجر کو آگے اور پھر کچھ سوچ کر لیٹا 
تقاضا کر رہی تھی نیند گویا چشم احمر سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        چشم احمر: سرخ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He put the dagger in front, and lied down in some thought: Sleep was demanding rest from the red eyes so to say.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بجھائے خواب کے پانی نے اخگر اس کی آنکھوں کے 
نظر شرما گئی ظالم کی درد انگیز منظر سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اخگر: شعلہ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The water of sleep extinguished the embers of his eyes; the tyrant’s sight became ashamed of the painful spectacle!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پھر اٹھا اور تیموری حرم سے یوں لگا کہنے 
شکایت چاہیے تم کو نہ کچھ اپنے مقدر سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He got up and started saying this to Taimur’s household: ‘You should have no complaint against your fate’.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مرا مسند پہ سو جانا بناوٹ تھی، تکلف تھا 
کہ غفلت دور سے شان صف آرایان لشکر سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My sleeping in the couch was a mere show, an affectation; because stupor is foreign to the dignity of fighters.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ مقصد تھا مرا اس سے، کوئی تیمور کی بیٹی 
مجھے غافل سمجھ کر مار ڈالے میرے خنجر سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It was my intention that some daughter of Taimur considering me unconscious might kill me with my own dagger.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مگر یہ راز آخر کھل گیا سارے زمانے پر 
حمیت نام ہے جس کا، گئی تیمور کے گھر سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        But at last this secret has dawned to the whole world: Concern for honor has departed from Taimur’s household’
[Translated by Dr M A K Khalil]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>