<Poem ID="08" Name="ــــــــ کی گود میں بلی دیکھ کر" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="2a" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تجھ کو دزدیدہ نگاہی یہ سکھا دی کس نے
رمز آغاز محبت کی بتا دی کس نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ON SEEING A CAT IN THE LAP OF SOMEONE
Who has taught you this glancing with shyness? Who has taught you the riddle of Love’s initiation?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہر ادا سے تیری پیدا ہے محبت کیسی
نیلی آنکھوں سے ٹپکتی ہے ذکاوت کیسی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Love comes out of each grace of yours. Wit is dripping from the blue eyes of yours.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دیکھتی ہے کبھی ان کو، کبھی شرماتی ہے
کبھی اٹھتی ہے، کبھی لیٹ کے سو جاتی ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You see him sometimes, you shy away sometimes. Rise up sometimes, lie down and sleep sometimes.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آنکھ تیری صفت آئنہ حیران ہے کیا
نور آگاہی سے روشن تری پہچان ہے کیا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Is your eye bewildered like the mirror? Are you recognized by the glow of knowledge?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مارتی ہے انھیں پونہچوں سے، عجب ناز ہے یہ
چھیڑ ہے، غصہ ہے یا پیار کا انداز ہے یہ؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You strike him with wrists, this is a strange playfulness! Is it aversion or anger? Or a way of Love it is?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شوخ تو ہوگی تو گودی سے اتاریں گے تجھے
گر گیا پھول جو سینے کا تو ماریں گے تجھے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You will be removed from the lap if you will be naughty. You will be beaten if the flower on the breast will fall.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کیا تجسس ہے تجھے، کس کی تمنائی ہے
آہ! کیا تو بھی اسی چیز کی سودائی ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What are you longing for? What are you seeking? Ah! Are you also in Love with the same thing?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خاص انسان سے کچھ حسن کا احساس نہیں
صورت دل ہے یہ ہر چیز کے باطن میں مکیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The feeling for Beauty is not special to Man: Like the heart it is present in everything.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شیشہ دہر میں مانند مے ناب ہے عشق
روح خورشید ہے، خون رگ مہتاب ہے عشق
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In the flask of time Love is like the pure wine. Love is the sun’s spirit, and the blood in moon’s veins.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دل ہر ذرہ میں پوشیدہ کسک ہے اس کی
نور یہ وہ ہے کہ ہر شے میں جھلک ہے اس کی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Its pain is concealed in every speck’s core; this is the light which is reflected in everything.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کہیں سامان مسرت، کہیں ساز غم ہے
کہیں گوہر ہے، کہیں اشک، کہیں شبنم ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It causes happiness somewhere, and sorrow somewhere; it is pearl somewhere, tear somewhere, dew somewhere
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>