<Poem ID="02" Name="لا الہ الا اللہ" BookID="03" BookName="ضربِ کلیم" SectionID="01" SectionName="اسلام اور مسلمان">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خودی کا سر نہاں لا الہ الا اللہ 
خودی ہے تیغ، فساں لا الہ الا اللہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        سر نہاں: چھپا ہوا بھید۔ 
فساں:تلوار کی دھار تیز کرنے والا آلہ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The secret of the Self is hid, in words ‘No god but He alone’. The Self is just a dull-edged sword, ‘No god but He’; the grinding stone.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ دور اپنے براہیم کی تلاش میں ہے 
صنم کدہ ہے جہاں، لا الہ الا اللہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        براہيم: ابراہیم (علیہ) جنہوں نے اپنے وقت کے بادشاہ کا بتخانہ تباہ کیا تھا۔ 
کدہ: بت خانہ۔ صنم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        An Abraham by the age is sought to break the idols of this Hall: The avowal of God's Oneness can make all these idols headlong fall.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کیا ہے تو نے متاع غرور کا سودا 
فریب سود و زیاں، لا الہ الا اللہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        متاع غرور: غرور کی دولت، مراد ہے دنیا کی دولت۔ 
سود و زياں: نفع اور نقصان۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A bargain you have struck for goods of life, a step that smacks conceit; all save the Call ‘No god but He’ is merely fraught with fraud and deceit.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ مال و دولت دنیا، یہ رشتہ و پیوند 
بتان وہم و گماں، لا الہ الا اللہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        رشتہ و پيوند: عزیز داریوں اور تعلقات کے رشتے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The worldly wealth and riches too, ties of blood and friends a dream the idols wrought by doubts untrue, all save God's Oneness empty seem.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خرد ہوئی ہے زمان و مکاں کی زناری 
نہ ہے زماں نہ مکاں، لا الہ الا اللہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        زمان و مکاں: وقت اور جگہ، مراد ہے دنیا۔ 
زناري: برہمنوں کا وہ دھاگہ پہننا جس کو جنیو کہتے ہیں، یعنی کافر ہو جانا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The mind has worn the holy thread of Time and Space like pagans all though Time and Space both illusive. ‘No god but He’ is true withal.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ نغمہ فصل گل و لالہ کا نہیں پابند 
بہار ہو کہ خزاں، لا الہ الا اللہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        These melodious songs are not confined to Time when rose and tulip bloom, whatever the season of year be ‘No god but He’ must ring till doom.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اگرچہ بت ہیں جماعت کی آستینوں میں 
مجھے ہے حکم اذاں، لا الہ الا اللہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Many idols are still concealed' in their sleeves by the Faithful fold, I am ordained by Mighty God to raise the call and be much bold.
(Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>