<Poem ID="03" Name="دو ستارے" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آئے جو قراں میں دو ستارے 
کہنے لگا ایک، دوسرے سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE TWO STARS
As two stars came together in the Holy Qur’an; one started saying this to the other:
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ وصل مدام ہو تو کیا خوب 
انجام خرام ہو تو کیا خوب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ‘How excellent if this union together be permanent! How excellent if the end be walking together!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تھوڑا سا جو مہرباں فلک ہو 
ہم دونوں کی ایک ہی چمک ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If the sky becomes slightly favourable; we two will be with similar glow.’
* Under the influence of Greek thought the sky was considered to influence the happenings on the earth as well as the destinies of its denizens. Though after the advent of Islam, this is no longer believed it continues to be so expressed in Urdu and Persian literature.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لیکن یہ وصال کی تمنا 
پیغام فراق تھی سراپا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        But this longing for the union proved completely a message of the end of the union.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گردش تاروں کا ہے مقدر 
ہر ایک کی راہ ہے مقرر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Revolution is the destiny of the stars; for each its special orbit is fixed.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے خواب ثبات آشنائی 
آئین جہاں کا ہے جدائی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The permanence of union is a mere dream; the rule of the universe is separation!
* Allusion to the fact that stars do not occur in pairs but all of them cohere together as components of the universe. Similarly, the soorahs of the Holy Qur’an constitute a coherent whole and so should the Muslim Ummah be.)
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>