<Poem ID="15" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="02" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خودی کی شوخی و تندی میں کبر و ناز نہیں 
جو ناز ہو بھی تو بے لذت نیاز نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In the coquetry and fierceness of the self there is no pride, there are no airs. Even if there are airs, then they are not without the pleasure of submission.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نگاہ عشق دل زندہ کی تلاش میں ہے 
شکار مردہ سزاوار شاہباز نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The eye of love is in search of the living heart; hunting for carrion does not befit up to the royal hawk.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مری نوا میں نہیں ہے ادائے محبوبی 
کہ بانگ صور سرافیل دل نواز نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In my song there is no charming and romantic grace, for the blast of the trumpet of Israfil is not meant to please the heart.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سوال مے نہ کروں ساقی فرنگ سے میں 
کہ یہ طریقہ رندان پاک باز نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I will not ask for wine from the Frank, saki, for this is not the way of the pure-hearted profligates.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہوئی نہ عام جہاں میں کبھی حکومت عشق 
سبب یہ ہے کہ محبت زمانہ ساز نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The rule of love has never been widespread in the world. The reason is this – that love is no time-server.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اک اضطراب مسلسل، غیاب ہو کہ حضور 
میں خود کہوں تو مری داستاں دراز نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        غياب: غائب ہونا، غیر حاضر ہونا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        One continual anxiety; whether absent or present! If I tell it myself, my story is not long.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اگر ہو ذوق تو خلوت میں پڑھ زبور عجم 
فغان نیم شبی بے نوائے راز نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        زبور عجم: علامہ کی مشہور فارسی کتاب۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If you desire then read the Persian Psalms; in seclusion; the midnight lament is not bereft of secrets. 
(Translated by D.J. Matthews)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>