<Poem ID="23" Name="" BookID="07" BookName="پیامِ مشرق" SectionID="03" SectionName="می باقے">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بہ شاخ زندگی ما نمی ز تشنہ لبی است
تلاش چشمۂ حیوان دلیل کم طلبی است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The sap in the tree of our life comes from our thirst. To seek the spring of immortality is to be unadventurous.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حدیث دل بہ کہ گویم چہ راہ بر گیرم
کہ آہ بی اثر است و نگاہ بی ادبی است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Whom shall I tell the story of my heart and in what way? For sighs are ineffectual and looking is irreverence.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        غزل بہ زمزمہ خوان پردہ پست تر گردان
ہنوز نالۂ مرغان نوای زیر لبی است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Chant your ghazals, but let the key be very low; for birdsong here is still in undertones.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        متاع قافلۂ ما حجازیان بردند
ولی زبان نگشائی کہ یار ما عربی است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Men of Hijaz have robbed our caravan of all its goods. But silence! For our friend is from Arabia.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہال ترک ز برق فرنگ بار آورد
ظہور مصطفوی را بہانہ بولہبی است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The tree of the Turks has borne fruit because it was struck by the lightning of the West. The advent of the Chosen One took place because of Abu Lahabism.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مسنج معنی من در عیار ہند و عجم
کہ اصل این گہر از گریہ ہای نیم شبی است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Do not assess what I sing by the standards of Iran and Hindustan. It is a gem which is the product of nocturnal tears.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بیا کہ من ز خم پیر روم آوردم
می سخن کہ جوان تر ز بادہ عنبی است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Come, I have brought from the vat of the guide of Rum the wine of poesy, much younger than the wine of grapes.
(Translated by M. Hadi Husain)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>