<Poem ID="06" Name="نوای وقت" BookID="07" BookName="پیامِ مشرق" SectionID="02" SectionName="افکار">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خورشید بدامانم انجم بہ گریبانم
در من نگری ہیچم در خود نگری جانم
در شہر و بیابانم در کاخ و شبستانم
من دردم و درمانم، من عیش فراوانم
من تیغ جہانسوزم، من چشمۂ حیوانم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        سورج میرے دامن میں ہے، ستارے میرے گریبان کے اندر ہیں، اگر تو مجھے دیکھنے کی کوشش کرے تو میں کچھ نہیں (یعنی نظر نہیں آتا) اگر دیکھے تو میں تیری جان ہوں۔ 
میں شہر بیابان میں ہوں، میں محل و شبستان میں ہوں، میں درد بھی ہوں، درمان بھی اور عیش فراوان بھی، میں تیغ جہان سوز بھی ہوں اور آب حیات کا چشمہ بھی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE SONG OF TIME
For all my solar heraldry and all my stellar pageantry, I am a mere nonentity, if you look hard enough at me. But from your human point of view I am the very life of you.
I dwell wherever you men dwell – in city, desert, hill and dell – and in ways no one can foretell I come into your life as well. I am both pain and remedy, both ennui and great luxury. I am an all-destroying sword; I am the fountain of eternity.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="06">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چنگیزی و تیموری، مشتی ز غبار من
ہنگامۂ افرنگی یک جستہ شرار من
انسان و جھان او از نقش و نگار من
خون جگر مردان، سامان بہار من
من آتش سوزانم من روضہ رضوانم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        چنگیزی ہو یا تیموری میرا غبار راہ ہیں، افرنگیوں کا ہنگامہ میرے اندر سے اٹھا ہوا ایک شرر ہے۔
انسان اور اس کا جہان سب میرے نقش و نگار ہیں، بہادروں کا خون جگر میری بہار کا سامان ہے۔ میں جلا دینے والی آگ ہوں، میں بہشت کا باغ ہوں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The ravages of Genghis Khan, the victories of Tamerlane, are merely handfuls of dust thrown up by my powerful typhoon. The West’s disaster-spelling reign is one of my stray sparks upflown.
Man and the planet he lives on are merely sketches I have drawn. The sketches have as yet to don a painting’s garb; and there has gone into them – all it foul or fair – the rich heart blood of men who dare. l am an all-consuming fire; I am the garden of immortality.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آسودہ و سیارم این طرفہ تماشا بین
در بادۂ امروزم کیفیت فردا بین
پنہان بہ ضمیر من صد عالم رعنا بین
صد کوکب غلطان بین صد گنبد خضرا بین
من کسوت انسانم پیراہن یزدانم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ساکن بھی اور حرکت میں بھی، یہ طرفہ تماشا دیکھ، میرے آج کی شراب میں آنے والے کل کا کیف دیکھ۔
میرے ضمیر کے اندرسینکڑوں عالم رعنا پنہاں ہیں، کئی ستارے آوارہ ہیں، کئی آسمان گردش میں ہیں۔ میں انسان کا لباس ہوں، میں یزدان کا پیرہن ہوں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My paradox is manifest (to take it at its trickiest) eternal flux, eternal rest; unchangingness in change’s breast. Derive tomorrow’s ecstacies from my today’s wine, if you please.
You will find hidden in my mind a hundred worlds still undefined, worlds of a beautifuller kind than yours. The worlds I have outlined for making are new galaxies, new suns and moons and lands and seas. I am the element that man lives in, the milieu of divinity.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="16">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تقدیر فسون من تدبیر فسون تو
تو عاشق لیلائی من دشت جنون تو
چون روح روان پاکم از چند و چگون تو
تو راز درون من، من راز درون تو
از جان تو پیدایم، در جان تو پنہانم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تقدیر میرے فسوں سے ظاہر میں آتی ہے، تدبیر تیرا طریقہ ہے، تو لیلی (جستجو) کا عاشق ہے، میں تیری جولان گاہ ہوں۔
میں تیرے کم و بیش سے روح رواں کی طرح پاک ہوں ، تو میرے اندر کا راز ہے اور میں تیرے اندر کا راز ہوں۔ میں تیری جان (کوششوں ) سے ظاہر ہوں اور تیری جان ہی میں پنہاں ہوں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Fate is my magic powers’ source. Endeavour is the source of yours. You pitch against me your will’s force, designing for yourself your course, I am the desert that you rove, seeking the Laila that you love.
I am free as the soul is free from attributes of quantity – duration and extensity, succession and priority. You are thc secret inside me I am your being’s mystery. I live because you have a soul; and my abode is your soul’s privacy.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        من رہرو و تو منزل من مزرع و تو حاصل
تو ساز صد آہنگی تو گرمی این محفل
آوارۂ آب و گل، دریاب مقام دل
گنجیدہ بجامی بین این قلزم بی ساحل
از موج بلند تو سر بر زدہ طوفانم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میں مسافر ہوں ، تو منزل مقصود، میں کھیتی ہوں تو میرا حاصل، تو ایسا ساز ہے جس سے سینکڑوں ساز نکلتے ہیں ، تو اس محفل کا ہنگامہ ہے۔
تو اس دنیا میں سرگرداں ہونے کی بجائے اپنے دل کا مقام پہچان، دیکھ اس جام (دل) میں ایک بحر بے پایاں سمایا ہوا ہے۔ میں (بھی) تیری موج بلند سے اٹھا ہوا ایک طوفان ہوں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I am a traveler on the road: You are my goal and my abode. I am a field that has been sowed and you the yield it has bestowed. By yourself a grand orchestra, you fill the world with your eclat.
O you, who have strayed from your way in this world made of grades of clay, try to find out what part it may be fitting for the heart to play. Contained in this cup you can see the whole of being’s boundless sea. It was your own tide riding high that made the raging storm that I am be.
[Translated by M Hadi Hussain]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>