<Poem ID="02" Name="" BookID="08" BookName="زبورِعجم" SectionID="02" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دو عالم را توان دیدن بمینائی کہ من دارم
کجا چشمی کہ بیند آن تماشائی کہ من دارم
دگر دیوانہ ئی آید کہ در شھر افکند ہوئی
دو صد ہنگامۂ خیزد ز سودائی کہ من دارم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میرے پاس جو جام ہے اس میں دونوں جہان دیکھے جا سکتے ہیں ، کہاں ہے وہ آنکھ جو وہ دیکھے جسے میں میں دیکھ رہا ہوں۔ 
ایک اور دیوانہ آیا ، جس نے شہر میں نعرہ مستانہ بلند کیا، میرے جنوں سے سینکڑوں ہنگامے پیدا ہو رہے ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In the flask that here I hold, both the worlds one may behold; where’s the vision, to divine the wide vista that is mine? 
Madman comes again to town crying clamour up and down: See, a hundred riots start from the passion of my heart. 
[Translated by Arthur J Arberry]

Both worlds may be seen in the wine-pitches I have! Where is the eye to view the sights I see? 
There will come another man, possessed, who will shout ‘hu’ in the city; two hundred commotions will arise from the obsession I have. 
[Translated by Mustansir Mir]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مخور نادان غم از تاریکی شبہا کہ میآید
کہ چون انجم درخشد داغ سیمائی کہ من دارم
ندیم خویش میسازی مرا لیکن از آن ترسم
نداری تاب آن آشوب و غوغائی کہ من دارم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ناداں ! راتوں کی تاریکی سے دلگیر نہ ہو، میری پیشانی پہ جو داغ ہے وہ ستاروں کی طرح چمک رہا ہے۔ 
تو مجھے اپنا ساتھی تو بناتا ہے لیکن میں ڈرتا ہوں ، کہ تو میرے آشوب و غوغا کی تاب نہیں لا سکے گا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Grieve not foolishly, my friend, lest the dark of night descend: Lo, the brand upon my brow gleams in starry splendour now. 
Take me for thy comrade true; yet I fear, if so thou do, thou hast not the strength to bear the vast tumult I prepare.
[Translated by Arthur J Arberry]

Do not worry, ignorant one, at the approaching darkness of nights; for the scar of my forehead sparkles like stars.
You take me as your companion, but I am afraid that you are not up to the tumult and uproar I have raised.
[Translated by Mustansir Mir]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>