<Poem ID="43" Name="تقدیر" BookID="03" BookName="ضربِ کلیم" SectionID="01" SectionName="اسلام اور مسلمان">
  <Para Name="ابلیس">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے خدائے کن فکاں! مجھ کو نہ تھا آدم سے بیر 
آہ! وہ زندانی نزدیک و دور و دیر و زود 
حرف 'استکبار' تیرے سامنے ممکن نہ تھا 
ہاں، مگر تیری مشیت میں نہ تھا میرا سجود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        خدائے کن فکاں: وہ خدا جس نے کہا ہو جا اور سب کچھ ہو گیا۔ 
استکبار: غرور۔ (Jald)زود: جلد۔
مشيت: مرضی (خدا کی)
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        FATE: (SATAN AND GOD)
O Lord of worlds, against Adam, no grudge or spite I did e'er bear. Alas! He is a captive still of late and soon, far off and near.
'Fore You, O mighty Lord of Worlds a haughty pose I could not show; it was pre-ordained by You God that I to You would never bow.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="یزداں">
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کب کھلا تجھ پر یہ راز، انکار سے پہلے کہ بعد؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Before denial or after, when did across your mind this mystery dart?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="ابلیس">
    <Verse ID="06">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بعد! اے تیری تجلی سے کمالات وجود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Aft Lord, who can by Your display perfection great to life impart.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="یزداں">
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پستی فطرت نے سکھلائی ہے یہ حجت اسے 
کہتا ہے 'تیری مشیت میں نہ تھا میرا سجود، 
دے رہا ہے اپنی آزادی کو مجبوری کا نام 
ظالم اپنے شعلہ سوزاں کو خود کہتا ہے دود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        سجود: سجدہ کی جمع
حجت: دلیل۔ 
دود:دھواں۔
شعلہ سوزاں:جلا دینےوالا شعلہ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        His low grovelling bent of mind has taught the wretch to argue and contend; he says it was pre-ordained, to God he would not bow or bend.
Unfettered freedom though he owns, yet gives it name of much constraint: The tyrant, though a blazing flame, to be mere smoke is his complaint.
[Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>