<Poem ID="33" Name="نوید صبح" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آتی ہے مشرق سے جب ہنگامہ در دامن سحر 
منزل ہستی سے کر جاتی ہے خاموشی سفر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ہنگامہ در دامن: دامن میں ہنگامہ لیے ہوئے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE GOOD NEWS OF THE DAWN
When the dawn full of action arrives from the east; the silence marches off from the stage of life.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        محفل قدرت کا آخر ٹوٹ جاتا ہے سکوت 
دیتی ہے ہر چیز اپنی زندگانی کا ثبوت
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The quietude of nature’s congregation ends at last; everything presents evidence of its life at last.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چہچاتے ہیں پرندے پا کے پیغام حیات 
باندھتے ہیں پھول بھی گلشن میں احرام حیات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        احرام: وہ ان سلا لباس جو حاجی پہنتے ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The birds warble on getting the message of life in the garden flowers also put on the robe of life.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مسلم خوابیدہ اٹھ، ہنگامہ آرا تو بھی ہو 
وہ چمک اٹھا افق، گرم تقاضا تو بھی ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O sleeping Muslim get up! You also engaged in action be! Look, the horizon has brightened up, you also busy in urgent tasks be.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وسعت عالم میں رہ پیما ہو مثل آفتاب 
دامن گردوں سے ناپیدا ہوں یہ داغ سحاب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        سحاب: بادل۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In the universe’s expanse a traveler like the sun be; so that the sky not producing these spots of clouds be.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کھینچ کر خنجر کرن کا، پھر ہو سرگرم ستیز 
پھر سکھا تاریکی باطل کو آداب گریز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ستيز: لڑائی، جنگ۔ 
آداب گريز: بھاگنے کے طریقے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Pulling the dagger of sun’s ray get busy again in the fight! Again teacher of escape’s rules to falsehood’s darkness be.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تو سراپا نور ہے، خوشتر ہے عریانی تجھے 
اور عریاں ہو کے لازم ہے خود افشانی تجھے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        خود افشاني: اپنے آپ کو چھڑکنا؛ مراد ہے جوہر نمایاں کرنا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You are head to foot Light; manifestation makes you happy and after being manifest spreading out is incumbent on you.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہاں، نمایاں ہو کے برق دیدئہ خفاش ہو 
اے دل کون ومکاں کے راز مضمر! فاش ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        خفاش: چمگادڑ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Yes! On being manifest become lightning to the bat’s eye! O hidden mystery of the heart of universe manifest be! 
(Translated by Dr. M.A.K. Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>