<Poem ID="32" Name="رخصت اے بزم جہاں" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="1a" SectionName="حصہ اول">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رخصت اے بزم جہاں! سوئے وطن جاتا ہوں میں
آہ! اس آباد ویرانے میں گھبراتا ہوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        FAREWELL O WORLD'S CONGREGATION!
(Adapted from Ralph Waldo Emerson)
Farewell O worldly companions! I am going to my homeland. I am feeling unhappy in this well populated wilderness.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بسکہ میں افسردہ دل ہوں، درخور محفل نہیں
تو مرے قابل نہیں ہے، میں ترے قابل نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        درخور محفل: محفل کے قابل۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I am very much dejected, unsuitable for assemblies I am; neither you are suitable for me nor suitable for you I am.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        قید ہے، دربار سلطان و شبستان وزیر
توڑ کر نکلے گا زنجیر طلائی کا اسیر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The king's audience and the minister's bed-chamber each is a prison; the golden chain's prisoner will break himself free from this prison.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گو بڑی لذت تری ہنگامہ آرائی میں ہے
اجنبیت سی مگر تیری شناسائی میں ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Though much pleasure is in embellishing your assembly, but some kind of strangeness is in your acquaintance.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مدتوں تیرے خود آرائوں سے ہم صحبت رہا
مدتوں بے تاب موج بحر کی صورت رہا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        خود آرائوں: خود پسند لوگ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I remained long in company of your self centered people; I remain restless for long like the waves of the ocean.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مدتوں بیٹھا ترے ہنگامہ عشرت میں میں
روشنی کی جستجو کرتا رہا ظلمت میں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I remained long in your luxury gatherings; I remained long searching for light in the darkness.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مدتوں ڈھونڈا کیا نظارئہ گل خار میں
آہ، وہ یوسف نہ ہاتھ آیا ترے بازار میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I searched long for the rose' sight among thorns; Ah! I have not found that Yusuf in your market place.
(Yusuf (A.S.) possessed both material and spiritual beauty, which has become proverbial in Islamic literature. Looking for and not getting Yusuf (A.S.) is metaphorically used for searching for and failing to find some invaluable object such as knowledge.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چشم حیراں ڈھونڈتی اب اور نظارے کو ہے
آرزو ساحل کی مجھ طوفان کے مارے کو ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The perplexed eye for another scene is searching; as storm-stricken my eye for coast is searching.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چھوڑ کر مانند بو تیرا چمن جاتا ہوں میں
رخصت اے بزم جہاں! سوئے وطن جاتا ہوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Leaving your garden like fragrance I am going. Farewell! O worldly company I am going to the homeland.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گھر بنایا ہے سکوت دامن کہسار میں
آہ! یہ لذت کہاں موسیقی گفتار میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I have made my home in the quietness of the mountain side. Ah! I do not get this pleasure in conversation's music!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہم نشین نرگس شہلا، رفیق گل ہوں میں
ہے چمن میرا وطن، ہمسایہء بلبل ہوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Associate of Nargis-i-Shahlah, and rose's companion I am; the garden is my homeland, nightingale's associate I am.
(Nargis-i-Shahlah: The narcissus which is reddish-blue instead of white or yellow. Nargis-i-Shahlah is invaluable on account of being very rare.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شام کو آواز چشموں کی سلاتی ہے مجھے
صبح فرش سبز سے کوئل جگاتی ہے مجھے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The sound of the spring's music lulls me to sleep. The morning cuckoo from the green carpet wakes me up.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بزم ہستی میں ہے سب کو محفل آرائی پسند
ہے دل شاعر کو لیکن کنج تنہائی پسند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        کنج: کونہ، گوشہ۔ 
Everyone in the world assemblage social life likes the poet's heart but the solitude's corner likes.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے جنوں مجھ کو کہ گھبراتا ہوں آبادی میں میں
ڈھونڈتا پھرتا ہوں کس کو کوہ کی وادی میں میں؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I am verged on lunacy by being perturbed in habitations, for whom I am searching, roaming in the mountain valleys?\
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شوق کس کا سبزہ زاروں میں پھراتا ہے مجھے
اور چشموں کے کنارے پر سلاتا ہے مجھے؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Whose love makes me roam in the meadows? And makes me sleep on the spring's banks?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="31">
      <Text Language="Original">
        طعنہ زن ہے تو کہ شیدا کنج عزلت کا ہوں میں
دیکھ اے غافل! پیامی بزم قدرت کا ہوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You taunt me that fond of the corner of retirement I am. Look O imprudent one! Messenger of Nature's assembly I am.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہم وطن شمشاد کا، قمری کا میں ہم راز ہوں
اس چمن کی خامشی میں گوش بر آواز ہوں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        گوش بر آواز: آواز پر کان لگائے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Compatriot of the elms, turtle dove's confidante I am! In this garden's silence in the state of anxiety I am!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="35">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کچھ جو سنتا ہوں تو اوروں کو سنانے کے لیے
دیکھتا ہوں کچھ تو اوروں کو دکھانے کے لیے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If I do hear something it is only to tell others. If I do see something it is only to show others.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="37">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عاشق عزلت ہے دل، نازاں ہوں اپنے گھر پہ میں
خندہ زن ہوں مسند دارا و اسکندر پہ میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        عاشق عزلت ميں: تنہائی کا عاشق۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My heart is a lover of retirement, proud of my home I am. Scoffing at the thrones of Dara and Sikandar I am.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="39">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لیٹنا زیر شجر رکھتا ہے جادو کا اثر
شام کے تارے پہ جب پڑتی ہو رہ رہ کر نظر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        How enchanting is the act of lying under the trees, as now and then my sight falls at the evening star.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="41">
      <Text Language="Original">
        علم کے حیرت کدے میں ہے کہاں اس کی نمود
گل کی پتی میں نظر آتا ہے راز ہست و بود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Where in the strange house of learning can this be seen! The secret of universe can only in the rose petal be seen.
(Translated by Dr. M.A.K. Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>