<Poem ID="16" Name="" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="04" SectionName="ظریفانہ">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دلیل مہر و وفا اس سے بڑھ کے کیا ہوگی 
نہ ہو حضور سے الفت تو یہ ستم نہ سہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What will be a better proof of affection and fidelity with no love for you how intolerable will this cruelty be.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مصر ہے حلقہ،کمیٹی میں کچھ کہیں ہم بھی 
مگر رضائے کلکٹر کو بھانپ لیں تو کہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مصر: بضد، اسرار کرنے والا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Insistence is that in the ward committee I should also speak, but I shall speak after guessing if the Collector agreeable with me will be.
(Collector – also known as Deputy Commissioner – is the highest administrative officer at the district level in the Indian sub-continent. He was so powerful during the British rule that the service to which he belonged was said to be the ‘steel frame of the British Empire’. This verse is sarcasm on the state of affairs in which nothing could happen in the district without the implicit or explicit concurrence of the Collector.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سند تو لیجیے، لڑکوں کے کام آئے گی 
وہ مہربان ہیں اب، پھر رہیں، رہیں نہ رہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Obtain the testimonial, it will be of use for sons; he is favorable now, later he may or may not be.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زمین پر تو نہیں ہندیوں کو جا ملتی 
مگر جہاں میں ہیں خالی سمندروں کی تہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Indians cannot find a place on the earth, but the oceans’ bottom available may be.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مثال کشتی بے حس مطیع فرماں ہیں 
کہو تو بستہ ساحل رہیں، کہو تو بہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کشتي بے حسي: بے حس کشتی۔ 
مطيع فرماں: فرمانبردار ۔
بستہ ساحل: ساحل سے چمٹے رہنا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Like the insensitive boat we are subservient to orders; we are bound to the bank or float as your desire may be. 
(Translated by M.A.K. Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>