<Poem ID="26" Name="حضور رسالت مآب میں" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گراں جو مجھ پہ یہ ہنگامہ زمانہ ہوا 
جہاں سے باندھ کے رخت سفر روانہ ہوا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        IN AUDIENCE WITH THE HOLY PROPHET S.A.W.
When I felt this ignoble strife of the world grievous; packing up my goods and chattel I departed from the world.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        قیود شام وسحر میں بسر تو کی لیکن 
نظام کہنہ عالم سے آشنا نہ ہوا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Though I did pass life within limits of morning and evening; I never got acquainted with the old system of the world.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فرشتے بزم رسالت میں لے گئے مجھ کو 
حضور آیہ رحمت میں لے گئے مجھ کو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The angles took me to the assembly of the Holy Prophet (S.A.W.): They took me to the audience of the symbol of God’s Mercy.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کہا حضور نے، اے عندلیب باغ حجاز! 
کلی کلی ہے تری گرمی نوا سے گداز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Holy Prophet said ‘O nightingale of the garden of Hijaz! Each flower-bud of yours is melted with your music’s warmth.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہمیشہ سرخوش جام ولا ہے دل تیرا 
فتادگی ہے تری غیرت سجود نیاز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your heart is always ecstatic with the wine-cup of God’s proximity; your supplication is the envy of prostrations in Divine Love.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اڑا جو پستی دنیا سے تو سوئے گردوں 
سکھائی تجھ کو ملائک نے رفعت پرواز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In your flight from the lowly world to the celestial world; the angels taught you the elegance of the flight.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نکل کے باغ جہاں سے برنگ بو آیا 
ہمارے واسطے کیا تحفہ لے کے تو آیا؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You have come like fragrance out of the world’s garden with what gift for me have come you?’
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حضور! دہر میں آسودگی نہیں ملتی 
تلاش جس کی ہے وہ زندگی نہیں ملتی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ‘Sir! Satisfaction on the earth is not available; the life I am searching for is not available.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہزاروں لالہ و گل ہیں ریاض ہستی میں 
وفا کی جس میں ہو بو' وہ کلی نہیں ملتی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Thousands of tulips and roses exist in the garden of existence; the flower-bud with the fragrance of fidelity is not available.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مگر میں نذر کو اک آبگینہ لایا ہوں 
جو چیز اس میں ہے' جنت میں بھی نہیں ملتی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        But I have brought a lover’s wine-glass as an offering; whatever is in this even in paradise is not available.
(This verse and the next one refer to Allamah Iqbal’s entire poetic works.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جھلکتی ہے تری امت کی آبرو اس میں 
طرابلس کے شہیدوں کا ہے لہو اس میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Glistens your Ummah’s honour in this; blood of Tripoli’s martyrs is in this.’
[Translated by Dr M A K Khalil]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>