<Poem ID="09" Name="بچے کی دعا" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="1a" SectionName="حصہ اول">
  <Para>
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لب پہ آتی ہے دعا بن کے تمنا میری
زندگی شمع کی صورت ہو خدایا میری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE CHILD'S INVOCATION
My longing comes to my lips as supplication of mine. O God! May like the candle be the life of mine!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دور دنیا کا مرے دم سے اندھیرا ہو جائے
ہر جگہ میرے چمکنے سے اجالا ہو جائے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        May the world's darkness disappear through the life of mine! May every place light up with the sparkling light of mine!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہو مرے دم سے یونہی میرے وطن کی زینت
جس طرح پھول سے ہوتی ہے چمن کی زینت
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        May my homeland through me attain elegance as the garden through flowers attains elegance.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زندگی ہو مری پروانے کی صورت یا رب
علم کی شمع سے ہو مجھ کو محبت یا رب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        May my life like that of the moth be, O Lord! May I love the lamp of knowledge, O Lord!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہو مرا کام غریبوں کی حمایت کرنا
دردمندوں سے ضعیفوں سے محبت کرنا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        May supportive of the poor my life's way be! May loving the old, the suffering my way be!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مرے اللہ! برائی سے بچانا مجھ کو
نیک جو راہ ہو اس رہ پہ چلانا مجھ ک
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O God! Protect me from the evil ways; show me the path leading to the good ways!

The mention of Allamah’s poetical works for children is far from complete without the poems he wrote and recited in public gatherings organized for fund-raising for the orphans. The poet decided not to include those poems in any of the books published by him. These were ‘omitted’ for the reasons best known to Allamah; possibly it was because the poems were written for a specific purpose and he had seen that being fulfilled spontaneously to his entire satisfaction. 
[Translated by M.A.K.Khalil]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>