<Poem ID="08" Name="" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="1b" SectionName="غزلیات 1">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کہوں کیا آرزوئے بے دلی مجھ کو کہاں تک ہے
مرے بازار کی رونق ہی سودائے زیاں تک ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What should I say how much Longing for dejection I have? The elegance of my market is only up to the ardent desire for losing.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وہ مے کش ہوں فروغ مے سے خود گلزار بن جائوں
ہوائے گل فراق ساقی نامہرباں تک ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I am the sot who himself becomes garden by the Wine’s Light. Rose’s love is only up to the departure of the unkind cup bearer.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چمن افروز ہے صیاد میری خوشنوائی تک
رہی بجلی کی بے تابی، سو میرے آشیاں تک ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Hunter’s enhancement of garden’s beauty is till start of my melodies; as for the thunderbolts’ restlessness, it is up to my nest.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وہ مشت خاک ہوں، فیض پریشانی سے صحرا ہوں
نہ پوچھو میری وسعت کی، زمیں سے آ سماں تک ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I am that handful of dust, which is changed to wilderness by distress’ grace. Do not ask me of my span; it is from the earth to the sky.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جرس ہوں، نالہ خوابیدہ ہے میرے ہر رگ و پے میں
یہ خاموشی مری وقت رحیل کارواں تک ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I am the bell, complaint is asleep in my whole nature; the silence of mine only is up to the caravan’s departure.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سکون دل سے سامان کشود کار پیدا کر
کہ عقدہ خاطر گرداب کا آب رواں تک ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        With a tranquil heart create means of attaining your aims, because the whirlpool’s knot is only up to the water’s flow.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چمن زار محبت میں خموشی موت ہے بلبل!
یہاں کی زندگی پابندی رسم فغاں تک ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Silence is death in the garden of Love, O nightingale this life is only up to observance of the wailing’s custom.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جوانی ہے تو ذوق دید بھی، لطف تمنا بھی
ہمارے گھر کی آبادی قیام میہماں تک ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In youth, there is Sight’s zeal as well as Longing’s pleasure. The happiness of our house is only up to the guest’s presence.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زمانے بھر میں رسوا ہوں مگر اے وائے نادانی!
سمجھتا ہوں کہ میرا عشق میرے رازداں تک ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Disgraced though I am in the whole world but, O ignorance; I understand that my Love is known only to my confidante.
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>