<Poem ID="25" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="02" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نگاہ فقر میں شان سکندری کیا ہے 
خراج کی جو گدا ہو، وہ قیصری کیا ہے!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The splendour of a monarch great is worthless for the free and bold: Where lies the grandeur of a king, whose riches rest on borrowed gold?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بتوں سے تجھ کو امیدیں، خدا سے نومیدی 
مجھے بتا تو سہی اور کافری کیا ہے!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You pin your faith on idols vain and turn your back on Mighty God: If this is not unbelief and sin, what else is unbelief and fraud?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فلک نے ان کو عطا کی ہے خواجگی کہ جنھیں 
خبر نہیں روش بندہ پروری کیا ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Luck favours the fool and the mean, and exalts and lifts to the skies: Only those who are base and low and know not how to patronize.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فقط نگاہ سے ہوتا ہے فیصلہ دل کا 
نہ ہو نگاہ میں شوخی تو دلبری کیا ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        One look from the eyes of the Fair can make a conquest of the heart: There is no charm in the fair sweet, if it lacks this alluring art.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اسی خطا سے عتاب ملوک ہے مجھ پر 
کہ جانتا ہوں مآل سکندری کیا ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I am a target for the hate of the mighty rich and the great, as I know the end of Caesars great and know the freaks of luck or fate.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کسے نہیں ہے تمنائے سروری، لیکن 
خودی کی موت ہو جس میں وہ سروری کیا ہے!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        To be a person great and strong is the end and aim of all; but that rank is not real and true that is attained by the ego’s fall.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خوش آگئی ہے جہاں کو قلندری میری 
وگرنہ شعر مرا کیا ہے، شاعری کیا ہے!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My bold and simple mode of life has captured each and every heart; though my numbers are lame and dull and lay no claim to poet’s art.
(Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>