<Poem ID="02" Name="مسجد قرطبہ" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="04" SectionName="منظومات">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سلسلہ روز و شب، نقش گر حادثات 
سلسلہ روز و شب، اصل حیات و ممات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        نقش گر حادثات: واقعات کے ہونے کا باعث۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        MOSQUE OF CORDOBA
The succession of day and night is the architect of events. The succession of day and night is the fountain-head of life and death.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سلسلہ روز و شب، تار حریر دو رنگ 
جس سے بناتی ہے ذات اپنی قبائے صفات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        قبا: لباس۔. حرير: ریشم ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The succession of day and night is a two-tone silken twine. With which the Divine Essence, prepares its apparel of Attributes.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سلسلہ روز و شب، ساز ازل کی فغاں 
جس سے دکھاتی ہے ذات زیروبم ممکنات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The succession of day and night is the reverberation of the symphony of Creation. Through its modulations, the Infinite demonstrates the parameters of possibilities.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تجھ کو پرکھتا ہے یہ، مجھ کو پرکھتا ہے یہ 
سلسلہ روز و شب، صیرفی کائنات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        صيرفي: صراف کی جمع ؛ صراف یعنی پرکھنے والا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Now sitting in judgement on you; now setting a value on me. The succession of day and night is the touchstone of the universe; (one who sifts pure from the impure).
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تو ہو اگر کم عیار، میں ہوں اگر کم عیار 
موت ہے تیری برات، موت ہے میری برات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        But what if you are found wanting; what if I am found wanting. Death is your ultimate destiny; death is my ultimate destiny.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تیرے شب وروز کی اور حقیقت ہے کیا 
ایک زمانے کی رو جس میں نہ دن ہے نہ رات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What else is the reality of your days and nights? Besides a surge in the river of time; sans day, sans night.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آنی و فانی تمام معجزہ ہائے ہنر 
کار جہاں بے ثبات، کار جہاں بے ثبات!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Frail and evanescent, all miracles of ingenuity; transient, all temporal attainments, ephemeral, all worldly accomplishments.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اول و آخر فنا، باطن و ظاہر فنا 
نقش کہن ہو کہ نو، منزل آخر فنا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Annihilation is the end of all beginnings; annihilation is the end of all ends. Extinction is the fate of everything; hidden or manifest, old or new.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے مگر اس نقش میں رنگ ثبات دوام 
جس کو کیا ہو کسی مرد خدا نے تمام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Yet in this very scenario indelible is the stamp of permanence’ on the deeds of the good and godly.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مرد خدا کا عمل عشق سے صاحب فروغ 
عشق ہے اصل حیات، موت ہے اس پر حرام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Deeds of the godly radiate with Love; the essence of life, which death is forbidden to touch.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تند و سبک سیر ہے گرچہ زمانے کی رو 
عشق خود اک سیل ہے، سیل کو لیتاہے تھام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        سيل: سیلاب۔ 	 تند و سبک: تیز اور بے آواز۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Fast and free flows the tide of time, but Love itself is a tide that stems all tides.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عشق کی تقویم میں عصررواں کے سوا 
اور زمانے بھی ہیں جن کا نہیں کوئی نام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        عصررواں: زمانہ جو جاری ہو۔ تقويم: جنتری، کلینڈر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In the chronicle of Love there are times other than the past, the present and the future; times for which no names have yet been coined.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عشق دم جبرئیل، عشق دل مصطفی 
عشق خدا کا رسول، عشق خدا کا کلام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Love is the breath of Jibril. Love is the heart of Holy Prophet (PBUH).
Love is the messenger of God. Love is the Word of God.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عشق کی مستی سے ہے پیکر گل تابناک 
عشق ہے صہبائے خام، عشق ہے کاس الکرام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        پيکر گل: مٹی کا بت، انسان۔ 
صہبائے خام: وہ شراب جس میں کوئی چیز ملی نہ ہو، خالص۔ 
کاس الکرام: اہل کرم کا پیالہ جس سے دوسروں کو بھی حصّہ ملے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Love is ecstasy lends luster to earthly forms. Love is the heady wine, Love is the grand goblet.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عشق فقیہ حرم، عشق امیر جنود 
عشق ہے ابن السبیل، اس کے ہزاروں مقام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ابن السبيل: مسافر جنود: فوجیں، لشکر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Love is the commander of marching troops, Love is a wayfarer with many a way-side abode.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="31">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عشق کے مضراب سے نغمہ تار حیات 
عشق سے نور حیات، عشق سے نار حیات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Love is the plectrum that brings music to the string of life. Love is the light of life, Love is the fire of life.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے حرم قرطبہ! عشق سے تیرا وجود 
عشق سراپا دوام، جس میں نہیں رفت و بود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        رفت و بود: گیا اور تھا یعنی فنا ہو جانا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        To Love, you owe your being, O, Haram of Cordoba; to Love, that is eternal; never waning, never fading.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="35">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رنگ ہو یا خشت و سنگ، چنگ ہو یا حرف و صوت 
معجزہ فن کی ہے خون جگر سے نمود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        خشت و سنگ: اینٹ اور پتّھر
چنگ: مونہہ سے بجایا جانے والا آلہء موسیقی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Just the media these pigments, bricks and stones; this harp, these words and sounds, just the media. The miracle of art springs from the lifeblood of the artist!
(Chung: Musical instrument that is played with mouth.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="37">
      <Text Language="Original">
        قطرہ خون جگر، سل کو بناتا ہے دل 
خون جگر سے صدا سوز و سرور و سرود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        سل: پتّھر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A droplet of the lifeblood transforms a piece of dead rock into a living heart; An impressive sound, into a song of solicitude, A refrain of rapture or a melody of mirth.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="39">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تیری فضا دل فروز، میری نوا سینہ سوز 
تجھ سے دلوں کا حضور، مجھ سے دلوں کی کشود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        دلوں کي کشود: دلوں کا کھل جانا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The aura you exude, illumines the heart. My plaint kindles the soul. You draw the hearts to the Presence Divine, I inspire them to bloom and blossom.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="41">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عرش معلی سے کم سینہ آدم نہیں 
گرچہ کف خاک کی حد ہے سپہر کبود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کف خاک: مٹھی بھر خاک - انسان۔
سپہر کبود: نیلا آسمان۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        No less exalted than the Exalted Throne; is the throne of the heart, the human breast! Despite the limit of azure skies; ordained for this handful of dust.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="43">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پیکر نوری کو ہے سجدہ میسر تو کیا 
اس کو میسر نہیں سوز و گداز سجود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        پيکر نوري: نورانی وجود یعنی فرشتے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Celestial beings, born of light; do have the privilege of supplication, but unknown to them are the verve and warmth of prostration.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="45">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کافر ہندی ہوں میں، دیکھ مرا ذوق و شوق 
دل میں صلوہ و درود، لب پہ صلوہ و درود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        An Indian infidel, perchance, am I; but look at my fervour, my ardour. ‘Blessings and peace upon the Prophet,’ sings my heart. ‘Blessings and peace upon the Prophet,’ echo my lips.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="47">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شوق مری لے میں ہے، شوق مری نے میں ہے 
نغمہ 'اللہ ھو' میرے رگ و پے میں ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My song is the song of aspiration. My lute is the serenade of longing. Every fibre of my being resonates with the refrains of Allah hoo!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="49">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تیرا جلال و جمال، مرد خدا کی دلیل 
وہ بھی جلیل و جمیل، تو بھی جلیل و جمیل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your beauty, your majesty, personify the graces of the man of faith. You are beautiful and majestic. He too is beautiful and majestic.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="51">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تیری بنا پائدار، تیرے ستوں بے شمار 
شام کے صحرا میں ہو جیسے ہجوم نخیل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ہجوم نخيل: کھجور کے درختوں کا جھنڈ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your foundations are lasting, your columns countless; like the profusion of palms in the plains of Syria.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="53">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تیرے در و بام پر وادی ایمن کا نور 
تیرا منار بلند جلوہ گہ جبرئیل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your arches, your terraces, shimmer with the light that once flashed in the Valley of Aiman. Your soaring minaret, all aglow in the resplendence of Jibril’s glory.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="55">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مٹ نہیں سکتا کبھی مرد مسلماں کہ ہے 
اس کی اذانوں سے فاش سر کلیم و خلیل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Muslim is destined to last as his Azan holds the key to the mysteries of the perennial message of Abraham and Moses.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="57">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اس کی زمیں بے حدود، اس کا افق بے ثغور 
اس کے سمندر کی موج، دجلہ و دنیوب و نیل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ثغور: (ثغر کی جمع) سرحدوں کے بغیر بے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        His world knows no boundaries, his horizon, no frontiers. Tigris, Danube and Nile: Billows of his oceanic expanse.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="59">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اس کے زمانے عجیب، اس کے فسانے غریب 
عہد کہن کو دیا اس نے پیام رحیل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        رحيل: کوچ –سفر کا آغاز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Fabulous, have been his times! Fascinating, the accounts of his achievements! He it was, who bade the final adieu to the outworn order.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="61">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ساقی ارباب ذوق، فارس میدان شوق 
بادہ ہے اس کا رحیق، تیغ ہے اس کی اصیل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        رحيق: خالص اور صاف شراب۔ فارس: شہسوار۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A cup-bearer is he; with the purest wine for the connoisseur; a cavalier in the path of Love with a sword of the finest steel.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="63">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مرد سپاہی ہے وہ اس کی زرہ 'لا الہ' 
سایہ شمشیر میں اس کہ پنہ 'لا الہ'
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A combatant, with 'La Ilah' as his coat of mail. Under the shadow of flashing scimitars, 'La Ilah' is his protection.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="65">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تجھ سے ہوا آشکار بندہ مومن کا راز 
اس کے دنوں کی تپش، اس کی شبوں کا گداز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your edifice unravels the mystery of the faithful; The fire of his fervent days, the bliss of his tender nights.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="67">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اس کا مقام بلند، اس کا خیال عظیم 
اس کا سرور اس کا شوق، اس کا نیاز اس کا ناز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your grandeur calls to mind the loftiness of his station, the sweep of his vision; his rapture, his ardour, his pride, his humility.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="69">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہاتھ ہے اللہ کا بندئہ مومن کا ہاتھ 
غالب و کار آفریں، کارکشا، کارساز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The might of the man of faith is the might of the Almighty: Dominant, creative, resourceful, consummate.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="71">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خاکی و نوری نہاد، بندہ مولا صفات 
ہر دو جہاں سے غنی اس کا دل بے نیاز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        نوري نہاد: جس کی فطرت نوری ہو – فرشتہ صفت۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He is terrestrial with celestial aspect; a being with the qualities of the Creator. His contented self has no demands on this world or the other.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="73">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اس کی امیدیں قلیل، اس کے مقاصد جلیل 
اس کی ادا دل فریب، اس کی نگہ دل نواز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        His desires are modest; his aims exalted; his manner charming; his ways winsome.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="75">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نرم دم گفتگو، گرم دم جستجو 
رزم ہو یا بزم ہو، پاک دل و پاک باز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Soft in social exposure, tough in the line of pursuit. But whether in fray or in social gathering; ever chaste at heart, ever clean in conduct.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="77">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نقطہ پرکار حق، مرد خدا کا یقیں 
اور یہ عالم تمام وہم و طلسم و مجاز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In the celestial order of the macrocosm, his immutable faith is the centre of the Divine Compass. All else: illusion, sorcery, fallacy.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="79">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عقل کی منزل ہے وہ، عشق کا حاصل ہے وہ 
حلقہ آفاق میں گرمی محفل ہے وہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He is the journey’s end for reason, he is the raison d ’etre of Love. An inspiration in the cosmic communion.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="81">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کعبہ ارباب فن! سطوت دین مبیں 
تجھ سے حرم مرتبت اندلسیوں کی زمیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        دين مبيں: روشن دین یعنی اسلام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O, Mecca of art lovers! You are the majesty of the true tenet. You have elevated Andalusia to the eminence of the holy Harem.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="83">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے تہ گردوں اگر حسن میں تیری نظیر 
قلب مسلماں میں ہے، اور نہیں ہے کہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your equal in beauty, if any under the skies; is the heart of the Muslim and no one else.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="85">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آہ وہ مردان حق! وہ عربی شہسوار 
حامل ' خلق عظیم'، صاحب صدق و یقیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        خلق عظيم: اشارہ ہے خلق عظيم کے مالک حضرت محمد (صلعم) کی طرف۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Ah, those men of truth, those proud cavaliers of Arabia; endowed with a sublime character, imbued with candour and conviction.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="87">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جن کی حکومت سے ہے فاش یہ رمز غریب 
سلطنت اہل دل فقر ہے، شاہی نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        رمز غريب: نادر نکتہ، عجیب بھید۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Their reign gave the world an unfamiliar concept; that the authority of the brave and spirited lay in modesty and simplicity, rather than pomp and regality.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="89">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جن کی نگاہوں نے کی تربیت شرق و غرب 
ظلمت یورپ میں تھی جن کی خرد راہ بیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Their sagacity guided the East and the West. In the dark ages of Europe, it was the light of their vision that lit up the tracks.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="91">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جن کے لہو کے طفیل آج بھی ہیں اندلسی 
خوش دل و گرم اختلاط، سادہ و روشن جبیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        گرم اختلاط: میل جول میں پر تپاک۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A tribute to their blood it is, that the Andalusians, even today, are effable and warm-hearted, ingenuous and bright of countenance.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="93">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آج بھی اس دیس میں عام ہے چشم غزال 
اور نگاہوں کے تیر آج بھی ہیں دل نشیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Even today in this land, eyes like those of gazelles are a common sight. And darts shooting out of those eyes, even today, are on target.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="95">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بوئے یمن آج بھی اس کی ہواوں میں ہے 
رنگ حجاز آج بھی اس کی نواوں میں ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Its breeze, even today, is laden with the fragrance of Yemen. Its music, even today, carries strains of melodies from Hijaz.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="97">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دیدہ انجم میں ہے تیری زمیں، آسماں 
آہ کہ صدیوں سے ہے تیری فضا بے اذاں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Stars look upon your precincts as a piece of heaven. But for centuries, alas! Your porticoes have not resonated with the call of the muezzin.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="99">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کون سی وادی میں ہے، کون سی منزل میں ہے 
عشق بلا خیز کا قافلہ سخت جاں!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What distant valley, what way-side abode is holding back? That valiant caravan of rampant Love.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="101">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دیکھ چکا المنی، شورش اصلاح دیں 
جس نے نہ چھوڑے کہیں نقش کہن کے نشاں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        المني: جرمنی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Germany witnessed the upheaval of religious reforms; that left no trace of the old perspective.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="103">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حرف غلط بن گئی عصمت پیر کنشت 
اور ہوئی فکر کی کشتی نازک رواں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        پير کنشت: کلیسا کا سب سے بڑا بزرگ - پوپ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Infallibility of the church sage began to ring false. Reason, once more, unfurled its sails.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="105">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چشم فرانسیس بھی دیکھ چکی انقلاب 
جس سے دگرگوں ہوا مغربیوں کا جہاں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        France too went through its revolution; that changed the entire orientation of Western life.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="107">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ملت رومی نژاد کہنہ پرستی سے پیر 
لذت تجدید سے وہ بھی ہوئی پھر جواں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ملت: مراد ہے اہل اٹلی ۔ رومي نژاد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Followers of Rome, feeling antiquated worshipping the ancientry, also rejuvenated themselves with the relish of novelty.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="109">
      <Text Language="Original">
        روح مسلماں میں ہے آج وہی اضطراب 
راز خدائی ہے یہ، کہہ نہیں سکتی زباں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The same storm is raging today in the soul of the Muslim. A Divine secret it is; not for the lips to utter.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="111">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دیکھیے اس بحر کی تہ سے اچھلتا ہے کیا 
گنبد نیلو فری رنگ بدلتا ہے کیا!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        گنبد: آسمان۔ نيلو فري
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Let us see what surfaces from the depths of the deep. Let us see what colour, the blue sky changes into.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="113">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وادی کہسار میں غرق شفق ہے سحاب 
لعل بدخشاں کے ڈھیر چھوڑ گیا آفتاب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        حاب: بادل ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Clouds in the yonder valley are drenched in roseate twilight. The parting sun has left behind mounds and mounds of rubies, the best from Badakhshan.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="115">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سادہ و پرسوز ہے دختر دہقاں کا گیت 
کشتی دل کے لیے سیل ہے عہد شباب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Simple and doleful is the song of the peasant’s daughter: Tender feelings adrift in the tide of youth.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="117">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آب روان کبیر! تیرے کنارے کوئی 
دیکھ رہا ہے کسی اور زمانے کا خواب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        آب روان کبير: وادی الکبیر اندلس کا مشہور دریا جس کے دونوں کناروں پر قرطبہ آباد ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O, the ever-flowing waters of Guadalquivir! Someone on your banks is seeing a vision of some other period of time. (Guadalquivir: The well-known river of Cordoba, near which the Mosque is located.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="119">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عالم نو ہے ابھی پردہ تقدیر میں 
میری نگاہوں میں ہے اس کی سحر بے حجاب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Tomorrow is still in the curtain of intention, but its dawn is flashing before my mind’s eye.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="121">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پردہ اٹھا دوں اگر چہرئہ افکار سے 
لا نہ سکے گا فرنگ میری نواوں کی تاب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Were I to lift the veil from the profile of my reflections, The West would be dazzled by its brilliance.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="123">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جس میں نہ ہو انقلاب، موت ہے وہ زندگی 
روح امم کی حیات کشمکش انقلاب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Life without change is death. The tumult and turmoil of revolution, keep the soul of a nation alive.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="125">
      <Text Language="Original">
        صورت شمشیر ہے دست قضا میں وہ قوم 
کرتی ہے جو ہر زماں اپنے عمل کا حساب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Keen, as a sword in the hands of Destiny: Is the nation that evaluates its actions at each step.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="127">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نقش ہیں سب ناتمام خون جگر کے بغیر 
نغمہ ہے سودائے خام خون جگر کے بغیر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Incomplete are all creations without the lifeblood of the creator. Soulless is the melody without the lifeblood of the maestro. 
(Translated by Naeem Siddiqui)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>