<Poem ID="18" Name="لالہ صحرا" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="04" SectionName="منظومات">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ گنبد مینائی، یہ عالم تنہائی 
مجھ کو تو ڈراتی ہے اس دشت کی پہنائی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        POPPY OF THE WILDERNESS
Oh blue sky-dome, oh world companionless! Fear comes on me in this wide desolation.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بھٹکا ہوا راہی میں، بھٹکا ہوا راہی تو 
منزل ہے کہاں تیری اے لالہء صحرائی!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Lost travelers, you and I; what destination is yours, bright poppy of the wilderness?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خالی ہے کلیموں سے یہ کوہ و کمر ورنہ 
تو شعلہء سینائی، میں شعلہء سینائی!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        No prophet walks these hills, or we might be; twin Sinai-flames; you bloom on Heaven’s spray.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تو شاخ سے کیوں پھوٹا، میں شاخ سے کیوں ٹوٹا 
اک جذبہء پیدائی، اک لذت یکتائی!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        For the same cause I tore myself away: To unfold; to be our selves, our wills agree.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        غواص محبت کا اللہ نگہباں ہو 
ہر قطرئہ دریا میں دریا کی ہے گہرائی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        On the diver of Love’s pearl-bank be God’s hand: In every ocean-drop all ocean’s deeps!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اس موج کے ماتم میں روتی ہے بھنور کی آنکھ 
دریا سے اٹھی لیکن ساحل سے نہ ٹکرائی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The whirlpool mourning for its lost wave weeps, born of the sea and never to reach the land.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے گرمی آدم سے ہنگامہء عالم گرم 
سورج بھی تماشائی، تارے بھی تماشائی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Man’s hot blood makes earth’s fevered pulses race, with stars and sun for audience.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے باد بیابانی! مجھ کو بھی عنایت ہو 
خاموشی و دل سوزی، سرمستی و رعنائی!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Oh cool air of the desert! Let it be mine too to share in silence and heart’s glow, rapture and grace.
[Translated by V.G. Kiernan]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>