<Poem ID="01" Name="بلاد اسلامیہ" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سرزمیں دلی کی مسجود دل غم دیدہ ہے 
ذرے ذرے میں لہو اسلاف کا خوابیدہ ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE ISLAMIC CITIES
The region of Delhi is adored by my grieved heart; in every speck of it the ancestors’ blood is asleep.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پاک اس اجڑے گلستاں کی نہ ہو کیونکر زمیں 
خانقاہ عظمت اسلام ہے یہ سرزمیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Why should not the land of this desolate garden be holy? This region is the shrine of the grandeur of Islam.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سوتے ہیں اس خاک میں خیر الامم کے تاجدار 
نظم عالم کا رہا جن کی حکومت پر مدار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        خير الامم: امتوں میں سب سے بہتر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Kings of the Khair al-Umam are asleep in this land; dependent on whose rule remained the world order.
(Khair al-Umam: The title of the Muslim Ummah as is conferred on them by the Holy Qur’an 3:110.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دل کو تڑپاتی ہے اب تک گرمی محفل کی یاد 
جل چکا حاصل مگر محفوظ ہے حاصل کی یاد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Memory of assembly’s warmth still renders the heart restless; the splendor has been burnt but memory of the splendor is still secure.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے زیارت گاہ مسلم گو جہان آباد بھی 
اس کرامت کا مگر حق دار ہے بغداد بھی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کرامت: بزرگی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Though Jahanabad also is a shrine for the Muslim; Baghdad as well is deserving of this magnificence.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ چمن وہ ہے کہ تھا جس کے لیے سامان ناز 
لالہ صحرا جسے کہتے ہیں تہذیب حجاز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This is the garden the source of whose pride was; the wild tulip which was called the culture of Hijaz.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خاک اس بستی کی ہو کیونکر نہ ہمدوش ارم 
جس نے دیکھے جانشینان پیمبر کے قدم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ہمدوش ارم: بہشت کی ہم پلّہ۔ (ارم: شدّاد کی بنائی ہوئی بہشت۔)
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Why should not the dust of this habitation be equivalent to Iram; which witnessed the footsteps of the Prophet’s successors.
(Iram: This was a famous garden in Yemen, established on the model of Paradise by Shaddad, an ancient king. This word is also used for Paradise.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جس کے غنچے تھے چمن ساماں، وہ گلشن ہے یہی 
کاپنتا تھا جن سے روما، ان کا مدفن ہے یہی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        چمن ساماں: باغ کا ساز و سامان رکھنے والا یعنی باغ کے برابر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The garden whose flower buds were the garden’s wealth is this. The graveyard of those who made Rome tremble is this.
(Allusion to the struggle of the Muslim mujahids whose struggle in the cause of God and Islam shook up and ultimately destroyed the Eastern or the Byzantine part of the Roman Empire.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے زمین قرطبہ بھی دیدہء مسلم کا نور 
ظلمت مغرب میں جو روشن تھی مثل شمع طور
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The land of Qurtubah also is the light of the Muslim’s eye; which shined in Europe’s darkness like the candle of Toor.
(Qurtubah: (Cordova) This important city in north-central Spain was the capital of the Muslim Khilafah in Andalus (Spain) for about three centuries from the middle of the eighth to the middle of the eleventh centuries. During this period its contribution to the strength of the Muslims and Islam in Spain as well as its rich and intellectual culture is famous… Allusion is to the leading role of Qurtubah in the spread of knowledge in Europe.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بجھ کے بزم ملت بیضا پریشاں کر گئی 
اور دیا تہذیب حاضر کا فروزاں کر گئی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        فروزاں: روشن۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Extinguishing of this lamp dispersed the assembly of Millat-i-Baidha and lighted the lamp of the present day’s materialistic civilization.
(Millat-i-Baidha: It means ‘the nation like the illuminated egg’, which comes from the bright egg-shaped mark on the palm of Mosa A.S. Conferred by God at Mount Toor (The Holy Qur’an 27:12). ‘Allamah Iqbal has frequently used this name for the Muslim Ummah.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        قبر اس تہذیب کی یہ سر زمین پاک ہے 
جس سے تاک گلشن یورپ کی رگ نم ناک ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تاک: انگور۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This holy region is the grave of that civilization with which the life blood still exists in the veins of Europe’s vines.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خطہ قسطنطنیہ یعنی قیصر کا دیار 
مہدی امت کی سطوت کا نشان پائدار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مہدي امت: ملّت کو ہدایت کرنے والا۔ 
سطوت: شان و شکوہ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The tract of Constantinople that is the Caesar’s city; the perpetual banner of the grandeur of the Ummah’s Mahdi.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        صورت خاک حرم یہ سر زمیں بھی پاک ہے 
آستان مسند آرائے شہ لولاک ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        شہ لولاک: محمد (صلعم ) کے القاب میں سے ایک لقب۔
(اشارہ ہے اس کہاوت کی طرف جس میں کہا گیا ہے کہ اے محمد (صلعم) اگر آپ نہ ہوتے تو میں آسمان پیدا نہ کرتا۔ اسے حدیث سمجھا جاتا ہے جو مستند نہیں)
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Like the Haram’s dust this region is also holy; it is the shrine of descendants of Shah-i-Lawlak.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نکہت گل کی طرح پاکیزہ ہے اس کی ہوا 
تربت ایوب انصاری سے آتی ہے صدا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Its breeze is holy like the fragrance of rose; a voice is calling from the tomb of Ayyub Ansari (R.A.). (Eminent companion of the Holy Prophet S.A.W, who was martyred in a battle for the conquest of Constantinople during the Khilafah of Mu`awiyah R.A.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے مسلماں! ملت اسلام کا دل ہے یہ شہر 
سینکڑوں صدیوں کی کشت و خوں کا حاصل ہے یہ شہر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O Muslim! This city is the heart of the Nation of Islam! This city is the reward for millenniums of blood sacrifices!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="31">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وہ زمیں ہے تو مگر اے خواب گاہ مصطفی
دید ہے کعبے کو تیری حج اکبر سے سوا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        حج اکبر: حج دو قسم کے ہوتے ہیں ؛ عمرہ کو حج اصغر کہتے ہیں اور حج کو حج اکبر بھی کہتے ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        But you are that land, O the resting place of Mustafa (S.A.W.); even to the Ka`bah whose sight is better than Hajj-i-Akbar.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خاتم ہستی میں تو تاباں ہے مانند نگیں 
اپنی عظمت کی ولادت گاہ تھی تیری زمیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ولادت گاہ: پیدائش کی جگہ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In the world’s ring you are shining like a gem; your land was the birth place of our grandeur.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="35">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تجھ میں راحت اس شہنشاہ معظم کو ملی 
جس کے دامن میں اماں اقوام عالم کو ملی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        That Magnificent Emperor got rest in your midst; under whose protection the world nations got security.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="337">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نام لیوا جس کے شاہنشاہ عالم کے ہوئے
جانشیں قیصر کے، وارث مسند جم کے ہوئے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Whose successors became rulers of world’s empires, became successors of Caesar, inheritors of Jam’s throne.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="39">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے اگر قومیت اسلام پابند مقام 
ہند ہی بنیاد ہے اس کی، نہ فارس ہے، نہ شام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If the Muslim nationalism is restricted to place; neither India nor Persia nor Syria is its base.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="41">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آہ یثرب! دیس ہے مسلم کا تو، ماوا ہے تو
نقطہ جاذب تاثر کی شعاعوں کا ہے تو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ماوا: پناہ کی جگہ۔
نقطہ جاذب: وہ نقطہ جس کی طرف ہر شے کھچی آئے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Ah Yathrib! You are the Muslim’s homeland and his shelter; you are the focal point of the rays of his inner feelings.
(Yathrib: The original name of Madinah Munawwarah which is also used as an alternate name.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="43">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جب تلک باقی ہے تو دنیا میں، باقی ہم بھی ہیں 
صبح ہے تو اس چمن میں گوہر شبنم بھی ہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        As long as you exist, we will also flourish in the world; you are the morning of this garden we are the dew’s pearls.
(This is a beautiful metaphor of the morning and its beauty created by the morning’s dew whose droplets shine like pearls. Just as the morning dew lends beauty to the morning, Muslims added beauty to the world (metaphor of a garden used) by shining like dew drops.)
[Translated by Dr M A K Khalil]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>