<Poem ID="19" Name="" BookID="04" BookName="ارمغانِ حجاز" SectionID="03" SectionName="ملا زادہ ضیغم لولا بے کشمیری کا بیاض">
  <Para>
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        غریب شہر ہوں میں، سن تو لے مری فریاد
کہ تیرے سینے میں بھی ہوں قیامتیں آباد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        To this poor man of town pay special heed, who craves great ferments for thy bosom’s feed.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مری نوائے غم آلود ہے متاع عزیز
جہاں میں عام نہیں دولت دل ناشاد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        نوائے غم آلود: غم سے بھری آواز۔ 
دل ناشاد: غمزدہ دل۔
متاع عزیز: قیمتی دولت۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My woeful tone thus, a great wealth to soul, a woeful heart’s wealth, not a common dole.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گلہ ہے مجھ کو زمانے کی کور ذوقی سے
سمجھتا ہے مری محنت کو محنت فرہاد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کور ذوقی: ذوق کا اندھا پن۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I have a right grievance on world’s taste blind, who took my love’s labour of Farhad’s kind.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        صدائے تیشہ کہ بر سنگ میخورد دگر است
خبر بگیر کہ آواز تیشہ و جگر است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        وہ آواز جو ہتھوڑے کے پتھر پر پڑنے سے نکلتی ہے اور ہے اور جو جگر پر پڑنے سے نکلتی ہے اور ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        On stone the axe sound, totally apart! Listen! That was sound of axe and the heart! 
(Note the great depth of thought in this Persian couplet of Mirza Mazhar Jan Janan of Delhi which Iqbal has quoted here. With this axe Farhad wanted to dig a canal from a mountain of Persia to win his lady love who was a Princess of that land. In that labour (of love) his whole blood of heart and soul is involved.)
[Translated by Q A Kabir]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="صدائے تیشہ الخ یہ شعر مرزاجانجاناں مظہر علیہ الرحمتہ کے مشہور بیاض خریطہ جواہر، میں ہے" />
</Poem>