<Poem ID="41" Name="میں اور تو" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مذاق دید سے ناآشنا نظر ہے مری 
تری نگاہ ہے فطرت کی راز داں، پھر کیا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My eye is unacquainted with the taste for the Sight your eye is the knower of Nature’s secret, so what?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رہین شکوئہ ایام ہے زبان مری 
تری مراد پہ ہے دور آسماں، پھر کیا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My tongue is indebted to the complaint against time; the universe’s rotation depends on your will, so what?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رکھا مجھے چمن آوارہ مثل موج نسیم 
عطا فلک نے کیا تجھ کو آشیاں، پھر کیا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The sky kept me wandering in garden like the breeze’s current; the sky has bestowed the abode over you, so what?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فزوں ہے سود سے سرمایہء حیات ترا 
مرے نصیب میں ہے کاوش زیاں، پھر کیا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The wealth of your life is free of desire for gain in my heart is the anxiety of loss, so what?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہوا میں تیرتے پھرتے ہیں تیرے طیارے 
مرا جہاز ہے محروم بادباں، پھر کیا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your planes are flying about in the air my ship is devoid of the sail, so what?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        قوی شدیم چہ شد، ناتواں شدیم چہ شد 
چنیں شدیم چہ شد یا چناں شدیم چہ شد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        طاقتور ہوئے تو کیا ؟ کمزور ہوئے تو کیا؟ ایسے ہوئے تو کیا؟ ویسے ہوئے تو کیا؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I became strong, so what, I became weak, so what? This happened, so what, that happened, so what?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بہیچ گونہ دریں گلستاں قرارے نیست 
توگر بہار شدی، ما خزاں شدیم، چہ شد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس باغ میں یعنی دنیا میں کسی طور بھی قرار و قیام ممکن نہیں؛ تو بہار ہو گیا تو کیا؟ میں خزاں ہو گیا تو کیا؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Tranquillity does not exist to any extent in this rose-garden! If you became spring, and I became autumn, so what?
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>