<Poem ID="43" Name="نیا شوالا" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="1a" SectionName="حصہ اول">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سچ کہہ دوں اے برہمن! گر تو برا نہ مانے
تیرے صنم کدوں کے بت ہو گئے پرانے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        صنم کدہ: بت خانہ، مندر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        May I tell the truth O Brahman! If it does not displease you! The idols of your temple have become anachronistic.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اپنوں سے بیر رکھنا تو نے بتوں سے سیکھا
جنگ و جدل سکھایا واعظ کو بھی خدا نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You have learnt grudge with your own people from the idols; God also has taught fighting to Muslim preachers.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تنگ آ کے میں نے آخر دیر و حرم کو چھوڑا
واعظ کا وعظ چھوڑا، چھوڑے ترے فسانے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Becoming tired, I finally abandoned the temple and the Haram; I abandoned the preacher's sermons, as well as your stories.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پتھر کی مورتوں میں سمجھا ہے تو خدا ہے
خاک وطن کا مجھ کو ہر ذرہ دیوتا ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You take the stone idols to contain God; every speck of the homeland's dust is holy to me.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آ، غیریت کے پردے اک بار پھر اٹھا دیں
بچھڑوں کو پھر ملا دیں نقش دوئی مٹا دیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        غيريت: غیر ہونا، بیگانہ ہونا۔ 
نقش دوئي: دو ہونے کا نشان، جدائی، بیگانکی کا نقش۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Come! Let us again roll up the curtains of strangeness. Let us unite the separated ones, let us remove the disunion.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سونی پڑی ہوئی ہے مدت سے دل کی بستی
آ، اک نیا شوالا اس دیس میں بنا دیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The heart's habitation is lying barren since long. Let us build a new temple in this country.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دنیا کے تیرتھوں سے اونچا ہو اپنا تیرتھ
دامان آسماں سے اس کا کلس ملا دیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تيرتھ: ہندوؤں کا مقدس مقام۔ 
کلس: گنبد کے اوپر کی کلغی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Let our shrine be higher than the world's shrines. Let us make its spire as high as the sky.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہر صبح اٹھ کے گائیں منتر وہ مٹیھے مٹیھے
سارے پجاریوں کو مے پیت کی پلا دیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Let our morning's incantations be so sweet every morning that all worshipers be ecstatic with the Love's wine.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شکتی بھی شانتی بھی بھگتوں کے گیت میں ہے
دھرتی کے باسیوں کی مکتی پریت میں ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        شانتي: اطمینان، آرام۔
شکتي: طاقت، قوّت۔
باسي: بسنے والا، رہنے والا۔
پريت: محبت۔
مکتي: نجات۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The power and tranquillity is in the devotees' song. The salvation of the denizens of the earth is in Love
[Translated by Dr M A K Khalil]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>