<Poem ID="11" Name="" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="1b" SectionName="غزلیات 1">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کشادہ دست کرم جب وہ بے نیاز کرے
نیاز مند نہ کیوں عاجزی پہ ناز کرے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When that Beniaz opens His Graceful Hand: Why should the niazmand be not proud of his humility.
(The words Beniaz and Niazmand are difficult to translate. Literally, they mean ‘the one without need’ and ‘the needy’ respectively. They are attributes of God and Man respectively and are used for them. This verse describes the correct psychology of a real man of God, in that on account of the boundless Grace and Beneficence of God, the man who is a real devotee of Him would be proud of his being the needy one. It is so because it is only in this way that he would deserve the Grace of his Lord. The use of Beniaz and Niazmand in the same verse is a mark of literary elegance.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بٹھا کے عرش پہ رکھا ہے تو نے اے واعظ!
خدا وہ کیا ہے جو بندوں سے احتراز کرے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        احتراز: پرہیز۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You have confined Him to the Arsh, O preacher! What kind of God would keep away from His people? 
(God is Omni-present and transcends time and space. In that way He is close to His people. See the Holy Quran 2:186 and 50:16 to cite only a few verses on this subject.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مری نگاہ میں وہ رند ہی نہیں ساقی
جو ہوشیاری و مستی میں امتیاز کرے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In my view he is not a rind at all, O cup-bearer, who would distinguish between ecstasy and lack of it.* 
(Rind: A person who has gone so far in the Love of God that he has become ecstatic and is not able to follow the requirements of the Shari‘h. *As long as a person is consciously aware of being or not being ecstatic he is not a rind. He becomes a rind only when he loses this consciousness also.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مدام گوش بہ دل رہ، یہ ساز ہے ایسا
جو ہو شکستہ تو پیدا نوائے راز کرے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مدام گوش بہ: ہمیشہ دل کی بات پر توجہ دینا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Always remain very attentive to the heart, this orchestra is such if broken, it would produce the music of the Secret.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کوئی یہ پوچھے کہ واعظ کا کیا بگڑتا ہے
جو بے عمل پہ بھی رحمت وہ بے نیاز کرے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Somebody should ask how it hurts the preacher, if God shows His Grace even to the sinner.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سخن میں سوز، الہی کہاں سے آتا ہے
یہ چیز وہ ہے کہ پتھر کو بھی گداز کرے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O God! From where does poetry acquire its heat? This is a thing with which even stone would soften.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تمیز لالہ و گل سے ہے نالہء بلبل
جہاں میں وانہ کوئی چشم امتیاز کرے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Nightingale’s lament comes from discrimination between tulip and rose; no one in the world should open the discriminating eye.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        غرور زہد نے سکھلا دیا ہے واعظ کو
کہ بندگان خدا پر زباں دراز کرے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The arrogance of piety has taught the preacher to use abusive language to the people of God.
(Allusion to and sarcasm on the arrogance of the seemingly pious persons who are so arrogant that they are rude to other people. Really pious people are not rude and are very modest. Modesty is one of the components of piety.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہوا ہو ایسی کہ ہندوستاں سے اے اقبال
اڑا کے مجھ کو غبار رہ حجاز کرے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Such wind should blow from India, O Iqbal which would blow me as dust to Hijaz.
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>