<Poem ID="59" Name="جنگ یر موک کاایک واقعہ" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        صف بستہ تھے عرب کے جوانان تیغ بند 
تھی منتظر حنا کی عروس زمین شام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        AN INCIDENT OF THE BATTLE OF YARMUK
The armed Arab youth were arrayed for battle; the bride of Syria’s land was waiting for myrtle.* 
(*This metaphor is used for the blood about to be shed in the battle.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اک نوجوان صورت سیماب مضطرب 
آ کر ہوا امیر عساکر سے ہم کلام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A young man who was restless like mercury approaching the army’s general started saying:
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے بوعبیدہ رخصت پیکار دے مجھے 
لبریز ہو گیا مرے صبر و سکوں کو جام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ‘O Abu Ubaidah* grant me permission to fight; the cup of my patience and calm is full.
(Abu Ubaidah ibn-Jarrah was an eminent companion of the Holy Prophet (S.A.W.) and was among those who joined him early. He took part in the fateful Battle of Badr and continued fighting for the cause of God all his life. He is famous for his services to Islam during the Khilafahs of Abu Bakr Siddiq R.A. and Umar Farooq R.A.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بے تاب ہو رہا ہوں فراق رسول میں 
اک دم کی زندگی بھی محبت میں ہے حرام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I am becoming impatient in the Holy Prophet’s separation; in his Love even a moment’s life has become hard.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جاتا ہوں میں حضور رسالت پناہ میں 
لے جائوں گا خوشی سے اگر ہو کوئی پیام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        As I am going to the Holy Prophet’s audience, I shall gladly convey if there is any message.’
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ ذوق و شوق دیکھ کے پرنم ہوئی وہ آنکھ 
جس کی نگاہ تھی صفت تیغ بے نیام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The general’s eye, whose sight was like an un-sheathed sword, noticing this zeal and fervor was moist with tears.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بولا امیر فوج کہ وہ نوجواں ہے تو 
پیروں پہ تیرے عشق کا واجب ہے احترام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The army’s general exclaimed: ‘You are that young man the respect for whose Love is binding on the elders.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پوری کرے خدائے محمد تری مراد 
کتنا بلند تیری محبت کا ہے مقام!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        May the God of Muhammad (S.A.W.) fulfill your wish! How elegant is the stage of your Love!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پہنچے جو بارگاہ رسول امیں میں تو 
کرنا یہ عرض میری طرف سے پس از سلام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When you arrive in the audience of the Holy Prophet (S.A.W.), present this petition with my sincere compliments:
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہم پہ کرم کیا ہے خدائے غیور نے 
پورے ہوئے جو وعدے کیے تھے حضور نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ‘The Exalted God has shown His Mercey to us; have been fulfilled all the promises you had made to us.* 
* This verse refers to the Holy Qur’an 2:155-157 read with 33:9-27. Unfavorable circumstances and adversity test the mettle of a person, and sort out the hypocrites from the sincere believers. The attitude of the former is portrayed in 33:9-21 and that of the latter in 33:22-27, particularly 33:22.
[Translated by Dr M A K Khalil]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>