<Poem ID="21" Name="پیام عشق" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="2a" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سن اے طلب گار درد پہلو! میں ناز ہوں، تو نیاز ہو جا
میں غزنوی سومنات دل کا، تو سراپا ایاز ہو جا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Listen O seeker of heart's pathos! I am Naz, you should become Niaz. I am the Ghaznavi of heart's Somnath, you completely become Ayaz.
(Naz and Niaz: In the first hemistich of this verse Love addresses those who are anxious to develop the Love of God and says that this Love is the beloved and it is necessary to become a true Lover to win it. In the second hemistich the same message is repeated in another form.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہیں ہے وابستہ زیر گردوں کمال شان سکندری سے
تمام ساماں ہے تیرے سینے میں، تو بھی آئینہ ساز ہو جا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Greatness in the world is not associated with the Alexander’s splendor; your breast has everything, you should also become the maker of mirrors.
Alexander is believed to have made a mirror of very highly polished copper plate, which is alluded to here. This verse means that being a conqueror like Alexander does not make a person 'great'. However making a mirror with the help of one's knowledge and effort does confer greatness. As a Mu’min has the potential for making the mirror he has also the potential for attaining greatness.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        غرض ہے پیکار زندگی سے کمال پائے ہلال تیرا
جہاں کا فرض قدیم ہے تو، ادا مثال نماز ہو جا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The aim of life's struggle is perfection of your Crescent's grandeur. You are the world's oldest Divine Command, be fulfilled like prayer.
(This is a reminder to the Muslim Ummah that they are the vice gerents of God on earth and for that reason are charged with the responsibility of establishing the sovereignty of God on earth. It is a reminder to them that they should rise to their responsibilities and achieve what is expected of them.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہ ہو قناعت شعار گلچیں! اسی سے قائم ہے شان تیری
وفور گل ہے اگر چمن میں تو اور دامن دراز ہو جا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        وفور: بہتات۔ 
ہوقناعت شعار: قناعت پسند۔ 
دامن دراز: لمبے دامن والا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Be not contented, O gardener, your dignity is established by this alone; if flowers abound in the garden, you should become a more ardent beggar.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گئے وہ ایام، اب زمانہ نہیں ہے صحرانوردیوں کا
جہاں میں مانند شمع سوزاں میان محفل گداز ہو جا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Gone are those days, these are not the times for wandering in wilderness; become melted in the world like the congregation's lighted candle.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وجود افراد کا مجازی ہے، ہستی قوم ہے حقیقی
فدا ہو ملت پہ یعنی آتش زن طلسم مجاز ہو جا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        آتش زن:آگ لگانے والا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The individual's existence is unreal, the nation's existence is real; be devoted to the nation, become destroyer of the unreal's magic.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ ہند کے فرقہ ساز اقبال آزری کر رہے ہیں گویا
بچا کے دامن بتوں سے اپنا غبار راہ حجاز ہو جا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Iqbal! These sectarians of India are working like Azar: Saving your skirt from idols become the dust of the way of Hijaz.
(This verse means that the people who are creating and nurturing sectarian poison in India are like Azar, and Muslims should avoid them and keep their own objectives before them, close their ranks and attain those objectives.)
(Translated by Dr. M.A.K. Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>