<Poem ID="35" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="02" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مجھے آہ و فغان نیم شب کا پھر پیام آیا 
تھم اے رہرو کہ شاید پھر کوئی مشکل مقام آیا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Once more I feel the urge to wail and weep at dead of night: O traveller, stop a bit, perchance I face some awful site.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ذرا تقدیر کی گہرائیوں میں ڈوب جا تو بھی 
کہ اس جنگاہ سے میں بن کے تیغ بے نیام آیا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Awhile in dark abyss of Fate dive and see beneath: Out of this battlefield I come like sword out of the sheath.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ مصرع لکھ دیا کس شوخ نے محراب مسجد پر 
یہ ناداں گر گئے سجدوں میں جب وقت قیام آیا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This verse some man with witty mind on niche of mosque did write: ‘These fools fell prostrate on the earth, when it was time to fight’.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چل، اے میری غریبی کا تماشا دیکھنے والے 
وہ محفل اٹھ گئی جس دم تو مجھ تک دور جام آیا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O man, who at my misery scoff, follow the road you tread: When the cup to me was passed, the gathering all had fled.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دیا اقبال نے ہندی مسلمانوں کو سوز اپنا 
یہ اک مرد تن آساں تھا، تن آسانوں کے کام آیا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Iqbal his glow to Muslims lent, who in India dwell: An easy-going man he was and served the sluggards well.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اسی اقبال کی میں جستجو کرتا رہا برسوں 
بڑی مدت کے بعد آخر وہ شاہیں زیر دام آیا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        To find Iqbal for years on end I did chafe and fret: By effort great that kingly hawk has come within my net.
(Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>