<Poem ID="60" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="02" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کمال جوش جنوں میں رہا میں گرم طواف 
خدا کا شکر، سلامت رہا حرم کا غلاف
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In my craze that knows no bound, of the Mosque I made the round: Thank God that outer vest of Shrine; still was left untorn and fine.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ اتفاق مبارک ہو مومنوں کے لیے 
کہ یک زباں ہیں فقیہان شہر میرے خلاف
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I wish good luck and pleasure great, to all, of faith who always prate: But all the jurists of the town with one accord upon me frown.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تڑپ رہا ہے فلاطوں میان غیب و حضور 
ازل سے اہل خرد کا مقام ہے اعراف
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Men, like Plato, still roam about betwixt belief and utter doubt: Men endowed with reason, aye, ever on the heights do stay.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ترے ضمیر پہ جب تک نہ ہو نزول کتاب 
گرہ کشا ہے نہ رازی نہ صاحب کشاف
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        گرہ کشا: گانٹھ کھولنے والا۔ 
صاحب کشاف: جار اللہ محمود زمخشری جس کی تفسیر کا نام کشاف ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Unless the Book’s each verse and part be revealed unto your heart; interpreters, though much profound, its subtle points cannot expound.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سرور و سوز میں ناپائدار ہے، ورنہ 
م ے فرنگ کا تہ جرعہ بھی نہیں ناصاف
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تہ جرعہ: پیالے کی تہ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The joy that Frankish wine does give lasts not for long nor always lives; though scum at bottom of its bowl is always pure and never foul.
[Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>