<Poem ID="35" Name="نالہ فراق آرنلڈ کی یاد میں" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="1a" SectionName="حصہ اول">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جا بسا مغرب میں آخر اے مکاں تیرا مکیں
آہ! مشرق کی پسند آئی نہ اس کو سر زمیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        LAMENT OF SEPARATION (In Memory of Arnold)
O house! Your resident is now residing in the West. Ah! The land of the East was not liked by him.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آ گیا آج اس صداقت کا مرے دل کو یقیں
ظلمت شب سے ضیائے روز فرقت کم نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Today my heart is convinced of this truth: The light of the separation's day is darker than night.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تا ز آغوش وداعش داغ حیرت چیدہ است
ہمچو شمع کشتہ در چشم نگہ خوابیدہ است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ‘As from his departure's breast the scar is picked up; sight is asleep in my eyes like the extinguished candle.’
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کشتہ عزلت ہوں، آبادی میں گھبراتا ہوں میں
شہر سے سودا کی شدت میں نکل جاتا ہوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I am fond of seclusion, I hate the habitation. I run away from the city in excruciation of love.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یاد ایام سلف سے دل کو تڑپاتا ہوں میں
بہر تسکیں تیری جانب دوڑتا آتا ہوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I make the heart restless from the olden days' memory; for satisfaction I come ardently running towards you.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آنکھ گو مانوس ہے تیرے در و دیوار سے
اجنبیت ہے مگر پیدا مری رفتار سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Though the eye is familiar with your nook and corner, still some strangeness is apparent from my speed.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ذرہ میرے دل کا خورشید آشنا ہونے کو تھا
آئنہ ٹوٹا ہوا عالم نما ہونے کو تھا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My heart's speck was just to be acquainted with the sun. The broken mirror was just to expand into the universe.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نخل میری آرزوئوں کا ہرا ہونے کو تھا
آہ! کیا جانے کوئی میں کیا سے کیا ہونے کو تھا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The tree of my longings was just going to green up. Ah! What does any one know what I was going to be!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ابر رحمت دامن از گلزار من برچید و رفت
اند کے بر غنچہ ہائے آرزو بارید و رفت
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Mercy's cloud gathered up its skirt from my garden and departed; rained a little over the flower buds of my desires and departed.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تو کہاں ہے اے کلیم ذروئہ سینائے علم
تھی تری موج نفس باد نشاط افزائے علم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Where are you! O Kalim of the pinnacle Sina of learning! Your breath was the breeze promoting the joy of learning.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اب کہاں وہ شوق رہ پیمائی صحرائے علم
تیرے دم سے تھا ہمارے سر میں بھی سودائے علم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Gone is that zeal for walking in the vast expanse of learning! In my intellect also you were the inspirer of love of learning.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شور لیلی کو کہ باز آرایش سودا کند
خاک مجنوں را غبار خاطر صحرا کند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ‘Where is Lailah's fervor, so as to decorate Love again; may make the dust of Majnun mixed with wilderness again.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کھول دے گا دشت وحشت عقدئہ تقدیر کو
توڑ کر پہنچوں گا میں پنجاب کی زنجیر کو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The wilderness of solitude will open the fate's knot; I shall reach you after breaking the chains of the Punjab.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دیکھتا ہے دیدئہ حیراں تری تصویر کو
کیا تسلی ہو مگر گرویدہء تقریر کو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The bewildered eye looks upon your picture, but how can one searching for speech be happy?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تاب گویائی نہیں رکھتا دہن تصویر کا"
"خامشی کہتے ہیں جس کو، ہے سخن تصویر کا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ‘No power to speak the picture's mouth has; silence is the speech which the picture has.’
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>