<Poem ID="26" Name="غزل" BookID="03" BookName="ضربِ کلیم" SectionID="02" SectionName="تعلیم و تربیت">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ملے گا منزل مقصود کا اسی کو سراغ 
اندھیری شب میں ہے چیتے کی آنکھ جس کا چراغ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        That man alone in lire shall find to aim and end a certain sign: Whose eyes in pitch dark night can see, and like the eyes of panther shine.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میسر آتی ہے فرصت فقط غلاموں کو 
نہیں ہے بندہ حر کے لیے جہاں میں فراغ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        فراغ: فرصت۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The slaves can get repose and rest in world confined by Time and Space: But men of high and noble birth haven't leisure in worldly race.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فروغ مغربیاں خیرہ کر رہا ہے تجھے 
تری نظر کا نگہباں ہو صاحب 'مازاغ'
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ترقی۔ فروغ
خيرہ کرنا : آنکھوں کو چندھیانا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The progress great that West has made, has bedazzled your eyes a deal. May Prophet (S.A.W.) guard your precious sight; to vouch him God did Najm reveal!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وہ بزم عیش ہے مہمان یک نفس دو نفس 
چمک رہے ہیں مثال ستارہ جس کے ایاغ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اياغ: پیالہ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        These revels do not last for long, like guests they stay for a breath or so: The bowls of wine that glint like stars, are soon deprived of gloss and glow.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کیا ہے تجھ کو کتابوں نے کور ذوق اتنا 
صبا سے بھی نہ ملا تجھ کو بوئے گل کا سراغ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کور ذوق: اندھا ذوق، ذوق کے بغیر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The books have marred your taste and zest to such a great and vast extent that breeze of morn has also failed to give you clue of rose and scent.
[Translated by Akbar Ali Shah]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>