<Poem ID="46" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="02" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہوا نہ زور سے اس کے کوئی گریباں چاک 
اگرچہ مغربیوں کا جنوں بھی تھا چالاک
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Intuition in the West was clever in its power, but had not the plenitude for absolute abandon.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مے يقيں سے ضمير حيات ہے پرسوز
مدرسہ يا رب يہ آب آتش ناک نصيب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        آب آتش ناک: آگ بھرا پانی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The quintessence of life is the force of faith supreme: It is a force denied to all our seats of learning.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عروج آدم خاکی کے منتظر ہیں تمام 
یہ کہکشاں، یہ ستارے، یہ نیلگوں افلاک
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The galaxies, the planets, the firmament, are all waiting for man’s rise, like a star in heaven.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہی زمانہ حاضر کی کائنات ہے کیا 
دماغ روشن و دل تیرہ و نگہ بے باک
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        دل تيرہ: دل کے اندر کا اندھیرا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Brains are bright and hearts are dark and eyes are bold, is this the sum and substance of what our age has gained?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تو بے بصر ہو تو یہ مانع نگاہ بھی ہے 
وگرنہ آگ ہے مومن، جہاں خس و خاشاک
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        بے بصر: بینائی سے محروم۔ 
خس و خاشاک: گھاس پھوس۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The world is a haystack forthe fire of theMuslim soul, but if thou art eyeless, thou canst not find thy way.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زمانہ عقل کو سمجھا ہوا ہے مشعل راہ 
کسے خبر کہ جنوں بھی ہے صاحب ادراک
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        صاحب ادراک: عقل و فہم والا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        To a multitude of men, reason is the guide; they know not that frenzy has a wisdom of its own.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جہاں تمام ہے میراث مرد مومن کی 
میرے کلام پہ حجت ہے نکتہ لولاک
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        لولاک: مراد ہے محمد (صلعم) جن کو صاحب لولاک بھی کہتے ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The world entire is a legacy of the Man of Faith: I say it on the authority of We would not have created it.
(Translated by Naim Siddiqui)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>