<Poem ID="37" Name="شبنم اور ستارے" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اک رات یہ کہنے لگے شبنم سے ستارے 
ہر صبح نئے تجھ کو میسر ہیں نظارے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE DEW AND THE STARS
One night stars started saying this to the dew; ‘Every morning new sights are available to you.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کیا جانیے، تو کتنے جہاں دیکھ چکی ہے 
جو بن کے مٹے، ان کے نشاں دیکھ چکی ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Who knows how many worlds you have seen! Relics of those who rose and fell you have seen.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زہرہ نے سنی ہے یہ خبر ایک ملک سے 
انسانوں کی بستی ہے بہت دور فلک سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Venus has heard this news from an angel that human habitation is very far from the sky.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کہہ ہم سے بھی اس کشور دلکش کا فسانہ 
گاتا ہے قمر جس کی محبت کا ترانہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Tell us the tale of this beautiful realm; the ode of whose love the moon sings.’
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے تارو نہ پوچھو چمنستان جہاں کی 
گلشن نہیں، اک بستی ہے وہ آہ و فغاں کی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ‘O stars! Do not ask me about the earth’s garden; a place of sighs and wailing it is, not a garden.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آتی ہے صبا واں سے پلٹ جانے کی خاطر
بے چاری کلی کھلتی ہے مرجھانے کی خاطر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The zephyr comes from there only to return; the poor flower-bud opens only to wither.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کیا تم سے کہوں کیا چمن افروز کلی ہے 
ننھا سا کوئی شعلہ بے سوز کلی ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What can I tell you how garden-brightening the flower-bud is; some little flame without warmth the flower-bud is.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گل نالہ بلبل کی صدا سن نہیں سکتا 
دامن سے مرے موتیوں کو چن نہیں سکتا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The rose cannot hear the nightingale’s call; it cannot pick up the pearls from my skirt.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہیں مرغ نواریز گرفتار، غضب ہے 
اگتے ہیں تہ سایہ گل خار، غضب ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The melodious birds are imprisoned, it is outrageous; the thorns grow just under the rose, it is outrageous.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رہتی ہے سدا نرگس بیمار کی تر آنکھ 
دل طالب نظارہ ہے، محروم نظر آنکھ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The eye of the sick narcissus always remains wet; the heart longs for sight, but the eye is sightless.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دل سوختہ گرمی فریاد ہے شمشاد 
زندانی ہے اور نام کو آزاد ہے شمشاد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The elm tree is tormented with the heat of complaint; the elm tree is nominally free but is really a prisoner.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تارے شرر آہ ہیں انساں کی زباں میں 
میں گریہ گردوں ہوں گلستاں کی زباں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The stars are the sparks of sighs to the human eye; in the rose garden’s language I am only lament’s cry.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نادانی ہے یہ گرد زمیں طوف قمر کا 
سمجھا ہے کہ درماں ہے وہاں داغ جگر کا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Circumambulation of moon round the earth ignorance is; it thinks there the cure for its scar of Love is.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بنیاد ہے کاشانہ عالم کی ہوا پر 
فریاد کی تصویر ہے قرطاس فضا پر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The foundation of the world’s abode is in the air; it is the picture of lament on the sheet of space!’
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>