<Poem ID="03" Name="خطاب بہ مہر عالمتاب " BookID="10" BookName="پس چہ بائد کرد" SectionID="01" SectionName="پس چہ بائد کرد">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے امیر خاور اے مہر منیر
می کنی ہر ذرہ را روشن ضمیر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اے آسمان کے شہزادے! اے آفتاب درخشاں! تو ہر ذرہ کے اندرون کو چمکا دیتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ADDRESS TO THE WORLD-ILLUMINATING SUN
O lord of the East, O shining Sun! Thou illuminest the heart of every mote of dust.
(Raushan zamir: One who can see into the heart of things; one whose heart is so illumined that everything can be seen in it. This is the epithet usually applied to God-intoxicated people who are credited with having the miraculous power of foreseeing and foretelling events.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        از تو این سوز و سرور اندر وجود
از تو ہر پوشیدہ را ذوق نمود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تیری وجہ سے وجود کائنات میں سوز و سرور ہے، تیری وجہ سے ہر پوشیدہ کے اندر اپنے آپ کو ظاہر کرنے کا شوق ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It is through thee that Being has ardour and exhilaration; it is through thee that every hidden thing desires to manifest itself.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        می رود روشنتر از دست کلیم
زورق زرین تو در جوی سیم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تیری زریں کشتی چاندی کے دریا میں چلتی ہوئی دست کلیم سے بھی زیادہ روشن (نظر آتی) ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Thy golden canoe in the silvery waters moves brighter than the hand of Moses.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پرتو تو ماہ را مہتاب داد
لعل را اندر دل سنگ آب داد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تیرے پرتو نے چاند کو چاندنی عطا کی اور لعل کو پتھر کے اندر آب و تاب بخشی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It is thy rays which give light to the Moon, and provide sustenance to the ruby within the heart of the stone.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لالہ را سوز درون از فیض تست
در رگ او موج خون از فیض تست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تیرے فیض سے گل لالہ کو سوز دروں ملا؛ اور اس کی رگ میں موج خون دوڑی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The inner burning of the tulip and the coursing of blood in its veins are the result of thy bounty.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نرگسان صد پردہ را بر می درد
تا نصیبی از شعاع تو برد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        نرگس نے سینکڑوں پردے پھاڑ دیے تاکہ تیری شعاع سے نور پا سکے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The narcissus tears away hundreds of veils to catch a glimpse of thy ray.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خوش بیا صبح مراد آوردہ ئی
ہر شجر را نخل سینا کردہ ئی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تیرا آنا مبارک ہو، تو میری صبح لایا ہے، تو نے ہر درخت کو درخت طور بنا دیا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Welcome, with thee comes the morning of our heart’s desire, thou hast transformed every tree into the Burning Bush of Mount Sina’i.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تو فروغ صبح و من پایان روز
در ضمیر من چراغی بر فروز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تو صبح کی روشنی ہے اور میں آخر روز ہوں، میرے ضمیر کے اندر (بھی) چراغ روشن کر دے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Thou art the beginning of the morning while I am at the end of my days; light a lamp in my heart.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تیرہ خاکم را سراپا نور کن
در تجلی ہای خود مستور کن
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میری تاریک خاک کو سراپا نور بنا دے، مجھے اپنی تجلّیات میں چھپا لے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Illumine my dark earth from head to foot; cover me up in thy illuminations.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تا بروز آرم شب افکار شرق
بر فروزم سینۂ احرار شرق
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تاکہ میں مشرق کے افکار کی رات کو دن میں تبدیل کر دوں، تاکہ میں مشرق کے احرار کا سینہ چمکا دوں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        That I may bring the light of the day to the night of the Orient’s thought; brighten up the heart of the free men of the Orient.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        از نوائی پختہ سازم خام را
گردش دیگر دہم ایام را
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تاکہ میں اپنی نوا سے ہر خام کو پختہ کر دوں اور ایّام کے دور کو بدل دوں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Give maturity to the inexperienced through my songs, and give a new turn to the events of the world.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فکر شرق آزاد گردد از فرنگ
از سرود من بگیرد آب و رنگ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تاکہ مشرق کا فکر مغرب سے آزاد ہو جائے اور میری لے سے آب و رنگ لے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Thus may the thought of the Orient free itself from the Franks and gain lustre through my songs.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زندگی از گرمی ذکر است و بس
حریت از عفت فکر است و بس
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        زندگی (کا مزہ) صرف گرمیء فکر سے ہے، حرّیت صرف فکر کی پاکیزگی کا نام ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Life comes not but through dhikr (meditation); (true) independence comes not but through purity of thought.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چون شود اندیشۂ قومی خراب
ناسرہ گردد بدستش سیم ناب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جب کسی قوم کی سوچ خراب ہو جاتی ہے تو اس کے ہاتھ میں خالص چاندی بھی کھوٹا سکّہ بن جاتی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When the thought of a people becomes corrupt, then in their hands pure silver turns into base metal.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میرد اندر سینہ اش قلب سلیم
در نگاہ او کج آید مستقیم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس کے سینہ میں قلب سلیم مر جاتا ہے، اسے سیدھی راہ کج دیکھائی دیتی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The pure heart dies in their breast, and to their eyes the crooked appears straight.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="31">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بر کران از حرب و ضرب کائنات
چشم او اندر سکون بیند حیات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        وہ کائنات کے ہنگاموں سے ایک طرف ہو کے بیٹھ جاتی ہے، اس کی نگاہ سکوں ہی میں زندگی دیکھتی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        From the battlefield of life they keep themselves safely away; for them life resides only in the stationary.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        موج از دریاش کم گردد بلند
گوہر او چون خزف نا ارجمند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس کے دریا ئے (حیات) سے کوئی موج نہیں اٹھی، اس کا گوہر بھی پتھر کے ٹکڑے کی مانند بے قیمت ہو جاتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Seldom do waves arise from their ocean; their pearls are as worthless as pieces of clay.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="35">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پس نخستین بایدش تطہیر فکر
بعد از آن آسان شود تعمیر فکر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس لیے سب سے پہلے فکر کی تطہیر کرنی چاہیے، اس کے بعد فکر کی تعمیر آسان ہو جاتی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It is therefore necessary that their thought should first be purified (of all dross); reconstruction of thought would then be easy for them.
(Translated by Jamil Naqvi)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>