<Poem ID="09" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="01" SectionName="حصہ اول">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مٹا دیا مرے ساقی نے عالم من و تو 
پلا کے مجھ کو مے لا الہ الا ھو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My Saki made me drink the wine of There is no god but He: From the illusive world of sense, this cup divine has set me free.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہ مے،نہ شعر، نہ ساقی، نہ شور چنگ و رباب 
سکوت کوہ و لب جوے و لالہ خود رو!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        چنگ و رباب: آلات موسیقی کے نام۔ 
لب جو: ندی کے کنارے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Now I find no charm or grace in song and ale, or harp and lute: To me appeal the tulips wild, the riverside and mountains mute.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گدائے مے کدہ کی شان بے نیازی دیکھ 
پہنچ کے چشمہ حیواں پہ توڑتا ہے سبو!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        چشمہ حيواں: آب حیات کا چشمہ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Thy mendicant, inebriate, has in great abandon, shattered his sustaining cup at the spring of life.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مرا سبوچہ غنیمت ہے اس زمانے میں 
کہ خانقاہ میں خالی ہیں صوفیوں کے کدو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کدو: شراب کا برتن۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My flagon small is blessing great, for the age athirst and dry: In the cells where mystics swell big empty gourds are lying by.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میں نو نیاز ہوں، مجھ سے حجاب ہی اولی 
کہ دل سے بڑھ کے ہے میری نگاہ بے قابو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In love a novice I am yet, much good for you to keep apart, for my glance is restive more than my wild and untam’d heart.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اگرچہ بحر کی موجوں میں ہے مقام اس کا 
صفائے پاکی طینت سے ہے گہر کا وضو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        صفائے پاکي طينت: فطری پاکیزگی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The dark unfathomed caves of sea hold gems of purest ray serene: The gems retain in midst of brine their essence bright and clean.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جمیل تر ہیں گل و لالہ فیض سے اس کے 
نگاہ شاعر رنگیں نوا میں ہے جادو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Through the poet’s quickening gaze; the rose and tulip lovelier seem: No doubt, the minstrel’s piercing glance is nothing less than magic gleam.
(Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>