<Poem ID="24" Name="" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="04" SectionName="ظریفانہ">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شام کی سرحد سے رخصت ہے وہ رند لم یزل 
رکھ کے میخانے کے سارے قاعدے بالائے طاق
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اشارہ ہے فرانس کی افواج ( جو ہمیشہ نشہ میں رہتی تھيں) کا شام کی سرحد سے واپسی کی طرف۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        That eternal rind has departed from the border of Syria shelving away all the rules and etiquette of the tavern.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ اگر سچ ہے تو ہے کس درجہ عبرت کا مقام 
رنگ اک پل میں بدل جاتا ہے یہ نیلی رواق
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If so, how much is this the occasion for admonition; the blue sky changes its colours in a moment.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حضرت کرزن کو اب فکر مداوا ہے ضرور 
حکم برداری کے معدے میں ہے درد لایطاق
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        درد لايطاق: شدید درد۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Curzon certainly would be concerned with remedial measures; in the belly of obedience has started unequaled convulsion.
(Curzon: He was the British Foreign Secretary during the period 1920-25 when an effort was made to settle the Middle East problem to the detriment of the Arabs and advantage of Jews. The part played by Sir Agha Khan III is referred to in the last verse.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وفد ہندستاں سے کرتے ہیں سرآغا خاں طلب 
کیا یہ چورن ہے پےء ہضم فلسطین و عراق؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Sir Agha Khan * is demanding the delegation from India: Is this the digestive for devouring Iraq and Palestine.
* Reference to Sir Sultan Muhammad Shah the Agha Khan III who was a veteran statesman of the Indian sub-continent and played an important role in the politics of India, particularly that of Muslims, including the settlement of the Middle East problem, to which reference is made in the last line of the poem.) 
(Translated by M.A.K. Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>