<Poem ID="08" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="01" SectionName="حصہ اول">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لا پھر اک بار وہی بادہ و جام اے ساقی 
ہاتھ آ جائے مجھے میرا مقام اے ساقی!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Set out once more that cup that wine, oh Saki! Let my true place at last be mine, oh Saki!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تین سو سال سے ہیں ہند کے میخانے بند 
اب مناسب ہے ترا فیض ہو عام اے ساقی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Three centuries India’s wine-shops have been closed, and now for your largesse we pine, oh Saki!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مری مینائے غزل میں تھی ذرا سی باقی 
شیخ کہتا ہے کہ ہے یہ بھی حرام اے ساقی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My flask of poetry held the last few drops; unlawful, says our crabb’d devine, oh Saki.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شیر مردوں سے ہوا بیشہء تحقیق تہی 
رہ گئے صوفی و ملا کے غلام اے ساقی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        بيشہء تحقيق تہي: تحقیق کا جنگل (شیر سے) خالی ہوا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Truth’s forest hides no lion-hearts now: Men grovel before the priest, or the saint’s shrine, oh Saki.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عشق کی تیغ جگردار اڑا لی کس نے 
علم کے ہاتھ میں خالی ہے نیام اے ساقی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تيغ جگردار: تلوار جس کی کاٹ بے پناہ ہو۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Who has borne off Love’s valiant sword? About an empty scabbard Wisdom’s hands twine, oh Saki.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سینہ روشن ہو تو ہے سوز سخن عین حیات 
ہو نہ روشن، تو سخن مرگ دوام اے ساقی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Verse lights up life, while heart burns bright, but fades for ever when those rays decline, oh Saki!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تو مری رات کو مہتاب سے محروم نہ رکھ 
ترے پیمانے میں ہے ماہ تمام اے ساقی!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Bereave not of its moon my night; I see a full moon in your goblet shine, oh Saki!
[Translated by V.G. Kiernan]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>