<Poem ID="48" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="02" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہ تخت و تاج میں، نے لشکر و سپاہ میں ہے 
جو بات مرد قلندر کی بارگاہ میں ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A monarch’s pomp and mighty arms can never give such glee, as can be felt in presence of a qalandar bold and free.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        صنم کدہ ہے جہاں اور مرد حق ہے خلیل 
یہ نکتہ وہ ہے کہ پوشیدہ لاالہ میں ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The world is like an idol house, God’s Friend, a person free: No doubt, this subtle point is hid in words, No god but He.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وہی جہاں ہے ترا جس کو تو کرے پیدا 
یہ سنگ و خشت نہیں، جو تری نگاہ میں ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        سنگ و خشت: اینٹ اور پتھر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The world that you with effort make to you belongs alone: The world of brick and stone you see, you cannot call your own.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مہ و ستارہ سے آگے مقام ہے جس کا 
وہ مشت خاک ابھی آوارگان راہ میں ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The clay-made man is still among the vagrants on the road, though man beyond the moon and stars can find his true abode.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خبر ملی ہے خدایان بحر و بر سے مجھے 
فرنگ رہ گزر سیل بے پناہ میں ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        رہ گزر سيل: سیلاب کی راہ میں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This news I have received from those who rule the sea and land, that Europe lies on course of flood ’gainst which no one can stand.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تلاش اس کی فضاوں میں کر نصیب اپنا 
جہان تازہ مری آہ صبح گاہ میں ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A world there is quite fresh and new in sighs at morn I have: Your portion seek within its tracts, thus goal and aim achieve.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مرے کدو کو غنیمت سمجھ کہ بادہ ناب 
نہ مدرسے میں ہے باقی نہ خانقاہ میں ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        بادہ ناب: خالص شراب۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Count my gourd an immense gain, for pure and sparkling wine no more the seats of learning store nor sells the Sacred Shrine.
(Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>