<Poem ID="01" Name="اشتراکیت" BookID="03" BookName="ضربِ کلیم" SectionID="05" SectionName="سیاست مشرق و مغرب">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        قوموں کی روش سے مجھے ہوتا ہے یہ معلوم 
بے سود نہیں روس کی یہ گرمی رفتار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        COMMUNISM
From wont and ways of nations all these facts so clear with ease I learn, the Russians seem to be in haste to gain the goal for which they yearn.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اندیشہ ہوا شوخی افکار پہ مجبور 
فرسودہ طریقوں سے زمانہ ہوا بیزار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The world is red tip with the modes that aren't in vogue and are outworn; my intellect, that was tame and mild much pert and insolent has grown.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        انساں کی ہوس نے جنھیں رکھا تھا چھپا کر 
کھلتے نظر آتے ہیں بتدریج وہ اسرار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        These mysteries which the greed of man had kept in veils of stuff so coarse are step by step emerging now and coming forth by dint of force.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        قرآن میں ہو غوطہ زن اے مرد مسلماں 
اللہ کرے تجھ کو عطا جدت کردار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O Muslim, dive deep in the Book, which was revealed to Prophets' Seal. May God, by grace on you bestow politeness, for good deeds much.zeal!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جو حرف 'قل العفو' میں پوشیدہ ہے اب تک 
اس دور میں شاید وہ حقیقت ہو نمودار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اشارہ ہے قرآن کی اس آیت کی طرف جس میں کہا گیا 'تجھ سے پوچھتے ہیں کہ کیا خرچ کریں' تو کہہ دے جو بچے اپنے خرچ سے'۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The fact concealed in words so far, ‘spend what is surplus and is spare’ may come to light in modern age and make the meanings clear and bare.
(Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>