<Poem ID="36" Name="فاطمہ بنت عبداللہ" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="عرب لڑکی جو طرابلس کی جنگ میں غازیوں کو پانی پلاتی ہوئی شہید ہوئی 1912ء">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فاطمہ! تو آبروئے امت مرحوم ہے 
ذرہ ذرہ تیری مشت خاک کا معصوم ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        FATIMAH DAUGHTER OF ABD ALLAH
An Arab Girl who was martyred while Serving Water to the Fighters against Infidels in the Battle of Tripoli, 1912CE

Fatimah! The honour of the blessed Ummah you are; all specks of your handful of dust innocent are.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ سعادت، حور صحرائی! تری قسمت میں تھی 
غازیان دیں کی سقائی تری قسمت میں تھی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O nymph of wilderness this happiness in your destiny was; serving water to fighters against infidels your destiny was.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ جہاد اللہ کے رستے میں بے تیغ و سپر
ہے جسارت آفریں شوق شہادت کس قدر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This holy war in God’s cause without armaments is! How courage-inspiring this desire for martyrdom is!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ کلی بھی اس گلستان خزاں منظر میں تھی 
ایسی چنگاری بھی یارب، اپنی خاکستر میں تھی!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This flower-bud also in the autumn-stricken garden was! O Lord! Such a spark also concealed in our ashes was!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اپنے صحرا میں بہت آہو ابھی پوشیدہ ہیں
بجلیاں برسے ہوئے بادل میں بھی خوابیدہ ہیں!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In our wilderness many a deer still concealed is! Many a lightning asleep even in the rained out clouds is!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فاطمہ! گو شبنم افشاں آنکھ تیرے غم میں ہے 
نغمہ عشرت بھی اپنے نالہ ماتم میں ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Fatimah! Though in your grief the eye shedding dew is! The tune of pleasure also in our wailing of grief is.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رقص تیری خاک کا کتنا نشاط انگیز ہے 
ذرہ ذرہ زندگی کے سوز سے لبریز ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        How pleasing the dancing of your dust is! Every speck full of the warmth of life is.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے کوئی ہنگامہ تیری تربت خاموش میں 
پل رہی ہے ایک قوم تازہ اس آغوش میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Some activity in your silent grave is; a nation being reared in this lap is.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بے خبر ہوں گرچہ ان کی وسعت مقصد سے میں 
آفرینش دیکھتا ہوں ان کی اس مرقد سے میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Though unaware of the extent of their aims I am; their re-birth from this grave discerning I am.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تازہ انجم کا فضائے آسماں میں ہے ظہور 
دیدئہ انساں سے نامحرم ہے جن کی موج نور
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        New stars appearing in the celestial space are; whose light waves strange to the human eye are.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جو ابھی ابھرے ہیں ظلمت خانہء ایام سے 
جن کی ضو ناآشنا ہے قید صبح و شام سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Who just arisen from the dark house of time are; whose lights unaware of limitations of day and night are.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جن کی تابانی میں انداز کہن بھی، نو بھی ہے 
اور تیرے کوکب تقدیر کا پرتو بھی ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In whose brightness the old as well as the new ways are and also the shadows of stars of your destiny are.
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>