<Poem ID="03" Name="" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="2b" SectionName="غزلیات 2">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زمانہ دیکھے گا جب مرے دل سے محشر اٹھے گا گفتگو کا 
مری خموشی نہیں ہے، گویا مزار ہے حرف آرزو کا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The world will know when the flood of conversation will emerge from my heart. This is not my silence, but is the shrine of the word of my Longing.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جو موج دریا لگی یہ کہنے، سفر سے قائم ہے شان میری 
گہر یہ بولا صدف نشینی ہے مجھ کو سامان آبرو کا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        As the ocean wave said, ‘My dignity is established by flowing’. The pearl said, ‘Sitting in shell is the safety of my brightness’.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہ ہو طبیعت ہی جن کی قابل، وہ تربیت سے نہیں سنورتے 
ہوا نہ سرسبز رہ کے پانی میں عکس سرو کنار جو کا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Whose temperament does not deserve are not improved by training; reflection of the river bank's cypress does not prosper by living in the water.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کوئی دل ایسا نظر نہ آیا نہ جس میں خوابیدہ ہو تمنا 
الہی تیرا جہان کیا ہے نگار خانہ ہے آرزو کا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I did not see any heart in which Longing is not concealed O God! What is Thy universe! It is a picture gallery of Longing.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کھلا یہ مر کر کہ زندگی اپنی تھی طلسم ہوس سراپا 
جسے سمجھتے تھے جسم خاکی، غبار تھا کوئے آرزو کا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It dawned after death that our life was a spell of greed: What we called material body, was dust cloud of greed's lane.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اگر کوئی شے نہیں ہے پنہاں تو کیوں سراپا تلاش ہوں میں 
نگہ کو نظارے کی تمنا ہے، دل کو سودا ہے جستجو کا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Why am I the embodiment of search if nothing is concealed? The sight is Longing for the Spectacle, the heart is mad after the Search.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چمن میں گلچیں سے غنچہ کہتا تھا، اتنا بیدرد کیوں ہے انساں 
تری نگاہوں میں ہے تبسم شکستہ ہونا مرے سبو کا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The garden's flower bud asked the gardener, ‘Why is Man so heartless? The breaking of my wine glass is occasion for smile in your eyes.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ریاض ہستی کے ذرے ذرے سے ہے محبت کا جلوہ پیدا 
حقیقت گل کو تو جو سمجھے تو یہ بھی پیماں ہے رنگ و بو کا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The effulgence of Love emanates from every speck of the existence' garden; if you know the reality of rose, it is also a combination of colour and fragrance.’
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تمام مضموں مرے پرانے، کلام میرا خطا سراپا 
ہنر کوئی دیکھتا ہے مجھ میں تو عیب ہے میرے عیب جو کا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        All my writings are anachronism; my poetry is completely defective; if somebody sees some skill in me it is the fault of my critic.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سپاس شرط ادب ہے ورنہ کرم ترا ہے ستم سے بڑھ کر 
ذرا سا اک دل دیا ہے، وہ بھی فریب خوردہ ہے آرزو کا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Decorum requires silence; otherwise Thy Mercy is worse than Tyranny. Thou hast given a tiny heart, which also is misled towards greed.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کمال وحدت عیاں ہے ایسا کہ نوک نشتر سے تو جو چھیڑے 
یقیں ہے مجھ کو گرے رگ گل سے قطرہ انسان کے لہو کا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Unity's perfection is so evident that if you cut with the knife's tip; sure you would see human blood trickling out of the rose' vein.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گیا ہے تقلید کا زمانہ، مجاز رخت سفر اٹھائے 
ہوئی حقیقت ہی جب نمایاں تو کس کو یارا ہے گفتگو کا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The age of taqlid has passed, allegorism should depart! When the Truth itself is evident who is authorized to talk?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جو گھر سے اقبال دور ہوں میں، تو ہوں نہ محزوں عزیز میرے 
مثال گوہر وطن کی فرقت کمال ہے میری آبرو کا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If I am far from home, my relatives should not be sad; like pearl separation from home is perfecting my elegance.
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>