<Poem ID="25" Name="انسان اور بزم قدرت" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="1a" SectionName="حصہ اول">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        صبح خورشید درخشاں کو جو دیکھا میں نے
بزم معمورہ ہستی سے یہ پوچھا میں نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        خورشید درخشاں: چمکتا ہوا سورج۔ 
معمورہ ہستی: زندگی کی بستی یعنی دنیا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        MAN AND NATURE'S ASSEMBLAGE
As I looked at the bright sun in the morning I asked the assemblage of Existence' habitation:
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پر تو مہر کے دم سے ہے اجالا تیرا
سیم سیال ہے پانی ترے دریائوں کا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        پر تو مہر: سورج کی روشنی۔ 
سیم سیال: بہتی ہوئی چاندی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ‘You owe your light to the reflection of the sun; the water of your rivers looks like flowing silver.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مہر نے نور کا زیور تجھے پہنایا ہے
تیری محفل کو اسی شمع نے چمکایا ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The sun has adorned your face with light's jewelry; this very candle has illuminated your assemblage.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گل و گلزار ترے خلد کی تصویریں ہیں
یہ سبھی سورہء 'والشمس' کی تفسیریں ہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        خلد: جنت۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your roses and rose gardens are pictures of Paradise; all these are the commentaries of Surah ‘Wa al-Shams’*
* This is an early Makkan Surah. It shows the beauties of Nature and brings home to Man the need for realizing his spiritual responsibilities. It ends with a stern warning to those who do not heed the teachings of the Holy Qur’an about the Hereafter.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سرخ پوشاک ہے پھولوں کی، درختوں کی ہری
تیری محفل میں کوئی سبز، کوئی لال پری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The dress of your flowers is red, of your trees is green; they exist in your garden like green and red fairies.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے ترے خیمہء گردوں کی طلائی جھالر
بدلیاں لال سی آتی ہیں افق پر جو نظر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The frill of your tent becomes golden as the red clouds appear over the horizon.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کیا بھلی لگتی ہے آنکھوں کو شفق کی لالی
مے گلرنگ خم شام میں تو نے ڈالی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        خم شام: شام کا پیالہ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        How pleasing to the eye is the red colour of the evening's twilight as if you have poured rose-coloured wine in the evening's jar.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رتبہ تیرا ہے بڑا، شان بڑی ہے تیری
پردہ نور میں مستور ہے ہر شے تیری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your rank is elegant, your grandeur is high; everything yours is concealed in the light's veil.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        صبح اک گیت سراپا ہے تری سطوت کا
زیر خورشید نشاں تک بھی نہیں ظلمت کا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        سطوت: رعب، دبدبہ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The morning head to foot is a song of your majesty; not even a trace of darkness is there under the sun.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میں بھی آباد ہوں اس نور کی بستی میں مگر
جل گیا پھر مری تقدیر کا اختر کیونکر؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In this habitation of light is my abode also; why then is the star of my destiny burnt down?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نور سے دور ہوں ظلمت میں گرفتار ہوں میں
کیوں سیہ روز، سیہ بخت، سیہ کار ہوں میں؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I am far from light and imprisoned in darkness. Why am I so unfortunate, unlucky and sinning’?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میں یہ کہتا تھا کہ آواز کہیں سے آئی
بام گردوں سے وہ یا صحن زمیں سے آئی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        As I was saying this a voice from somewhere came; from the sky's roof or the earth's expanse it came.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے ترے نور سے وابستہ مری بود و نبود
باغباں ہے تری ہستی پے گلزار وجود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        بود و نبود: ہونا نہ ہونا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ‘My existence is dependent on your light. Your personality is the gardener of Universe' garden.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        انجمن حسن کی ہے تو، تری تصویر ہوں میں
عشق کا تو ہے صحیفہ، تری تفسیر ہوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        صحیفہ: آسمانی کتاب۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You are the assemblage of beauty, your picture I am. You are the Scripture of Love, your commentary I am.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میرے بگڑے ہوئے کاموں کو بنایا تو نے
بار جو مجھ سے نہ اٹھا وہ اٹھایا تو نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You have put my disordered affairs in order. You have shouldered the burden which I could not bear.*
* This is an allusion to the Holy Qur'an 59:21, according to which, in his capacity of being the custodian of the Holy Qur'an, Man has exhibited higher strength and fortitude than the mountains which are proverbial for their height, strength and firmness.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="31">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نور خورشید کی محتاج ہے ہستی میری
اور بے منت خورشید چمک ہے تری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My existence depends upon the light of the sun and your splendor is not indebted to the sun.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہو نہ خورشید تو ویراں ہو گلستاں میرا
منزل عیش کی جا نام ہو زنداں میرا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        زنداں: قید خانہ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Without the sun my rose garden would be desolate; instead of happiness prison would be my name.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="35">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آہ! اے راز عیاں کے نہ سمجھے والے
حلقہ، دام تمنا میں الجھنے والے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        دام تمنا: خواہشات کا جال۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Ah! The one who does not understand the open secret! The one prone to be entangled in the desires' net.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="37">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہائے غفلت کہ تری آنکھ ہے پابند مجاز
ناز زیبا تھا تجھے، تو ہے مگر گرم نیاز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Alas insensible! Confined to the material is your eye; Naz behooved you, but prone to Niyaz is your eye.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="39">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تو اگر اپنی حقیقت سے خبردار رہے
نہ سیہ روز رہے پھر نہ سیہ کار رہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If aware of your reality you would be; neither unlucky nor sinning you would be. 
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>