<Poem ID="32" Name="مسولینی" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="04" SectionName="منظومات">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ندرت فکر و عمل کیا شے ہے، ذوق انقلاب 
ندرت فکر و عمل کیا شے ہے، ملت کا شباب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ندرت: تازگی ، انوکھا پن۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        MUSSOLINI
What is the originality of thought and action? A taste for revolution. What is the originality of thought and action? The age of youth for a nation.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ندرت فکر و عمل سے معجزات زندگی 
ندرت فکر و عمل سے سنگ خارا لعل ناب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Originality of thought and action creates miracles of life: It turns pebbles into ruby stones.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رومتہ الکبرے! دگرگوں ہوگیا تیرا ضمیر 
اینکہ می بینم بہ بیدار یست یارب یا بہ خواب!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        یہ بیداری کے عالم میں دیکھ رہا ہوں یا یہ خواب کی دنیا کے نظارے ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O Great Rome! Your conscience has changed altogether: Is this a dream I see or is this for real!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چشم پیران کہن میں زندگانی کا فروغ 
نوجواں تیرے ہیں سوز آرزو سے سینہ تاب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        سينہ تاب: جن کے سینے گرم ہوں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your old have the gleam of life in their eyes; the flame of desire warms up the hearts of your young.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ محبت کی حرارت، یہ تمنا، یہ نمود 
فصل گل میں پھول رہ سکتے نہیں زیر حجاب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        زير حجاب: پردے میں، چھپے ہوئے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This warmth of love, this longing and this self-expression: Flowers cannot hide themselves in the season of spring.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نغمہ ہائے شوق سے تیری فضا معمور ہے 
زخمہ ور کا منتظر تھا تیری فطرت کا رباب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        معمور: بھرا ہوا۔
زخمہ ور: ساز بجانے والا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Songs of passion fill your air now: The instrument of your nature was awaiting someone to play on it!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فیض یہ کس کی نظر کا ہے، کرامت کس کی ہے؟ 
وہ کہ ہے حس کی نگہ مثل شعاع آفتاب!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Whose benevolent eye has graced this miracle upon you? He whose vision is like the light of the Sun! 
(Translated by Naim Siddiqui)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>