<Poem ID="08" Name="فرشتوں کاگیت" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="04" SectionName="منظومات">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عقل ہے بے زمام ابھی، عشق ہے بے مقام ابھی 
نقش گر، ازل! ترا نقش ہے نا تمام ابھی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        زمام: لگام، نکیل۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Reason is unbridled yet, love is still a dream; thy work remains unfinished still, O Craftsman of Eternity!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خلق خدا کی گھات میں رند و فقیہ و میر و پیر 
تیرے جہاں میں ہے وہی گردش صبح و شام ابھی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The days and nights revolve, unfolding evils new; the rulers of body and soul are ruthless tyrants, all.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تیرے امیر مال مست، تیرے فقیر حال مست 
بندہ ہے کوچہ گرد ابھی، خواجہ بلند بام ابھی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The rich are drunk with wealth; the pious are drunk with piety; the homeless wander in the streets, the lords of palaces are Olympian.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دانش و دین و علم و فن بندگی ہوس تمام 
عشق گرہ کشاے کا فیض نہیں ہے عام ابھی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Learning, religion, art and science, are all slaves of greed; thy love that solves all riddles, has yet to shower its blessings.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جوہر زندگی ہے عشق، جوہر عشق ہے خودی
آہ کہ ہے یہ تیغ تیز پردگی نیام ابھی!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        پردگي نيام: میان کے اندر چھپی ہوئی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The essence of Life is Love, the essence of Love is the self; Alas! This cutting sword as yet rests in the sheath!
(Translated by Naim Siddiqui)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(فرمان خدا - (فرشتوں سے">
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اٹھو! مری دنیا کے غریبوں کو جگا دو 
کاخ امرا کے در و دیوار ہلا دو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کاخ امرا: امیروں کا محل۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        GOD’S COMMAND (to His angels)
Rise, and from their slumber wake the poor ones of My world shake the walls and windows of the mansions of the great!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گرماو غلاموں کا لہو سوز یقیں سے 
کنجشک فرومایہ کو شاہیں سے لڑا دو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کنجشک: چڑیا۔ 
فرومايہ: بے حقیقت، بے حثیت، ناچیز۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Kindle with the fire of faith the slow blood of the slaves; make the fearful sparrow bold to meet the falcon's hate!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سلطانی جمہور کا آتا ہے زمانہ 
جو نقش کہن تم کو نظر آئے، مٹا دو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Close the hour approaches of the kingdom of the poor: Every imprint of the past find and annihilate!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جس کھیت سے دہقاں کو میسر نہیں روزی 
اس کھیت کے ہر خوشہ گندم کو جلا دو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Find the field whose harvest is no peasant's daily bread: Garner in the furnace every ripening ear of wheat!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کیوں خالق و مخلوق میں حائل رہیں پردے 
پیران کلیسا کو کلیسا سے اٹھا دو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Banish from the house of God the mumbling priest whose prayers like a veil creation from Creator separate!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حق را بسجودے، صنماں را بطوافے 
بہتر ہے چراغ حرم و دیر بجھا دو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        حق را بسجودے، صنماں را بطوافے: خدا کو سجدے اور بتوں کا طواف۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        God by mm's prostrations, by man's vows are idols cheated: Quench at once in My shrine and their fane the sacred light!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میں ناخوش و بیزار ہوں مرمر کی سلوں سے 
میرے لیے مٹی کا حرم اور بنا دو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Rear for me another temple, build its walls with mud: Wearied of their columned marbles, sickened is My sight!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تہذیب نوی کارگہ شیشہ گراں ہے 
آداب جنوں شاعر مشرق کو سکھا دو!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تہذیب نوی: نئی تہذیب۔
شيشہ گراں: شیشہ بنانے والے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        All their fine new world a workshop filled with brittle glass: Go! My poet of the East to madness dedicate.
(Translated by Naim Siddiqui)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>