<Poem ID="69" Name="خضرراہ" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="شاعر">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ساحل دریا پہ میں اک رات تھا محو نظر 
گوشہ دل میں چھپائے اک جہان اضطراب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE TRAVELER’S GUIDE
Poet: One night at the river-bank I was absorbed in contemplation with a world of restlessness concealed in the heart’s recesses.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شب سکوت افزا، ہوا آسودہ، دریا نرم سیر
تھی نظر حیراں کہ یہ دریا ہے یا تصویر آب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        سکوت افزا: خاموشی کو بڑھانے والی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The night was tranquil, air calm, river gently flowing was; my eye was amazed whether the river or a picture of water it was!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جیسے گہوارے میں سو جاتا ہے طفل شیر خوار 
موج مضطر تھی کہیں گہرائیوں میں مست خواب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        گہوارا: پنگوڑا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        As the suckling baby falls asleep in the cradle; the restless wave had fallen asleep somewhere else!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رات کے افسوں سے طائر آشیانوں میں اسیر 
انجم کم ضو گرفتار طلسم ماہتاب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        افسوں؛ طلسم: جادو۔
انجم کم ضو: کم روشنی والے ستارے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        With the spell of night the birds were confined in nests. The twinkling stars were caught in the moon’s spell!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دیکھتا کیا ہوں کہ وہ پیک جہاں پیما خضر 
جس کی پیری میں ہے مانند سحر رنگ شباب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        پيک جہاں پيما: دنیا کی سیر کرنے والا قاصد۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Suddenly I saw that the globe-trotting Khizar, whose old age contained youth’s colour like dawn.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کہہ رہا ہے مجھ سے، اے جویائے اسرار ازل! 
چشم دل وا ہو تو ہے تقدیر عالم بے حجاب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جويائے اسرار: راز کا متلاشی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Was saying to me: ‘O seeker of the eternal secrets, if the inner eye be open world’s destiny would be unveiled’!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دل میں یہ سن کر بپا ہنگامہ محشر ہوا 
میں شہید جستجو تھا، یوں سخن گستر ہوا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        On hearing this; an uproaring tumult rose in my heart, being devoted to seeking the Truth I started talking thus:
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے تری چشم جہاں بیں پر وہ طوفاں آشکار 
جن کے ہنگامے ابھی دریا میں سوتے ہیں خموش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        چشم جہاں بيں: دنیا کو دیکھنے والی آنکھ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ‘O you whose world-encompassing eye sees those storms, whose tumults are still sleeping quietly in the river.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        'کشتی مسکین، و 'جان پاک' و 'دیوار یتیم، 
علم موسی بھی ہے تیرے سامنے حیرت فروش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کشتي مسکين و جان پاک و ديوار يتيم: یہ تینوں تلمیہات ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The ‘indigent’s boat’* the chaste soul*, the ‘orphan’s wall’,* even the knowledge of Mosa (A.S.) before you is in amazement.
* All allusions to the Holy Qur’an.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چھوڑ کر آبادیاں رہتا ہے تو صحرا نورد 
زندگی تیری ہے بے روز و شب و فردا دوش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Leaving habitations you remain wandering in wilderness; no day and night, no yesterday and tomorrow is in your life.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زندگی کا راز کیا ہے، سلطنت کیا چیز ہے 
اور یہ سرمایہ و محنت میں ہے کیسا خروش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What is the secret of life? What is imperialism? And what is this struggle between labour and capital?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہو رہا ہے ایشیا کا خرقہ دیرینہ چاک 
نوجواں اقوام نو دولت کے ہیں پیرایہ پوش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The ancient patched garment of Asia is being torn! The youth of parvenu nations are adorned with ornaments!
(Allusion to the conditions after World War I in which the imperialist hold of Western countries over the rest of the world had become stronger and more secure than before the war. In India itself promises of gradual self rule were made during the war. However, on termination of the war and victory of the Allies Britain’s hold over India became tighter as is evidenced by the repressive legislation and suppressive actions of the British Government in the post-war period. In the Muslim countries the conditions were even worse.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گرچہ اسکندر رہا محروم آب زندگی 
فطرت اسکندری اب تک ہے گرم نائونوش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        گرم نائونوش: کھانے پینے میں مصروف۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Though Alexander remained deprived of eternity’s water; the nature of Alexander is busy still in merry-making!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بیچتا ہے ہاشمی ناموس دین مصطفی 
خاک و خوں میں مل رہا ہے ترکمان سخت کوش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Holy Prophet’s progeny is selling his din’s honour and the struggling Turk is smeared in dust and blood *!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آگ ہے، اولاد ابراہیم ہے، نمرود ہے 
کیا کسی کو پھر کسی کا امتحاں مقصود ہے!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اولاد ابراہيم: مراد ہے مسلمان۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        There is fire, there is Ibrahim’s progeny; there is Namrud! Does someone desire someone’s test again.* 
(Reference to the world-wide calamities for the Asian and African countries resulting from the victories of the Western countries to which reference has been made in pervious notes; of special concern to Allamah Iqbal was the plight of the Muslim world to which special reference is made in this verse.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="جواب خضر صحرا نوردی ">
    <Verse ID="31">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کیوں تعجب ہے مری صحرا نوردی پر تجھے 
یہ تگا پوئے دمادم زندگی کی ہے دلیل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        دمادم: مسلسل۔
تگا پوئے: دوڑ دھوپ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The response of Khizar (wandering in deserts):
Why are you amazed at my wandering in the deserts? This incessant toil is demonstration of life.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے رہین خانہ تو نے وہ سماں دیکھا نہیں 
گونجتی ہے جب فضائے دشت میں بانگ رحیل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        رہين خانہ: خانہ نشین۔ 
بانگ رحيل: قافلے کے روانگی کی صدا دینے والا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O the one confined to home, you have not seen that sight when the call for battle march resounds in the desert air!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="35">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ریت کے ٹیلے پہ وہ آہو کا بے پروا خرام 
وہ حضر بے برگ و ساماں، وہ سفر بے سنگ و میل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        حضر: قیام، پڑاؤ۔
آہو: ہرن۔ 
سنگ و ميل: راستہ کے نشان۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="37">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وہ نمود اختر سیماب پا ہنگام صبح 
یا نمایاں بام گردوں سے جبین جبرئیل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        نمود اختر سيماب پا: تیز رفتار ستارے کا نکلنا ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        That appearance of the fast-moving star at the dawn; or the forehead of Jibrail manifest from the sky!
(This is a message of hope for the Muslim Ummah in the hour of their trial.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="39">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وہ سکوت شام صحرا میں غروب آفتاب 
جس سے روشن تر ہوئی چشم جہاں بین خلیل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        سکوت شام صحرا: صحرا میں شام کے وقت کا سکون۔ 
چشم جہاں بين: دور رس نگاہ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        That setting of the sun in the silence of the desert air by which increased the insight of Khalil’s universe-envisaging eye!
(Reference to the Holy Qur’an 6:75-79: This whole stanza emphasizes the evils of inaction and need for activism by Muslims. It also shows the value of studying the physical world as a means of understanding the Existence and nature of God, as is repeatedly emphasized by the Holy Qur’an. This verse is the climax of this message and shows how the world of stars, moon and sun led Ibrahim A.S. towards recognizing the Unity, Uniqueness and Superiority of God.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="41">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اور وہ پانی کے چشمے پر مقام کارواں 
اہل ایماں جس طرح جنت میں گرد سلسبیل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        سلسبيل: جنت کی ایک نہر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        And that halting of the caravan at the stream bank; as the believers’ gathering round the Salsabil!
(Salsabil: This is a spring in the Paradise and the stream ensuing from it.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="43">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تازہ ویرانے کی سودائے محبت کو تلاش 
اور آبادی میں تو زنجیری کشت و نخیل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        زنجيري کشت و نخيل: کھیت اور باغات کے کاموں میں مصروف۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The ardent Love is in search of an ever new wild land and in city your effort is in farming and horticulture.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="45">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پختہ تر ہے گردش پہیم سے جام زندگی 
ہے یہی اے بے خبر راز دوام زندگی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        گردش پہيم: مسلسل چلتے جانا۔ 
راز دوام زندگي: ہمیشہ کی زندگی کا راز۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The cup of life becomes more mature by revolving; O negligent one, this alone is the secret of life’s permanence!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="زندگی">
    <Verse ID="47">
      <Text Language="Original">
        برتر از اندیشہء سود و زیاں ہے زندگی 
ہے کبھی جاں اور کبھی تسلیم جاں ہے زندگی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        انديشہء سود و زياں: نفع و نقصان کا خوف۔ 
تسليم جاں: جان قربان کرنا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Life:
Much above the fear of profit and loss is life! Now the soul now the surrender of soul is life!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="49">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تو اسے پیمانہ امروز و فردا سے نہ ناپ 
جاوداں پیہم دواں، ہر دم جواں ہے زندگی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        امروز و فردا: آج اور کل۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Do not measure it on the scale of today and tomorrow! Eternal, incessantly struggling, ever young is life!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="51">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اپنی دنیا آپ پیدا کر اگر زندوں میں ہے 
سر آدم ہے، ضمیر کن فکاں ہے زندگی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        سر آدم: انسان کی تخلیق کا راز۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Create your own world if you claim to be among the living; the secret of Adam and the object of ‘Kun fikoon’* is life.
(Reference to the Holy Qur’an 6:73 in which God describes the creation of the universe as His Will and Command. As the Holy Qur’an has repeatedly said the creation of the universe is purposeful. That purpose was the eventual creation of Man as the master-piece of His creation and Man’s subsequent perfection into ‘perfect man’ (Allamah Iqbal’s Mard-i-Kamil) in the personality of the Holy Prophet (S.A.W.). This is supported by a Hadith to the effect that ‘God would not have created the universe if He had not created me’. God also created the Holy Qur’an for the guidance of Man with which every person can be perfected…)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="53">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زندگانی کی حقیقت کوہکن کے دل سے پوچھ 
جوئے شیر و تیشہ و سنگ گراں ہے زندگی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کوہکن: پہاڑ کھودنے والا، مراد ہے فرہاد۔
جوئے شير: دودھ کی نہر۔
سنگ گراں: بھاری پتھر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Ask the mountain digger for the reality of life; the canal of milk, the axe, the heavy rock is life.* 
(Heavy rock: Reference to Farhad in the epic of love known as ‘Shirin O Farhad’. Farhad is known as ‘mountain digger’ because he successfully dug a canal through a mountain and filled it with milk in compliance with a requirement for getting the hand of Shirin, his beloved.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="55">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بندگی میں گھٹ کے رہ جاتی ہے اک جوئے کم آب 
اور آزادی میں بحر بے کراں ہے زندگی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جوئے کم آب: کم پانی والی ندی۔
بندگي: غلامی۔
بحر بے کراں: لا محدود سمندر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In slavery it is choked to a mere trickling brook and in freedom like the boundless ocean is life.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="57">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آشکارا ہے یہ اپنی قوت تسخیر سے 
گرچہ اک مٹی کے پیکر میں نہاں ہے زندگی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        قوت تسخير: فتح کرنے کی طاقت۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It is manifested by its power of subduing; though concealed in a body of dust is life.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="59">
      <Text Language="Original">
        قلزم ہستی سے تو ابھرا ہے مانند حباب 
اس زیاں خانے میں تیرا امتحاں ہے زندگی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        حباب: بلبلہ۔
قلزم: سمندر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You have emerged from the existence’ ocean like a bubble; in this losing battle your examination is life.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="61">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خام ہے جب تک تو ہے مٹی کا اک انبار تو 
پختہ ہو جائے تو ہے شمشیر بے زنہار تو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        شمشير بے زنہار: پناہ نہ دینے والی تلوار۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        While you are immature only a heap of dust you are; on attaining maturity a merciless sword you are!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="63">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہو صداقت کے لیے جس دل میں مرنے کی تڑپ 
پہلے اپنے پیکر خاکی میں جاں پیدا کرے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The heart which is restless for death in defense of Truth should first life in his own body must create.
(This stanza is a description of the pre-requisites to be acquired by a person who is prepared to struggle in the cause of God and Islam.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="65">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پھونک ڈالے یہ زمین و آسمان مستعار 
اور خاکستر سے آپ اپنا جہاں پیدا کرے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        خاکستر: راکھ۔
مستعار: مانگے ہوے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Should burn down this borrowed universe and from the ashes his own universe should create.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="67">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زندگی کی قوت پنہاں کو کر دے آشکار 
تا یہ چنگاری فروغ جاوداں پیدا کرے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Should demonstrate the potential power of life; so that this spark may the eternal light create.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="69">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خاک مشرق پر چمک جائے مثال آفتاب 
تا بدخشاں پھر وہی لعل گراں پیدا کرے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        لعل گراں: قیمتی پتھر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Should shine like the sun over the lands of the East; so that Badakhshan the same invaluable rubies may again create!
(Badakhshan: This is a region in the present day Afghanistan which is famous for rubies and other precious stones.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="71">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سوئے گردوں نالہ شب گیر کا بھیجے سفیر 
رات کے تارں میں اپنے رازداں پیدا کرے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        نالہ شب گير: رات کو اپنے گھیرے میں لینے والی فریاد۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Should send heaven-ward the emissary of nightly wailing and in the night’s stars its confidantes should create.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="73">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ گھڑی محشر کی ہے، تو عرصہء محشر میں ہے 
پیش کر غافل، عمل کوئی اگر دفتر میں ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        عرصہء محشر: محشر کا میدان۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This is the hour of Judgment you in the Judgment’s field are O negligent one, present actions if some in your treasure are!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="سلطنت ">
    <Verse ID="75">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آبتائوں تجھ کو رمز آیہء 'ان الملوک' 
سلطنت اقوام غالب کی ہے اک جادوگری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        قرآن کی سورہ نمل کی اس آیہ کی طرف اشارہ ہے جب بادشاہ کسی بستی میں داخل ہوتے ہی فساد برپا کر دیتے ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Imperialism:
Come, I shall tell you the secret of the verse ‘Inn al-mulook’;* imperialism is an enchantment of the victorious nations. 
(This alludes to The Holy Qur’an 27:34 in which the Queen of Saba (Shiba), on receiving the letter of Sulaiman A.S. inviting her to accept Islam, addressed her courtiers thus: ‘Kings, when they enter a country despoil it, and make the noblest of its people its meanest. Thus do they behave’. This verse is a clear condemnation of imperialism in Islam.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="77">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خواب سے بیدار ہوتا ہے ذرا محکوم اگر 
پھر سلا دیتی ہے اس کو حکمراں کی ساحری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ساحري: جادوگری، مراد ہے دھوکہ بازی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If the ruled from his stupor slightly wakes up; the ruler’s spell lulls him back to sleep again.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="79">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جادوئے محمود کی تاثیر سے چشم ایاز 
دیکھتی ہے حلقہء گردن میں ساز دلبری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        From the effect of the spell of Mahmood the eye of Ayaz, sees the accouterments of loveliness round his neck.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="81">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خون اسرائیل آجاتا ہے آخر جوش میں 
توڑ دیتا ہے کوئی موسی طلسم سامری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        طلسم سامري: سامری کا جادو۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        At last the blood of Israel boils up with anger; the spell of Samiri is smashed up by some Musa.
(The blood of Israel: This verse refers to the magic of the sorcerer Samiri. During the period between the prophethood of Musa A.S. and Isa A.S. the people of Israel were the inheritors of the vice-regency of God and they are treated like ‘Muslims’ in the Holy Qur’an. Samiri: This is an allusion to Holy Qur’an 20: 85, 95-97.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="83">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سروری زیبا فقط اس ذات بے ہمتا کو ہے 
حکمراں ہے اک وہی، باقی بتان آزری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        سروري: سرداری۔ 
ذات بے ہمتا: ایسی ذات جس کی کوئی مثال نہ ہو۔
بتان آزري: آزر کے بنائے ہوئے بت۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Sovereignty befits only that Peerless Essence; only He is the sovereign, the rest are Azar’s idols.
(Peerless Essence: Reference to God.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="85">
      <Text Language="Original">
        از غلامی فطرت آزاد را رسوا مکن 
تا تراشی خواجہ ے از برہمن کافر تری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تو اپنی آزاد فطرت کو غلامی میں پھنسا کر ذلیل نہ کر ؛ اگر تو کسی کو آقا بنائے گا اور یہ بت تراشے گا تو تو سمجھ لے کہ تو برہمن سے بھی بڑا کافر ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Do not disgrace your independent disposition with slavery; so that you do not mold yourself into the master who would be a worse infidel than the Brahman.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="87">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے وہی ساز کہن مغرب کا جمہوری نظام
جس کے پردوں میں نہیں غیر از نوائے قیصری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        نوائے قیصری : شہنشاہ کی صدا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Western democratic system is the same old orchestra in whose frets is nothing different from the Qaisar’s tune. 
(Qaiser’s tune: Reference to the imperialism of the Roman Empire which is famous for its atrocities.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="89">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دیو استبداد جمہوری قبا میں پاے کوب 
تو سمجھتا ہے یہ آزادی کی ہے نیلم پری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        پاے کوب: نیچے والا ۔
استبداد: ظلم۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The monster of despotism is treading in democracy’s robe; you consider it as the beautiful ferry of independence!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="91">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مجلس آئین و اصلاح و رعایات و حقوق 
طب مغرب میں مزے میٹھے، اثر خواب آوری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The legislative assembly, the reforms, the rights and concessions: In Western medicine the tastes are sweet, the effect is soporific!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="93">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گرمی گفتار اعضائے مجالس، الاماں! 
یہ بھی اک سرمایہ داروں کی ہے جنگ زرگری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اعضائے مجالس: قانون ساز اسمبلیوں کے ایوان۔ 
الاماں: خدا محفوظ رکھے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        May God protect us from the fervor of speeches of members of assemblies; this also is the capitalists’ sham quarreling to deceive the poor!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="95">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اس سراب رنگ و بو کو گلستاں سمجھا ہے تو 
آہ اے ناداں! قفس کو آشیاں سمجھا ہے تو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        سراب: دھوکہ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You have taken this apparent beauty’s mirage as a garden! Ah! O ignorant one! You have taken the cage to be the nest!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="سرمایہ ومحنت ">
    <Verse ID="97">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بندئہ مزدور کو جا کر مرا پیغام دے 
خضر کا پیغام کیا، ہے یہ پیام کائنات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        پيام کائنات: کائنات کے دل کی آواز۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Sarmayah-O-Mehnat (Capital and Labour):
Go and deliver my message to the labouring person: ‘Not only Khizar’s message, this is the universal message!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="99">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے کہ تجھ کو کھا گیا سرمایہ دار حیلہ گر 
شاخ آہو پر رہی صدیوں تلک تیری برات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        آہو: ہرن کا سینگ۔ شاخ
برات: حصّہ، مراد ہے رزق۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O whom the fraudulent capitalist has destroyed! Your destiny has remained a fugitive for centuries.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="101">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دست دولت آفریں کو مزد یوں ملتی رہی 
اہل ثروت جیسے دیتے ہیں غریبوں کو زکات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        دولت آفريں: دولت پیدا کرنے والے ہاتھ۔ دست
امیر لوگ۔ ثروت: اہل
مزد: مزدور۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The wealth-creating hand had been paid wages as the rich pay charity to the poor!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="103">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ساحر الموط نے تجھ کو دیا برگ حشیش 
اور تو اے بے خبر سمجھا اسے شاخ نبات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        الموط: موط کا جادوگر ، مراد ہے سرمایہ دار ۔ ساحر
برگ حشيش: بھنگ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The magician of Alamut gave you the hashish leaves and you, O negligent one, took it as a tuft of candy!
(Magician of Alamut: Reference to the Hasan Bin Öabbat (d. 1138) who was a wizard of his age. He lived in Iran in the eleventh century C.E. He built a fort at Alamut, between Qazwain and Jilan. He furnished its interior with the state of the art furnishings and accouterment of comfort and luxury, including the most beautiful girls available. He designated this fort ‘Paradise’, and laid claims to prophet-hood. He had a body of followers who enticed unwary people in cities with administration of hemp and transported them to the Alamut Fort when they became intoxicated with hemp. On gaining consciousness they found themselves in strange surroundings which were the ultimate in luxury, including ‘houri’s’. When they thus became convinced of being in ‘paradise’ they accepted Hasan Bin Öabbat as their prophet. He had built formidable strength which the State could not subdue with mere force. He was a contemporary of Ghias al-Din Abu al-Faté Qamar Bin Ibrahim al-Khayyam, the famous ‘Umar Khayyam’: who was a mathematician, astronomer and poet (ca. 1050-1123). The latter ultimately subdued Hasan Bin Öabbat with better wisdom, based on righteousness instead of wizardry. Later this organization was destroyed by the Mongols about the middle of the 13th century.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="105">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نسل، قومیت، کلیسا، سلطنت، تہذیب، رنگ 
خواجگی نے خوب چن چن کے بنائے مسکرات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مسکرات: وہ چیزیں جو نشہ پیدا کرتی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Race, nation, church, empire, civilization, colour: This assortment of intoxicants is made by ‘imperialism’.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="107">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کٹ مرا ناداں خیالی دیوتائوں کے لیے 
سکرکی لذت میں تو لٹوا گیا نقد حیات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        سکر: نشہ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The ignorant one gave up his life for mythical gods; you destroyed your life’s capital under intoxicants’ love.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="109">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مکر کی چالوں سے بازی لے گیا سرمایہ دار 
انتہائے سادگی سے کھا گیا مزدور مات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The capitalist has won with deceitful stratagems due to extreme naivete the laborer is checkmated.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="111">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اٹھ کہ اب بزم جہاں کا اور ہی اندازہے 
مشرق و مغرب میں تیرے دور کا آغاز ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Rise, as the world’s assembly has adopted different ways; in the East and the West is the beginning of your age.
(Allusion to the labour movements all over the world starting at that time: These movements are usually credited to communism and general awakening in the West. However, in reality they owe their origin to the awakening kindled by Islam and Muslim scholars in Spain and Iraq in the middle ages which brought about Reformation and Renaissance in Europe and which is an on-going movement of human liberation from the forces of undue domination.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="113">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہمت عالی تو دریا بھی نہیں کرتی قبول 
غنچہ ساں غافل ترے دامن میں شبنم کب تلک
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Those with elegant courage do not accept even the ocean O negligent one, how long would you hold dew in your skirt like the flower bud?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="115">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نغمہ بیداری جمہور ہے سامان عیش 
قصہ خواب آور اسکندر و جم کب تلک
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Music of masses’ renaissance is a means of pleasure; the soporific tale of Alexander and Jam how long?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="117">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آفتاب تازہ پیدا بطن گیتی سے ہوا 
آسمان! ڈوبے ہوئے تاروں کا ماتم کب تلک
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A new sun has arisen from the bowels of the earth O Sky! Mourning of stars which have set how long?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="119">
      <Text Language="Original">
        توڑ ڈالیں فطرت انساں نے زنجیریں تمام 
دوری جنت سے روتی چشم آدم کب تلک
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Human nature has broken down all the chains! Man’s eye would weep for the lost Paradise how long?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="121">
      <Text Language="Original">
        باغبان چارہ فرما سے یہ کہتی ہے بہار 
زخم گل کے واسطے تدبیر مرہم کب تلک
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The spring says this to the helping gardener: You would apply ointment to the rose’ wounded heart how long?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="123">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کرمک ناداں! طواف شمع سے آزاد ہو 
اپنی فطرت کے تجلی زار میں آباد ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کرمک ناداں: بھنورا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O simple fire-fly, be free of revolving round the candle and be living in the illuminated place of your own nature!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="دنیائے اسلام">
    <Verse ID="125">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کیا سناتا ہے مجھے ترک و عرب کی داستاں 
مجھ سے کچھ پنہاں نہیں اسلامیوں کا سوز و ساز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        پنہاں: چھپا ہوا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The World of Islam:
Why are you relating to me the story of Turks and Arabs! Nothing of the grief and joys of Muslims is hidden from me.*
(This means that the whole history of the Muslim Ummah was known to Khizar A.S. It also refers to the history of secession of the Arab world from the fold of the Uthmaniya Khilafah and its aftermath.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="127">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لے گئے تثلیث کے فرزند میراث خلیل 
خشت بنیاد کلیسا بن گئی خاک حجاز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تثليث: مراد ہے عیسائی۔ 
ميراث خليل: مراد ہے مسلمانوں کا ورثہ۔ 
خشت: اینٹ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The sons of the Cross have taken away the heritage of Khalil; the soil of Hijaz has become the brick of the church’s foundation!
(Reference to the upper hand of Christians in Islamic countries, particularly those with Muslim majorities and Muslim governments.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="129">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہوگئی رسوا زمانے میں کلاہ لالہ رنگ 
جو سراپا ناز تھے، ہیں آج مجبور نیاز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کلاہ لالہ رنگ: سرخ ٹوپی، ترکی ٹوپی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The red cap* has become disgraced in the world! Those who were formerly proud are in need of others!
* This refers to the Turkish cap which was red in colour and had a black frill. It was used as a national cap by Muslims in greater part of the world. It lasted till the beginning of World War II.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="131">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لے رہا ہے مے فروشان فرنگستاں سے پارس 
وہ مےء سرکش حرارت جس کی ہے مینا گداز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        سرکش: تند و تیز۔ 
مينا گداز: صراحی کو پگھلا دینے والی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        From the wine sellers of Europe Iran is purchasing that strong wine by whose heat the decanter is melted.*
(Reference to the inordinate Western influence in the politics and, still worse, in social life of the people in the Muslim world.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="133">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حکمت مغرب سے ملت کی یہ کیفیت ہوئی 
ٹکڑے ٹکڑے جس طرح سونے کو کر دیتا ہے گاز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        گاز: سونے کو کاٹنے کی قینچی ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The politics of the West has reduced the nation such as gold is rendered to pieces by scissors.*
(Reference to the division of the Muslim world into a large number of secular nation states after World War I. However, our misfortune is that, in spite of the efforts of `Allamah Iqbal and a large number of other reformers all over the Muslim world, the trend towards fragmentation of theUmmah is continuing un-abated.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="135">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہوگیا مانند آب ارزاں مسلماں کا لہو 
مضطرب ہے تو کہ تیرا دل نہیں دانائے راز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ارزاں: سستا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The blood of the Muslim has become cheap like water; you are restless as your heart is unaware of their fate.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="137">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گفت رومی ہر بناے کہنہ کآباداں کنند 
می ندانی اول آں بنیاد را ویراں کنند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        رومی نے کہا کہ ہر پرانی عمارت کو دوبارہ بنانے سے پہلے؛ کیا تو نہیں جانتا ، پہلے اس کو گرانا پڑتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Rumi said that every old building that is to be rebuilt! Do you not know that the building is first demolished?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="139">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ملک ہاتھوں سے گیا ملت کی آنکھیں کھل گئیں 
حق ترا چشمے عطا کردست غافل در نگر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اللہ نے تجھے آنکھیں عطا کی ہیں، غافل (آنکھیں کھول) اور دیکھ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ‘The homeland has been lost; the nation has been jolted O negligent one, look deep as God has granted you insight!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="141">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مومیائی کی گدائی سے تو بہتر ہے شکست 
مور بے پر! حاجتے پیش سلیمانے مبر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Defeat is better than helplessly begging for momiyai O helpless ant! Do not take your requests to a Sulaiman.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="143">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ربط و ضبط ملت بیضا ہے مشرق کی نجات 
ایشیا والے ہیں اس نکتے سے اب تک بے خبر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The salvation of the East is in organization of the Muslim nations; the people of Asia are still unaware of this mystery.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="145">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پھر سیاست چھوڑ کر داخل حصار دیں میں ہو 
ملک و دولت ہے فقط حفظ حرم کا اک ثمر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        حصار ديں: مذہب کا قلعہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Relinquishing ‘politics’ enter the fort of din again; country and wealth is only a reward for Haram’s defense.
(This verse does not teach Muslims to withdraw from politics. It preaches only refraining from God-less Western politics, on the vices of which he is very emphatic.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="147">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ایک ہوں مسلم حرم کی پاسبانی کے لیے 
نیل کے ساحل سے لے کر تا بخاک کاشغر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Muslims should unite into one body for Haram’s defense from the banks of the Nile to the City of Kashghar!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="149">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جو کرے گا امتیاز رنگ و خوں، مٹ جائے گا 
ترک خرگاہی ہو یا اعرابی والا گہر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        خرگاہي: خیمہ میں رہنے والا ترکی باشندہ۔ ترک
اعرابي والا گہر: اعلی منصب عرب۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Whoever would discriminate for colour and race would perish; whether he be the tent-dwelling Turk or the high ranking Arab!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="151">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نسل اگر مسلم کی مذہب پر مقدم ہوگئی 
اڑ گیا دنیا سے تو مانند خاک رہ گزر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If race would become more important than din to the Muslim; he would be blown away from the world like the dust of the road!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="153">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تا خلافت کی بنا دنیا میں ہو پھر استور 
لا کہیں سے ڈھونڈ کر اسلاف کا قلب و جگر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        To establish the Khilafah’s foundations in the world again; the need is to bring from somewhere the ancestors’ mettle.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="155">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے کہ نشناسی خفی را از جلی ہشیار باش 
اے گرفتار ابوبکر و علی ہشیار باش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ہوشیار ، اے وہ جو پوشیدہ اور ظاہر میں فرق نہیں پہچانتا! ہوشیار اے ابو بکر اور علی کی بڑائیاں بیان کرنے والے (شیعہ سنّی تفرقہ کی طرف اشارہ ہے)۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O You who do not distinguish between the tangible and the intangible, beware; O the captive of Abu Bakr and Ali, beware. 
(This is a stern warning to Muslims to refrain from Shi‘a-Sunni controversies and quarrels which are sapping the strength of the Muslim society and the Muslim world.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="157">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عشق کو فریاد لازم تھی سو وہ بھی ہو چکی 
اب ذرا دل تھام کر فریاد کی تاثیر دیکھ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تاثير: اثر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Complaint was incumbent on Love and it has been lodged with a cool heart now watch the effect of the complaint!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="159">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تو نے دیکھا سطوت رفتار دریا کا عروج 
موج مضطر کس طرح بنتی ہے اب زنجیر دیکھ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        دریا کی رفتار کی تیزی کی ہیبت۔ سطوت رفتار دريا:
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You have witnessed the zenith of the majesty of the river’s flow; now watch how the restless wave becomes a chain in which it gets entangled.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="161">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عام حریت کا جو دیکھا تھا خواب اسلام نے 
اے مسلماں آج تو اس خواب کی تعبیر دیکھ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The dream of universal freedom which was seen by Islam O Muslim, you should watch the interpretation of that dream today!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="163">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اپنی خاکستر سمندر کو ہے سامان وجود 
مر کے پھر ہوتا ہے پیدا یہ جہان پیر، دیکھ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        خاکستر: راکھ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Its own ashes are a means of existence to salamander; you should watch the resurrection of this world after death!
(Salamander: This is a legendary animal which lives and flourishes in fire. This verse is a repetition of Allamah Iqbal’s message on Islam’s renaissance.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="165">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کھول کر آنکھیں مرے آئینہء گفتار میں 
آنے والے دور کی دھندلی سی اک تصویر دیکھ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        With open eyes in the mirror or my discourses; you should watch a faint image of the coming age.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="167">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آزمودہ فتنہ ہے اک اور بھی گردوں کے پاس 
سامنے تقدیر کے رسوائی تدبیر دیکھ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The sky has one more tested trick preserved in its store; watch the disgrace of planning in face of destiny’s strength.
(This is a message of hope to Muslims. It reminds us of the promise of God that Divine planning and Help will be with us if we are steadfast in our mission. There are many verses in the Holy Qur’an to this effect, e.g. 3:54 and 27:50.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="169">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مسلم استی سینہ را از آرزو آباد دار 
ہر زماں پیش نظر، 'لایخلف المیعاد' دار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مسلمان ہونے کی حیثیت سے (اللہ کی رحمت سے مایوس نہ ہو اور) امید سے اپنا دل آباد رکھ؛ ہر وقت مد نظر رہے کہ اللہ تعالے اپنے وعدہ کے خلاف نہیں کرتا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You are a Muslim keep your breast happy with Longing; every moment keep your eye on ‘La yukhlif-ul-Mi’ad’.*
(Allusion to the Holy Qur’an 3:9 which ends in ‘God never fails in His promise’.)
(Translated by M.A.K. Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>