<Poem ID="05" Name="رومی" BookID="11" BookName="ارمغانِ حجاز" SectionID="03" SectionName="حضور ملت">
  <Para Name="(1)">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بکام خود دگر ن کہنہ می ریز
کہ با جامش نیرزد ملک پرویز
ز اشعار جلال الدین رومی
بدیوار حریم دل بیاویز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اپنے حلق میں پھر وہی پرانی شراب اونڈیل ؛ جس کا ایک جام سلطنت پرویز سے بڑھ کر ہے۔
جلال الدین رومی (رحمتہ الّہ) کے اشعار ؛ حریم دل کی دیوار پر آویزاں کر لے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        RUMI
Pour in thy self that old wine again; his one cup’s worth is more than a reign.
Keep the verses of Rumi in thy brain; and paste them around the heart’s walls again.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(2)">
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بگیر از ساغرش ن لالہ رنگی
کہ تاثیرش دہد لعلی بہ سنگی
غزالی را دل شیری ببخشد
بشوید داغ از پشت پلنگی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        رومی (رحمتہ الّہ) کے ساغر سے وہ لالہ رنگ شراب لے ؛ جس کی تاثیر سنگ کو لعل عطا کرتی ہے۔ 
جو ہرن کو شیر دل بنا دیتی ہے؛ اور چیتے کی پشت سے داغ دھو ڈالی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Take from his cup those poppy like stems; whose one sip can turn a stone into gem.
The heart of a lion who gave to the deer; who shaved the black spots from a panther’s rear.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(3)">
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نصیبی بردم از تاب و تب او
شبم مانند روز از کوکب او
غزالی در بیابان حرم بین
کہ ریزد خندہ شیر از لب او
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میں نے اسی کی چمک اور تپش سے حصّہ پایا ہے؛ اسی کے ستارے نے میری رات کو دن کی طرح روشن کر دیا ہے۔
(اب) بیابان حرم میں (اس) غزال کو دیکھ؛ اس کے لبوں پر شیر کی سی مسکراہٹ ہے (اپنی طرف اشارہ ہے)۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        From his verve and heat I got a good share; my night was a day from that bught star’s flare.
See a gazelle on ‘Harem’s’ desert sands; he smiles like a lion on oasis or lands.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(4)">
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سراپا درد و سوز شنائی
وصال او زبان دان جدائی
جمال عشق گیرد از نے او
نصیبی از جلال کبریائی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        رومی (رحمتہ الّہ) کا کلام سراپا درد و سوز محبت ہے؛ اس کا وصل، ہجر کا ترجمان ہے۔
اس کے نغموں کی بدولت، جمال عشق ؛ جلال کبریا ئی کی شان رکھتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Being full of pathos and passion’s heat; his tete-a-tete thus had the pangs sweet treat.
By flute gets beauty of His Love’s sweet light; a gift and share good of His Glory and Might.*

* Tete-a-tete, private conversation between two persons. (here it is wisal-i-llahi). Treat; something that comes unexpected, especially something that gives pleasure, not often enjoyed.
Here Iqbal’s wants self on tete-a-tete differs from other mystics. It is neither pantheism nor neo-platonism as enunciated by Plotinus (Plotinus) 205-270 A.D. in Alexandira postulating a single source (God) from which all forms of existence emanate and with whom the soul seeks mystical union. It is also called ‘Hama andar Wajud’ (all within His Being) or ‘wahdat-is-shahud’. His self goes higher to both, higher than ‘fana-fihlah’ (destruction or elimination within God).
Here poet’s self wants to achieve ‘Baqa Billah’ (permanence! everlasting life with God. This is the highest stage for a faithful when the self feels his entity alongwith the God’s (presence) vision. As such in his tete-a-tete of God the self is still conscious of long period of separation from that place, the place of souls in the heavens (Alam-i-Arwah). Iqbal is hinting here to those sweet pangs of separation (a) Wisal-i-ou; (his tete-a-tete) (b) Zubandan-i- (having the tongue, the ken of the feeling of), Judai, (separation). Flute; (his songs of lover message of love, poesy of amatory, his poesy full of love of God.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(5)">
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گرہ از کار این نا کارہ وا کرد
رہگزر را کیمیا کرد غبا ر
نے آن نے نوزاے پاکبازے
مرا با عشق و مستی آشنا کرد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس نے مجھ ناکارہ کی مشکلات حل کر دیں؛ مجھ جیسے غبار راہ کو کیمیا بنا دیا۔
اس پاکباز نے نواز آواز کے نغموں نے مجھے عشق و مستی (کی دولت) سے آشنا کر دیا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He solved many ties I had to face; he gave to way’s dust* his exir’s grace.
The tone of this flutist, tender heart hence; made me conscious of Love and fervour sense. 
* Way’s dust the poet himself.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(6)">
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بروے من در دل باز کردند
ز خاک من جھانی ساز کردند
ز فیض او گرفتم اعتباری
کہ با من ماہ و انجم ساز کردند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مجھ پر دل کے دروازے کھول دیے گئے ؛ میری خاک سے ایک نیا جہان تعمیر کیا گیا۔
میں نے رومی (رحمتہ الّہ) کے فیض سے وہ مرتبہ پاتا ؛ کہ اب چاند ستارے میری موافقت میں چلتے ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        To me his heart’s door was always ope; from my dust he caused a world’s new hope.
From his grace I got a grace and trust. For me he tamed the Moon and Stars first.*
* Moon and stars here it means the angels of fate (who are the proctors of fate as well) or those who are living heavens became my supporters.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(7)">
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خیالش با مہ و انجم نشیند
نگاہش ن سوی پروین ببیند
دل بیتاب خود را پیش او نہ
دم او رعشہ از سیماب چیند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس کا فکر (بلندی میں) مہ و انجم کا ہم نشین ہے؛ اس کی نگاہ ثریا (جو بلندی کے لیے مشہور ہے) کے اس جانب دیکھتی ہے ۔ 
اپنا دل بےتاب اس کے سامنے پیش کر؛ رومی (رحمتہ الّہ) کا دم پارے سے بے تابی چن لیتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        His thought thus flies with stars and moon rays; his eye thus views beyond milky ways.
Lay thy restive heart at his fluid tune; from his quick silver get a quick calm soon.* 
* If you shake a restive heart it gets content. As such the poet is seeking Rumi’s shaking for a content, peace and tranquility.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(8)">
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ز رومی گیر اسرار فقیری 
کہ ن فقر است محسود امیری
حذر زان فقر و درویشی کہ از وی
رسیدی بر مقام سر بزیری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        فقیری کے اسرار رومی (رحمتہ الّہ) سے سیکھ؛ اس کے فقر پر امیری رشک کرتی ہے۔
ایسے فقر و درویشی سے بچ؛ جو تجھے عاجزی و درماندگی کے مقام پر پہنچا دے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Take secrets of content from Rumi’s call; that content is envied by rich men all.
Be cautious from content which may take thee, to a place of bow1down and sheer slavery.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(9)">
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خودی تا گشت مہجور خدائی
بہ فقر موخت داب گدائی
ز چشم مست رومی وام کردم
سروری از مقام کبریائی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جب خودی نے خدائی چھوڑ دی، تو اس نے فقر کو گدائی کے آداب سکھائے۔
(مگر) میں نے رومی (رحمتہ الّہ) کی چشم مست سے؛ مقام کبریائی کا سرور قرض لیا ہے (پا لیا ہے)۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When self is deprived from godly tint; the content then gets a beggar’s print.
From Rumi’s drunk eyes I borrowed a trance, to taste a sweet joy of his godly glance.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(10)">
    <Verse ID="37">
      <Text Language="Original">
        می روشن ز تاک من فرو ریخت
خوشا مردی کہ در دامانم ویخت
نصیب از تشی دارم کہ اول
سنائی از دل رومی برانگیخت
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میرے انگور سے روشن شراب ٹپک رہی ہے؛ خوش نصیب ہے وہ شخص جس نے میرا دامن تھام لیا۔
میں نے بھی اس آتش (عشق) سے حصّہ پایا ہے؛ جو سنائی (رحمتہ الّہ) نے پہلے پہل رومی (رحمتہ الّہ) کے دل میں بھڑکائی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        That bright wine scattered from my wineyard; who hung to my shirt, got the lucks award.
To Rumi I owe a share of his flame, which Sinai took first and earned great fame. 
[Translated by Qazi Ahdul Kabir]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>