<Poem ID="63" Name="پھول" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تجھے کیوں فکر ہے اے گل دل صد چاک بلبل کی 
تو اپنے پیرہن کے چاک تو پہلے رفو کر لے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O flower! Why do you care for the nightingale’s wounded heart! First you should darn the slits of your own shirt!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تمنا آبرو کی ہو اگر گلزار ہستی میں 
تو کانٹوں میں الجھ کر زندگی کرنے کی خو کرلے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If you long for respect in the rose garden of existence; you should get accustomed to living entangled in thorns!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        صنوبر باغ میں آزاد بھی ہے، پا بہ گل بھی ہے 
انھی پابندیوں میں حاصل آزادی کو تو کر لے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The juniper in the garden is free as well as chained to the soil; you should acquire freedom within these constraints!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تنک بخشی کو استغنا سے پیغام خجالت دے 
نہ رہ منت کش شبنم نگوں جام وسبو کر لے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        With contentment give message of embarrassment to miserliness: Do not remain obliged to dew, you should empty the cup and the bottle!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہیں یہ شان خودداری، چمن سے توڑ کر تجھ کو 
کوئی دستار میں رکھ لے، کوئی زیب گلو کر لے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It does not befit self respect that being picked from the garden you should be put in some turban or pinned to some collar!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چمن میں غنچہ گل سے یہ کہہ کر اڑ گئی شبنم 
مذاق جور گلچیں ہو تو پیدا رنگ و بو کر لے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The dew disappeared from garden saying to the flower bud: If you love gardener’s oppression, you should create beauty.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اگر منظور ہو تجھ کو خزاں ناآشنا رہنا 
جہان رنگ و بو سے، پہلے قطع آرزو کر لے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If you want to remain unacquainted with autumn; first you should abandon the desire for the beauty’s world.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اسی میں دیکھ، مضمر ہے کمال زندگی تیرا 
جو تجھ کو زینت دامن کوئی آئینہ رو کر لے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Look, in this alone is concealed your life’s perfection! If you should be the decoration of some beauty’s robe!
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>