<Poem ID="09" Name="غزل" BookID="03" BookName="ضربِ کلیم" SectionID="02" SectionName="تعلیم و تربیت">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہ میں اعجمی نہ ہندی، نہ عراقی و حجازی 
کہ خودی سے میں نے سیکھی دوجہاں سے بے نیازی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I don't belong to Fars or Hind, to Iraq or Hejaz don't trace my breed. The Self to me this much has taught spurn both the worlds and pay no heed.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تو مری نظر میں کافر، میں تری نظر میں کافر 
ترا دیں نفس شماری، مرا دیں نفس گدازی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        نفس شماري: سانس گننا۔ 
نفس گدازي: سانس کو گرم کرنا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You are a heathen in my view, the same to you may seem my creed: To count the breath, your Faith and goal, while melting breath my job and deed.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تو بدل گیا تو بہتر کہ بدل گئی شریعت 
کہ موافق تدرواں نہیں دین شاہبازی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تدرواں: چکوروں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your change, no doubt, is good and well, and so your change of Moslem Creed. This Faith is meant for men, like hawks, it suits not pheasants' quivering breed.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ترے دشت و در میں مجھ کو وہ جنوں نظر نہ آیا 
کہ سکھا سکے خرد کو رہ و رسم کارسازی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        رہ و رسم کارسازي: کام سنوارنے والے طریقے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Such passionate Love of God and craze, in wilds and wastes has not caught my sight; whose magic force and rapture great, the faults of reason may set right.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہ جدا رہے نوا گر تب و تاب زندگی سے 
کہ ہلاکی امم ہے یہ طریق نے نوازی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        نوا گر: گانے والا۔ 
ہلاکي امم: قوموں کی حلاکت۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A poet must ne'er keep aloof from noisy fretful stream of life; the bard, who shuns the facts and truths, can't make the nation face its strife.
[Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>