<Poem ID="61" Name="پیوستہ رہ شجر سے، امید بہار رکھ" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ڈالی گئی جو فصل خزاں میں شجر سے ٹوٹ 
ممکن نہیں ہری ہو سحاب بہار سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        REMAIN ATTACHED TO THE TREE KEEP PRING’S EXPECTATION
The branch of the tree which got separated in autumn is not possible to green up with the cloud of spring.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے لازوال عہد خزاں اس کے واسطے 
کچھ واسطہ نہیں ہے اسے برگ و بار سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The autumn season for this branch is ever-lasting; it has no connection with flourishing in the spring.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے تیرے گلستاں میں بھی فصل خزاں کا دور 
خالی ہے جیب گل زر کامل عیار سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        زر کامل عيار: کسوٹی پر پورا اترنے والا سونا؛ کھرا سونا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Autumn season prevails in your rose garden also; the pocket of the rose is devoid of good cash.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جو نغمہ زن تھے خلوت اوراق میں طیور 
رخصت ہوئے ترے شجر سایہ دار سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The birds which were singing in the seclusion of leaves have departed from your shady tree’s leaves.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شاخ بریدہ سے سبق اندوز ہو کہ تو 
ناآشنا ہے قاعدئہ روزگار سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You should learn a lesson from the separated branch as you are unacquainted with the customs of the world.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ملت کے ساتھ رابطہء استوار رکھ 
پیوستہ رہ شجر سے، امید بہار رکھ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Keep very strong communication with the nation; remain attached to the tree and have spring’s expectation! 
(Translated by Dr. M.A.K. Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>