<Poem ID="12" Name="قطعہ" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کل ایک شوریدہ خواب گاہ نبی پہ رو رو کے کہہ رہا تھا 
کہ مصر و ہندوستاں کے مسلم بنائے ملت مٹا رہے ہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        شوريدہ: دیوانہ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Yesterday a desperate Lover was saying with wailing at the Prophet’s tomb: The Egyptian and Indian Muslims dare destroying the Millat’s foundation!
(The reference to Egypt and India is not indicative of this condition being restricted to these two countries. It has been used to meet poetic needs, which implied that the evil practice existed all over the Muslim world.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ زائران حریم مغرب ہزار رہبر بنیں ہمارے 
ہمیں بھلا ان سے واسطہ کیا جو تجھ سے نا آشنا رہے ہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        These pilgrims to the West’s sanctuary may fake our leadership. What bond do we have with those who have remained unacquainted with you?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        غضب ہیں یہ 'مرشدان خود بیں خدا تری قوم کو بچائے! 
بگاڑ کر تیرے مسلموں کو یہ اپنی عزت بنا رہے ہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مرشدان خود بيں: صرف اپنی عزّت اور نفع پر نظر رکھنے والے راہنما۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Outrageous are these ‘self-seeking spiritual leaders’. May God protect your Millat! They are promoting their own glory by destroying the Muslims.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سنے گا اقبال کون ان کو، یہ انجمن ہی بدل گئی ہے 
نئے زمانے میں آپ ہم کو پرانی باتیں سنا رہے ہیں !
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O Iqbal who would listen to you, the congregation has changed. You are telling us these tales of the old in the new age.
[Translated by Dr M A K Khalil]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>