<Poem ID="59" Name="مرد مسلمان" BookID="03" BookName="ضربِ کلیم" SectionID="01" SectionName="اسلام اور مسلمان">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہرلحظہ ہے مومن کی نئی شان، نئی آن 
گفتار میں، کردار میں، اللہ کی برہان!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        برہان: نشان، حجت۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A MUSLIM
A Muslim true gets grandeur new with moment's change and every hour; by words and deeds he gives a proof of Mighty God, His reach and power.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        قہاری و غفاری و قدوسی و جبروت 
یہ چار عناصر ہوں تو بنتا ہے مسلمان
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        قہاری: جس سے دشمن ڈر جائے ۔ 
غفار: بادشاہ، خطا کاروں سے درگزر کرنے والا۔ 
قدوسی: کردار کی پاکیزگی والا۔ 
جبروت: عظمت اور بزرگی والا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        To rout the foes, to grant them reprieve, do pious deeds and show great might are four ingredients that make a Muslim Devout who shuns not fight.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہمسایہء جبریل امیں بندئہ خاکی 
ہے اس کا نشیمن نہ بخارا نہ بدخشان
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        With Gabriel trusted and steadfast this clay-born man has kinship close, a dwelling in some land or clime for himself Muslim never chose.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ راز کسی کو نہیں معلوم کہ مومن 
قاری نظر آتا ہے، حقیقت میں ہے قرآن!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This secret yet none has grasped that Muslim Scripture reads so sweet practising rules by it prescribed, becomes its pattern quite complete.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        قدرت کے مقاصد کا عیار اس کے ارادے 
دنیا میں بھی میزان، قیامت میں بھی میزان
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Faithful acts on aims and ends that Nature keeps before its sight in world he sifts the good and bad, in future shall judge wrong and right.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جس سے جگر لالہ میں ٹھنڈک ہو، وہ شبنم 
دریاوں کے دل جس سے دہل جائیں، وہ طوفان
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        While dealing with friends and mates, he is dew that thirst of tulip slakes: When engaged with his foes in fight, like torrent strong makes rivers shake.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فطرت کا سرود ازلی اس کے شب و روز 
آہنگ میں یکتا صفت سورئہ رحمن
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The charm of Nature's eternal song in Muslim's life, no doubt is found like chapter Rahman of the Koran, is full of sweet melodious sound.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بنتے ہیں مری کارگہ فکر میں انجم 
لے اپنے مقدر کے ستارے کو تو پہچان
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Such thoughts that shine like lustrous stars my brain, like workshop, can provide, you can select the star you like, so that your Fate this star may guide.
(Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>