<Poem ID="46" Name="تہذیب حاضر" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="تضمین بر شعر فیضی">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حرارت ہے بلاکی بادئہ تہذیب حاضر میں 
بھڑک اٹھا بھبوکا بن کے مسلم کا تن خاکی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        بادئہ تہذیب حاضر: موجودہ تہذیب کی شراب۔ 
بھبوکا بن کے: شعلہ بن کر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE PRESENT CIVILIZATION
(Based on a Verse of Faizi)

Extremely excessive is the heat of current civilization’s wine; the clay body of the Muslim has exploded into flames.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کیا ذرے کو جگنو دے کے تاب مستعار اس نے 
کوئی دیکھے تو شوخی آفتاب جلوہ فرما کی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تاب مستعار: مانگی ہوئی روشنی ؛ عارضی چمک۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It made the speck into fire-fly by giving it borrowed light; just look at what the trickery of the splendid sun is.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نئے انداز پائے نوجوانوں کی طبیعت نے 
یہ رعنائی، یہ بیداری، یہ آزادی، یہ بے باکی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The nature of the young generation has found new ways: This beauty, this alertness, this freedom, this fearlessness.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تغیر آگیا ایسا تدبر میں، تخیل میں 
ہنسی سمجھی گئی گلشن میں غنچوں کی جگر چاکی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Such a change has come about in planning and thought; bursting of the garden’s flower-buds in Love is considered trivial.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کیا گم تازہ پروازوں نے اپنا آشیاں لیکن 
مناظر دلکشا دکھلا گئی ساحر کی چالاکی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ساحر: جادوگر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The newly flying birds have lost their nests but a pretty sight has been shown by magician’s cunningness.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حیات تازہ اپنے ساتھ لائی لذتیں کیا کیا 
رقابت، خودفروشی، ناشکیبائی، ہوسناکی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The new life brought with it ever changing pleasures: Rivalry, selling conscience, impatience, greed.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فروغ شمع نو سے بزم مسلم جگمگا اٹھی 
مگر کہتی ہے پروانوں سے میری کہنہ ادراکی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کہنہ ادراکی: پختہ سمجھ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Muslim’s assembly is glittering with the new candle’s light, but my old time wisdom is saying this to the moths:
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تو اے پروانہ ! ایں گرمی ز شمع محفلے داری 
چو من در آتش خود سوز اگر سوز دلے داری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اے پروانے تو نے یہ گرمی محفل کی شمع سے لی ہے؛ اگر دل میں سوز ہے تو میری طرح اپنی آگ میں جلنا سیکھ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ‘O moth! You have derived this warmth from the assembly’s candle: Burn in your own fire like me if you have the warmth of the heart. 
[Translated by M.A.K.Khalil]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>