<Poem ID="39" Name="ترانہء ہندی" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="1a" SectionName="حصہ اول">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سارے جہاں سے اچھا ہندوستاں ہمارا
ہم بلبلیں ہیں اس کی، یہ گلستاں ہمارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        AN ODE TO INDIA
Better than the whole world is this India of ours. We are its nightingales; it is the garden of ours.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        غربت میں ہوں اگر ہم، رہتا ہے دل وطن میں
سمجھو وہیں ہمیں بھی، دل ہو جہاں ہمارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        غربت: سفر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If we are in foreign lands our hearts think of the homeland; consider us present where this heart of ours is present.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پربت وہ سب سے اونچا، ہمسایہ آسماں کا
وہ سنتری ہمارا، وہ پاسباں ہمارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        سنتري: چوکیدار۔
پربت: پہاڑ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The highest mountain, touching the sky; it is our sentinel, it is our watchman.*
* Allusion to the Himalayan Range.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گودی میں کھیلتی ہیں اس کی ہزاروں ندیاں
گلشن ہے جن کے دم سے رشک جناں ہمارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        رشک جناں: جنت سے بڑھ کر خوبصورت ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Thousands of rivers are playing in its lap are playing which make this garden of ours to be the world’s envy.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے آب رود گنگا، وہ دن ہیں یاد تجھ کو؟
اترا ترے کنارے جب کارواں ہمارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        آب رود گنگا: دریائے گنگا کا پانی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O, The River Ganga’s waters! Do you remember the day when our caravan landed at your banks.*
* Allusion to the arrival of Muslims in India: Unlike the British the Muslims settled in the Indian sub continent and made it their homeland, which establishes their claim to settle the political problems of India with due regard to their interests.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مذہب نہیں سکھاتا آپس میں بیر رکھنا
ہندی ہیں ہم وطن ہے ہندوستاں ہمارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Religion does not teach hostility with each other, we are Indians, India is our homeland.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یونان و مصر و روما سب مٹ گئے جہاں سے
اب تک مگر ہے باقی نام و نشاں ہمارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Greece, Egypt, Rome are all extinct from the world, but our renown and fame have continued so far.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کچھ بات ہے کہ ہستی مٹتی نہیں ہماری
صدیوں رہا ہے دشمن دور زماں ہمارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        دور زماں: زمانے کی گردش۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        There is some secret that our existence is not effaced; for centuries time's vicissitudes have been our foe.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اقبال! کوئی محرم اپنا نہیں جہاں میں
معلوم کیا کسی کو درد نہاں ہمارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        درد نہاں: چھپا ہوا درد۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Iqbal! In the world there is no confidante of ours: How would anyone know the hidden pathos of ours.* 
* Allusion to the callousness of the world community to the calamity of the people of the Indian sub continent resulting from their political subjugation by the British.) 
(Translated by M.A.K. Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>