<Poem ID="03" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="01" SectionName="حصہ اول">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گیسوئے تاب دار کو اور بھی تاب دار کر 
ہوش و خرد شکار کر، قلب و نظر شکار کر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Bright are Thy tresses, brighten them even more, and ravish my eyes, ravish my mind, ravish my heart and soul.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عشق بھی ہو حجاب میں، حسن بھی ہو حجاب میں 
یا تو خود آشکار ہو یا مجھے آشکار کر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        That love should be concealed, and beauty should be veiled! Reveal Thyself to me, O Lord, or reveal me to myself.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تو ہے محیط بے کراں، میں ہوں ذرا سی آبجو 
یا مجھے ہمکنار کر یا مجھے بے کنار کر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Thou art the eternal ocean; I am a rivulet; make me a part of Thee, O Lord, or make me fathomless.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میں ہوں صدف تو تیرے ہاتھ میرے گہر کی آبرو 
میں ہوں خزف تو تو مجھے گوہر شاہوار کر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If I possess a pearl within, give it a starry lustre, but if I am a piece of brick, give it a diamond’s sheen.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نغمہء نو بہار اگر میرے نصیب میں نہ ہو 
اس دم نیم سوز کو طائرک بہار کر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If of spring I cannot sing as a bird of paradise; make this half-enrapturcd soul a skylark of Thy spring.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        باغ بہشت سے مجھے حکم سفر دیا تھا کیوں 
کار جہاں دراز ہے، اب مرا انتظار کر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Why did You order me to quit the Garden of Eden? Now there is much to be done here, so just wait for me!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        روز حساب جب مرا پیش ہو دفتر عمل 
آپ بھی شرمسار ہو، مجھ کو بھی شرمسار کر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When the roll of my deeds is brought up on the Day of Reckoning; be ashamed as You will shame me. 
[Translated by Naim Siddiqui]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>