<Poem ID="23" Name="غرہ شوال یا ہلال عید" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        غرہء شوال! اے نور نگاہ روزہ دار 
آ کہ تھے تیرے لیے مسلم سراپا انتظار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        غرہء شوال: شوال کے مہینے کا ہلال۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O the pride of Shawwal! O the fasting person’s darling! Come! As Muslims were very anxiously waiting for you.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تیری پیشانی پہ تحریر پیام عید ہے 
شام تیری کیا ہے، صبح عیش کی تمید ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The message of Eid is written on your forehead; your evening is the preface to the dawn of pleasure.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سرگزشت ملت بیضا کا تو آئینہ ہے 
اے مہ نو! ہم کو تجھ سے الفت دیرینہ ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You are the mirror of the history of Millat-i-Baidah. O crescent! We are your lovers since a very long time.
(Millat-i-Baidah: Allusion to the egg-shaped radiant mark on the palm of S. Messiah A.S., which was bestowed on him by God (The Holy Qur’an 7: 108). ‘Allamah Iqbal calls the Muslim Ummah as ‘Millat-i-Baidah’ because he is confident of the rise of Islam in the world.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جس علم کے سائے میں تیغ آزما ہوتے تھے ہم 
دشمنوں کے خون سے رنگیں قبا ہوتے تھے ہم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The banner under whose shade we wielded our swords; under whose shade we used the blood of our enemies.
(The banner: Allusion to the inclusion of the crescent on the flags of Muslim countries as an insignia of Islam and its rising power.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تیری قسمت میں ہم آغوشی اسی رایت کی ہے 
حسن روز افزوں سے تیرے آبرو ملت کی ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        رايت: جھنڈا۔ 
حسن روز افزوں: ہر روز بڑھتی ہوئی خوبصورتی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The companionship of this very banner is your destiny; the Millat’s honor is by your ever-increasing beauty.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آشنا پرور ہے قوم اپنی، وفا آئیں ترا 
ہے محبت خیز یہ پیراہن سیمیں ترا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        پيراہن سيميں: چاندی جیسا لباس۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Our nation is cherisher of friends, fidelity is your way; this silvery shirt of yours is the propagator of love.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اوج گردوں سے ذرا دنیا کی بستی دیکھ لے 
اپنی رفعت سے ہمارے گھر کی پستی دیکھ لے !
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Look at the earth’s habitation from your celestial apses! Look at the depth of our abode from your eminence!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        قافلے دیکھ اور ان کی برق رفتاری بھی دیکھ 
رہر و درماندہ کی منزل سے بیزاری بھی دیکھ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Look at the caravans and also look at their fast speed; at the destitute traveler’s estrangement with destination also look.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دیکھ کر تجھ کو افق پر ہم لٹاتے تھے گہر 
اے تہی ساغر! ہماری آج ناداری بھی دیکھ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        On sighting you we used to give charity lavishly; O empty cup! Today at our indigence also look.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فرقہ آرائی کی زنجیروں میں ہیں مسلم اسیر 
اپنی آزادی بھی دیکھ، ان کی گرفتاری بھی دیکھ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Muslims are tightly bound in chains of sectarianism; look at your freedom and at their bondage also look.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دیکھ مسجد میں شکست رشتہ تسبیح شیخ 
بت کدے میں برہمن کی پختہ زناری بھی دیکھ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        پختہ زناري: مراد ہے مذہب کا پکا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In the mosque look at disintegration of the priest’s love; in the temple at the Brahman’s strong idol-worship also look.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کافروں کی مسلم آئینی کا بھی نظارہ کر
اور اپنے مسلموں کی مسلم آزاری بھی دیکھ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Look at the sight of the Muslim ways in the infidels’ life; and at your Muslims’ tormenting other Muslims also look.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بارش سنگ حوادث کا تماشائی بھی ہو 
امت مرحوم کی آئینہ دیواری بھی دیکھ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        حوادث: حادثہ کی جمع۔ 
ينہ ديواري: آئینہ کی دیوار کی طرح کمزور ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Be the spectator of the shower of rocks of misfortunes; at the frailty of the Muslims Ummah’s abodes also look.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہاں، تملق پیشگی دیکھ آبرو والوں کی تو
اور جو بے آبرو تھے، ان کی خود داری بھی دیکھ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تملق پيشگي: پہلے سے خوشامد۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Yes, look at the advance flattery of the ‘honorable’ people and at the self-respect of the formerly shameless people also look.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جس کو ہم نے آشنا لطف تکلم سے کیا 
اس حریف بے زباں کی گرم گفتاری بھی دیکھ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Whom we got acquainted with the taste of eloquence at the haughty speech of that former speechless adversary look.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="31">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ساز عشرت کی صدا مغرب کے ایوانوں میں سن 
اور ایراں میں ذرا ماتم کی تیاری بھی دیکھ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Listen to sounds of pleasurable orchestra in West’s palaces and at the preparations for the mourning in Iran also look (allusion to the poor condition of Iran at that time).
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چاک کر دی ترک ناداں نے خلافت کی قبا 
سادگی مسلم کی دیکھ، اوروں کی عیاری بھی دیکھ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The imprudent Turk has torn the cloak of the Divine Khilafah; look at Muslims’ simplicity at other’s cunningness also look.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="35">
      <Text Language="Original">
        صورت آئینہ سب کچھ دیکھ اور خاموش رہ
شورش امروز میں محو سرود دوش رہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        شورش امروز:آج کا ہنگامہ۔ 
سرود دوش: گزرے کل کا گیت۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Look at everything, and remain quiet like a mirror; in today tumult remain occupied in evening’s music!
[Translated by Dr M A K Khalil]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>