<Poem ID="16" Name="عشرت امروز" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="2a" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہ مجھ سے کہہ کہ اجل ہے پیام عیش و سرور 
نہ کھینچ نقشہ کیفیت شراب طہور
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You should not tell me, ‘Death is a message of luxury and pleasure’; You should not draw the picture of Sharab-i-Tuhoor's* ecstasy.
(Sharab-i-Tuhoor: This is the holy beverage, or wine of Paradise which, according to the Holy Qur’an is free from the evils of the earthly wines – 47:15; 76:21; 78:35 and 83:25 28.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فراق حور میں ہو غم سے ہمکنار نہ تو 
پری کو شیشہ الفاظ میں اتار نہ تو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Do not feel grieved by separation from the Houri; do not present the Houri in the mirror of words.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مجھے فریفتہ ساقی جمیل نہ کر 
بیان حور نہ کر، ذکر سلسبیل نہ کر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Do not make me fascinated by the beautiful cup bearer; do not describe the Houri, do not relate the Salsabil’s* story’
* One of the streams of Paradise.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مقام امن ہے جنت، مجھے کلام نہیں 
شباب کے لیے موزوں ترا پیام نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I do not doubt Paradise being the place of peace; your message is not proper for the life's prime!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شباب، آہ! کہاں تک امیدوار رہے 
وہ عیش، عیش نہیں، جس کا انتظار رہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Ah! How long should youth linger in hope; joy is not joy for which you remain waiting.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وہ حسن کیا جو محتاج چشم بینا ہو 
نمود کے لیے منت پذیر فردا ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What worth is the beauty which is in need of the discerning eye; which is obligated for the tomorrow for its manifestation?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عجیب چیز ہے احساس زندگانی کا 
عقیدہ 'عشرت امروز' ہے جوانی کا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Strange is the feeling for life: ‘Today's joy’ is the belief of youth.
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>