<Poem ID="42" Name="تضمین بر شعر ابوطالب کلیم" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خوب ہے تجھ کو شعار صاحب ثیرب کا پاس 
کہہ رہی ہے زندگی تیری کہ تو مسلم نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        صاحب ثيرب: محمد (صلعم)
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE POEM BASED ON A VERSE OF ABU TALIB KALIM
Your regard for the ways of the Lord of Yathrib is strange; your life is exhibiting that you are not a Muslim.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جس سے تیرے حلقہء خاتم میں گردوں تھا اسیر 
اے سلیماں! تیری غفلت نے گنوایا وہ نگیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        حلقہء خاتم: انگوٹھی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What made heavens contained in your ring’s circle? O Sulaiman (A.S.)! That jewel is lost by your negligence!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وہ نشان سجدہ جو روشن تھا کوکب کی طرح 
ہوگئی ہے اس سے اب ناآشنا تیری جبیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        That mark of prostration which used to shine like a star; your forehead has now become unacquainted with that mark!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دیکھ تو اپنا عمل، تجھ کو نظر آتی ہے کیا 
وہ صداقت جس کی بے باکی تھی حیرت آفریں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Just look at your actions, do you envisage that candor whose fearlessness was always wonderful.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تیرے آبا کی نگہ بجلی تھی جس کے واسطے 
ہے وہی باطل ترے کاشانہء دل میں مکیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your ancestors’ eye was the thunderbolt for falsehood; the same falsehood is now lodged in your breast.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        غافل! اپنے آشیاں کو آ کے پھر آباد کر 
نغمہ زن ہے طور معنی پر کلیم نکتہ بیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O negligent one come and inhabit in your abode again; the discerning Kalim is singing on the spiritual Toor.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سرکشی باہر کہ کردی رام او باید شدن، 
شعلہ ساں از ہر کجا برخاستی، آنجانشیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تو نے جس سے بغاوت کی اب پھر اس کی اطاعت کر لے، تو جس مقام سے شعلے کی طرح بلند ہوا تھا پھر اسی پر مرتکز ہو جا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ‘You must be subservient to whom you had become rebellious: From wherever you departed like flame, turn back to it.’
[Translated by Dr M A K Khalil]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>