<Poem ID="03" Name="تمہید" BookID="03" BookName="ضربِ کلیم" SectionID="00" SectionName="ابتدا">
  <Para Name="(1)">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہ دیر میں نہ حرم میں خودی کی بیداری 
کہ خاوراں میں ہے قوموں کی روح تریاکی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تریاکی: افیون۔ 
خاوراں : ایشیا کی قومیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE PROLOGUE
In fane and shrine the self in slumber deep is sunk, it seems that soul of East an opiate strong has drunk.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اگر نہ سہل ہوں تجھ پر زمیں کے ہنگامے 
بری ہے مستی اندیشہ ہائے افلاکی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If freaks of fate with smile on lips you can not face, the secrets hid in firmament n're claim to trace.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تری نجات غم مرگ سے نہیں ممکن 
کہ تو خودی کو سمجھتا ہے پیکر خاکی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your anguish sharp for Death you can not keep at bay, because you deem that Self is merely made of clay.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زمانہ اپنے حوادث چھپا نہیں سکتا 
ترا حجاب ہے قلب و نظر کی ناپاکی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Time can conceal mishaps at all from you, Alas! Your heart and soul are foul and are not true.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عطا ہوا خس و خاشاک ایشیا مجھ کو 
کہ میرے شعلے میں ہے سرکشی و بے باکی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The straws and thorns of East to me have been assigned, for flame that burns in me is rash and unconfined. 
(Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(2)">
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ترا گناہ ہے اقبال! مجلس آرائی 
اگرچہ تو ہے مثال زمانہ کم پیوند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Iqbal, you sin because the throngs you tingle though keep aloof and seldom with them mingle.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جو کوکنار کے خوگر تھے، ان غریبوں کو 
تری نوا نے دیا ذوق جذبہ ہائے بلند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Men wont to qaff extract from poppies drawn, have courage gained for deeds requiring brawn.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تڑپ رہے ہیں فضاہائے نیلگوں کے لیے 
وہ پر شکستہ کہ صحن سرا میں تھے خورسند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The birds, who spite of pinions rent were glad, in nests, for azure sky now feel so sad.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تری سزا ہے نوائے سحر سے محرومی 
مقام شوق و سرور و نظر سے محرومی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You ought to be deprived of songs of morn, deserve to miss delight and feel forlorn.
(Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>