<Poem ID="24" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="02" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خرد کے پاس خبر کے سوا کچھ اور نہیں 
ترا علاج نظر کے سوا کچھ اور نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The mind can give you naught, but what with doubt is fraught: One look of Saintly Guide can needful cure provide.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہر اک مقام سے آگے مقام ہے تیرا 
حیات ذوق سفر کے سوا کچھ اور نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The goal that you presume is far and out of view: What else can be this life but zeal for endless strife?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گراں بہا ہے تو حفظ خودی سے ہے ورنہ 
گہر میں آب گہر کے سوا کچھ اور نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Much worth the pearl begets, for guard on self it sets: What else in pearl is found except its sheen profound?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رگوں میں گردش خوں ہے اگر تو کیا حاصل 
حیات سوز جگر کے سوا کچھ اور نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Though blood in veins may race, to Life it lends no grace: Only the glow of heart to Life can zeal impart.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عروس لالہ! مناسب نہیں ہے مجھ سے حجاب 
کہ میں نسیم سحر کے سوا کچھ اور نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Wherefore, O Tulip Bride, from me your charms you hide? I am the breath of morn, your face I would adorn.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جسے کساد سمجھتے ہیں تاجران فرنگ 
وہ شے متاع ہنر کے سوا کچھ اور نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کساد:بے رونقی، بے رواجی، کاروبار کا مندہ پڑ جانا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What Frankish dealers take for counterfeit and fake, is true and real art – not valued in their Mart.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بڑا کریم ہے اقبال بے نوا لیکن 
عطائے شعلہ شرر کے سوا کچھ اور نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Though indigent I be, I am of hand yet free: What can the Flame bestow except its spark and glow? 
(Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>