<Poem ID="08" Name="اے فرزند صحرا" BookID="11" BookName="ارمغانِ حجاز" SectionID="03" SectionName="حضور ملت">
  <Para Name="(1)">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سحرگاہان کہ روشن شد در و دشت
صدا زد مرغی از شاخ نخیلی
فروھل خیمہ اے فرزند صحرا
کہ نتوان زیست بے ذوق رحیلی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        صبح کے وقت جب آبادی و صحرا میں روشنی پھیل گئی؛ تو درخت کی شاخ سے پرندے نے آواز دی: 
اے فرزند صحرا! خیمہ چھوڑ ! ذوق سفر کے بغیر کوئی زندگی نہیں ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O SON OF THE DESERT
When all the desert sides were bright from dawn; from tree a bird tuned to a youth in lawn.
O desert’s son! Leave thy tent with haste; you lead a dull life which lacks journey taste.
(In the above three quatrains (twin couplets) the poet has addressed an immaculate son of the desert, a young Muslim, free from the impure taints of city life. In the next couplets he has addressed the upper strata, the intellectuals, the teachers and philosophers of the desert land.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(2)">
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عرب را حق دلیل کاروان کرد
کہ او با فقر خود را امتحان کرد
اگر فقر تہی دستان غیور است
جہانے را تہ و بالا توان کرد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        (قرون اولی میں) اللہ تعالے نے عرب کو قافلے کا سالار بنایا؛ کیونکہ اس نے فقر کے ذریعہ اپنے آپ کو آزمایا۔
اگر بے مایہ لوگوں کا طریقہ غیور ہو ؛ تو اس سے ساری دنیا کو تہ و بالا کیا جا سکتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Truth chose Arab for caravan’s lead; on faqr since he tested his own self’s breed.
If the poor’s content with envy is green*; his growth can upset the whole world’s scene.
* Here green means flourishing, in ‘figurative’ sense. It means full of vigour as we say (keep a man’s memory green). He lives to a green old age, although looking green with envy also means pale or sickly looking.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(3)">
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        در ن شبہا خروش صبح فرداست
کہ روشن از تجلیہای سیناست
تن و جان محکم از باد در و دشت
طلوع امتان از کوہ و صحراست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        صحرا کی راتوں میں آنے والی صبح کا غلغلہ ہے؛ کیونکہ یہ راتیں سینا کی تجلیات سے منوّر ہیں۔
کوہ و صحرا کی ہوا بدن اور روح دونوں کو محکم کرتی ہے؛ (یہی وجہ ہے کہ) نئی امتوں کا ظہور کوہ و صحرا سے ہوتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Those nights had the uproar for future’s dawn; being lit up with light of the Sinai’s lawn.
Thus the desert life made their brawns and brains; arid nations arose Crom those desert lanes.
[Translated by Qazi Ahdul Kabir]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>