<Poem ID="42" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="02" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خودی ہو علم سے محکم تو غیرت جبریل 
اگر ہو عشق سے محکم تو صور اسرافیل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If self with knowledge strong becomes, Gabriel it can envious make: If fortified with passion great, like trump of Israfil can shake.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عذاب دانش حاضر سے باخبر ہوں میں 
کہ میں اس آگ میں ڈالا گیا ہوں مثل خلیل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The scourge of present science and thought, to me, no doubt, is fully known, like Abraham, the Friend of God, in its flame I have been thrown.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فریب خوردہ منزل ہے کارواں ورنہ 
زیادہ راحت منزل سے ہے نشاط رحیل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        رحيل:کوچ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The caravan in quest of goal by charm of lodge is led astray, though never can the ease of lodge be same as joy to be on way.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نظر نہیں تو مرے حلقہ سخن میں نہ بیٹھ 
کہ نکتہ ہائے خودی ہیں مثال تیغ اصیل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تيغ اصيل:جوہر دار تلوار؛ یعنی تیز دھار تلوار،
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If seeing eye you do not own, among my listeners do not pause, for subtle points about the self, like sword, deep yawning wounds can cause.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مجھے وہ درس فرنگ آج یاد آتے ہیں 
کہاں حضور کی لذت، کہاں حجاب دلیل!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Still to mind I can recall, in Europe what I learnt by heart: But can the veil of Reason match with joy that Presence can import.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اندھیری شب ہے، جدا اپنے قافلے سے ہے تو 
ترے لیے ہے مرا شعلہ نوا، قندیل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        From caravan you are adrift, and night has donned a mantle black: For you my song that burns as flame, like a torch, can light the track.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        غریب و سادہ و رنگیں ہے داستان حرم 
نہایت اس کی حسین، ابتدا ہے اسمعیل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The tale of the Holy Shrine, if told, is simple, strange and red in hue: With Ismail the tale begins, ends with Husain, the martyr true.
(Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>