<Poem ID="08" Name="مسجد قوت الاسلام" BookID="03" BookName="ضربِ کلیم" SectionID="04" SectionName="ادبیات فنون لطیفہ">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے مرے سینہ بے نور میں اب کیا باقی 
'لاالہ' مردہ و افسردہ و بے ذوق نمود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        بے ذوق نمود: اظہار کے ذوق کا نہ ہونا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Now naught remains in Muslim's breast, his heart devoid of glint and glow: He avowed with zeal 'No God but He', but dead and cold the zeal for show.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چشم فطرت بھی نہ پہچان سکے گی مجھ کو 
کہ ایازی سے دگرگوں ہے مقام محمود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        دگرگوں: منتشر۔
ايازي: غلامی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Muslim's state has so declined that Nature fails to know at sight, because the slavish acts of Ayaz have put Mahmud's high rank in plight.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کیوں مسلماں نہ خجل ہو تری سنگینی سے 
کہ غلامی سے ہوا مثل زجاج اس کا وجود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مثل زجاج: شیشے کی مانند۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You have withstood the ruin of Time and kept your ground as firm as rock. Constraint has turned the Muslims weak; you put them all to shame and shock.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے تری شان کے شایاں اسی مومن کی نماز 
جس کی تکبیر میں ہو معرکہ بود و نبود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        بود و نبود: ہستی و نیستی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The worship of such Muslims suits your structure immense and so vast, who with one breath that God is Great; found truth and lies away are cast.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اب کہاں میرے نفس میں وہ حرارت، وہ گداز 
بے تب و تاب دروں میری صلوہ اور درود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        بے تب و تاب دروں: اندرونی تڑپ اور گرمی کے بغیر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Muslim's breast is quite bereft of previous heat and ardour strong; his blessings, worship are devoid of innate heat and fret since long.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے مری بانگ اذاں میں نہ بلندی، نہ شکوہ 
کیا گوارا ہے تجھے ایسے مسلماں کا سجود؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        شکوہ: دبدبہ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        His call to prayer is devoid of lofty tones and grandeur great; O God, let this be known to him, will you let him 'fore you prostrate?
[Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>