<Poem ID="33" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="02" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خردمندوں سے کیا پوچھوں کہ میری ابتدا کیا ہے 
کہ میں اس فکر میں رہتا ہوں، میری انتہا کیا ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What should I ask the sages about my origin: I am always wanting to know my goal.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خودی کو کر بلند اتنا کہ ہر تقدیر سے پہلے 
خدا بندے سے خود پوچھے، بتا تیری رضا کیا ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Develop the self so that before every decree God will ascertain from you: ‘What is your wish?’
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مقام گفتگو کیا ہے اگر میں کیمیا گرہوں 
یہی سوز نفس ہے، اور میری کیمیا کیا ہے!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It is nothing to talk about if I transform base selves into gold: The passion of my voice is the only alchemy I know!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نظر آئیں مجھے تقدیر کی گہرائیاں اس میں 
نہ پوچھ اے ہم نشیں مجھ سے وہ چشم سرمہ سا کیا ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O Comrade, I beheld the secrets of Destiny in them: What should I tell you of those lustrous eyes!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اگر ہوتا وہ مجذوب فرنگی اس زمانے میں 
تو اقبال اس کو سمجھاتا مقام کبریا کیا ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Only if that majzub* of the West were living in these times, Iqbal could have explained to him the ‘I am.’

* Allusion to Nietzsche: the famous self-absorbed German philosopher who could not interpret his inner experience correctly and was therefore misled by his philosophical thoughts.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نواے صبح گاہی نے جگر خوں کر دیا میرا 
خدایا جس خطا کی یہ سزا ہے، وہ خطا کیا ہے!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My heart bleeds from the song of the early morning: O Lord! What is the sin for which this is a punishment?
[Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>