<Poem ID="51" Name="نانک" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        قوم نے پیغام گو تم کی ذرا پروا نہ کی 
قدر پہچانی نہ اپنے گوہر یک دانہ کی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        گوہر يک دانہ: بے مثال موتی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The nation did not care for the message of Gautam at all; the value of its own single pearl* it did not appreciate at all.
* In the Urdu and Persian literary works a belief is expressed that pearls are formed in the oyster shell by the spring rain drops. If the shell is contented with one drop only one pearl is formed. Such a pearl is larger in size and superior in brightness than those of the shells with many pearls.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آہ! بد قسمت رہے آواز حق سے بے خبر 
غافل اپنے پھل کی شیرینی سے ہوتا ہے شجر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Ah! The unfortunate nation remained unaware of the call of the Truth; the tree is unaware of the sweetness of its own fruit.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آشکار اس نے کیا جو زندگی کا راز تھا 
ہند کو لیکن خیالی فلسفے پر ناز تھا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He exhibited whatever the secret of life was, but India proud of its visionary philosophy was.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شمع حق سے جو منور ہو یہ وہ محفل نہ تھی 
بارش رحمت ہوئی لیکن زمیں قابل نہ تھی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The assembly which could be illuminated by Truth’s light was not this; the rain of mercy did come but the soil was not suitable!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آہ! شودر کے لیے ہندوستاں غم خانہ ہے 
درد انسانی سے اس بستی کا دل بیگانہ ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Ah! India is a place of sorrow for the Shudra; this habitation’s heart is unaware of human sympathy.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        برہمن سرشار ہے اب تک مےء پندار میں 
شمع گوتم جل رہی ہے محفل اغیار میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        شمع گوتم: مراد ہے بدھ مت۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Brahman is still intoxicated with the wine of arrogance; Gautam’s candle is alight in the assembly of strangers.*
* Allusion to the fact that on account of the atrocities perpetrated by Hindus on the Buddhists in the Indian Sub-continent. Buddhism all but disappeared from that region by about the commencement of the Christian era. However, the Buddhists migrated to the neighboring countries of Ceylon (present day Sri Lanka), Burma, Malaya, China and Japan, where it flourished and still exists.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بت کدہ پھر بعد مدت کے مگر روشن ہوا 
نور ابراہیم سے آزر کا گھر روشن ہوا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        However, the temple again became lighted after eons; the house of Azar became lighted with Ibrahim’s light.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پھر اٹھی آخر صدا توحید کی پنجاب سے 
ہند کو اک مرد کامل نے جگایا خواب سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مرد کامل: مراد ہے گورو نانک۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        At last the call of Tawhid rose from the Punjab again! A perfect man roused India from its slumber again! 
(Translated by M.A.K. Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>