<Poem ID="47" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="02" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یوں ہاتھ نہیں آتا وہ گوہر یک دانہ 
یک رنگی و آزادی اے ہمت مردانہ!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O manly heart, the goal you seek is hard to gain like gem unique: Get firm resolve and freedom true, if aim of life you wish to woo.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یا سنجر و طغرل کا آئین جہاں گیری 
یا مرد قلندر کے انداز ملوکانہ!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Like Sanjar great and Tughral just to rule and conquer learn you must: Or like a qalandar true and bold the wont and way of monarch hold.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یا حیرت فارابی یا تاب و تب رومی 
یا فکر حکیمانہ یا جذب کلیمانہ!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Farabi’s thirst for lore beget, or Rumi’s fever great and fret: You need a thinker’s lofty gaze, or Moses’ passion to amaze.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یا عقل کی روباہی یا عشق ید اللہی 
یا حیلہ افرنگی یا حملہ ترکانہ!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Learn the wolfish tricks and guile, be like Franks in wit and wile: Else own the passion of God’s Hand, or strike the foes like Tartar band.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یا شرع مسلمانی یا دیر کی دربانی 
یا نعرہ مستانہ، کعبہ ہو کہ بت خانہ!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Act on Muslim law and rites, or sit in fane like acolytes: Be it the Shrine or temple high, ever like a drunkard cry.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میری میں فقیری میں، شاہی میں غلامی میں 
کچھ کام نہیں بنتا بے جرأت رندانہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In whatsoever state you be, a fettered thrall or monarch free: No wonder ever can be wrought, with Love, if courage be not fraught.
(Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>