<Poem ID="02" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="01" SectionName="حصہ اول">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اگر کج رو ہیں انجم، آسماں تیرا ہے یا میرا 
مجھے فکر جہاں کیوں ہو، جہاں تیرا ہے یا میرا؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کج رو: ٹیڑھا چلنا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If the stars are astray, the heavens are Thine, not mine. Why should I fret about the world? The world is Thine, not mine.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اگر ہنگامہ ہائے شوق سے ہے لامکاں خالی 
خطا کس کی ہے یا رب! لامکاں تیرا ہے یا میرا؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If Thy world is cold, devoid of the warmth of passion; whose fault is it, my Lord? That world is Thine, not mine.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اسے صبح ازل انکار کی جرات ہوئی کیونکر 
مجھے معلوم کیا، وہ راز داں تیرا ہے یا میرا؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        How dared he defy Thee, at the dawn of life? It was he who was Thy confidant; it is Thy secret, not mine.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        محمد بھی ترا، جبریل بھی، قرآن بھی تیرا 
مگر یہ حرف شیریں ترجماں تیرا ہے یا میرا؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        حرف شيريں: میٹھے الفاظ، اشارہ ہے اپنی شاعری کی طرف۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The apostle is Thine, and Gabriel, and so is the Holy Word, but whose life does the Holy Word concern? Is it Thine or mine?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اسی کوکب کی تابانی سے ہے تیرا جہاں روشن 
زوال آدم خاکی زیاں تیرا ہے یا میرا؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اسي کوکب: اسی ستارے، مراد ہے انسان۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Man is the star that brightens Thy lonely, desolate world; will the eclipse of this star be a loss of Thine or mine?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ترے شیشے میں مے باقی نہیں ہے 
بتا، کیا تو مرا ساقی نہیں ہے 
سمندر سے ملے پیاسے کو شبنم 
بخیلی ہے یہ رزاقی نہیں ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        All potent wine is emptied of Thy cask; art Thou, indeed, a Cup’s bearer, may I ask?
Thou gavest me a drop from an ocean; Art Thou a miser in a Nourisher’s mask?
[Translated by Naim Siddiqui]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>