<Poem ID="01" Name="None" BookID="04" BookName="ارمغانِ حجاز" SectionID="03" SectionName="ملا زادہ ضیغم لولا بے کشمیری کا بیاض">
  <Para>
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پانی ترے چشموں کا تڑپتا ہوا سیماب
مرغان سحر تیری فضاوں میں ہیں بیتاب
اے وادی لولب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        وادی لولب : کشمیر کی ایک مشہور وادی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        From the Note Book of MuIlah Zada Zaighum Laulaabi of Kashmir

Thy fonts quick silver bewails with grace. The birds at dawn are restive in thy space. O Valley of Laulaab’s Grace.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="04">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گر صاحب ہنگامہ نہ ہو منبر و محراب
دیں بندۂ مومن کے لیے موت ہے یا خواب
اے وادی لولب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When the pulpit and the niche cease to re-create Resurrections, faith then is dead or a mere dream, for thee, me and for all. O Valley of Laulaab!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہیں ساز پہ موقوف نوا ہائے جگر سوز
ڈھیلے ہوں اگر تار تو بے کار ہے مضراب
اے وادی لولب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        On harp thus depend the heart rending moons. If the wries are loose, no quill makes the tones. O Valley of Laulaab’s Groans.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="10">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مل کی نظر نور فراست سے ہے خالی
بے سوز ہے میخانۂ صوفی کی مے ناب
اے وادی لولب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Mullah’s glance lacks the insight’s sense; the pure wine of Sufi lacks booze and trance. O Valley of Laulaab Hence.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بیدار ہوں دل جس کی فغان سحری سے
اس قوم میں مدت سے وہ درویش ہے نایاب
اے وادی لولب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Who wakes up the hearts from the morning wails, to see such Dervesh for long my sense fails. O Valley of Laulaab Tales.
[Translated by Q A Kabir]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>