<Poem ID="03" Name="اناالحق" BookID="11" BookName="ارمغانِ حجاز" SectionID="03" SectionName="حضور ملت">
  <Para Name="(1)">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اناالحق جز مقام کبریا نیست 
سزای او چلیپا ہست یا نیست
اگر فردی بگوید سر زنش بہ
اگر قومے بگوید ناروا نیست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اناالحق صرف مقام کبریا ہے؛ (کوئی انسان کہے تو ) اس کی سزا صلیب ہے یا نہیں؟ 
اس سوال کا جواب یہ ہے کہ) اگر فرد اناالحق کہے تو وہ قابل سزا ہے ؛ لیکن اگر قوم کہے ، تو جائز ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ANA-AL-HAQ
A place of I am God is God’s own place. This sin takes to gallows* or no disgrace?
* This sin takes to gallows or just gets grace. It refers to ‘Ana-al-Haq’ of Mansoor Hallaj.)
If one man says this reprove at this wrong; if a nation says, then you get along.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(2)">
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بہ آن ملت اناالحق سازگار است
کہ از خونش نم ہر شاخسار است
نہان اندر جلال او جمالی
کہ او را نہ سپہر آئینہ دار است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اناالحق کہنا اس ملت کو زیب دیتا ہے؛ جس کا خون (نہال باغ کی ) ہر شاخ کی آبیاری کرتا ہے۔ 
جس کے جلال میں جمال نہاں ہے؛ کیونکہ نو آسمان (ساری کائنات) اسی (کی جولانیوں ) کے آئینہ دار ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I am the God suits to that nation lone; whose blood’s moisture feels each branch grown.
In whose power hids a beauty queer; to him the nine heavens are servants clear.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(3)">
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میان امتان والا مقام است
کہ ن امت دو گیتی را امام است
نیاساید ز کار فرینش
کہ خواب و خستگی بر وی حرام است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ایسی امت ، امتوں میں بلند مرتبت ہے؛ کیونکہ وہ دونوں جہانوں کی سردار ہے۔
وہ (ہر دم) نئی تخلیق میں مصروف رہتی ہے؛ نیند اور تکان اس پر حرام ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Among nations large she holds a place great; that race is the leader of both worlds’ fate.
From her novel acts, new miracles breed; to dream and weaken is banned in her creed.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(4)">
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وجودش شعلہ از سوز درون است
چو خس او را جہان چند و چون است
کند شرح اناالحق ھمت او
پی ہر کن کہ میگوید یکون است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس امت کا وجود اپنے سوز دروں کے باعث شعلہ کی مانند ہے؛ یہ جہان اسباب و اعداد اس کے (شعلہ کے ) سامنے خس کی مانند ہے۔
اس کی ہمت (کے کارناموں ) سے اناالحق کی وضاحت ہوتی ہے؛ وہ جب کن کہتی ہے تو یکون اس کا ساتھ دیتا ہے (ایسی قوم جو کام شروع کرتی ہے، اسے پایہء تکمیل تک پہنچاتی ہے)۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        From her inner verve* that race is a flame; to her the world charms is a worthless game.
What means by I’m God her efforts define; her each ‘Kun’/’be’ says ‘Yakun’/‘become’ an object fine. 
* What is Soz-i-Daroon (inner flame of love or inner verve of faithful is further defined by Iqbal in Javed Namah, under the beading of Afghani (Syed Jamaluddin Afghani) and Piyam-i-Mashriq: 1). He is making efforts from Inner verve’s flame, From bonds of East and West to one world’s frame. 2). My heart is lit up from inner flame; from blood tears my eye views the world’s frame. 3). To secrets of life they are almost blind, They brand the love’s pathos to deranged mind. 4). Like moths how long you lead fool’s life; how long you wont face the life’s hard strife. 5). Burn thy self once with thy inner flame; round one’s fire how long you move sans aim.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(5)">
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پرد در وسعت گردون یگانہ
نگاہ او بہ شاخ شیانہ
مہ و انجم گرفتار کمندش
بدست اوست تقدیر زمانہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        وہ فضا کی وسعتوں میں یگانہ پرواز کرتی ہے (ان میں کھو نہیں جاتی؛ اس کی نگاہ ( ہمیشہ ) اپنے آشیانہ کی شاخ پر رہتی ہے (مقصود کو نہیں بھولتی)۔
وہ مہ و انجم کو اپنی کمند کا اسیر بناتی ہے؛ زمانے کی تقدیر اس کے ہاتھ میں ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Like a unique race thus she flies in space; with eyes ever set on her centre’s base.
The moon and stars in her lasso’s reach; lies in her hand the fate of age each.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(6)">
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بہ باغان عندلیبی خوش صفیری 
بہ راغان جرہ بازی زود گیری
امیر او بہ سلطانی فقیری
فقیر او بہ درویشے امیری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        (ایسی امت) باغوں میں خوش آواز عندلیب ہے؛ لیکن پہاڑوں کے دامن میں وہ نر باز کی طرح شکار پر جھپٹتی ہے۔
اس کے امیر سلطانی میں فقیر ہیں؛ اور اس کے فقیر درویشی میں امیر ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In garden’s lawn he is song bird sweet; in jungles a hawk with ruthless heat.
Her king in power is a poor man’s base; her poor man in want has a kingly grace.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="(7)">
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بجام نو کہن می از سبو ریز
فروغ خویش را بر کاخ و کو ریز
اگر خواہی ثمر از شاخ منصور
بہ دل لا غالب الا اللہ فرو ریز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اپنے نئے جام میں سبو سے پرانی شراب (اسلام کے دور اوّل کی) ڈالی؛ پھر اپنی چمک دمک سے محل اور کوچے روشن کر دے،
اگر شاخ منصور سے پھل حاصل کرنا چاہتا ہے ؛ تو اپنے دل پر لا غالب الا اللہ کا نقش منقش کر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Fill the old wine in the New Age bowl. Cast the self’s light on hills and lands whole.
If you wish to eat fruits from Mansoor’s bowl; say none save Allah can rule the world whole.*
* Basic thought: Take the world’s order in you own hand; throw other Gods from your heart’s land.)
[Translated by Qazi Ahdul Kabir]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>