<Poem ID="28" Name="ز ہد اور رندی" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="1a" SectionName="حصہ اول">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اک مولوی صاحب کی سناتا ہوں کہانی
تیزی نہیں منظور طبیعت کی دکھانی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        PIETY AND ECSTASY
I am only relating to you the story of a maulavi; I have no intention of showing my smartness.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شہرہ تھا بہت آپ کی صوفی منشی کا
کرتے تھے ادب ان کا اعالی و ادانی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        His pious nature was widely known; all the high and low respected him.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کہتے تھے کہ پنہاں ہے تصوف میں شریعت
جس طرح کہ الفاظ میں مضمر ہوں معانی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مضمر: چھپے ہوئے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He used to say that Shari‘ah was veiled in tassawuf; as meanings were veiled within words.
(Tassawuf: In this verse it is used in the sense in which the Ulama of the type described in this poem use it. This consists of merely a means of curing illness and helping people solve their day to day problems through amulets and by pretending to subdue secret spirits to carry out the subduer's behests. They use this ‘art’ for worldly gains and respectability, and have commercialized a noble concept.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لبریز مےء زہد سے تھی دل کی صراحی
تھی تہ میں کہیں درد خیال ہمہ دانی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ہمہ داني: سب کچھ جاننا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        His heart's flask was filled to the brim with piety's wine. He also had lees of the thought of pantology at the bottom.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کرتے تھے بیاں آپ کرامات کا اپنی
منظور تھی تعداد مریدوں کی بڑھانی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He often used to describe his supernatural powers. He always intended increase of his disciples' numbers.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مدت سے رہا کرتے تھے ہمسائے میں میرے
تھی رند سے زاہد کی ملاقات پرانی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He had been living in my neighborhood since long; the ascetic and the rind were mutual friends since long.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حضرت نے مرے ایک شناسا سے یہ پوچھا
اقبال، کہ ہے قمری شمشاد معانی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        قمري شمشاد: شمشاد کی قمری، مراد ہے بہت بلند۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The dignitary asked a friend of mine one day: ‘Iqbal who is a dignitary in the field of literature.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پابندی احکام شریعت میں ہے کیسا؟
گو شعر میں ہے رشک کلیم ہمدانی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کليم ہمداني: ہمایوں اور جہانگیر کے دور کا ایران کے شہر ہمدان میں پیدا ہونے والا نامور شاعر جو کشمیر میں فوت ہوا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        How is he in the obedience to the rules of Shari‘ah? Though in poetry he is envy of the Kalim of Hamadan.*
* Abu Talib Kalim Hamadani Kashani: A well known Persian poet of India and Persia. He belonged to Kashan by descent and to Hamadan by birth. He was educated and brought up in both cities and then arrived in the Indian sub-continent during the reign of Noor al-Din Jahangir… He went to Kashmir with Shahjahan, where he died and was buried.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سنتا ہوں کہ کافر نہیں ہندو کو سمجھتا
ہے ایسا عقیدہ اثر فلسفہ دانی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I hear he does not consider the Hindu a non-believer; he has such beliefs as a result of philosophy.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے اس کی طبیعت میں تشیع بھی ذرا سا
تفضیل علی ہم نے سنی اس کی زبانی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تشيع: شیعہ پن۔ 
علي: حضرت علی (رضی الّہ) باقی خلفاء سے بلند مرتبت سمجھنا۔ تفضيل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He has accepted a little bit of Shiaism also; I have heard the greatness of Ali (R.A.) from him.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سمجھا ہے کہ ہے راگ عبادات میں داخل
مقصود ہے مذہب کی مگر خاک اڑانی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He considers music as part of adoration. He aims at making a mockery of religion.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کچھ عار اسے حسن فروشوں سے نہیں ہے
عادت یہ ہمارے شعرا کی ہے پرانی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He does not feel shy with amorous people; this is a very old habit of our poets.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گانا جو ہے شب کو تو سحر کو ہے تلاوت
اس رمز کے اب تک نہ کھلے ہم پہ معانی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He has music at night, Qur’an's recitation in the morning; this secret is not yet fully understood by me.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لیکن یہ سنا اپنے مریدوں سے ہے میں نے
بے داغ ہے مانند سحر اس کی جوانی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        But the information obtained from my disciples is that spotless like the dawn's whiteness his youth is.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مجموعہ اضداد ہے، اقبال نہیں ہے
دل دفتر حکمت ہے، طبیعت خفقانی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مجموعہ اضداد: متضاد عادات کا حامل۔
خفقاني: سودائی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He is not Iqbal but a strange mixture of opposites he is; treasure of wisdom is his heart, but enigmatic his temper is.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="31">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رندی سے بھی آگاہ شریعت سے بھی واقف
پوچھو جو تصوف کی تو منصور کا ثانی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This appeared obviously contrary to the Shari‘ah and was considered heretic by the ulama of the time, including Junaid Baghdadi, who passed the edict of death against him. He was imprisoned for about a year by the Khalifah pending his final judgment, which was ultimately given against him. He was hanged, his body was burnt and the ashes were blown into the air. Mansoor recited The Holy Qur’an 42: 18 (part), which says, ‘only those wish to hasten it (the Hour) who believe not in it: those who believe hold it in awe, and know that it is the Truth’.
The cry of Mansoor has made him perhaps the most controversial figure in the spiritual history of Islam. The Sufis are divided about the justice of the edict, but the ulama are unanimous in their opinion on its correctness and justice. Allamah Iqbal also was against Mansoor… however, more study, contemplation and meditation convinced him about the correctness of Mansoor, and he has praised his sincere and ardent Love for God.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اس شخص کی ہم پر تو حقیقت نہیں کھلتی
ہو گا یہ کسی اور ہی اسلام کا بانی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I am unable to understand his reality; founder of another kind of Islam he appears to be.’
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="35">
      <Text Language="Original">
        القصہ بہت طول دیا وعظ کو اپنے
تا دیر رہی آپ کی یہ نغز بیانی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        نغز بياني: خوش گفتاری۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In short he prolonged his sermon very much; he long continued this wonderful speech.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="37">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اس شہر میں جو بات ہو اڑ جاتی ہے سب میں
میں نے بھی سنی اپنے احبا کی زبانی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Everyone soon hears all happenings in this city; I myself heard it through my friends in the city.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="39">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اک دن جو سر راہ ملے حضرت زاہد
پھر چھڑ گئی باتوں میں وہی بات پرانی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        One day as the respected ascetic met me in the street. The old story restarted during the talk in the street.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="41">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فرمایا، شکایت وہ محبت کے سبب تھی
تھا فرض مرا راہ شریعت کی دکھانی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He said: ‘That accusation was due to my affection. It was my duty to show you the path of the Shari‘ah’.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="43">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میں نے یہ کہا کوئی گلہ مجھ کو نہیں ہے
یہ آپ کا حق تھا ز رہ قرب مکانی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        قرب مکاني: ہمسائیگی ، پڑوسی ہونا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I said: ‘I have no intention of any complaint at all. It was your right due to being my neighbour.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="45">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خم ہے سر تسلیم مرا آپ کے آگے
پیری ہے تواضع کے سبب میری جوانی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I bow my head respectfully before you; my youth is accustomed to respect for the old.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="47">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گر آپ کو معلوم نہیں میری حقیقت
پیدا نہیں کچھ اس سے قصور ہمہ دانی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If you do not know the reality about me; it does not show any lack of pantology.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="49">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میں خود بھی نہیں اپنی حقیقت کا شناسا
گہرا ہے مرے بحر خیالات کا پانی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I myself do not know my reality; very deep is the sea of my thoughts.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="51">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مجھ کو بھی تمنا ہے کہ 'اقبال' کو دیکھوں
یکی اس کی جدائی میں بہت اشک فشان
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اشک فشاني: آنسو بہانا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Since long I am also longing to see Iqbal; for long I have shed tears in his separation.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="53">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اقبال بھی 'اقبال' سے آگاہ نہیں ہے
کچھ اس میں تمسخر نہیں، واللہ نہیں ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Iqbal also is not acquainted with Iqbal; there is no joke in it, by God he is not.
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>