<Poem ID="54" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="02" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مری نوا سے ہوئے زندہ عارف و عامی 
دیا ہے میں نے انھیں ذوق آتش آشامی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Gnostic and the common throng new life have gained through my song: I have conferred relish fine on them for Love’s fiery wine.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حرم کے پاس کوئی اعجمی ہے زمزمہ سنج 
کہ تار تار ہوئے جامہ ہائے احرامی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Some Ajami near the Holy Shrine did sadly sing this song and pine, ‘Alas! The robes by pilgrims worn to threads and pieces now are torn.’
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حقیقت ابدی ہے مقام شبیری 
بدلتے رہتے ہیں انداز کوفی و شامی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The place of Husain, the Martyr great is fact, not bound to Space or Date, though the Syrians and the Kufis may often change their wont and way.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مجھے یہ ڈر ہے مقامر ہیں پختہ کار بہت 
نہ رنگ لائے کہیں تیرے ہاتھ کی خامی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The gamblers who with you compete are deft of band and they can cheat: Your fumbling shaky hands, I fear, may bring about your ruin so drear.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عجب نہیں کہ مسلماں کو پھر عطا کر دیں 
شکوہ سنجر و فقر جنید و بسطامی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        No wonder if the Muslims gain their ancient glory once again; Sanjar’s splendour pomp and state, the piety and faqr of mystics great.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        قبائے علم و ہنر لطف خاص ہے، ورنہ 
تری نگاہ میں تھی میری ناخوش اندامی!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The robe of art and lore I wear is through Your special bounty there: You know my coarse and homely frame, to honour great I have no claim.
(Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>