<Poem ID="27" Name="تنہائی" BookID="07" BookName="پیامِ مشرق" SectionID="02" SectionName="افکار">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بہ بحر رفتم و گفتم بہ موج بیتابی
ہمیشہ در طلب استی چہ مشکلی داری؟
ہزار لولوی لالاست در گریبانت
درون سینہ چو من گوہر دلی داری؟
تپید و از لب ساحل رمید و ہیچ نگفت
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        SOLITUDE
I went down to the sea, and said to the restless wave, ‘You are for ever searching – what is your trouble? 
Your bag contains a thousand glowing pearls, but do you, like me, have in your breast a pearl of a heart?’ It writhed in pain and drew away from the shore. It did not say a word.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="06">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بہ کوہ رفتم و پرسیدم این چہ بیدردیست؟
رسد بگوش تو آہ و فغان غم زدہ ئی
اگر بہ سنگ تو لعلی ز قطرۂ خونست
یکی در آبہ سخن با من ستم زدہ ئی
بخود خزید و نفس در کشید و ہیچ نگفت
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I went up to the mountain and said, ‘How unfeeling you are! Have the sighs and screams of a soul in torment ever reached your ears? 
If within your rocks there is only one diamond formed from a drop of blood. Then come for a moment and talk to a wretched man like me. It withdrew into itself and held its breath; it did not say a word.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رہ دراز بریدم ز ماہ پرسیدم
سفر نصیب، نصیب تو منزلی است کہ نیست
جہان ز پرتو سیمای تو سمن زاری
فروغ داغ تو از جلوۂ دلی است کہ نیست
سوی ستارہ رقیبانہ دید و ہیچ نگفت
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I traveled far, and asked the moon, ‘Your lot is to keep traveling, is it also your lot to reach a destination?
Your face sends out rays that turn the world into a land of Jasmine. But does the radiance of the scar on your face come from the glow of a heart or not? It cast a jealous glance at the star; it did not say a word.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="16">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شدم بحضرت یزدان گذشتم از مہ و مہر
کہ در جہان تو یک ذرہ آشنایم نیست
جہان تہی ز دل و مشت خاک من ہمہ دل
چمن خوش است ولی درخور نوایم نیست
تبسمی بلب او رسید و ہیچ نگفت
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I left the moon and the sun behind, and reached the presence of God. I said, ‘Not one atom in Your world is intimate with me. 
The world has no heart, but I, though a handful of dust, am all heart. It is a pleasant garden, but unworthy of my song!’ A smile appeared on His lips He did not say a word. 
(Translated by Mustansir Mir)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>