<Poem ID="53" Name="بلال" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para>
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لکھا ہے ایک مغربی حق شناس نے 
اہل قلم میں جس کا بہت احترام تھا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        BILAL R.A. 
A righteous Western writer has written; who was highly respected among the literateur:
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جولاں گہ سکندر رومی تھا ایشیا 
گردوں سے بھی بلند تر اس کا مقام تھا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ‘Asia was the marshaling place of Sikandar of Rome; his status was more elegant than even the sky.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تاریخ کہہ رہی ہے کہ رومی کے سامنے 
دعوی کیا جو پورس و دارا نے، خام تھا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        History attests that in combat with the Romans the claims of Porus and Dara were vain.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دنیا کے اس شہنشہ انجم سپاہ کو 
حیرت سے دیکھتا فلک نیل فام تھا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        At this emperor with the myriad-man army the blue sky was looking with amazement.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آج ایشیا میں اس کو کوئی جانتا نہیں 
تاریخ دان بھی اسے پہچانتا نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Today nobody knows him in Asia; even the historian does not recognize him.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لیکن بلال، وہ حبشی زادئہ حقیر 
فطرت تھی جس کی نور نبوت سے مستنیر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        But Bilal (R.A.), that humble person with Negroid origin, whose nature had been brightened by the Prophethood’s (S.A.W.) Light.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جس کا امیں ازل سے ہوا سینہء بلال 
محکوم اس صدا کے ہیں شاہنشہ و فقیر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The call whose custodian the breast of Bilal since eternity,* became subservient to which call emperors as well as the indigent became!
* Allusion to Azan.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہوتا ہے جس سے اسود و احمر میں اختلاط 
کرتی ہے جو غریب کو ہم پہلوئے امیر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Which brings amity between the black and the red; by which the poor and the rich are placed together.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے تازہ آج تک وہ نوائے جگر گداز 
صدیوں سے سن رہا ہے جسے گوش چرخ پیر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        That heart-melting song is fresh till the present age; which the old sky’s ear has been hearing for centuries.’
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اقبال! کس کے عشق کا یہ فیض عام ہے 
رومی فنا ہوا، حبشی کو دوام ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Iqbal! This general blessing is due to whose love? The Roman has perished, the Negro is immortal!
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>