<Poem ID="59" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="02" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فقر کے ہیں معجزات تاج و سریر و سپاہ 
فقر ہے میروں کا میر، فقر ہے شاہوں کا شاہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The crown, the throne, and mighty arms by faqr are wrought these wonders all: In short, it is the chief of chiefs and king of other kings withal.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        علم کا مقصود ہے پاکی عقل و خرد 
فقر کا مقصود ہے عفت قلب و نگاہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        By means of learning mind and brain, no doubt, become refined and pure: Faqr makes the heart and gaze of man from earthly filth and dross secure.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        علم فقیہ و حکیم، فقر مسیح و کلیم 
علم ہے جویائے راہ، فقر ہے دانائے راہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Scholar and sage knowledge makes, but Christ and Moses by faqr are wrought: To faqr the road is fully known, of road the scholar knows not aught.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فقر مقام نظر، علم مقام خبر 
فقر میں مستی ثواب، علم میں مستی گناہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The state of seeing faqr bestows, but knowledge makes on new rely: Rapture in faqr is virtue great, whereas in knowledge sin so high.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        علم کا 'موجود' اور، فقر کا 'موجود' اور 
اشھد ان لا الہ' اشھد ان لا الہ!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        One God there is that knowledge owns to other God faqr lays a claim: No god but He, I do proclaim, No god but He, I do proclaim.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چڑھتی ہے جب فقر کی سان پہ تیغ خودی 
ایک سپاہی کی ضرب کرتی ہے کار سپاہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        On the whetting stone of faqr, when sword of Self gets sharp and bright, a single stroke by warrior bold can out an army big to flight.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دل اگر اس خاک میں زندہ و بیدار ہو 
تیری نگہ توڑ دے آئنہء مہروماہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Within your clay, if there exist a heart alive and wide awake, the glass of sun and moon as well one look of yours forthwith can break.
(Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>