<Poem ID="55" Name="پھولوں کی شہزادی" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کلی سے کہہ رہی تھی ایک دن شبنم گلستاں میں 
رہی میں ایک مدت غنچہ ہائے باغ رضواں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE PRINCESS OF FLOWERS
One day the dew in the garden was saying to the flower bud: ‘I lived for a long time among the flower buds of Paradise.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تمھارے گلستاں کی کیفیت سرشار ہے ایسی 
نگہ فردوس در دامن ہے میری چشم حیراں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The condition of your garden is so elegant; the Paradise’s sight is concealed in my bewildered eye.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سنا ہے کوئی شہزادی ہے حاکم اس گلستاں کی 
کہ جس کے نقش پا سے پھول ہوں پیدا بیاباں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I have heard that some princess is the ruler of this garden with whose foot-prints the wilderness would produce flowers.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کبھی ساتھ اپنے اس کے آستاں تک مجھ کو تو لے چل 
چھپا کر اپنے دامن میں برنگ موج بو لے چل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Some day take me with you up to her palace; take me concealed in your skirt like fragrance.’
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کلی بولی، سریر آرا ہماری ہے وہ شہزادی 
درخشاں جس کی ٹھوکر سے ہوں پتھر بھی نگیں بن کر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The flower bud said: ‘On the throne is that princess of ours by whose kick even stones become resplendent jewels.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مگر فطرت تری افتندہ اور بیگم کی شان اونچی 
نہیں ممکن کہ تو پہنچے ہماری ہم نشیں بن کر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        But your nature is bright and princess’ rank is elegant. It is not possible that you reach her in company with me.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پہنچ سکتی ہے تو لیکن ہماری شاہزادی تک 
کسی دکھ درد کے مارے کا اشک آتشیں بن کر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        However you can reach up to our princess by becoming the hot tear of some afflicted person.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نظر اس کی پیام عید ہے اہل محرم کو 
بنا دیتی ہے گوہر غم زدوں کے اشک پیہم کو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Her glance is the message of ‘Eid to the Muharram’s people; turns the continuous tears of afflicted people into pearls.
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>