<Poem ID="19" Name="ایک آرزو" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="1a" SectionName="حصہ اول">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دنیا کی محفلوں سے اکتا گیا ہوں یا رب
کیا لطف انجمن کا جب دل ہی بجھ گیا ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O Lord! I have become weary of human assemblages! When the heart is sad no pleasure in assemblages can be.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شورش سے بھاگتا ہوں، دل ڈھونڈتا ہے میرا
ایسا سکوت جس پر تقریر بھی فدا ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I seek escape from tumult, my heart desires; the silence which speech may ardently love!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مرتا ہوں خامشی پر، یہ آرزو ہے میری
دامن میں کوہ کے اک چھوٹا سا جھونپڑا ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I vehemently desire silence, I strongly long that a small hut in the mountain's side may there be.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آزاد فکر سے ہوں، عزلت میں دن گزاروں
دنیا کے غم کا دل سے کانٹا نکل گیا ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        عزلت: تنہائی، گوشہ نشینی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Freed from worry I may live in retirement; freed from the cares of the world I may be.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لذت سرود کی ہو چڑیوں کے چہچہوں میں
چشمے کی شورشوں میں باجا سا بج رہا ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Birds' chirping may give the pleasure of the lyre; in the spring's noise may the orchestra's melody be.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گل کی کلی چٹک کر پیغام دے کسی کا
ساغر ذرا سا گویا مجھ کو جہاں نما ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The flower bud bursting may give God's message to me; showing the whole world to me this small wine-cup may be.
(The flower bud bursting: This metaphor refers to the wine-cup of Jamshaid, a Persian king, who could see the whole world in it. This is one of the innumerable messages in `Allamah Iqbal's works through which he requires his readers to comprehend and enjoy the creative artistry of God.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہو ہاتھ کا سرھانا سبزے کا ہو بچھونا
شرمائے جس سے جلوت، خلوت میں وہ ادا ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جلوت: ظاہر ہونا یعنی سب کے سامنے منظر عام پر رہنا۔ 
خلوت: جلوت کے بر عکس یعنی تنہائی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My arm may be my pillow, and the green grass my bed be; putting the congregation to shame my solitude's quality be.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مانوس اس قدر ہو صورت سے میری بلبل
ننھے سے دل میں اس کے کھٹکا نہ کچھ مرا ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مانوس: جان پہچان رکھنے والی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The nightingale be so familiar with my face that her little heart harboring no fear from me may be.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        صف باندھے دونوں جانب بوٹے ہرے ہرے ہوں
ندی کا صاف پانی تصویر لے رہا ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Avenues of green trees standing on both sides be; the spring's clear water providing a beautiful picture be.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہو دل فریب ایسا کہسار کا نظارہ
پانی بھی موج بن کر اٹھ اٹھ کے دیکھتا ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The view of the mountain range may be so beautiful; to see it the waves of water again and again rising be.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آغوش میں زمیں کی سویا ہوا ہو سبزہ
پھر پھر کے جھاڑیوں میں پانی چمک رہا ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The verdure may be asleep in the lap of the earth; water running through the bushes may glistening be.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پانی کو چھو رہی ہو جھک جھک کے گل کی ٹہنی
جیسے حسین کوئی آئینہ دیکھتا ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Again and again the flowered boughs touching the water be; as if some beauty looking at itself in mirror be.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مہندی لگائے سورج جب شام کی دلھن کو
سرخی لیے سنہری ہر پھول کی قبا ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When the sun apply myrtle to the evening's bride; the tunic of every flower may pinkish golden be.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        راتوں کو چلنے والے رہ جائیں تھک کے جس دم
امید ان کی میرا ٹوٹا ہوا دیا ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When night's travelers falter behind with fatigue; their only hope my broken earthenware lamp may be.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بجلی چمک کے ان کو کٹیا مری دکھا دے
جب آسماں پہ ہر سو بادل گھرا ہوا ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        May the lightning lead them to my hut; when clouds hovering over the whole sky be.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="31">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پچھلے پہر کی کوئل، وہ صبح کی موذن
میں اس کا ہم نوا ہوں، وہ میری ہم نوا ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The early dawn's cuckoo, that morning's mu’adhin; may my confidante he be, and may his confidante I be.
(Mu’adhin: The person calling Muslims to congregational prayers. This is a beautiful metaphor calling the cuckoo as the herald of the morning prayer time.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کانوں پہ ہو نہ میرے دیر وحرم کا احساں
روزن ہی جھونپڑی کا مجھ کو سحر نما ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        سحر نما: صبح کا پتا دینے والا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        May I not be obligated to the temple or to the mosque; may the hut’s hole alone herald of morning’s arrival be.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="35">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پھولوں کو آئے جس دم شبنم وضو کرانے
رونا مرا وضو ہو، نالہ مری دعا ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When the dew may come to perform the flowers’ ablution’ may wailing my supplication, weeping my ablution be.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="37">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اس خامشی میں جائیں اتنے بلند نالے
تاروں کے قافلے کو میری صدا درا ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In this silence may my heart’s wailing rise so high that for stars’ caravan the clarion’s call my wailing be.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="39">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہر دردمند دل کو رونا مرا رلا دے
بے ہوش جو پڑے ہیں، شاید انھیں جگا دے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        May every compassionate heart weeping with me be; perhaps it may awaken those who may unconscious be
[Translated by Dr M A K Khalil]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>