<Poem ID="10" Name="اشکے چند بر افتراق ہندیان" BookID="10" BookName="پس چہ بائد کرد" SectionID="01" SectionName="پس چہ بائد کرد">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے ھمالہ ! اے اطک، اے رود گنگ
زیستن تا کی چنان بی آب و رنگ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ہندوستانیوں کے آپس میں نفاق پر چند آنسو
اے ہمالہ ! اے اٹک! اے گنگا ! یہ بے آب و رنگ زندگی کب تک؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        LAMENT ON THE DIFFERENCES AMONG INDIANS
O Himalayas! O Attock! O Ganges! How long shall we go on living sordidly like this?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پیر مردان از فراست بی نصیب
نوجوانان از محبت بی نصیب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        بزرگوں میں فراست نہیں ، نوجوان محبت سے خالی ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The old lack insight, the young are devoid of love.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شرق و غرب آزاد و ما نخچیر غیر
خشت ما سرمایۂ تعمیر غیر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مشرق و مغرب آزاد ہیں مگر ہم غیروں کے غلام ہیں۔ ہماری اینٹیں غیروں کی تعمیر میں صرف ہو رہی ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        East and West are free, but we are slaves of others;	our bricks go to the building of others’ mansions.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زندگانے بر مراد دیگران
جاودان مرگست، نے خواب گران
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        دوسروں کی مرضی کے مطابق زندگی بسر کرنا خواب گراںنیں بلکہ مرگ جاوداں ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        To live according to the wish of others; is not deep slumber; it is eternal death.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نیست این مرگی کہ آید ز آسمان
تخم او می بالد ز اعماق جان
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        یہ وہ موت نہیں جو آسمان سے نازل ہوتی ہے بلکہ اس موت کا بیج جان کی گہرائیوں سے پھوٹتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This is not a death that comes from the sky; its seed grows out of the depths of one’s soul. 
(‘Death from the sky’ means natural death. ‘Death from the depth of the heart’ means spiritual death as a result of wrong ideological affiliations.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        صید او نے مردہ شو خواہد نہ گور
نے ھجوم دوستان از نزد و دور
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس موت کے شکار کو نہ غسل کی ضرورت ہے، نہ قبر کی، نہ اس کی موت پر (جنازہ اٹھتا ہے) اور نہ احباب تعزیت کے لیے نزدیک و دور سے آتے ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Its prey waits neither for the undertaker nor for the grave, nor for friends from far and near.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جامۂ کس در غم او چاک نیست
دوزخ او آنسوی افلاک نیست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس مردے کے غم میں کوئی کپڑے نہیں پھاڑتا، اس کی دوزخ آسمانوں کے دوسری جانب نہیں (بلکہ یہیں ہے)۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        No clothes are torn in grief over his death, his hell is not on the other side of the skies.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        در ھجوم روز حشر او را مجو
ہست در امروز او فردای او
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اسے روز محشر کے ہجوم میں نہ تلاش کر اس کا کل (قیامت) اس کے آج ہی میں موجود ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Do not seek him among the crowd on the Day of Judgment, his tomorrow lies in his today.
(These verses describe the state of spiritual death and therefore the ceremonies usually performed on the natural death of a person are not performed on this occasion. Iqbal describes in Zabur-i ‘Ajam this kind of death: ‘This is a more subtle inner death which makes me tremble! Cutting one’s shroud with one’s own hands; seeing one’s death with one’s own eyes. This death lies in ambush for thee; fear it, for that is really our death’.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہر کہ اینجا دانہ کشت اینجا درود
پیش حق آن بندہ را بردن چہ سود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جس نے یہاں دانہ بو کر یہیں فصل برداشت کر لی، ایسے بندے کو اللہ تعالے کے سامنے لے جانے کی کیا ضرورت۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What use is there to produce before God one; who has both sown the seed and reaped the fruit in this world?	
(The idea that those who work for gain in this life only will be given their reward here, is based on the following verse of the Qur’an, xvii. 18: ‘Whoso desires this transitory life, We hasten to him therein what we please…’ After death, he will be deprived of the opportunity to experience Beatific Vision.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        امتے کز آرزو نیشی نخورد
نقش او را فطرت از گیتی سترد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جس قوم نے آرزو کا زخم نہ کھایا ا س کے نقش کو فطرت نے زمانے (کی تختی) سے مٹا دیا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A nation that does not relish the prodding of desire is wiped off the face of the earth by Nature.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اعتبار تخت و تاج از ساحری است
سخت چون سنگ این زجاج از ساحریست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تخت و تاج کا بھرم جادوگری سے ہے، اسی سے یہ شیشہ پتھر کی طرح سخت نظر آتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It is through magic that the crown and the throne acquire authority; what is frail as glass becomes through magic bard as stone.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        در گذشت از حکم این سحر مبین
کافری از کفر، دینداری ز دین
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اسی کھلے جادو کے حکم سے کافری نے کفر اور دینداری نے دین چھوڑ دیا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Under the influence of this clear enchantment; Muslims abjured their faith and unbelievers, their unbelief,
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہندیان با یکدگر آویختند
فتنہ ہای کہنہ باز انگیختند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ہندوستانیوں نے ایک دوسرے سے لڑائی جھگڑا شروع کر دیا اور اس طرح پرانے فتنوں کو پھر سے ہوا دی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Indians quarrel with one another, having revived their old differences.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تا فرنگی قومی از مغرب زمین
ثالث آمد در نزاع کفر و دین
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        یہاں تک کہ یورپ سے ایک فرنگی قوم کفر و دین کی ثالث بن کر آ گئی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Until a Frankish nation from the land of the West; assumed the role of a mediator between Islam and kufr.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کس نداند جلوۂ آب از سراب
انقلاب اے انقلاب اے انقلاب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کوئی شخص سراب اور جلوہ آب کے درمیان امتیاز نہیں کرتا ۔ انقلاب! اے انقلاب! اےانقلاب!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Nobody knows water from mirage. Revolution, O revolution, O revolution!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="31">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے ترا ہر لحظہ فکر آب و گل
از حضور حق طلب یک زندہ دل
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اے وہ شخص جسے ہر لحظہ بدن کی فکر کھاے جا رہی ہے تو اللہ تعالے سے ایک دل زندہ مانگ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O you who are always anxious for material sustenance, ask of God a living heart.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آشیانش گرچہ در آب و گل است
نہ فلک سر گشتہ این یک دل است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        دل زندہ کا آشیانہ اگرچہ بدن میں ہے لیکن نو آسمان اس ایک گل زندہ کے گرد گھومتے ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Although its seat is in water and clay, yet the nine heavens are under its authority.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="35">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تا نپنداری کہ از خاک است او
از بلندی ہای افلاک است او
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        یہ نہ سمجھ کہ دل زندہ خاکی بدن سے پیدا ہوتا ہے۔ وہ افلاک کی بلندیوں سے ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Do not think it belongs to the earth; it really comes from the highest heavens.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="37">
      <Text Language="Original">
        این جہان او را حریم کوی دوست
از قبای لالہ گیرد بوی دوست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        یہ جہان اس کے لیے محبوب (حق تعالے) کا حریم ہے۔ وہ یہاں کے گل لالہ کی قبا سے محبوب کی خوشبو پاتا ہے (تخلیق اسے خالق کی طرف لے جاتی ہے)۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The world is for it the Friend’s abode and gets the Friend’s smell from the tulip’s tunic.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="39">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہر نفس با روزگار اندر ستیز
سنگ رہ از ضربت او ریز ریز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        صاحب دل شخص ہر لحظہ زمانے سے نبرد آزما رہتا ہے۔ اس کی ضرب سے راستے کا پہاڑ ریزہ ریزہ ہو جاتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It is constantly at war with the world, the stones on the path are broken to pieces by its strokes.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="41">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آشنای منبر و دار است او
آتش خود را نگہدار است او
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        وہ منبر و دار کا آشنا ہے۔ وہ اپنی آتش (عشق) کو سنبھال کر رکھتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It is familiar with the pulpit and the gibbet, and keeps a strict watch over its own fire.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="43">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آب جوی و بحر ہا دارد بہ بر
می دہد موجش ز طوفانی خبر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ہے وہ ندی مگر کئی سمندر اس کےہمراہ ہوتے ہیں۔ اس کی موج آنے والے طوفان کی خبر دیتی ہے (وہ انقلاب پیدا کرتا ہے)۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It is only a streamlet but has oceans in its lap; its ripples bring tidings of storms.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="45">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زندہ و پایندہ بی نان تنور
میرد آن ساعت کہ گردد بی حضور
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        وہ ظاہری خوراک کے بغیر ہی زندہ و پائیندہ ہے (حضوری اس کی زندگی ہے) اور بے حضوری موت۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It is not by bread that it lives; it dies as soon as it loses its vision of the Truth.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="47">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چون چراغ اندر شبستان بدن
روشن از وی خلوت و ہم انجمن
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ایسا زندہ دل شبستان بدن میں چراغ کی مانند ہے، وہ خلوت و انجمن کو روشن کر دیتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It is like a lamp in the dark chamber of the body: it illumines both multitude and solitude.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="49">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اینچنین دل، خود نگر، اﷲ مست
جز بہ درویشی نمے آید بدست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        یہ خود نگر اور خدا مست دل درویشی کے بغیر ہاتھ نہیں آتا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Such a heart, ever watchful of itself and God-intoxicated, is not achieved except through Faqr.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="51">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے جوان دامان او محکم بگیر
در غلامی زادہ ئی آزاد میر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اے جوان! ایسے صاحب دل کا دامن مظبوتی سے تھام لے اور غلامی میں پیدا ہونے کے باوجود آزادی کی موت پا لے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O young man, catch hold of its skirt firmly; you have been born in slavery, now live free. 	
(Translated by Bashir Ahmad Dar)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>