<Poem ID="07" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="01" SectionName="حصہ اول">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دگرگوں ہے جہاں، تاروں کی گردش تیز ہے ساقی 
دل ہر ذرہ میں غوغائے رستا خیز ہے ساقی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        غوغائے رستا خيز: قیامت کے دن کا شور۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Contrary runs our planet, the stars whirl fast, oh Saki! In every atom’s heartbeat a Doomsday blast, oh Saki!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        متاع دین و دانش لٹ گئی اللہ والوں کی 
یہ کس کافر ادا کا غمزئہ خوں ریز ہے ساقی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Torn from God’s congregation its dower of faith and reason, and godlessness in fatal allurement dressed, oh Saki!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وہی دیرینہ بیماری، وہی نا محکمی دل کی 
علاج اس کا وہی آب نشاط انگیز ہے ساقی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        For our inveterate sickness, our wavering heart, the cure; that same joy-dropping nectar as in the past, oh Saki.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حرم کے دل میں سوز آرزو پیدا نہیں ہوتا 
کہ پیدائی تری اب تک حجاب آمیز ہے ساقی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        پيدائي: ظہور۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Within Islam’s cold temple no fire of longing stirs; for still your face is hidden, veiled and un-guessed, oh Saki.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہ اٹھا پھر کوئی رومی عجم کے لالہ زاروں سے 
وہی آب و گل ایراں، وہی تبریز ہے ساقی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Unchanged is Persia’s garden: soil, stream, Tabriz, unchanged; and yet with no new Rumi is her land graced, oh Saki.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہیں ہے ناامید اقبال اپنی کشت ویراں سے 
ذرا نم ہو تو یہ مٹی بہت زرخیز ہے ساقی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کشت ويراں: ویران کھیتی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        But of his barren acres Iqbal will not despair: a little rain and harvests shall wave at last, oh Saki!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فقیر راہ کو بخشے گئے اسرار سلطانی 
بہا میری نوا کی دولت پرویز ہے ساقی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        On me, a beggar, secrets of empire are bestowed; my songs are worth the treasures Parvez amassed, oh Saki.
[Translated by V.G. Kiernan]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>