<Poem ID="07" Name="" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="1b" SectionName="غزلیات 1">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ظاہر کی آنکھ سے نہ تماشا کرے کوئی
ہو دیکھنا تو دیدہء دل وا کرے کوئی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        One should not see the Spectacle with the material eye; if one wants to see Him he should open the insight's eye.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        منصور کو ہوا لب گویا پیام موت
اب کیا کسی کے عشق کا دعوی کرے کوئی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        His talking lip was death's message to Mansoor; how can anybody dare to claim Someone's Love now?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہو دید کا جو شوق تو آنکھوں کو بند کر
ہے دیکھنا یہی کہ نہ دیکھا کرے کوئی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Close your eyes if you want taste for the Sight; the real Seeing is that one should not try to see Him. 
* God cannot be seen with the physical human eye but His Existence can be felt with a clean Mu’min’s clean heart.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میں انتہائے عشق ہوں، تو انتہائے حسن
دیکھے مجھے کہ تجھ کو تماشا کرے کوئی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I am the extreme Love, Thou art the extreme Beauty. One should see me or witness Thy Spectacle.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عذر آفرین جرم محبت ہے حسن دوست
محشر میں عذر تازہ نہ پیدا کرے کوئی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Beloved's Beauty is the creator of excuse for Love's crime; one need not create a new excuse on the Day of Judgment. 
* The Jamal (Beauty) of God is sufficient reason for loving Him and for longing for His Sight. No other reason is necessary for the Longing to see Him on the Day of Judgment.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چھپتی نہیں ہے یہ نگہ شوق ہم نشیں!
پھر اور کس طرح انھیں دیکھا کر ے کوئی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O Companion! It is not possible to close this zealous eye! In what other manner should one try to witness Him.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اڑ بیٹھے کیا سمجھ کے بھلا طور پر کلیم
طاقت ہو دید کی تو تقاضا کرے کوئی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        With what thought did Kalim become insistent on the Toor? One should request for the Sight if he has the power for the Sight.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نظارے کو یہ جنبش مژگاں بھی بار ہے
نرگس کی آنکھ سے تجھے دیکھا کرے کوئی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Even the eyebrow's movement is unwelcome to the Sight; with the eye of the narcissus should one see Thee.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کھل جائیں، کیا مزے ہیں تمنائے شوق میں
دو چار دن جو میری تمنا کرے کوئی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The pleasures of the Longings of Love will be manifest, if one has Longing like me for a few days.
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>