<Poem ID="11" Name="وصال" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="2a" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جستجو جس گل کی تڑپاتی تھی اے بلبل مجھے
خوبی قسمت سے آخر مل گیا وہ گل مجھے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE UNION (MEETING THE BELOVED)
O Nightingale! The rose whose search made me flounced; by dint of good luck that rose I have finally found.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خود تڑپتا تھا، چمن والوں کو تڑپاتا تھا میں
تجھ کو جب رنگیں نوا پاتا تھا، شرماتا تھا میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I used to flounce myself; I used to make others flounced. I used to feel shy when I found you singing beautifully.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میرے پہلو میں دل مضطر نہ تھا، سیماب تھا
ارتکاب جرم الفت کے لیے بے تاب تھا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A mere restless heart was not in my bosom, it was mercury. I was impatient for fulfillment of the Longing of Love.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نامرادی محفل گل میں مری مشہور تھی
صبح میری آئنہ دار شب دیجور تھی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My misfortune was famous in the assembly of the rose; my morning was the reflection of my dark night.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        از نفس در سینہء خوں گشتہ نشتر داشتم
زیر خاموشی نہاں غوغائے محشر داشتم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        With my breath I have a blood stained knife in the bosom; under the cloak of silence I have Judgment Day's uproar.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اب تاثر کے جہاں میں وہ پریشانی نہیں
اہل گلشن پر گراں میری غزل خوانی نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Now that distress does not exist in my reflections' world; my reciting ghazals is no longer irksome to rose garden's assembly.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عشق کی گرمی سے شعلے بن گئے چھالے مرے
کھلیتے ہیں بجلیوں کے ساتھ اب نالے مرے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        With the heat of Love my blisters became flames; now playing with thunderbolts are my wailings.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        غازئہ الفت سے یہ خاک سیہ آئینہ ہے
اور آئینے میں عکس ہمدم دیرینہ ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Ghazah-e-olfat sey yeh khak-e-seih aeinah hai; aur aeinay mein aks-e-humdam-e-deirinah hai. 
(Ghazah: Powder.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        قید میں آیا تو حاصل مجھ کو آزادی ہوئی
دل کے لٹ جانے سے میرے گھر کی آبادی ہوئی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        By becoming a prisoner I gained my freedom; by ruining the heart I got prosperity for my house.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ضو سے اس خورشید کی اختر مرا تابندہ ہے
چاندنی جس کے غبار راہ سے شرمندہ ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My star is shining with this sun's light, by whose path's dust the moon light is shy.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یک نظر کر دی و آداب فنا آموختی
اے خنک روزے کہ خاشاک مرا واسوختی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        By a glance you taught me the rules of annihilation; how cool the day that has burnt away the motes from me.
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>