<Poem ID="24" Name="جبریل وابلیس" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="04" SectionName="منظومات">
  <Para Name="جبریل">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہمدم دیرینہ! کیسا ہے جہان رنگ و بو؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        GABRIEL AND SATAN
Gabriel: My old friend, how is the world of sight and sound?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="ابلیس">
    <Verse ID="02">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سوز و ساز و درد و داغ و جستجوے و آرزو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Satan: Pain and passion; quest and yearning.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="جبریل">
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہر گھڑی افلاک پر رہتی ہے تیری گفتگو 
کیا نہیں ممکن کہ تیرا چاک دامن ہو رفو؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Gabriel: Thou never talkest of anything but the heavens. Is there no cure for thy constant pain?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="ابلیس">
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آہ اے جبریل! تو واقف نہیں اس راز سے 
کر گیا سرمست مجھ کو ٹوٹ کر میرا سبو 
اب یہاں میری گزر ممکن نہیں، ممکن نہیں 
کس قدر خاموش ہے یہ عالم بے کاخ و کو! 
جس کی نومیدی سے ہو سوز درون کائنات 
اس کے حق میں 'تقنطوا' اچھا ہے یا 'لاتقظوا'؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تقنطوا: تم نا امید ہو۔ 
لاتقظوا: تم نا امید نہ ہو۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Satan: Thou knowest not, alas, the secret of my pain! The loss I have suffered has increased my passion more.
How silent is this world; desolate and wild! I cannot ever live here; I cannot!
For one whose despair throbs in the heart of the universe, what is better-despair, or hope?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="جبریل">
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کھو دیے انکار سے تو نے مقامات بلند 
چشم یزداں میں فرشتوں کی رہی کیا آبرو!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Gabriel: By thy refusal thou hast lost thy place in heaven – and disgraced the angels in the eyes of the Lord.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="ابلیس">
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے مری جرأت سے مشت خاک میں ذوق نمو 
میرے فتنے جامہء عقل و خرد کا تاروپو 
دیکھتا ہے تو فقط ساحل سے رزم خیر و شر 
کون طوفاں کے طمانچے کھا رہا ہے، میں کہ تو؟ 
خضر بھی بے دست و پا، الیاس بھی بے دست و پا 
میرے طوفاں یم بہ یم، دریا بہ دریا، جو بہ جو 
گر کبھی خلوت میسر ہو تو پوچھ اللہ سے 
قصہء آدم کو رنگیں کر گیا کس کا لہو! 
میں کھٹکتا ہوں دل یزداں میں کانٹے کی طرح 
تو فقط اللہ ھو، اللہ ھو، اللہ ھو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تاروپو: تانا بانا ۔ 
رزم خير و شر: نیکی اور بدی کی جنگ۔ 
دست و پا: ہاتھ پاؤں۔ 
جو: ندی۔ 
يم: سمندر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Satan: My courage gave a speck of dust the impulse to grow; my cunning is the fabric of man’s intellect.
Thou watchest the war of good and evil, safely ashore, and who is battered by the storm-thou or I?
Both Khizr and Ilyas feel helpless: The storms I have stirred up rage in oceans, rivers, and streams.
Ask God, if thou hast the time to ask: Whose blood gave colour to Adam’s inglorious tale?
I am a thorn in the Almighty’s mighty heart, and thou but mumblest His praise day and night.
(Translated by Naim Siddiqui)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>