<Poem ID="47" Name="بچہ اور شمع" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="1a" SectionName="حصہ اول">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کیسی حیرانی ہے یہ اے طفلک پروانہ خو
شمع کے شعلوں کو گھڑیوں دیکھتا رہتا ہے تو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE CHILD AND THE CANDLE
O Child with moth-like nature! ‘How strange that you keep gazing at the flame of the candle for hours?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ مری آغوش میں بیٹھے ہوئے جنبش ہے کیا
روشنی سے کیا بغل گیری ہے تیرا مدعا؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What is this movement, when you are in my lap? Are you intending to embrace the light?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اس نظارے سے ترا ننھا سا دل حیران ہے
یہ کسی دیکھی ہوئی شے کی مگر پہچان ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Though your tiny heart is surprised at this spectacle, but this is recognition of some object already seen!*
* This is the first hint in the poem that the candle's light is the same light as the Light of God seen by Man on the Primeval Day.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شمع اک شعلہ ہے لیکن تو سراپا نور ہے
آہ! اس محفل میں یہ عریاں ہے تو مستور ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The candle is but a flame, you are the Light embodied.Ah! In this assembly that is manifest, you are concealed.*
* Allusion to the manifest glow of the candle in the transparent mantle of glass and the veiled Light of God in the opaque earthen mantle of human body.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دست قدرت نے اسے کیا جانے کیوں عریاں کیا!
تجھ کو خاک تیرہ کے فانوس میں پنہاں کیا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It is not known why the Nature's hand made it manifest! And concealed you in the dark soil's mantle.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نور تیرا چھپ گیا زیر نقاب آگہی
ہے غبار دیدہء بینا حجاب آگہی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your light has been concealed under the veil of Intellect! The veil of Cognition is a mere mist to the wise eye!
(This and the remaining verses mean that God (His Beauty) is present in the multitudes of worldly objects mentioned in those verses. He can be discerned by the discerning eye with the help of Khudi. The Holy Qur'an also teaches us to understand God from the objects of the universe and Man's own self, which is Khudi. The power of Khudi distinguishes Man from and makes him superior to the rest of the creation of God. However, Knowledge or Intellect conceals Khudi and with it the Light of God fades away from Man's eyes. This Light dawns only when Man throws away the earthly mantle of Intellect and activates the Love of God…)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زندگانی جس کو کہتے ہیں فراموشی ہے یہ
خواب ہے، غفلت ہے، سرمستی ہے، بے ہوشی ہے یہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What is called life really a mirage it is; a dream, a swoon, an ecstasy, oblivion it is.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        محفل قدرت ہے اک دریائے بے پایان حسن
آنکھ اگر دیکھے تو ہر قطرے میں ہے طوفان حسن
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Nature's assembly is the Beauty's boundless ocean; for the discerning eye every drop is the Beauty's storm.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حسن، کوہستاں کی ہیبت ناک خاموشی میں ہے
مہر کی ضوگستری، شب کی سیہ پوشی میں ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Beauty is in the frightening silence of the mountain; in shedding of sun's light, and in night's darkness’
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آسمان صبح کی آئینہ پوشی میں ہے یہ
شام کی ظلمت، شفق کی گل فرو شی میں ہے یہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It is in the morning sky's mirror-like glitter; in the night's darkness and in the twilight's floridity.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عظمت دیرینہ کے مٹتے ہوئے آثار میں
طفلک ناآشنا کی کوشش گفتار میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It is in the disappearing relics of the old magnificence; in the small child's effort to commence speaking.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ساکنان صحن گلشن کی ہم آوازی میں ہے
ننھے ننھے طائروں کی آشیاں سازی میں ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It is in the harmony of the denizens of the rose-garden; in the nest-building efforts of the tiny little birds.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چشمہ کہسار میں، دریا کی آزادی میں حسن
شہر میں، صحرا میں، ویرانے میں، آبادی میں حسن
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In the mountain stream, in the ocean's freedom is Beauty; in the city, the forest, the wilderness, the habitation is Beauty.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        روح کو لیکن کسی گم گشتہ شے کی ہے ہوس
ورنہ اس صحرا میں کیوں نالاں ہے یہ مثل جرس
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The soul but longing for some lost object is; or else why is it lamenting in wilderness like a bell?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حسن کے اس عام جلوے میں بھی یہ بے تاب ہے
زندگی اس کی مثال ماہی بے آب ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It is restless even in this general splendour of Beauty; its life is like a fish out of water.
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>