<Poem ID="26" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="02" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہ تو زمیں کے لیے ہے نہ آسماں کے لیے 
جہاں ہے تیرے لیے، تو نہیں جہاں کے لیے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Thou art not for the earth or for the heaven alone; the world is for thee, not thou for the world.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ عقل و دل ہیں شرر شعلہ محبت کے 
وہ خار و خس کے لیے ہے، یہ نیستاں کے لیے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The mind and the heart are sparks in the flame of love; one for a moment’s flash, the other for – a blazing fire.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مقام پرورش آہ و نالہ ہے یہ چمن 
نہ سیر گل کے لیے ہے نہ آشیاں کے لیے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This garden of’ delight is not for thy delight; thou art here to yearn, to seek a beatific vision.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رہے گا راوی و نیل و فرات میں کب تک 
ترا سفینہ کہ ہے بحر بے کراں کے لیے!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Equipped for unfathomed seas, thy vessel should not confine itself to rivers, and to familiar shores.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نشان راہ دکھاتے تھے جو ستاروں کو 
ترس گئے ہیں کسی مرد راہ داں کے لیے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        They were a beacon once to the brightest stars of heaven, but now they languish in darkness, in search of a guide to lead them.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نگہ بلند، سخن دل نواز، جاں پرسوز 
یہی ہے رخت سفر میر کارواں کے لیے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A lofty vision, gracious speech, and a passionate soul: These are the attributes of the leaders of all men.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ذرا سی بات تھی، اندیشہ عجم نے اسے 
بڑھا دیا ہے فقط زیب داستاں کے لیے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It was a plain and simple truth but the imagination of the Persian mind has confounded it with the poetic license.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مرے گلو میں ہے اک نغمہ جبرئیل آشوب 
سنبھال کر جسے رکھا ہے لامکاں کے لیے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My soul has a secret song, a defiance to Gabriel: A song I have preserved for life in eternity. 
(Translated by Naeem Siddiqui)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>