<Poem ID="01" Name="دعا" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="04" SectionName="منظومات">
  <Para Name="مسجد قرطبہ ميں لکھي گئي">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے یہی میری نماز، ہے یہی میرا وضو 
میری نواوں میں ہے میرے جگر کا لہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A PRAYER: Written in the Mosque of Cordova.
My invocations are sincere and true, they form my ablutions and prayers due.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        صحبت اہل صفا، نور و حضور و سرور 
سر خوش و پرسوز ہے لالہ لب آبجو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        لب آبجو: ندی کے کنارے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        One glance of guide such joy and warmth can grant, on marge of stream can bloom the tulip plant.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        راہ محبت میں ہے کون کسی کا رفیق 
ساتھ مرے رہ گئی ایک مری آرزو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        One has no comrade on Love’s journey long save fervent zeal, and passion great and strong.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میرا نشیمن نہیں درگہ میر و وزیر 
میرا نشیمن بھی تو، شاخ نشیمن بھی تو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O God, at gates of rich I do not bow, you are my dwelling place and nesting bough.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تجھ سے گریباں مرا مطلع صبح نشور 
تجھ سے مرے سینے میں آتش 'اللہ ھو'
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        صبح نشور: قیامت کی صبح۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your Love in my breast burns like Doomsday morn, the cry, He is God, on my lips is born.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تجھ سے مری زندگی سوز و تب و درد و داغ 
تو ہی مری آرزو، تو ہی مری جستجو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your Love, makes me fret with pain and pine, You are the only quest and aim of mine.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پاس اگر تو نہیں، شہر ہے ویراں تمام 
تو ہے تو آباد ہیں اجڑے ہوئے کاخ و کو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کاخ و کو: گلیاں اور محل۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Without You town appears devoid of life, when present, same town appears astir with strife.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پھر وہ شراب کہن مجھ کو عطا کہ میں 
ڈھونڈ رہا ہوں اسے توڑ کے جام و سبو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        For wine of gnosis I request and ask, to get some dregs I break the cup and glass.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چشم کرم ساقیا! دیر سے ہیں منتظر 
جلوتیوں کے سبو، خلوتیوں کے کدو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جلوتي: مجلسی لوگ۔
خلوتي: گوشہ نشین لوگ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The mystics’ gourds and commons’ pitchers wait for liquor of your Grace and Bounty great.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تیری خدائی سے ہے میرے جنوں کو گلہ 
اپنے لیے لامکاں، میرے لیے چار سو!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Against Your godhead I have a genuine plaint, for You the Spaceless, while for me restraint.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فلسفہ و شعر کی اور حقیقت ہے کیا 
حرف تمنا، جسے کہہ نہ سکیں رو برو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Both verse and wisdom indicate the way which longing face to face can not convey.
(Translated by Naeem Siddiqui)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>