<Poem ID="01" Name="" BookID="11" BookName="ارمغانِ حجاز" SectionID="05" SectionName="بہ یاران طریق">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بیا تا کار این امت بسازیم
قمار زندگے مردانہ بازیم
چنان نالیم اندر مسجد شہر
کہ دل در سینۂ ملا گدازیم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        آؤ ، ہم اس امت کے معاملات درست کریں ، زندگی کا کھیل مردانہ وار کھیلیں۔
شہر کی مسجد میں اس طرح سے نالہ و فریاد کریں، کہ ملّا کے سینہ میں جو (پتھر جیسا سخت) دل ہے، وہ بھی گداز ہو جائے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Come to set right the task of this race, to play life’s gamble with manly grace.
To weep in City mosque with such deep groans, that it melts the Mullah with our moans.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        قلندر جرہ باز سمانہا
بہ بال او سبک گردد گرانہا
فضای نیلگون نخچیر کاہش
نمی گردد بہ گرد شیانہا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        قلندر آسمانوں کا نر باز ہے، اس کی پرواز کے سامنے مشکل (مراحل) آسان ہو جاتے ہیں۔
اس کی شکارگاہ یہ نیلگوں فضا ہے، وہ (چڑیوں کے ) آشیانوں کے گرد نہیں گھومتا ۔ (اقبال اپنے آپ کو قلندر کہتے ہیں)
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Qalandar is a bold hawk of sky, a heavy weight to him so light like fly.
To him his hunting ground the whole blue space, on dust he makes never his aery’s base. 
(Qalandar; A Muslim sect of Faqirs (mendicants) who shave off the head and beard and abandon all worldly allurements, friends and relatives, travel from place to place, worshipping one God (now extinct). 
In this quatrain Iqbal expresses desire to create a Qalandar’s grace who paves little heed to this material life and its allurements.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ز جانم نغمہء ’’اللہ ہو‘‘ ریخت
چو کرد از رخت ہستی چار سو ریخت
بگیر از دست من سازی کہ تارش
ز سوز زخمہ چون اشکم فرو ریخت
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میری جان سے اللہ ہو کا نغمہ بکھرا ، تو یہ (جہان) چار سو میرے وجود کے لباس سے غبار کی مانند جھڑ گیا۔
میرے ہاتھ سے ساز لے لو کہ (اب) اس کے تار ، مضراب کے سوز سے میرے آنسوؤں کی مانند نیچے گر رہے ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When the Allah Hoo’s tick did hit my soul, I dusted the clothes’ of the cosmos whole.
Hold the violin quick as the chords so soon, are loosing my grip by quill’s burning tune. 
(Allah Hoo; is a hit of ‘Asbat’ or affirmation (of Allah) which takes a man to Baqa-billah (to become immortal in God’s presence); in the wake of Hazrat Mujaddad Alf Sani of Sarhand (Patiala State, in India). From Nafi (negation of gods) Iqbal flies higher to Asbat direct in wake of Sheikh Ahmad Sarhandi.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چو اشک اندر دل فطرت تپیدم
تپیدم تا بہ چشم او رسیدم
درخش من ز مژگانش توان دید
کہ من بر برگ کاہی کم چکیدم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میں فطرت کے دل میں آنسو کی مانند تڑپ تڑپ کے اس کی آنکھ تک پہنچا ہوں۔ 
میری چمک اس کی پلکوں پر دیکھی جا سکتی ہے ، کیونکہ میں گھاس کی پتّی پر کبھی نہیں ٹپکا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In the heart of nature like tears I groan, till I got in her eyes a place by moans.
On nature’s eyelash my shine could be seen. I fall seldom thus on leaves of grass green.
I am not such an ordinary thing which you can see on a grass leaf. (See me in nature’s heart and eye)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مرا از منطق ید بوی خامے
دلیل او دلیل ناتمامے
برویم بستہ درہا را کشاید
دو بیت از پیر رومی یا ز جامی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مجھے منطق سے خامی کی بو آتی ہے، اس کے دلائل اس کی ناتمامی کا ثبوت ہیں۔ 
پیر رومی یا جامی کے چند اشعار ، مجھ پر (حقیقت کے) بند دروازے کھول دیتے ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In logic I feel a smell of raws, its pleas and reasons are full of flaws.
To me the shut doors are opened soon; from a verse of Rumi or Jami’s croon.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بیا از من بگیر ن دیر سالہ
کہ بخشد روح با خاک پیالہ
اگر بش دہی از شیشۂ من
قد دم بروید شاخ لالہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        آ، مجھ سے وہ کہنہ شراب حاصل کر، جو پیالے کی خاک میں جان ڈال دیتی ہے۔
اگر تو شاخ لالہ کی آبیاری میری صراحی سے کرے ، وہ قد آدم تک بڑھ جائے ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Come and take from me that old wine’s bowl,* which gives the dust of bowl** quite a new soul; 
If you water this poppy from my can, a branch*** will grow to the size of a man.
*Means the lover’s way. 
**A hint or allusion to the lover’s heart. 
***If you would learn some knowledgeable things from me, the branch (an individual) of this poppy may be six feet long against its usual length of one foot.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بدست من ہمان دیرینہ چنگ است
درونش نالہ ہای رنگ رنگ است
ولی بنوازمش با ناخن شیر
کہ او را تار از رگہای سنگ است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میرے ہاتھ میں وہی پرانا ساز ہے، اس کے اندر رنگا رنگ نالے ہیں۔
لیکن میں اسے ناخن شیر سے بچاتا ہوں ، کیونکہ اس کے تار پتھر کی رگوں سے بنائے گئے ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The same old harp I hold in my hand, in which are hidden tunes of that land. 
With the lions claw, that harp I play, whose chords are made of rocky clay.
Iqbal wishes to infuse a spirit of jingoistic chauvinism in his nation as such he uses such symbols like rocky chords and rocky veins in his poetry. Such constructions are not used in the English language.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بگو از من بہ پرویزان این عصر
نہ فرہادم کہ گیرم تیشہ در دست
ز خاری کو خلد در سینۂ من
دل صد بیستون را میتوان خست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس دور کے پرویزوں سے کہہ دو، میں فرہاد نہیں کہ ہاتھ میں تیشہ لوں۔
میرے دل کے اندر جو کانٹا کھٹک رہا ہے، اس سے بیستوں جیسے سینکڑوں پہاڑوں کے دل زخمی کیے جا سکتے ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        To tyrants of this age I would thus say an axe I use not in the Farhad’s way.
From the prick of thorn I cherish in heart, a mountain’s heart too could be torn apart.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فقیرم ساز و سامانم نگاہی است
بہ چشمم کوہ یاران برگ کاہی است
ز من گیر این کہ زاغ دخمہ بہتر
از ن بازی کہ دست موز شاہیست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میں فقیر ہوں ، نگاہ میرا ساز و سامان ہے، جو چیز دوستوں کے لیے پہاڑ ہے، وہ میری نظر میں پر کاہ کے برابر ہے۔
مجھ سے سن کہ مرگھٹ کا کوا ، اس باز سے بہتر ہے، جو بادشاہ کے ہاتھ پر بیٹھنے والا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A poor I am whose asset is glance, a mountain to friends, to me a grass hence.
Listen this point that a vulture to me is better than a hawk tied on king’s knee.
A mountain to friends means viz, to whom my friends consider mountain due to his wealth and worldly pomp and show.)
(Translated by Q A Kabir)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="37">
      <Text Language="Original">
        در دل را بروی کس نبستم 
نہ از خویشان نہ از یاران گسستم
نشیمن ساختم در سینۂ خویش
تہ این چرخ گردان خوش نشستم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میں نے کسی پر اپنے دل کا دروازہ بند نہیں کیا ، نہ میں نے رشتہ داروں سے قطع تعلق کیا، نہ دوستوں سے۔ 
(البتہ) میں نے اپنا نشیمن اپنے سینہ میں بنا رکھا ہے، (اور) اس چرخ گرداں کے نیچے خوش بیٹھا ہوں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My heart’s door I shut not to any one, with kiths and kins I break links none.
I made my cottage in my bosom own, and passed my days with a happy tone.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="41">
      <Text Language="Original">
        درین گلشن ندارم ب و جاہی
نصیبم نے قبائی نے کلاہی
مرا گلچین بد موز چمن خواند
کہ دادم چشم نرگس را نگاہی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میں اس باغ (دنیا) میں کوئی شان و مرتبہ نہیں رکھتا، نہ میرے پاس قبا ہے، نہ کلاہ۔
گلچیں کہتا ہے کہ میں اہل چمن کو بری باتیں پڑھاتا ہوں، کیونکہ میں نے چشم نرگس کو دیکھنا سکھا دیا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        No pomp and show I have in this globe; nor destined to me a crest or robe.
As the garden’s foe the florist* dubbed me, since I gave to ‘nargis’ an eye to see.
The florist or gardener is an allusion to his country men or the Mullah, who dubbed the poet as an enemy of the nation because they were too loyal to the British in his opinion.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="45">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دو صد دانا درین محفل سخن گفت
سخن نازکتر از برگ سمن گفت
ولی با من بگو ن دیدہ ور کیست؟
کہ خاری دید و احوال چمن گفت
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس محفل (دنیا) میں سینکڑوں داناؤں نے برگ سمن سے نازک تر باتیں ہیں۔
لیکن مجھے بتا کہ وہ صاحب نظر کون ہے، جس نے کانٹے دیکھے اور چمن (اسلام) میں آنے والی بہار کی خبر دی۔ (اپنے متعلق کہہ رہے ہیں۔)
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Some points were discussed by hundred wise men, like jasmine fragrance the talks gave a ken. 
Who was that speaker and wise man great, from a thorn1 who told the Garden’s state.
A thorn: a Muslim who was treated like a thorn by rulers and his country men. Could be Mullah or title holder landlords who treated Iqbal like a thorn. Here Iqbal is giving a picture of events before 1937. Garden: means the nation.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="49">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ندانم نکتہ ہای علم و فن را
مقامی دیگرے دادم سخن را
میان کاروان سوز و سرورم
سبک پی کرد پیران کہن را
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میں علم و فن کے نکتے نہیں جانتا، مگر میں نے شاعری کو نیا مقام عطا کیا ہے۔
میرے سوز و سرور سے قافلے کے پیران کہن بھی، تیز رفتار ہو گئے ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The science or art points I claim not to wield, I gave a new style to poesy’s field.
In caravans see, my flame and sweet pace, I gave the old riders a taste for a race.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="53">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نپنداری کہ مرغ صبح خوانم
بجزہ و فغان چیزی ندانم
مدہ از دست دامانم کہ یابی
کلید باغ را در شیانم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        یہ گمان نہ کر کہ میں صبح کے وقت چہچہانے والے عام پرندوں کی طرح ہوں، اور آہ و فغاں کے علاوہ میرے پاس اور کچھ نہیں۔
میرا دامن مضبوطی سے تھام لے، تجھے باغ (حیات) کی چابی میرے ہی آشیانے سے ملے گی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I boast not to be a song bird1 of dawn; I know not any thing save wails long drawn. Leave not as such what I gave to thee, from my cottage take the Garden’s Key. 
(Cottage: Nest. Garden’s Key: Iqbal’s symbol for an inspired communication.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="57">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بچشم من جہان جز رہگذر نیست
ہزاران رہرو و یک ہمسفر نیست
گذشتم از ھجوم خویش و پیوند
کہ از خویشان کسی بیگانہ تر نیست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میری نظر میں یہ دنیا راہگذر کے سوائے اور کچھ نہیں ، مسافر ہزاروں ہیں، مگر ہمسفر ایک بھی نہیں۔
میں رشتہ داروں کے ہجوم سے الگ ہو گیا ہوں ، کیونکہ یہاں اپنوں سے زیادہ بیگانہ اور کوئی نہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This world is a path to my eyes and sense; none shares my journey in a thousand hence.
I saved my skin from scores of kith and kin; none stands in with me through thick and thin.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="61">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بہ این نابودمندی بودن موز
بہای خویش را افزودن موز
بیفت اندر محیط نغمہء من
بہ طوفانم چو در سودن موز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس فنا کے باوجود بقا میں آنا سیکھ، اپنی قدر و قیمت میں اضافہ کرنا سیکھ۔
میرے نغمہ کے سمندر میں چھلانگ لگا کے ، میرے طوفان کے اندر موتی کی مانند آرام پانا سیکھ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        With nothingness learn to live with grace, raise thy worth more and keep the faqr’s face.
Dive a bit deep in my song’s big main, like pearls learn to live in my storms rain.
Like pearls live with ease in floods and rain storms. As a poetical licence the rainstorm has been written as storms rain.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="65">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کہن پروردہء این خاکدانم
دلی از منزل خود دل گرانم
دمیدم گرچہ از فیض نم او
زمین راسمان خود ندانم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جانتا ہوں کہ میں اسی خاک (زمین) کا قدیم پروردہ ہوں، مگر میں اپنی اس منزل سے دل گراں ہوں۔
اگرچہ میں نے اسی کے نم کے فیض سے پرورش پائی ہے، مگر میں زمین کو اپنا آسمان (منزل مقصود) نہیں سمجھتا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        For long I’m gaining from this dusty mart, of my place yet I feel a heavy heart.
From boon of its moist I feel a life though. I never took this earth like a sky so.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="69">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ندانی تا نباشی محرم مرد
کہ دلھا زندہ گردد از دم مرد
نگہدارد زہ و نالہ خود را
کہ خود دار است چون مردان، غم مرد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جب تک تو کسی صاحب دل کی صحبت میں نہ بیٹھے، تو یہ بات نہیں سمجھ سکتا، کہ دل صاحب دل کی توجہ سے زیادہ ہوتے ہیں۔
 صاحب دل اپنے آہ و نالہ کی حفاظت کرتے ہیں ، کیونکہ ان کا غم (عشق) بھی انہی کی طرح خود دار ہے، (انداز جنوں کون سا ہم میں نہیں مجنوں! پر تیری طرح عشق کو رسوا نہیں کرتے۔)
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You cant learn aught ‘sans’ a conscious soul, the hearts get a life from breath of man’s dole. 
Who guards his ego by wails and sighs, and keeps self’s honour by ruthful eyes.
(Sans: French for without. Dole: Pain, grief.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="73">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نگاہی فرین جان در بدن بین
بشاخان نادمیدہ یاسمن بین
وگرنہ مثل تیری در کمانی
ہدف را با نگاہ تیر زن بین
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اپنے اندر ایسی نگاہ پیدا کر ، جو بدن میں موجود جان کو دیکھ لے، جو ان ان دیکھے پھولوں کو دیکھ سکے (جو) ابھی شاخ کے اندر ہیں۔
یا پھر کمان پر چڑھے ہوئے تیر کی مانند، تیر زن کی نظر سے ہدف دیکھ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Get a self knowing eye and see thy soul, in stems hidden yet see a jasmine whole.
If not like an arrow in the bow still, se aim from the archers eye and will.
Since the arrow is not conscious of itself, it does not know how the bowman would use it.Here it means that your position would then be like a slave to be used at the will of the master.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="77">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خرد بیگانہء ذوق یقین است
قمار علم و حکمت بد نشین است
دو صد بوحامد و رازی نیزرد
بنادانی کہ چشمش راہ بین است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        خرد ، ذوق یقین سے بینصیب ہے، علم و حکمت کا جوا بد آموز ہے،
اس ان پڑھ کے سامنے سینکڑوں غزالی اور رازی ہیچ ہیں، جس کی آنکھ سیدھی راہ دیکھتی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The wisdom knows not the certitude eyes, its gamble of knowledge on vice path lies. 
Hundred Razis, Ghazalis wont equalize, to worth of a fool who holds seeing eye.
Basic thought: What is certitude? What wisdom will say? Thy logic’s gamble would lead astray.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="81">
      <Text Language="Original">
        قماش و نقرہ و لعل و گہر چیست؟
غلام خوشگل و زرین کمر چیست؟
چو یزدان از دو گیتی بے نیازند
دگر سرمایۂ اہل ہنر چیست؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        (اہل ہنر کی نظروں میں) قماش (ریشمی لباس) چاندی ، لعل و گوہر؛ اور خوبصورت اور زرّیں کمر خادموں کی کیا حیثیت ہے۔
وہ اپنے اللہ تعالے کی طرح دونوں جہانوں سے بے نیاز ہیں ، اور یہی بے نیازی ان کی دولت ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What are the clothes, gold jewels and gems? Rows of slaves handsome, and gold waist femme?
Like God they ‘are free’* from both worlds needs, is this not wealth which a skill’d man** heeds.
*Unconcerned. 
**A godly man, virtuous.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="85">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خودی را نشۂ من عین ہوش است
ازن میخانۂ من کم خروش است
می من گرچہ نا صاف است درکش
کہ این تہ جرعۂ خمہای دوش است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        خودی کے لیے میرا نشہ عین ہوش ہے، یہی وجہ ہے کہ میرے میکدہ میں شور و غوغا نہیں۔
اگرچہ میری شراب اتنی صاف نہیں، مگر اسے پی جا، کیونکہ یہ قدیم (دور اسلام) کے خموں کی بچی ہوئی شراب کا آخری گھونٹ ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        To self my wine1 gives full sense and poise, my pub since shuns all the din and noise. 
My wine not so fine in its first sip though, in bottom lies but a slip of past glow. 
My wine: My education.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="89">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ترا با خرقہ و عمامہ کاری
من از خود یافتم بوی نگاری
ہمین یک چوب نے سرمایۂ من
نہ چوب منبری نے چوب داری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تو گدڑی (پیروں) اور دستار (عالموں ) کے پیچھے بھاگتا ہے، (مگر) میں نے اپنے آپ سے محبوب کی خوشبو پائی ہے۔ 
یہی ایک چوب نے میرا سرمایہ ہے ، نہ میں چوب منبر کی خواہش رکھتا ہوں ، نہ چوبدار کی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        For robes and turbans why you feel a bent, I have found in my ego that beauty’s scent.
To me wooden life* is wealth and heart’s gloss, I carve not a wood for pulpit or cross. 
*A wooden fife or flute.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="93">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چو دیدم جوھر ئینۂ خویش
گرفتم خلوت اندر سینۂ خویش
ازین دانشوران کور و بے ذوق
رمیدم با غم دیرینۂ خویش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جب میں نے اپنے آئینہ (قلب) کا جوہر دیکھا، تو میں اپنے سینے کے اندر خلوت گزیں ہو گیا۔
اور اپنے غم دیرینہ (عشق) کو لے کر، ان اندھے اور بے ذوق دانشوروں سے دور بھاگ گیا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        As soon I espied my ego’s essence, I took a lone retreat in bosom hence.
From these wise blinds who have no taste, for old love’s flame I ran with haste.
Ego’s essence: The hidden qualities of ego (khudi). A lone retreat in bosom: Meditations, self consciousness (viz Moraqaba). Wise blinds: Mullah and Sufi.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="97">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چو رخت خویش بر بستم ازین خاک
ہمہ گفتند با ما شنا بود
ولیکن کس ندانست این مسافر
چہ گفت و با کہ گفت و از کجا بود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جب میں نے اس دنیا سے رخت (سفر) باندھا ، تو سب نے کہا: یہ ہمارا جاننے والا تھا۔
 مگر کوئی نہیں سمجھا کہ اس مسافر نے کیا کہا ، کس سے کہا اور یہ کہاں سے تھا؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When I packed my self from this dusty fuss, all were saying he was so close to us. 
But no one ever knew this seeker’s aim, I said to them what? From where I came. 
This quatrain (twin couplet) was written by Iqbal a few months before his death.
[Translated by Q A Kabir]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>