<Poem ID="07" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="02" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پھر چراغ لالہ سے روشن ہوئے کوہ و دمن 
مجھ کو پھر نغموں پہ اکسانے لگا مرغ چمن
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Hill and vale once more under the poppy’s lamps are bright; in my heart the nightingale has set new songs alight.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پھول ہیں صحرا میں یا پریاں قطار اندر قطار 
اودے اودے، نیلے نیلے، پیلے پیلے پیرہن
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Violet, violet, azure, azure, golden, golden mantles: Flowers, or fairies of the desert, rank on rank in sight?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        برگ گل پر رکھ گئی شبنم کا موتی باد صبح 
اور چمکاتی ہے اس موتی کو سورج کی کرن
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        On the rosy-spray dawn’s soft breeze has left a pearl of dew; now the sunbeam turns this gem a yet more glittering white.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حسن بے پروا کو اپنی بے نقابی کے لیے 
ہوں اگر شہروں سے بن پیارے تو شہر اچھے کہ بن
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Town or woodland, which is sweeter, if for her unveiling careless beauty love towns less than where green woods invite?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اپنے من میں ڈوب کر پا جا سراغ زندگی 
تو اگر میرا نہیں بنتا نہ بن، اپنا تو بن
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Delve into your soul and there seek our life’s buried tracks; will you not be mine? Then be not mine, be your own right!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        من کی دنیا ! من کی دنیا سوز و مستی، جذب و شوق 
تن کی دنیا! تن کی دنیا سود و سودا، مکروفن
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        World of soul – the world of fire and ecstasy and longing: World of sense – the world of gain that fraud and cunning blight.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        من کی دولت ہاتھ آتی ہے تو پھر جاتی نہیں 
تن کی دولت چھاوں ہے، آتا ہے دھن جاتا ہے دھن
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Treasure of the soul once won is never lost again: Treasure gold, a shadow – wealth soon comes and soon takes flight.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        من کی دنیا میں نہ پایا میں نے افرنگی کا راج 
من کی دنیا میں نہ دیکھے میں نے شیخ و برہمن
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In the spirit’s world I have not seen a white man’s Raj, in that world I have not seen Hindu and Muslim fight.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پانی پانی کر گئی مجھ کو قلندر کی یہ بات 
تو جھکا جب غیر کے آگے، نہ من تیرا نہ تن
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Shame and shame that hermit’s saying pouted on me – you forfeit body and soul alike if once you cringe to another’s might! 
(Translated by V.G. Kiernan)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>