<Poem ID="25" Name="اذان" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="04" SectionName="منظومات">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اک رات ستاروں سے کہا نجم سحر نے 
آدم کو بھی دیکھا ہے کسی نے کبھی بیدار؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        One night in a vision, I saw a morning star, asking the stars if they saw man ever awake.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کہنے لگا مریخ، ادا فہم ہے تقدیر 
ہے نیند ہی اس چھوٹے سے فتنے کو سزاوار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Mercury said, ‘Destiny has wisely decreed, that this impish trouble maker should always be asleep.’
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زہرہ نے کہا، اور کوئی بات نہیں کیا؟ 
اس کرمک شب کور سے کیا ہم کو سروکار!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Venus replied ill disdain ‘Let us mind our business; thus night-blind insect is beneath our contempt.’
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بولا مہ کامل کہ وہ کوکب ہے زمینی 
تم شب کو نمودار ہو، وہ دن کو نمودار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The full moon said, ‘He is a star of the earth; you appear by night, and he appears by day;
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        واقف ہو اگر لذت بیداری شب سے 
اونچی ہے ثریا سے بھی یہ خاک پر اسرار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This handful of dust, when keeping awake at night, is loftier than the galaxies in heaven;
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آغوش میں اس کی وہ تجلی ہے کہ جس میں 
کھو جائیں گے افلاک کے سب ثابت و سیار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He has a beatific light concealed in his soul: A light that will eclipse the brightest stars and planets.’
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ناگاہ فضا بانگ اذاں سے ہوئی لبریز 
وہ نعرہ کہ ہل جاتا ہے جس سے دل کہسار!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Then came the echoing thunder of the sound of azan; the thunder which gives shivers to mountains’ hearts.
(Translated by Naim Siddiqui)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>