<Poem ID="23" Name="سید کی لوح تربت" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="1a" SectionName="حصہ اول">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے کہ تیرا مرغ جاں تار نفس میں ہے اسیر
اے کہ تیری روح کا طائر قفس میں ہے اسیر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE TOMB-STONE OF SAIYYID
O you whose life is confined in the material world. O you whose soul is imprisoned in the cage.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اس چمن کے نغمہ پیرائوں کی آزادی تو دیکھ
شہر جو اجڑا ہوا تھا اس کی آبادی تو دیکھ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Look at the freedom of this garden's warblers. Look at the prosperity of those once desolate.
* This and the following verse allude to the beginning of the renaissance of the Indian Muslims resulting from the efforts of Sir Saiyyid Ahmad Khan.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فکر رہتی تھی مجھے جس کی وہ محفل ہے یہی
صبر و استقلال کی کھیتی کا حاصل ہے یہی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This is the congregation with which I was concerned. This is the reward of patience and perseverance.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سنگ تربت ہے مرا گرویدہ تقریر دیکھ
چشم باطن سے ذرا اس لوح کی تحریر دیکھ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My tomb-stone is ardently desirous of speech, look! At this tomb-stone's inscription with insight look!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مدعا تیرا اگر دنیا میں ہے تعلیم دیں
ترک دنیا قوم کو اپنی نہ سکھلانا کہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If your aim in the world is din's education; never teach your nation world's abdication.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وا نہ کرنا فرقہ بندی کے لیے اپنی زباں
چھپ کے ہے بیٹھا ہوا ہنگامہ محشر یہاں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Do not use your tongue for sectarianism; Resurrection Day's tumult for booty is stalking.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وصل کے اسباب پیدا ہوں تری تحریر سے
دیکھ کوئی دل نہ دکھ جائے تری تقریر سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your writings should pave the way for unity. Beware! No heart should be hurt by your speech.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        محفل نو میں پرانی داستانوں کو نہ چھیڑ
رنگ پر جو اب نہ آئیں ان فسانوں کو نہ چھیڑ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In the new congregation do not start old tales; do not start again what are now unacceptable tales.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تو اگر کوئی مدبر ہے تو سن میری صدا
ہے دلیری دست ارباب سیاست کا عصا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Listen to my advice if you are any statesman: Courage is your support if you are a leader of men.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عرض مطلب سے جھجک جانا نہیں زیبا تجھے
نیک ہے نیت اگر تیری تو کیا پروا تجھے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Hesitation in expressing your purpose does not behoove you; if your intentions are good you should not fear anything.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بندہ مومن کا دل بیم و ریا سے پاک ہے
قوت فرماں روا کے سامنے بے باک ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Mu’min's heart is clear of fear and hypocrisy. The Mu’min's heart is fearless against the ruler's power.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہو اگر ہاتھوں میں تیرے خامہء معجز رقم
شیشہ دل ہو اگر تیرا مثال جام جم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If your hands do hold the miraculous pen; if your heart's cup is clear like the cup of Jam and his cooperators.
Jam: This is the legendary wine-cup of a pre-Islamic Persian emperor, Jamshâd, in which he could see the world.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پاک رکھ اپنی زباں، تلمیذ رحمانی ہے تو
ہو نہ جائے دیکھنا تیری صدا بے آبرو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You are a Divine pupil! Keep your tongue immaculate! Beware! Lest your prayer's call remains unanswered!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سونے والوں کو جگا دے شعر کے اعجاز سے
خرمن باطل جلا دے شعلہ آواز سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        With the miracle of your verse awaken those sleeping; burn down falsehood's produce with the flame of your call.
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>