<Poem ID="09" Name="ترانہ ملی" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چین و عرب ہمارا، ہندوستاں ہمارا 
مسلم ہیں ہم، وطن ہے سارا جہاں ہمارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE MUSLIM NATIONAL ANTHEM
China and Arabia are ours, India is also ours; we are Muslims, whole world is homeland of ours.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        توحید کی امانت سینوں میں ہے ہمارے 
آساں نہیں مٹانا نام و نشاں ہمارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The trust of Divine Unity is in the breasts of ours; it is not easy to destroy the identity of ours.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دنیا کے بت کدوں میں پہلا وہ گھر خدا کا 
ہم اس کے پاسباں ہیں، وہ پاسباں ہمارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Among the world’s temples that first House of God; we are its sentinels, it is the sentinel of ours.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تیغوں کے سائے میں ہم پل کر جواں ہوئے ہیں 
خنجر ہلال کا ہے قومی نشاں ہمارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        We have been brought up under the shade of swords; the crescent’s dagger is the national insignia of ours.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مغرب کی وادیوں میں گونجی اذاں ہماری 
تھمتا نہ تھا کسی سے سیل رواں ہمارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Our Adhan echoed in the valleys of the West; none could stop the advancing flood of ours.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        باطل سے دنبے والے اے آسماں نہیں ہم 
سو بار کر چکا ہے تو امتحاں ہمارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        We cannot be bowed down by falsehood, O sky! Hundreds of times you have done tests of ours.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے گلستان اندلس! وہ دن ہیں یاد تجھ کو 
تھا تیری ڈالیوں پر جب آشیاں ہمارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O garden of Andalus! Do you remember the days when your branches harbored the nest of ours?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے موج دجلہ! تو بھی پہچانتی ہے ہم کو 
اب تک ہے تیرا دریا افسانہ خواں ہمارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O wave of the Tigris! You also recognize us; your river still recites the stories of ours.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے ارض پاک! تیری حرمت پہ کٹ مرے ہم
ہے خوں تری رگوں میں اب تک رواں ہمارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O Holy Land! For your honor we fought to the bitter end; still flowing in your veins is the blood of ours.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سالار کارواں ہے میر حجاز اپنا 
اس نام سے ہے باقی آرام جاں ہمارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مير حجاز: مراد ہے محمد (صلعم)۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Hijaz’s Chief is the commander of our caravan; this name preserves solace of the hearts of ours.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اقبال کا ترانہ بانگ درا ہے گویا 
ہوتا ہے جادہ پیما پھر کارواں ہمارا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جادہ پيما: سفر پر روانہ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This anthem of Iqbal is the clarion’s* call so to say; again prepares for the journey the caravan of ours.
* This is also a subtle reference to his book Bang-i-Dara which contains material for the rejuvenation and renaissance of world Muslims.)
(Translated by Dr. M.A.K. Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>