<Poem ID="19" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="02" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کمال ترک نہیں آب و گل سے مہجوری 
کمال ترک ہے تسخیر خاکی و نوری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مہجوري: جدائی، علیحدگی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The way to renounce is to conquer the earth and heaven; the way to renounce is not to starve oneself to death.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میں ایسے فقر سے اے اہل حلقہ باز آیا 
تمھارا فقر ہے بے دولتی و رنجوری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اہل حلقہ:تصوّف کی ایک اصطلاح۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O cultists! I like not your austere piety; your piety is penury, suffering and grief.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہ فقر کے لیے موزوں، نہ سلطنت کے لیے 
وہ قوم جس نے گنوایا متاع تیموری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A nation that has lost Taimur’s great heritage, is unfit for piety, and is unfit to rule.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سنے نہ ساقی مہ وش تو اور بھی اچھا 
عیار گرمی صحبت ہے حرف معذوری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If the sweet cup-bearer listens not to me, it is good; when I say, ‘no more’, that will only bring me more.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حکیم و عارف و صوفی، تمام مست ظہور 
کسے خبر کہ تجلی ہے عین مستوری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Sufi and his peers are all engrossed in a glimpse; they know not that concealment is itself a vision.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وہ ملتفت ہوں تو کنج قفس بھی آزادی 
نہ ہوں تو صحن چمن بھی مقام مجبوری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اہل حلقہ:متوجہ ، مہربان۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Bondage is freedom with favours from on high, and when favours are withheld, even freedom is bondage.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        برا نہ مان، ذرا آزما کے دیکھ اسے 
فرنگ دل کی خرابی، خرد کی معموری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The West is a treasure-house for the reason’s quest; but for the heart it is a source of decay and death. 
(Translated by Naim Siddiqui)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>