<Poem ID="40" Name="جگنو" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="1a" SectionName="حصہ اول">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جگنو کی روشنی ہے کاشانہء چمن میں
یا شمع جل رہی ہے پھولوں کی انجمن میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE FIRE-FLY
The fire-fly's light is shining in the garden's abode; or a candle is lighted in the assembly of flowers?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آیا ہے آسماں سے اڑ کر کوئی ستارہ
یا جان پڑ گئی ہے مہتاب کی کرن میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Has some star flown down from the sky? Or has a moon's ray been brought to life?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یا شب کی سلطنت میں دن کا سفیر آیا
غربت میں آ کے چمکا، گمنام تھا وطن میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Or the emissary of the day has come to the night's kingdom? Has become prosperous in foreign land was unknown in homeland?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تکمہ کوئی گرا ہے مہتاب کی قبا کا
ذرہ ہے یا نمایاں سورج کے پیرہن میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Has some button fallen from the cloak of the moon? Or some speck has become prominent in the sun's shirt?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حسن قدیم کی یہ پوشیدہ اک جھلک تھی
لے آئی جس کو قدرت خلوت سے انجمن میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Was it the concealed glimpse of the Eternal Beauty, which was brought by Nature out of solitude into the assembly?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چھوٹے سے چاند میں ہے ظلمت بھی روشنی بھی
نکلا کبھی گہن سے، آیا کبھی گہن میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Darkness as well as light is in this little moon; now it is out of eclipse, now it is in eclipse.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پروانہ اک پتنگا، جگنو بھی اک پتنگا
وہ روشنی کا طالب، یہ روشنی سراپا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The moth is an insect, as the fire-fly is an insect; the former needs light, the latter is light's embodiment.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہر چیز کو جہاں میں قدرت نے دلبری دی
پروانے کو تپش دی، جگنو کو روشنی دی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Nature gave beauty to everything in the universe. It gave agitation to moth; it gave light to fire-fly.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رنگیں نوا بنایا مرغان بے زباں کو
گل کو زبان دے کر تعلیم خامشی دی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It gave flowery music to the speechless bird. Having given tongue to the rose* taught it to be silent.
* This is a beautiful metaphor for the petals of the rose flower.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نظارئہ شفق کی خوبی زوال میں تھی
چمکا کے اس پری کو تھوڑی سی زندگی دی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The beauty of twilight's spectacle was decaying; brightening up this fairy, a short life it gave.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رنگیں کیا سحر کو، بانکی دلھن کی صورت
پہنا کے لال جوڑا شبنم کی آرسی دی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It gave colour to the dawn like a beautiful bride; clothing it in red dress gave it the mirror of dew.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سایہ دیا شجر کو، پرواز دی ہوا کو
پانی کو دی روانی، موجوں کو بے کلی دی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It gave shade to the tree, gave flight to the wind. It gave flow to water, gave restlessness to waves.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ امتیاز لیکن اک بات ہے ہماری
جگنو کا دن وہی ہے جو رات ہے ہماری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This distinction but is a way of our thinking; the fire-fly's day is the same as our night.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حسن ازل کی پیدا ہر چیز میں جھلک ہے
انساں میں وہ سخن ہے، غنچے میں وہ چٹک ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Eternal Beauty's reflection is present in everything. It is speech in man. It is blooming in the flower bud.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ چاند آسماں کا شاعر کا دل ہے گویا
واں چاندنی ہے جو کچھ، یاں درد کی کسک ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This moon in the sky is the poet's heart so to say. It is moonlight there what here the prick of pathos is.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="31">
      <Text Language="Original">
        انداز گفتگو نے دھوکے دیے ہیں ورنہ
نغمہ ہے بوئے بلبل، بو پھول کی چہک ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The manners of speech have deceived us, otherwise song is nightingale's fragrance; flower's fragrance is its song.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کثرت میں ہو گیا ہے وحدت کا راز مخفی
جگنو میں جو چمک ہے وہ پھول میں مہک ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Concealed in plurality is the secret of the Unity. What is fire-fly’s brightness is flower’s fragrance.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="35">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ اختلاف پھر کیوں ہنگاموں کا محل ہو
ہر شے میں جبکہ پنہاں خاموشی ازل ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Why should this difference be occasion for dissensions? When the Primeval Day’s silence be concealed in everything.
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>