<Poem ID="57" Name="اے پیر حرم" BookID="03" BookName="ضربِ کلیم" SectionID="01" SectionName="اسلام اور مسلمان">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے پیر حرم! رسم و رہ خانقہی چھوڑ 
مقصود سمجھ میری نوائے سحری کا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        TO ELDER OF THE SHRINE
O Shaikh, who tend the Holy Shrine, discard these monkish modes of thine; grasp what morning songs denote, what aim or end I would promote.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اللہ رکھے تیرے جوانوں کو سلامت! 
دے ان کو سبق خود شکنی، خود نگری کا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        خود شکني: اپنے آپ کو توڑنا، مراد ہے انسان کو غرور اور تکبر سے پاک کرنا۔ 
خود نگري: اپنے آپ کو دیکھنا؛ مراد ہے اپنے آپ کی پہچان۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        May God preserve the youth you guide, and may they all by Faith abide! Restraint and order you must teach to shun conceit you ought to preach.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تو ان کو سکھا خارا شگافی کے طریقے 
مغرب نے سکھایا انھیں فن شیشہ گری کا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        خارا شگافي: سخت پتھر میں سراخ کرنا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Those who blow on glass in West have taught the youth repose and rest; let them imbibe to bear the shocks, and cut the stones and hew the rocks.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دل توڑ گئی ان کا دو صدیوں کی غلامی 
دارو کوئی سوچ ان کی پریشاں نظری کا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        دارو: دوا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The foreign Yoke that ran for periods long has drained the blood or heart, so strong. Think of some cure, panacea or aught to bring to end their sight distraught.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کہہ جاتا ہوں میں زور جنوں میں ترے اسرار 
مجھ کو بھی صلہ دے مری آشفتہ سری کا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In fits of frenzy strong and great of mysteries, God I start to Prate, bestow on my distracted brain some recompense for this pain. 
(Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>