<Poem ID="11" Name="سیاسیات حاضرہ" BookID="10" BookName="پس چہ بائد کرد" SectionID="01" SectionName="پس چہ بائد کرد">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        می کند بند غلامان سخت تر
حریت می خواند او را بی بصر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        آج کل کا سیا ستدان محکوموں کی زنجیروں کو زیادہ مظبوط بناتا ہے ۔ کم نظر یہ سمجھتا ہے کہ وہ غلاموں کی آزادی کے لیے کام کر رہا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It strengthens the chains of the slaves; the inexperienced call it ‘freedom’.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گرمی ہنگامۂ جمہور دید
پردہ بر روی ملوکیت کشید
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جب اس نے عوام کی (تحریک آزادی) کے ہنگامے کی گرمی دیکھی تو بادشاہت کے چہرے پر پردہ ڈال دیا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When it saw the people’s agitation, it drew a curtain over the face of imperialism.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سلطنت را جامع اقوام گفت
کار خود را پختہ کرد و خام گفت
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ( کہنے لگا ) کہ سلطنت تو مختلف اقوام کو اکٹھا کر دیتی ہے، بات اس نے کام کی کہی لیکن اپنے مطلب کا پکّا رہا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It characterized State as multi-national, and thus covered its trickery under this naïve phrase.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        در فضایش بال و پر نتوان گشود
با کلیدش ہیچ در نتوان گشود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ایسی سیاست کی فضا میں غلاموں کے لیے بال و پر کھولنا ممکن نہیں ۔ اس کی چابی سے کوئی دروازہ نہیں کھولا جا سکتا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        One can hardly move about freely in its environment, no door can be opened by its keys.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گفت با مرغ قفس "اے دردمند
آشیان در خانۂ صیاد بند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کوئی سیاستدان مرغ قفس سے کہتا ہے کہ 'اے دردمند تو شکاری کے گھر کے اندر آشیانہ بنا لے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It said to the bird in cage, ‘O sorrow-stricken bird, build thy nest in the house of the hunter.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہر کہ سازد آشیان در دشت و مرغ"
او نباشد ایمن از شاہین و چرغ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جو کوئی صحرا و مرغزار میں آشیانہ بناتا ہے، وہ شاہین اور شکرے سے محفوظ نہیں رہتا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He who builds his nest in meadows and gardens cannot be secure from falcon and hawk.’
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        از فسونش مرغ زیرک دانہ مست
نالہ ہا اندر گلوی خود شکست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس کےفسوں سے سمجھدار پرندہ جو دانے پر فریفتہ ہے اپنے نالہ و فریاد کو بلند نہں کرتا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Under its spell, the self-deluding bird, enamoured of grain, choked its wailings in its throat.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حریت خواہی بہ پیچاکش میفت
تشنہ میر و بر نم تاکش میفت
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اگر تو آزادی چاہتا ہے تو ایسے سیاستدان کے فریب میں نہ آ، پیاسا مر جا لیکن اس کے انگور کے رس کا طالب نہ ہو۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If you desire (real) freedom, do not get caught in its coils, remain thirsty rather than pine for moisture from its vine.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        الحذر از گرمی گفتار او
الحذر از حرف پہلو دار او
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ایسے سیاستدان کی گرمئ گفتار اور حرف پہلودار (ذو معنی) سے اللہ تعالے بچائیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        May God protect you from its speech and its equivocal word!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چشم ہا از سرمہ اش بی نور تر
بندۂ مجبور ازو مجبور تر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس کا سرمہ آنکھوں کو اور زیادہ بے نور کر دیتا ہے اور اس کی سیاست مجبور انسان کو اور مجبور بنا دیتی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The eyes (of the people), through its collyrium, become more blind, and the helpless are rendered more helpless through its subterfuges.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        از شراب ساتگینش الحذر
از قمار بدنشینش الحذر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس کے جام کی شراب اور اس کی بدنیتی پر مبنی کھیل سے اللہ تعالے بچائیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        May God protect us from the wine of its cup, and from its gamester’s tricks!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        از خودی غافل نگردد مرد حر
حفظ خود کن حب افیونش مخور
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مرد حر اپنی خودی سے غافل نہیں ہوتا۔ تو اپنی حفاظت کے لیے ایسے سیاستدان کی افیون کی گولی نہ کھا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The free man does not neglect his ego; protect yourself, do not take its opium pill.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پیش فرعونان بگو حرف کلیم
تا کند ضرب تو دریا را دونیم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        فرعونوں کے سامنے حضرت موسی (علیہ) کی بیباکانہ بات کر تا کہ تیری ضرب سمندر کو دو ثکڑے کر دے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Speak the word of (truth like) Moses before Pharaohs1 so that your stroke may split the river into two.2
(1. Moses was ordered by God to go to Pharaoh to warn him of the wrongs being done by him. According to a well-known tradition, it is jihad to speak the truth before a tyrant. 2. This refers to the incident in the history of the Israelites when Moses threw his staff into the river which sundered its water giving way to his followers to cross it safely while being pursued by the army of the Pharaoh.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        داغم از رسوائی این کاروان
در امیر او ندیدم نور جان
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس قافلے کی رسوائی کے خیال سے میرا دل داغ داغ ہے میں اس کے امیر کے قلب میں کوئی نور نہیں دیکھتا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My heart is grieved at the dishonour suffered by the caravan; I do not see the light of soul in its leader.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تن پرست و جاہ مست و کم نگہ
اندرونش بی نصیب از لاالہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        امیر کاروان ، تن پرست، جاہ مست اور کوتاہ نظر ہے اس کا اندرون لا الہ کے نور سے خالی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He is a worshipper of the body, ambitious of worldly honour and short-sighted, his heart devoid of the light of la ilah.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="31">
      <Text Language="Original">
        در حرم زاد و کلیسا را مرید
پردۂ ناموس ما را بر درید
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        یہ شخص حرم میں پیدا ہوا تھا کللیسا کا مرید ہو گیا۔ اس نے ہماری غیرت ملّی کا پردہ چاک چاک کر دیا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He was born a Muslim but is a disciple of the church; he rent asunder the veil of our honour.	 
(‘Disciples of the church’ refers to Muslim leaders who sided with the British rulers (Christians) and thus jeopardized the interests of the Muslim community. The best example was provided by some members of the Muslim Delegation at the Second Round Table Conference in London in 1931.) This ‘tradition’ of the disciples of the church is followed more devotedly by the contemporary Muslim rulers.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دامن او را گرفتن ابلہی است
سینۂ او از دل روشن تہی است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ایسے شخص کا دامن پکڑنا حماقت ہے کیونکہ اس کا سینہ قلب منوّر سے خالی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        To catch hold of his skirt is the height of foolishness; his breast is devoid of a shining heart.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="35">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اندرین رہ تکیہ بر خود کن کہ مرد
صید آہو با سگ کوری نکرد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تو اس راہ میں اپنے آپ پر اعتماد کر کیونکہ کوئی شخص اندھے کتّے کے ساتھ ہرن کا شکار نہیں کر سکتا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In this path rely on yourself, for nobody goes hunting deer with the help of blind dogs.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="37">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آہ از قومی کہ چشم از خویش بست
دل بہ غیر ﷲ داد، از خود گسست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        افسوس اس قوم پر جو اپنے آپ سے آنکھیں بند کر لے، اپنے آپ سے کٹ جاے اور دل غیر اللہ کو دے دے ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Alas! For the nation that shuts its eyes from itself, gives its heart to the other-than-God, and breaks loose from itself.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="39">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تا خودی در سینۂ ملت بمرد
کوہ، کاہی کرد و باد او را ببرد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جب ملّت کے سینے میں خودی مر گئی تو اس کے کوہ نے کاہ کا انداز اختیار کر لیا اور اسے ہوا اڑا کر لے گئی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When khudi died in the breast of the millat, the mountain became a straw and was blown away by the wind.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="41">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گرچہ دارد لاالہ اندر نھاد
از بطون او مسلمانی نزاد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اگرچہ یہ ملّت اپنی نہاد میں لا الہ رکھتی ہے مگر اس کی ماؤں کے پیٹ سے کوئی ایسا مسلمان پیدا نہیں ہوا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Although it has la ilah in its very constitution, yet it gave birth to no true Muslim.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="43">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آنکہ بخشد بی یقینان را یقین
آنکہ لرزد از سجود او زمین
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جو بے یقینوں کو یقین بخشے، جس کے سجدے سے زمین لرز اٹھے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        One who gives faith to the faithless, whose self-prostration makes the earth tremble,
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="45">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آنکہ زیر تیغ گوید لاالہ
آنکہ از خونش بروید لاالہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جو تلوار کے نیچے بھی لا الہ کہے جس کے خون کے (ہر قطرے ّ) سے لا الہ کا نقش ابھرے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Who utters ‘there is no god’ at the risk of his life, from whose blood grows (the flower of) there is no god.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="47">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آن سرور، آن سوز مشتاقی نماند
در حرم صاحبدلی باقی نماند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        نہ وہ سرور باقی رہا اور نہ وہ شوق (محبت) کا سوز ۔ حرم کے اندر کوئی صاحب دل نظر نہیں آتا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        That ecstasy, that ardour of longing, has disappeared, no longer is there such a man of heart in the sanctuary.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="49">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے مسلمان اندرین دیر کہن
تا کجا باشی بہ بند اھرمن
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اے مسلمان تو اس دنیا میں کب تک شیطان کا اسیر رہے گا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O Muslim, in this ancient tavern, how long will you remain in the snares of Satan?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="51">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جہد با توفیق و لذت در طلب
کس نیابد بی نیاز نیم شب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تجھے ایسی کوشش کی ضرورت ہے جو تا حد ہمت کی جاے اور جس کے اندر لذّت محسوس ہو مگر یہ چیز گریہ نیم شب کے بغیر حاصل نہیں ہو سکتی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Ask (of God) His blessing in your striving and delight therein, nothing is attained without midnight supplications.
(Midnight supplications: ‘The rising by night is surely the fiercest way to tread and most effective in speech’ – the Qur’an, lxxiii. 6. In Payom-i M’ashriq, Allamah said: The root of this gem lies in midnight bewailings. And, in Zabur-i ‘Ajam : Sprinkle thy morning tears upon life’s desert plain. New harvest scarce appears except thou sow thy grain.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="53">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زیستن تا کی بہ بحر اندر چو خس
سخت شو چون کوہ از ضبط نفس
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تو کب تک دریا میں پڑے ہوے تنکے کی مانند زندگی بسر کرے گا ۔ ضبط نفس سے اپنے اندر پہاڑ کی مظبوتی پیدا کر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        How long to live in the ocean like a floating straw? Become hard like a mountain through self-control.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="55">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گرچہ دانا حال دل با کس نگفت
از تو درد خویش نتوانم نہفت
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اگرچہ سمجھدار آدمی اپنے دل کی بات کسی کو نہیں بتاتا مگر میں تجھ سے اپنا درد چھپا نہیں سکتا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Although the wise do not reveal the state of their heart to anybody, I cannot hide from you my heart’s grief.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="57">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تا غلامم در غلامی زادہ ام
ز آستان کعبہ دور افتادہ ام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        چونکہ میں غلام ہوں اور غلامی کے اندر پیدا ہوا ہوں اس لیے آستان کعبہ سے دور جا پڑا ہوں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Being a slave and born in slavery, I have wandered away from the threshold of the Ka’bah.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="59">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چون بنام مصطفی خوانم درود
از خجالت آب می گردد وجود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جب میں حضور اکرم (صلعم) پر درود شریف بھیجتا ہوں تو میرا وجود شرم سے پانی پانی ہو جاتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When I recite salutations in the name of Mustafa (S.A.W.), my whole being suffers acutely through shame.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="61">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عشق میگوید کہ اے محکوم غیر
سینۂ تو از بتان مانند دیر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        عشق مجھ سے کہتا ہے کہ 'اے غیر کے محکوم بتوں کی وجہ سے تیرا سینہ بتخانہ بنا ہوا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Love says: ‘O slave of others, your breast is like a temple full of idols.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="63">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تا نداری از محمد رنگ و بو
از درود خود میالا نام او
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جب تک آنحضور (صلعم) کے (اخلاق عالیہ ) کا رنگ و بو اختیار نہیں کر تا اپنے درود شریف سے ان کے نام کو آلودہ نہ کر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        So long as you do not have the colour of Muhammad (S.A.W.) do not pollute his name by your salutations.’
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="65">
      <Text Language="Original">
        از قیام بی حضور من مپرس
از سجود بی سرور من مپرس
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میری نماز کے قیام بے حضور اور سجود بےسرور کی بات نہ پوچھ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Do not ask me about my inattentive standing in prayer and about my prostration lacking in ecstasy.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="67">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جلوۂ حق گرچہ باشد یک نفس
قسمت مردان آزاد است و بس
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اللہ تعالے کا جلوہ خواہ ایک لمحہ کے لیے ہو صرف مرد آزاد کو نصیب ہوتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        God’s manifestation, although it may last but for a moment, is enjoyed by free people alone.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="69">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مردی آزادے چو آید در سجود
در طوافش گرم رو چرخ کبود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        آزاد مرد جب سجدے میں گرتا ہے تو یہ نیلا آسمان اس کے طواف میں سرگرم ہو جاتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When a free man falls down in prostration before God, the blue sky revolves round him ecstatically;
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="71">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ما غلامان از جلالش بیخبر
از جمال لازوالش بیخبر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ہم غلام ایسے آزاد مرد کے جلال اور لازوال جمال سے نا آشنا ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        We slaves are unaware of his might and of his beauty and grace.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="73">
      <Text Language="Original">
        از غلامی لذت ایمان مجو
گرچہ باشد حافظ قرآن، مجو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ایسے غلام میں خواہ وہ حافظ ‍ قرآن ہو، ایمان کی لذّت تلاش نہ کر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Do not seek the ecstasy of faith in a slave, even if he be a hafiz of the Qur’an.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="75">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مومن است و پیشۂ او آزری است
دین و عرفانش سراپا کافری است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        غلام اگرچہ ایمان کا دعویدار ہے مگر اس کا پیشہ بت گری ہے، اس کا دین بھی کافری ہے اور عرفان بھی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He is a Muslim but behaves like an Azar, his religion and gnosis are all kufr (unbelief).
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="77">
      <Text Language="Original">
        در بدن داری اگر سوز حیات
ہست معراج مسلمان در صلوت
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اگر تو اپنے اندر سوز حیات رکھتا ہے تو تو محسوس کرے گا کہ نماز میں مسلمان کی معراج ہے ( اسے نماز میں معراج کی سی کیقیت حاصل ہوتی ہے)۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If you have life’s ardour in your body, you will know that the ascension of a Muslim is in his prayer.
(‘Life’s ardour’: It is the same thing which in some places Iqbal calls ‘light of God’ and in other places as ‘light of soul’. All these terms stand for spiritual orientation. Ascension (Mi’raj): It is the direct experience of God which the Prophet had. The verse is a rendering of the famous tradition ‘Prayer (Namaz) is a Muslim’s ascension’.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="79">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ور ندارے خون گرم اندر بدن
سجدۂ تو نیست جز رسم کہن
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        لیکن اگر تو اپنے بدن میں خون گرم نہيں رکھتا تو تیرا سجدہ سواۓ ایک رسم کہن کے اور کچھ نہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If you have no warm blood in your body, your prostration is but conformity to an ancient custom.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="81">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عید آزادان شکوہ ملک و دین
عید محکومان ھجوم مومنین
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        آزادوں کی عید سلطنت و دین کے شکوہ کا اظہار ہے ، جب کہ محکوموں کی عید صرف مومنوں کا ہجوم۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Eid of the free people is the glory of State and religion, the ‘Id of the slaves is but a congregation of Muslims.	
(Translated by Bashir Ahmad Dar)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>