<Poem ID="29" Name="سرود حلال" BookID="03" BookName="ضربِ کلیم" SectionID="04" SectionName="ادبیات فنون لطیفہ">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کھل تو جاتا ہے مغنی کے بم و زیر سے دل 
نہ رہا زندہ و پائندہ تو کیا دل کی کشود!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        بم و زير: اتار چڑھاؤ ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        LAWFUL MUSIC
The bass and treble of minstrel's song much joy to human heart imparts what is the use of pleasure that is e'er on wings and soon departs?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے ابھی سینہ افلاک میں پنہاں وہ نوا 
جس کی گرمی سے پگھل جائے ستاروں کا وجود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        That melodious song is still unborn and is concealed in heaven's breast, whose intense heat may transform the solid stars to liquid form.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جس کی تاثیر سے آدم ہو غم و خوف سے پاک 
اور پیدا ہو ایازی سے مقام محمود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A song that may have such results which set men free from grief and pain; and makes Ayaz break slavish bands and learn like kings to rule and reign.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مہ و انجم کا یہ حیرت کدہ باقی نہ رہے 
تو رہے اور ترا زمزمہ لا موجود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        زمزمہ لا موجود: مراد ہے توحید کا نعرہ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Perplexing maze of moon and stars may flop down, leave their course O God, you shall last and the cry ‘God is Great’, uttered with much force.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جس کو مشروع سمجھتے ہیں فقیہان خودی 
منتظر ہے کسی مطرب کا ابھی تک وہ سرود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مشروع: شریعت کی رو سے جائز۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The song that jurists of the Self deem lawful in their mystic creed has been expecting since a long a bard, who can acquit indeed.
(Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>