<Poem ID="02" Name="گل رنگیں" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="1a" SectionName="حصہ اول">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تو شناسائے خراش عقدئہ مشکل نہیں
اے گل رنگیں ترے پہلو میں شاید دل نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        شناسا: واقف، جاننے والا۔ 
عقدئہ مشکل: وہ گتھی جسے سلجھانا آسان نہ ہو۔ 
گل رنگیں: رنگوں بھرا پھول۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE COLORFUL ROSE
You are not familiar with the hardships of solving enigmas O Beautiful Rose! Perhaps you do not have sublime feelings in your heart.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زیب محفل ہے، شریک شورش محفل نہیں
یہ فراغت بزم ہستی میں مجھے حاصل نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        زیب محفل: محفل کی زینت۔ 
فراغت: فرصت، مہلت۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Though you adorn the assembly yet do not participate in its struggles; in life's assembly I am not endowed with this comfort.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اس چمن میں میں سراپا سوز و ساز آرزو
اور تیری زندگانی بے گداز آرزو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        گداز: نرم، گھولنا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In this garden I am the complete orchestra of Longing and your life is devoid of the warmth of that Longing.
(Longing: Or ardent desire is one of the important planks of `Allamah Iqbal’s philosophy. However, this longing is not for the material things of life or the satisfaction of physical desires, which is found in all living things. What distinguishes Man from other creation and entitles him to the honor of being God’s vicegerent on earth is the ‘longing’ for more elegant goals and more sublime desires than mere indulgence in material pleasures. His longing is a limitless ocean of search for knowing the Truth and the Purpose of the creation of God, knowledge of His Essence, and fixing of high ideals for life, such as struggle in the cause of God.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        توڑ لینا شاخ سے تجھ کو مرا آئیں نہیں
یہ نظر غیر از نگاہ چشم صورت بیں نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        To pluck you from the branch is not my custom; this sight is not different from the sight of the eye which can only see the appearances.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آہ! یہ دست جفاجو اے گل رنگیں نہیں
کس طرح تجھ کو یہ سمجھائوں کہ میں گلچیں نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        گل رنگیں: رنگوں بھرا پھول۔ 
گلچیں: پھول چننے والا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Ah! O colorful rose this hand is not one of a tormentor; how can I explain to you that I am not a flower picker.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کام مجھ کو دیدئہ حکمت کے الجھیڑوں سے کیا
دیدئہ بلبل سے میں کرتا ہوں نظارہ ترا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        دیدئہ حکمت: تدبیر والی آنکھ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I am not concerned with intricacies of the philosophic eye, like a lover I see you through the nightingale's eye.
(Bulbul, or Nightingale: This is a special Persian bird found in gardens and proverbially engaged in melodious music round flowers. It is imagined to be and is described as an ardent lover of flowers in Persian and Urdu literature, especially poetry.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سو زبانوں پر بھی خاموشی تجھے منظور ہے
راز وہ کیا ہے ترے سینے میں جو مستور ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مستور: چھپا ہوا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In spite of innumerable tongues* you have chosen silence. What is the secret which is concealed in your bosom?
* This alludes to the anatomy of the rose flower, whose petals are innumerable, look like tongues and also add to its beauty, which proclaims the artistry of its Creator in spite of the apparent silence of the flower.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میری صورت تو بھی اک برگ ریاض طور ہے
میں چمن سے دور ہوں تو بھی چمن سے دور ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Like me you are also a leaf from the garden of Toor; far from the garden I am, far from the garden you are.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مطمئن ہے تو، پریشاں مثل بو رہتا ہوں میں
زخمی شمشیر ذوق جستجو رہتا ہوں میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        زخمی شمشیر ذوق جستجو: تلاش کے شوق کی تلوار کا زخمی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You are content but scattered like fragrance I am wounded by the sword of love for search I am.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ پریشانی مری سامان جمعیت نہ ہو
یہ جگر سوزی چراغ خانہ حکمت نہ ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        سامان جمعیت: سکون اور تسلی کا سبب۔ 
چراغ خانہ حکمت: عقل و دانش کے گھر کا چراغ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This perturbation of mine a means for fulfillment could be; this torment a source of my intellectual illumination could be.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ناتوانی ہی مری سرمایہ قوت نہ ہو
رشک جام جم مرا آ ینہ حیرت نہ ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جام جم: جمشید بادشاہ کا پیالہ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This very frailty of mine the means of strength could be; this mirror of mine envy of the cup of Jam* could be.
* This is the legendary cup of the Persian emperor Jam in which he could see whatever he wanted to see wherever he wanted to see.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ تلاش متصل شمع جہاں افروز ہے
توسن ادراک انساں کو خرام آموز ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ادراک: عقل۔
توسن: گھوڑا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This constant search is a world-illuminating candle and teaches to the steed of human intellect its gait.
(This last stanza expresses Allamah Iqbal's strong hope that his present condition may be the means of attaining his objective which is described in the stanza.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>