<Poem ID="03" Name="" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3b" SectionName="غزلیات 3">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نالہ ہے بلبل شوریدہ ترا خام ابھی 
اپنے سینے میں اسے اور ذرا تھام ابھی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        بلبل شوريدہ: دیوانی بلبل۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O dejected nightingale your lament is immature still; you should hold it in your breast for a little while still.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پختہ ہوتی ہے اگر مصلحت اندیش ہو عقل 
عشق ہو مصلحت اندیش تو ہے خام ابھی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مصلحت انديش: اچھا برا سوچنے والا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If Intellect is prudent it is considered mature. If Love is prudent it is considered immature still.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بے خطر کود پڑا آتش نمردو میں عشق 
عقل ہے محو تماشائے لب بام ابھی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Love fearlessly jumped into the fire of Namrud; Intellect is absorbed in the spectacle from roof-top still.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عشق فرمودئہ قاصد سے سبک گام عمل
عقل سمجھی ہی نہیں معنی پیغام ابھی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        فرمودئہ قاصد: قاصد کی ہدایت۔ 
سبک گام عمل: تیزی سے عمل۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Love moves fast in action under the messenger’s precept; Intellect has not even understood the Love’s message still.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شیوئہ عشق ہے آزادی و دہر آشوبی 
تو ہے زناری بت خانہء ایام ابھی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        دہر آشوبي: دنیا بھر میں قیامت کا ہنگامہ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The way of Love is freedom and world revolution; you are imprisoned in day and night’s temple still.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عذر پرہیز پہ کہتا ہے بگڑ کر ساقی 
ہے ترے دل میں وہی کاوش انجام ابھی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        On the plea of temperance the cup-bearer says rudely: In your heart is the same anxiety for the end still.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سعی پیہم ہے ترازوئے کم و کیف حیات 
تیری میزاں ہے شمار سحر و شام ابھی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        پيہم: لگا تار کوشش۔ سعي
کم و کيف حيات: زندگی کی مقدار اور کیفیت۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Constant struggle is the measure for life’s Kamm and Kaif; your measure is the counting of days and nights still.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ابر نیساں! یہ تنک بخشی شبنم کب تک 
مرے کہسار کے لالے ہیں تہی جام ابھی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تنک بخشي: کنجوسوں کی طرح بہت تھوڑی چیز دینا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O spring rain! How long this miserliness? The tulips of my hillside are thirsty still.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بادہ گردان عجم وہ، عربی میری شراب 
مرے ساغر سے جھجکتے ہیں مے آشام ابھی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        They are accustomed to Ajam’s wine I have the Arab wine; my cup makes wine-drinkers startled still.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خبر اقبال کی لائی ہے گلستاں سے نسیم 
نو گرفتار پھڑکتا ہے تہ دام ابھی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Zepheyr has brought news about Iqbal from the garden: The newly seized is writhing under the net still.
(Translated by Dr. M.A.K. Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>