<Poem ID="23" Name="مدرسہ" BookID="03" BookName="ضربِ کلیم" SectionID="02" SectionName="تعلیم و تربیت">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عصر حاضر ملک الموت ہے تیرا، جس نے 
قبض کی روح تری دے کے تجھے فکر معاش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE SCHOOL
Tile present age, your constant foe, like Ezrail has snatched your soul you have imbibed much care and grief pursuit of wealth your only goal.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دل لرزتا ہے حریفانہ کشاکش سے ترا 
زندگی موت ہے، کھو دیتی ہے جب ذوق خراش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ذوق خراش: تکلیف برداشت کرنے کی لذت۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When faced by rivals strong and brave: your heart beats fast and shakes with fear: Such life is naught but Death, in fact, when blows of life you can not.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اس جنوں سے تجھے تعلیم نے بیگانہ کیا 
جو یہ کہتا تھا خرد سے کہ بہانے نہ تراش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The knowledge that this age imparts hs made forget you craze and zest, which bade the mind to keep away from pretexts that on truth didn't rest.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فیض فطرت نے تجھے دیدہ شاہیں بخشا 
جس میں رکھ دی ہے غلامی نے نگاہ خفاش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        خفاش: چمگادڑ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        With free hand Nature has bestowed on you the eyes of hawk so keen; but bondage has replaced them with the eyes, of bat, devoid of sheen.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مدرسے نے تری آنکھوں سے چھپایا جن کو 
خلوت کوہ و بیاباں میں وہ اسرار ہیں فاش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The things on which schools throw no light and keep them from your eyes concealed, go to retreats of mount and waste and get them by some Guide revealed.
[Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>