<Poem ID="04" Name="" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="2b" SectionName="غزلیات 2">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چمک تیری عیاں بجلی میں، آتش میں، شرارے میں 
جھلک تیری ہویدا چاند میں،سورج میں، تارے میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Thy splendor is manifest in thunder, in fire, in spark. Thy luster is evident in the moon, in the sun, in the star.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بلندی آسمانوں میں، زمینوں میں تری پستی 
روانی بحر میں، افتادگی تیری کنارے میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Thy elegance exists in skies' heights, and in earths' depths; It is in the ocean's flow, and in falling behind of the shore.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شریعت کیوں گریباں گیر ہو ذوق تکلم کی
چھپا جاتا ہوں اپنے دل کا مطلب استعارے میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Why should Shariah be the accuser of the eloquence' taste? I only conceal the meaning of my heart in metaphors.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جو ہے بیدار انساں میں وہ گہری نیند سوتا ہے 
شجر میں، پھول میں، حیواں میں، پتھر میں، ستارے میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The real life in Man is pervading in everything: It is in tree, in flower, in animal, in stone, in star.
(Real Life: Means the Love of God and the Longing to see and know Him.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مجھے پھونکا ہے سوز قطرہء اشک محبت نے 
غضب کی آگ تھی پانی کے چھوٹے سے شرارے میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The heat of the drop of Love's tear has consumed me: Boundless fire existed in this little drop of water.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہیں جنس ثواب آخرت کی آرزو مجھ کو 
وہ سوداگر ہوں، میں نے نفع دیکھا ہے خسارے میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        There is no longing in me for reward of the Judgment Day; I am the merchant who sees profit in the loss.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سکوں نا آشنا رہنا اسے سامان ہستی ہے 
تڑپ کس دل کی یا رب چھپ کے آ بیٹھی ہے پارے میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Being unaware of tranquillity is existence for it O God! Restlessness of which heart is residing in mercury?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        صدائے لن ترانی سن کے اے اقبال میں چپ ہوں 
تقاضوں کی کہاں طاقت ہے مجھ فرقت کے مارے میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O Iqbal I am silent after hearing the call of ‘Lan Tarani’. Being afflicted with separation I have no strength for importunity.
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>