<Poem ID="08" Name="علم و عشق" BookID="03" BookName="ضربِ کلیم" SectionID="01" SectionName="اسلام اور مسلمان">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        علم نے مجھ سے کہا عشق ہے دیوانہ پن
عشق نے مجھ سے کہا علم ہے تخمین و ظن
بندہ تخمین و ظن! کرم کتابی نہ بن
عشق سراپا حضور، علم سراپا حجاب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تخمین: وہم و گمان۔ 
کرم کتابی: کتابی کیڑا ؛ پڑھاکو۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Knowledge said to me, Love is madness; Love said to me, Knowledge is calculation: O slave of calculation, do not be a bookworm! Love is Presence entire, Knowledge nothing but a Veil.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عشق کی گرمی سے ہے معرکہء کائنات
علم مقام صفات، عشق تماشائے ذات
عشق سکون و ثبات، عشق حیات و ممات
علم ہے پیدا سوال، عشق ہے پنہاں جواب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The universe is moved by the warmth of Love; knowledge deals with the Attributes, Love is a vision of the Essence; Love is peace and permanence, Love is Life and Death: Knowledge is the rising question, Love is the hidden answer.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عشق کے ہیں معجزات سلطنت و فقر و دیں
عشق کے ادنی غلام صاحب تاج و نگیں
عشق مکان و مکیں، عشق زمان و زمیں
عشق سراپا یقیں، اور یقیں فتح باب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        فتح باب: دروازہ کھولنا، مراد ہے کامیابی ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Kingdom, faith and faqr are all miracles of Love; the crowned kings and lords are base slaves of Love; Love is the Space and the Creation, Love is Time and Earth! Love is conviction entire, and conviction is the key!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شرع محبت میں ہے عشرت منزل حرام
شورش طوفاں حلال، لذت ساحل حرام
عشق پہ بجلی حلال، عشق پہ حاصل حرام
علم ہے ابن الکتاب، عشق ہے ام الکتاب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The luxury of destination is forbidden in the religion of Love; fighting the storms is permitted, but the comfort of the shore is forbidden; lightning is permitted to Love, harvest is forbidden. Knowledge is the child of the Book, Love is the mother of the Book.
(Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah/Editors)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>