<Poem ID="19" Name="" BookID="08" BookName="زبورِعجم" SectionID="02" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عرب کہ باز دہد محفل شبانہ کجاست
عجم کہ زندہ کند رود عاشقانہ کجاست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        وہ عرب کہاں ہے جو پھر وہی محفل شبانہ سجائے، کہاں ہے وہ عجم جو دریا عشق (تصوّف ) کو از سر نو زندہ کرے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Where is the Arab, to revive the old night-revelry, and where the Persian, to bring alive the love-lute’s minstrelsy?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بزیر خرقۂ پیران سبوہا چہ خالی است
فغان کہ کس نشناسد می جوانہ کجاست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        صوفیا کے پاس خرقہ تو ہے لیکن ان کی سبو (معرفت) سے خالی ہے۔ فریاد ! کہ کوئی نہیں پہچانتا کہ وہ مئے جواں (عشق الہی) کہاں ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Under the Sufi elder’s gown the flagon is bare and dry: Alas, for none can tell in the town where young red wine’s to buy.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        درین چمنکدہ ہر کس نشیمنی سازد
کسی کہ سازد و وا سوزد آشیانہ کجاست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس باغ جہاں میں ہر کوئی نشیمن بناتا ہے، ایسا شخص کہاں ہے جو آشیانہ بنا کر پھونک دے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Every man in this grassy mead fashions and takes his rest, but where is he, ah, where indeed, who will make, and burn, his nest?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہزار قافلہ بیگانہ وار دید و گذشت
دلے کہ دید بہ انداز محرمانہ کجاست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ہزاروں قافلے بیگانہ وار دیکھتے ہوئے گزر گئے ، ایسا شخص کہاں ہے جو دنیا کو محرمانہ انداز سے دیکھے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A thousand caravan-trains have stared like a stranger, and then passed on, but he that close as a lover dared to gaze – is there anyone?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چو موج خیز و بہ یم جاودانہ می آویز
کرانہ می طلبی ؟ بی خبر کرانہ کجاست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        موج کی طرح اٹھ اور سمندر سے مسلسل کشمکش جاری رکھ۔ تو ساحل کی تلاش میں ہے؟ بے خبر! ساحل کہاں ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Rise like a wave, and surging flow in the ocean eternally? Thou seek’st the shore, and dost not know where ever the shore may be.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بیا کہ در رگ تاک تو خون تازہ دوید
دگر مگوی کہ آن بادۂ مغانہ کجاست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        دیکھ کہ تیری رگوں میں خون تازہ دوڑ رہا ہے، اب نہ کہہ کہ وہ بادہ ء مغانہ کہاں ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Hither (for in thy tendril’s vein the fresh young blood doth bound) hither hasten, nor ask again where the Magian wine is found.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بیک نورد فرو پیچ روزگاران را
ز دیر و زود گذشتی دگر زمانہ کجاست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ایک ہی جھپٹ میں زمانے کو دبوچ لے، اگر تو دیر و زود سے نکل جائے تو پھر زمانہ کہاں؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Twist into one vast war-array all ages that ever were; later and sooner are passed away; where now is Time, ah, where?
[Translated by Arthur J Arberry]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>