<Poem ID="12" Name="نگاہ شوق" BookID="03" BookName="ضربِ کلیم" SectionID="04" SectionName="ادبیات فنون لطیفہ">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ کائنات چھپاتی نہیں ضمیر اپنا 
کہ ذرے ذرے میں ہے ذوق آشکارائی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        آشکارائي: ظاہر ہونا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        EAGER GLANCE
Contents of soul this world can not conceal, for every mote has longing to reveal.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کچھ اور ہی نظر آتا ہے کاروبار جہاں 
نگاہ شوق اگر ہو شریک بینائی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The course of life some what distinct appears, if eager looks and sight become corn peers.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اسی نگاہ سے محکوم قوم کے فرزند 
ہوئے جہاں میں سزاوار کار فرمائی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کار فرمائي: حکومت۔
سزاوار: حقدار۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The members of a subject race by dint of glance, its gloss and grace, have acquired the right and claim to rule and get renown and fame.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اسی نگاہ میں ہے قاہری و جباری 
اسی نگاہ میں ہے دلبری و رعنائی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The glance has might to cause defeat, it has the strength, its foes to beat; we see through glance great charm and grace; it brings the lovers face to face.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اسی نگاہ سے ہر ذرے کو، جنوں میرا 
سکھا رہا ہے رہ و رسم دشت پیمائی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        دشت پيمائي: بیابان میں پھرنا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Through self-same glance my craze imparts to motes and their most inner parts, the wont and mode of wandering tramps, who pay no heed to need of camps.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نگاہ شوق میسر نہیں اگر تجھ کو 
ترا وجود ہے قلب و نظر کی رسوائی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If fervent glance and vision keen you have not met or ever seen; your being is a source of shame on heart and sight can bring a blame.
(Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>