<Poem ID="13" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="02" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ حوریان فرنگی، دل و نظر کا حجاب 
بہشت مغربیاں، جلوہ ہائے پا بہ رکاب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        These Western nymphs, a challenge to the eye and the heart; are bold of glance in a paradise of instant bliss.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دل و نظر کا سفینہ سنبھال کر لے جا 
مہ و ستارہ ہیں بحر وجود میں گرداب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Thy heart is a wavering ship tossed by beauty’s assault; these moons and stars that glisten, are whirlpools in thy sea.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جہان صوت و صدا میں سما نہیں سکتی 
لطیفہ ازلی ہے فغان چنگ و رباب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The warblings of the harp and lyre have wondrous powers; powers that cannot be captured in the world of sound.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سکھا دیے ہیں اسے شیوہ ہائے خانقہی 
فقیہ شہر کو صوفی نے کر دیا ہے خراب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        By teaching him the monastic wont and way; the Sufi has led astray the jurist of the town.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وہ سجدہ، روح زمیں جس سے کانپ جاتی تھی 
اسی کو آج ترستے ہیں منبر و محراب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The prostration that once shook the earth’s soul; now leaves not a trace on the mosque’s decadent walls.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سنی نہ مصر و فلسطیں میں وہ اذاں میں نے 
دیا تھا جس نے پہاڑوں کو رعشہ سیماب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        رعشہ سيماب: پارے کی طرح لرزنا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I have not heard in the Arab world the thunderous call; the call to prayer that pierced the hearts of hills in the past.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہوائے قرطبہ! شاید یہ ہے اثر تیرا 
مری نوا میں ہے سوز و سرور عہد شباب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O Qartaba! Perhaps, some magic in thy air has breathed into my song the buoyancy of youth.
(Translated by Naeem Siddiqui)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>