<Poem ID="32" Name="شاعر" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جوئے سرود آفریں آتی ہے کوہسار سے 
پی کے شراب لالہ گوں مے کدئہ بہار سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE POET
The melodious brook is coming down from the mountain after drinking red wine from the tavern’s spring.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مست مے خرام کا سن تو ذرا پیام تو 
زندہ وہی ہے کام کچھ جس کو نہیں قرار سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Just listen to the message of the ecstatic stroller; only he is living who unconcerned with resting is.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پھرتی ہے وادیوں میں کیا دخترخوش خرام ابر 
کرتی ہے عشق بازیاں سبزئہ مرغزار سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In the valleys the cloud’s elegant daughter is roaming; exhibiting her love for the greenery of the meadow is.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جام شراب کوہ کے خم کدے سے اڑاتی ہے 
پست و بلند کرکے طے کھیتوں کو جا پلاتی ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Stealing away the cup of wine from mountain’s tavern; passing throughout ups and downs suckling the fields is.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شاعر دل نواز بھی بات اگر کہے کھری 
ہوتی ہے اس کے فیض سے مزرع زندگی ہری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If the affectionate poet also exhibits the truth; life’s cultivation greens up from his bountiful ways.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شان خلیل ہوتی ہے اس کے کلام سے عیاں 
کرتی ہے اس کی قوم جب اپنا شعار آزری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Khalil’s* glory is evident from his verse; when his nation exhibits the Azar’s ways. 
(Khalil: This is abbreviation of Khalil Allah which is a title of Ibrahim A.S.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اہل زمیں کو نسخہء زندگی دوام ہے 
خون جگر سے تربیت پاتی ہے جو سخنوری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        For earth’s inhabitants is the recipe of eternal life; the literature which is nurtured in sincere ways.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گلشن دہر میں اگر جوئے مے سخن نہ ہو
پھول نہ ہو، کلی نہ ہو، سبزہ نہ ہو، چمن نہ ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If the book of literature’s wine in the world’s garden does not exist; the flower, the bud, the verdure, even the garden will not exist.
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>