<Poem ID="18" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="02" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ دیر کہن کیا ہے، انبار خس و خاشاک 
مشکل ہے گزر اس میں بے نالہ آتش ناک
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The ancient fane in which we live has heaps of thorns at every turn; too hard to cross it safe and sound without the aid of sighs that burn.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نخچیر محبت کا قصہ نہیں طولانی 
لطف خلش پیکاں، آسودگی فتراک
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        نخچير: شکار کیا ہوا پرندہ یا جانور۔ 
لطف خلش پيکاں: تیر لگنے کے درد کا مزا۔
آسودگي فتراک: شکار بند میں لٹک جانے کا سکون۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The tale of quarry shot by Love is simple, brief and not too long: The victim feels the joy of prick and then the rest of saddle thong.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کھویا گیا جو مطلب ہفتاد و دو ملت میں 
سمجھے گا نہ تو جب تک بے رنگ نہ ہو ادراک
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ہفتاد و دو: بہتّر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The sterling truth to Muslim taught, in feuds of different sects is lost; how can you catch this truth again, with bias if your mind be fraught?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اک شرع مسلمانی، اک جذب مسلمانی 
ہے جذب مسلمانی سر فلک الافلاک
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        فلک الافلاک:آسمانوں کا آسمان، یعنی عرش۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        One is the outward form of faith, the other its spirit deep and true: He, who quaffs its spirits deep, brings secrets hidden to his view.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے رہرو فرزانہ، بے جذب مسلمانی 
نے راہ عمل پیدا نے شاخ یقیں نم ناک
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O pilgrim wise, who tread the path, if passion strong for faith you lack, the bough of faith shall whither fast, obscure and dim become the path.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رمزیں ہیں محبت کی گستاخی و بے باکی 
ہر شوق نہیں گستاخ، ہر جذب نہیں بے باک
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Courage and valour are the signs by which the state of Love is known: Not every zeal is pert and rude, nor daring by ev’ry person shown.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فارغ تو نہ بیٹھے گا محشر میں جنوں میرا 
یا اپنا گریباں چاک یا دامن یزداں چاک
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        On the Day of Judgment too my frenzy will not let me rest: With Mighty God I shall contend or rend to fragments my own vest.
(Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>