<Poem ID="17" Name="" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="04" SectionName="ظریفانہ">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فرما رہے تھے شیخ طریق عمل پہ وعظ 
کفار ہند کے ہیں تجارت میں سخت کوش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Shaikh was giving a sermon on the mode of operation: ‘The infidels of India are very hard working in business.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مشرک ہیں وہ جو رکھتے ہیں مشرک سے لین دین 
لیکن ہماری قوم ہے محروم عقل و ہوش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Polytheists are those having trade relations with polytheists; but our nation’s people are lacking in intelligence and sense.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ناپاک چیز ہوتی ہے کافر کے ہاتھ کی 
سن لے، اگر ہے گوش مسلماں کا حق نیوش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        حق نيوش: سننے کا حق۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Unclean is the article touched by the infidel; should listen if Muslim’s ears are amenable to truth!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اک بادہ کش بھی وعظ کی محفل میں تھا شریک 
جس کے لیے نصیحت واعظ تھی بار گوش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A drunkard was also present in the sermon’s assembly; to whom such talks as those of the preacher were irksome.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کہنے لگا ستم ہے کہ ایسے قیود کی 
پابند ہو تجارت سامان خورد و نوش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He said, ‘It is atrocious that in such restrictions are imprisoned the dealings in articles of eating and drink’.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میں نے کہا کہ آپ کو مشکل نہیں کوئی 
ہندوستاں میں ہیں کلمہ گو بھی مے فروش
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I said, ‘There is no difficulty for you as in India Muslims also are liquor sellers!’ (This is a sarcasm on the fact that a fairly large number of the Muslims in India were dealing in wine and other intoxicants.)
[Translated by Dr M A K Khalil]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>