<Poem ID="12" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="01" SectionName="حصہ اول">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ضمیر لالہ مے لعل سے ہوا لبریز 
اشارہ پاتے ہی صوفی نے توڑ دی پرہیز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        By dint of spring the poppy-cup, with vintage red is over-flown: With her advent the hermit too temperance to the wind hath thrown.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بچھائی ہے جو کہیں عشق نے بساط اپنی 
کیا ہے اس نے فقیروں کو وارث پرویز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When great and mighty force of Love at some place its flag doth raise, beggars dressed in rags and sack become heirs true to King Parvez.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پرانے ہیں یہ ستارے، فلک بھی فرسودہ 
جہاں وہ چاہیے مجھ کو کہ ہو ابھی نوخیز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Antique the stars and old the dome in which they roam about and move: I long for new and virgin soil where my mettle I may prove.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کسے خبر ہے کہ ہنگامہ نشور ہے کیا 
تری نگاہ کی گردش ہے میری رستاخیز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ہنگامہ نشور: قیامت کا شور۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The stir and roar of Judgement Day hath no dread for me at all: Thine roving glance doth work on me like the Last Day’s Trumpet Call.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نہ چھین لذت آہ سحر گہی مجھ سے 
نہ کر نگہ سے تغافل کو التفات آمیز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Snatch not from me the blessing great of sighs heaved at early morn: With a casual loving look weaken not thine fierce scorn.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دل غمیں کے موافق نہیں ہے موسم گل 
صدائے مرغ چمن ہے بہت نشاط انگیز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        نشاط انگیز: خوشی سے لبریز۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My sad and broken heart disdains the spring and dower that she brings: Too joyous the song of nightingale! I feel more gloomy when it sings.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حدیث بے خبراں ہے، تو با زمانہ بساز 
زمانہ با تو نسازد، تو با زمانہ ستیز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Unwise are those who tell and preach accord with times and the age. If the world befits you not, a war against it you must wage.
(Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>