<Poem ID="01" Name="" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3b" SectionName="غزلیات 3">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے باد صبا! کملی والے سے جا کہیو پیغام مرا 
قبضے سے امت بیچاری کے دیں بھی گیا، دنیا بھی گئی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O zephyr! Convey my message to the one wrapped in blanket: The poor Ummah has lost both din and material resources.
(The one wrapped in blanket: The word in the original is ‘One wrapped in a small blanket’. This is the title of the Holy Prophet (S.A.W.) as a mark of affection and is based on such affection shown by no less an entity than God in the opening verses of the Holy Qur’an, Surahs 73 and 74.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ موج پریشاں خاطر کو پیغام لب ساحل نے دیا 
ہے دور وصال بحر بھی، تو دریا میں گھبرا بھی گئی!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The river bank gave this message to the restless wave: ‘Union with ocean is still far and you have already lost patience in the river’.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عزت ہے محبت کی قائم اے قیس! حجاب محمل سے 
محمل جو گیا عزت بھی گئی، غیرت بھی گئی لیلا بھی گئی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O Qais! Love’s honour is made durable with litter’s curtain; if litter is lost, glory, honor as well as Lailah is lost!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کی ترک تگ و دو قطرے نے تو آبروئے گوہر بھی ملی 
آوارگی فطرت بھی گئی اور کشمکش دریا بھی گئی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Though the drop got pearl’s dignity by abandoning struggle; it lost taste for wandering and struggle in the river.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نکلی تو لب اقبال سے ہے، کیا جانیے کس کی ہے یہ صدا 
پیغام سکوں پہنچا بھی گئی، دل محفل کا تڑپا بھی گئی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Though this voice has emerged from Iqbal’s lips its source is unknown; the assembly got hope’s message as well as became restless for activism.
[Translated by Dr M A K Khalil]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>