<Poem ID="11" Name="امید" BookID="03" BookName="ضربِ کلیم" SectionID="04" SectionName="ادبیات فنون لطیفہ">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مقابلہ تو زمانے کا خوب کرتا ہوں 
اگرچہ میں نہ سپاہی ہوں نے امیر جنود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جنود: فوج کی جمع۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        HOPE
With courage great a war I wage 'gainst evils of the present age I do not bear a fighter's name, to chieftainship I lay no claim.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مجھے خبر نہیں یہ شاعری ہے یا کچھ اور 
عطا ہوا ہے مجھے ذکر و فکر و جذب و سرود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I am not conscious 'bout this fact if it is Verse or other tact; God has bestowed on me since long His praise, reflection, charm and song.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جبین بندہ حق میں نمود ہے جس کی 
اسی جلال سے لبریز ہے ضمیر وجود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The flood of light that makes its show on true and faithful Muslim's brow with grandeur same is quite replete that fills being's soul and makes complete.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ کافری تو نہیں، کافری سے کم بھی نہیں 
کہ مرد حق ہو گرفتار حاضر و موجود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        You do not call it unbelief, no less it is than disbelief' that truthful man may get content I with today, for change show no intent.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        غمیں نہ ہو کہ بہت دور ہیں ابھی باقی 
نئے ستاروں سے خالی نہیں سپہر کبود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        سپہر کبود: نیلا آسمان۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Don't grieve, for millenniums and aeons more still lie ahead for man in store the ever spinning heaven blue is not devoid of planets new.
(Written in Riaz Manzil, Bhopal residence of Sir Rass Masood.)
(Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>