<Poem ID="37" Name="بلال" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="1a" SectionName="حصہ اول">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چمک اٹھا جو ستارہ ترے مقدر کا
حبش سے تجھ کو اٹھا کر حجاز میں لایا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        As the star of your destiny ascended to shine; it lifted and brought you from Abyssinia to Hijaz.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہوئی اسی سے ترے غم کدے کی آبادی
تری غلامی کے صدقے ہزار آزادی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This alone made inhabited your desolate house better than a thousand freedoms is your slavery.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وہ آستاں نہ چھٹا تجھ سے ایک دم کے لیے
کسی کے شوق میں تو نے مزے ستم کے لیے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        That threshold not even for a moment you could leave; in some one's Love all torments you bore cheerfully.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جفا جو عشق میں ہوتی ہے وہ جفا ہی نہیں
ستم نہ ہو تو محبت میں کچھ مزا ہی نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The oppression befalling in Love is not oppression; if there is no torment, there is no pleasure in Love.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نظر تھی صورت سلماں ادا شناس تری
شراب دید سے بڑھتی تھی اور پیاس تری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Full of Intellection like Salman was your insight; the wine of sight used to increase your thirst. 
(Salman Abu Abd Allah Farisi (R.A.) The famous Companion of the Holy Prophet S.A.W. He was of Persian origin. Early in his life he left his home in search of the Truth. First he accepted Christianity, studied its literature deeply and persevered through all the hardships he had to encounter. He was caught by an Arab tribe and sold to a Jew. Later, the Holy Prophet S.A.W. purchased him and set him free. Salman accepted Islam after the emigration of the Holy Prophet S.A.W. to Madinah Munawwarah…)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تجھے نظارے کا مثل کلیم سودا تھا
اویس طاقت دیدار کو ترستا تھا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Like Kalim you were in search of the Sight. Uwais was tantalized for the power of Sight.
(Uwais Qarani (R.A.) was a contemporary of the Holy Prophet (S.A.W.) and had accepted Islam. He could not achieve his life-long ambition and longing of being a Companion of him. This was so because he could not leave his home town of Qaran in Najd due to the blindness of his old mother. The Holy Prophet (S.A.W.) had knowledge of him and used to say that he felt breeze of God's Beneficence from Yemen. The Holy Prophet's (S.A.W.) love for Uwais is shown by the fact that he made him the inheritor of his shirt. Umar (R.A.) and Ali (R.A.) went to meet him in Qaran after the death of the Holy Prophet (S.A.W.). Later Uwais moved to Kufah and attained martyrdom in the battle of Siffin where he was in the camp of Ali (R.A.) He is one of the most eminent sufis, often placed second to Ali (R.A.) He was fully absorbed in the Love of God and the Holy Prophet (S.A.W.), but his longing to see the Holy Prophet (S.A.W.)…Allamah Iqbal has referred to him in many places in his works.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مدینہ تیری نگاہوں کا نور تھا گویا
ترے لیے تو یہ صحرا ہی طور تھا گویا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Madinah was the light for your eyes so to say; for you this wilderness was the ñër so to say.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تری نظر کو رہی دید میں بھی حسرت دید
خنک دلے کہ تپید و دمے نیا سائید
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your longing for Sight continued even after witnessing the Sight. The cold heart warmed up but its breath did not rest even for a moment.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گری وہ برق تری جان ناشکیبا پر
کہ خندہ زن تری ظلمت تھی دست موسی پر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Such a lightning struck your impatient soul that your darkness was scoffing at the Musa's palm.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تپش ز شعلہ گر فتند و بر دل تو زدند
چہ برق جلوہ بخاشاک حاصل تو زدند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ‘They captured warmth from the flame and struck it on your heart. What a lightning of Effulgence they struck on motes of your efforts!’
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ادائے دید سراپا نیاز تھی تیری
کسی کو دیکھتے رہنا نماز تھی تیری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The charm of your longing for the Sight was the embodiment of supplication. The continuous sighting of someone was your prayer.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اذاں ازل سے ترے عشق کا ترانہ بنی
نماز اس کے نظارے کا اک بہانہ بنی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Since eternity the Adhan was the anthem of your Love. Prayer was the subtle pretext for the Sight.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خوشا وہ وقت کہ یثرب مقام تھا اس کا
خوشا وہ دور کہ دیدار عام تھا اس کا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Happy was the age when Yathrib was his abode! How happy was the time when common was his Sight!
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>