<Poem ID="19" Name="" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="04" SectionName="ظریفانہ">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گائے اک روز ہوئی اونٹ سے یوں گرم سخن 
نہیں اک حال پہ دنیا میں کسی شے کو قرار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The cow one day started saying to the camel: Nothing in the world rests in one condition.
(One angle to look at these verses is that camel and cow represent Muslims and Hindus inhabiting the Indian Subcontinent)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میں تو بد نام ہوئی توڑ کے رسی اپنی 
سنتی ہوں آپ نے بھی توڑکے رکھ دی ہے مہار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I am ignominious by breaking my rope; I hear you have also broken your nose string.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہند میں آپ تو از روئے سیاست ہیں اہم 
ریل چلنے سے مگر دشت عرب میں بیکار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Though you are important in India for political reasons; but due to railway the Arabian desert finds no use for you.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کل تلک آپ کو تھا گائے کی محفل سے حذر 
تھی لٹکتے ہوئے ہونٹوں پہ صدائے زنہار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        صدائے زنہار: نہ کی تکرار۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Till yesterday you were avoiding the cow’s companionship; the voice of ‘never’ on your hanging lips was persistent.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آج یہ کیا ہے کہ ہم پر ہے عنایت اتنی 
نہ رہا آئنہء دل میں وہ دیرینہ غبار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What is the matter that you are so favourable to me today that old displeasure does not exist in your heart today.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جب یہ تقریر سنی اونٹ نے، شرما کے کہا 
ہے ترے چاہنے والوں میں ہمارا بھی شمار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Hearing this speech the camel bashfully said: I am also to be counted among your lovers.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رشک صد غمزئہ اشتر ہے تری ایک کلیل 
ہم تو ہیں ایسی کلیلوں کے پرانے بیمار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کليل: چھلانگ۔
غمزئہ اشتر: اونٹ کا کودنا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The envy of hundreds of camel’s ogle is your one frisk; since long I am the lover of such a frisk.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ترے ہنگاموں کی تاثیر یہ پھیلی بن میں 
بے زبانوں میں بھی پیدا ہے مذاق گفتار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The effects of your tumults have spread in the forest such that speech has produced its taste even among the speechless.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ایک ہی بن میں ہے مدت سے بسیرا اپنا 
گرچہ کچھ پاس نہیں، چارا بھی کھاتے ہیں ادھار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I am living only in one desert since a long time; as I have nothing I am fed on borrowed money.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گوسفند و شتر و گاو و پلنگ و خر لنگ 
ایک ہی رنگ میں رنگیں ہوں تو ہے اپنا وقار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        و شتر و گاو و پلنگ و خر لنگ : بکری، اونٹ، گائے، شیر ، لنگڑا گدھا۔ گوسفند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If goat, camel, cow, leopard and the lame donkey; all exist in the same condition we shall have prestige.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        باغباں ہو سبق آموز جو یکرنگی کا 
ہمزباں ہو کے رہیں کیوں نہ طیور گلزار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If the gardener learns the lesson of uniformity; why should not the gardens’ birds live in harmony?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دے وہی جام ہمیں بھی کہ مناسب ہے یہی 
تو بھی سرشار ہو، تیرے رفقا بھی سرشار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Give me also the same cup as only this appears proper; you should be intoxicated, your companions should also be intoxicated.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دلق حافظ بچہ ارزد بہ میش رنگیں کن 
وانگہش مست و خراب از رہ بازار بیار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        حافظ کی گدڑی کو جس قیمت پر بھی ہو رنگین کرو اور اس انداز میں اسے بدمست کر کے بازار جاتے ہوئے پکڑ لاؤ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ‘The patched garment of Hafiz is worthless, colour him with wine, then bring him to the market, lost and intoxicated’.
[Translated by Dr M A K Khalil]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>