<Poem ID="16" Name="بزم انجم" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سورج نے جاتے جاتے شام سیہ قبا کو 
طشت افق سے لے کر لالے کے پھول مارے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE ASSEMBLY OF STARS
While setting, the sun threw at the dark-clothed evening tulip flowers which it had collected from horizon’s basin:
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پہنا دیا شفق نے سونے کا سارا زیور 
قدرت نے اپنے گہنے چاندی کے سب اتارے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The twilight of evening put all ornaments of gold on it, Nature put off its entire set of silver ornaments.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        محمل میں خامشی کے لیلائے ظلمت آئی 
چمکے عروس شب کے موتی وہ پیارے پیارے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Lailah of the night in the litter of silence arrived; started shining the beautiful pearls of the evening’s bride.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وہ دور رہنے والے ہنگامہء جہاں سے 
کہتا ہے جن کو انساں اپنی زباں میں 'تارے'
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Those living far from the commotion of the world which Man calls ‘stars’ in his own language.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        محو فلک فروزی تھی انجمن فلک کی 
عرش بریں سے آئی آواز اک ملک کی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        فلک فروزي: آسمان کو روشن کرنا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The sky’s assembly was busy lighting up the sky from the`Arsh-i-Barin the call of an angel came:
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے شب کے پاسانو، اے آسماں کے تارو! 
تابندہ قوم ساری گردوں نشیں تمھاری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ‘O sentinels of the night! O stars of the sky! The whole shining nation of yours inhabits the sky.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چھیڑو سرود ایسا، جاگ اٹھیں سونے والے 
رہبر ہے قافلوں کی تاب جبیں تمھاری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Start such music as may awaken all those sleeping; the brightness of your forehead is guide for caravans.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آئینے قسمتوں کے تم کو یہ جانتے ہیں 
شاید سنیں صدائیں اہل زمیں تمھاری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The earth’s denizens consider you the destiny’s mirrors; perhaps they will listen to your call.’
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رخصت ہوئی خموشی تاروں بھری فضا سے 
وسعت تھی آسماں کی معمور اس نوا سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Silence departed from this star-spangled expanse, the sky’s expanse was filled with this music.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حسن ازل ہے پیدا تاروں کی دلبری میں 
جس طرح عکس گل ہو شبنم کے آرسی میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Eternal Beauty is produced in the stars’ loveliness as the image of rose is in the looking glass of the dew.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آئین نو سے ڈرنا، طرز کہن پہ اڑنا 
منزل یہی کھٹن ہے قوموں کی زندگی میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        To be afraid of the new ways, to insist on the old ones; this is the only difficult stage in the life of nations.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ کاروان ہستی ہے تیز گام ایسا 
قومیں کچل گئی ہیں جس کی رواروی میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This caravan of life is so fast moving; many a nation is trampled in whose race.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آنکھوں سے ہیں ہماری غائب ہزاروں انجم 
داخل ہیں وہ بھی لیکن اپنی برادری میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Thousands of stars are hidden from our eyes, but their existence is also included in our group.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اک عمر میں نہ سمجھے اس کو زمین والے 
جو بات پا گئے ہم تھوڑی سی زندگی میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The earth’s denizens did not understand in a whole life: What has come in our comprehension in a short span of life.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہیں جذب باہمی سے قائم نظام سارے 
پوشیدہ ہے یہ نکتہ تاروں کی زندگی میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جذب باہمي: ایک دوسرے کو کھینچنے والے؛ آپس کی محبت اور لگاؤ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        All systems are established on mutual attraction; this secret is concealed in the life of the stars.’ 
(Translated by Dr. M.A.K. Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>