<Poem ID="47" Name="والدہ مرحومہ کی یاد میں" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ذرہ ذرہ دہر کا زندانی تقدیر ہے 
پردئہ مجبوری و بے چارگی تدبیر ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        IN MEMORY OF LATE MOTHER
Every particle of the universe is a prisoner of destiny; prudence is a cover for helplessness and compulsion.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آسماں مجبور ہے، شمس و قمر مجبور ہیں 
انجم سیماب پا رفتار پر مجبور ہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The sky, the sun and the moon all are helpless; the fast moving stars are compelled to moving.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے شکت انجام غنچے کا سبو گلزار میں 
سبزہ و گل بھی ہیں مجبور نمو گلزار میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Breaking is the end of flower bud’s pitcher in the garden; the garden’s verdure and flowers are also compelled to grow.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نغمہ بلبل ہو یا آواز خاموش ضمیر 
ہے اسی زنجیر عالم گیر میں ہر شے اسیر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It may be nightingale’s song or conscience’ silent call; everything is chained in the same universal chain!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آنکھ پر ہوتا ہے جب یہ سر مجبوری عیاں 
خشک ہو جاتا ہے دل میں اشک کا سیل رواں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When this secret of helplessness becomes evident to the eye; the turbulent flood of tears in the heart dries up.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        قلب انسانی میں رقص عیش و غم رہتا نہیں 
نغمہ رہ جاتا ہے، لطف زیروبم رہتا نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The dance of pleasure and grief does not remain in the human heart; the song remains but the pleasure of treble and bass does not remain.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        علم و حکمت رہزن سامان اشک و آہ ہے 
یعنی اک الماس کا ٹکڑا دل آگاہ ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Knowledge and wisdom are robbers of tears and sighs’ wealth that is the intelligent heart is a piece of diamond!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گرچہ میرے باغ میں شبنم کی شادابی نہیں 
آنکھ میری مایہ دار اشک عنابی نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Though the dew’s freshness does not exist in my garden; my eye is not enriched with the red tears.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جانتا ہوں آہ، میں آلام انسانی کا راز 
ہے نوائے شکوہ سے خالی مری فطرت کا ساز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Ah! I am aware of the secret of human afflictions, but my nature’s orchestra is unaware of complaint’s song.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        میرے لب پر قصہ نیرنگی دوراں نہیں 
دل مرا حیراں نہیں، خنداں نہیں، گریاں نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The story of vicissitudes of time does not come on my lips; my heart is not astonished, not laughing, not crying.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پر تری تصویر قاصد گریہء پیہم کی ہے 
آہ! یہ تردید میری حکمت محکم کی ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        But, O messenger, your picture is one of constant wailing. Ah! This is the contradiction of my firm wisdom!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گریہ سرشار سے بنیاد جاں پائندہ ہے 
درد کے عرفاں سے عقل سنگدل شرمندہ ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Life’s foundation becomes lasting with overflowing wailing; the hard hearted Intellect is embarrassed with the knowledge of pathos.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        موج دود آہ سے آئینہ ہے روشن مرا 
گنج آب آورد سے معمور ہے دامن مرا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My mirror is bright with the wave of sighs’ smoke; my skirt is full with the treasure of tears.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حیرتی ہوں میں تری تصویر کے اعجاز کا 
رخ بدل ڈالا ہے جس نے وقت کی پرواز کا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The miracle of your picture has surprised me, which has completely changed the flight of time.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رفتہ و حاضر کو گویا پا بپا اس نے کیا 
عہد طفلی سے مجھے پھر آشنا اس نے کیا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        As if it brought the past and present together; it acquainted me again with the age of infancy.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="31">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جب ترے دامن میں پلتی تھی وہ جان ناتواں 
بات سے اچھی طرح محرم نہ تھی جس کی زباں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When that feeble soul was being nurtured by your side, whose tongue was not adequately familiar with talking.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اور اب چرچے ہیں جس کی شوخی گفتار کے 
بے بہا موتی ہیں جس کی چشم گوہربار کے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        And whose linguistic spice is now the subject of conversation; the pearls of whose jewel-shedding eyes are priceless.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="35">
      <Text Language="Original">
        علم کی سنجیدہ گفتاری، بڑھاپے کا شعور 
دنیوی اعزاز کی شوکت، جوانی کا غرور
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The learning’s serious discourses, the shrewdness of old age; the dignity of worldly honours, the pride of young age:
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="37">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زندگی کی اوج گاہوں سے اتر آتے ہیں ہم
صحبت مادر میں طفل سادہ رہ جاتے ہیں ہم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        We descend from the positions of dignity in life; we descend as a simple child in the lap of the mother.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="39">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بے تکلف خندہ زن ہیں، فکر سے آزاد ہیں 
پھر اسی کھوئے ہوئے فردوس میں آباد ہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        We are laughing informally, we are free from care; we are once more living in the same lost paradise.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="41">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کس کو اب ہوگا وطن میں آہ! میرا انتظار 
کون میرا خط نہ آنے سے رہے گا بے قرار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Ah! Who will now be waiting for me in the homeland? Who will become restless by not getting my letter?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="43">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خاک مرقد پر تری لے کر یہ فریاد آئوں گا 
اب دعائے نیم شب میں کس کو یاد میں آئوں گا!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I will come to your grave carrying this lament! To whose thoughts will I come in the midnight prayers?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="45">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تربیت سے تیری میں انجم کا ہم قسمت ہوا 
گھر مرے اجداد کا سرمایہ عزت ہوا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        With your up-bringing I became fortunate like stars; the house of my ancestors became a source of pride.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="47">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دفتر ہستی میں تھی زریں ورق تیری حیات 
تھی سراپا دیں و دنیا کا سبق تیری حیات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your life was written in gold letters in the existence’ book; your life was a full lesson of secular and religious education.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="49">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عمر بھر تیری محبت میری خدمت گر رہی
میں تری خدمت کے قابل جب ہوا تو چل بسی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your love remained in my service for your whole life; when I was able to serve you, you did not survive.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="51">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وہ جواں، قامت میں ہے جو صورت سرو بلند 
تیری خدمت سے ہوا جو مجھ سے بڑھ کر بہرہ مند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        That youth who equals the slender cypress in stature, * who became more fortunate in serving you than me.
* Allusion to his brother, which extends up to the end of this stanza.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="53">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کاروبار زندگانی میں وہ ہم پہلو مرا 
وہ محبت میں تری تصویر، وہ بازو مرا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        That constant companion of mine in the business of life; that picture of yours in love that source of my strength.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="55">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تجھ کو مثل طفلک بے دست و پا روتا ہے وہ 
صبر سے ناآشنا صبح و مسا روتا ہے وہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He is crying like a helpless infant for you; he is crying with impatience from morning till evening.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="57">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تخم جس کا تو ہماری کشت جاں میں بو گئی 
شرکت غم سے وہ الفت اور محکم ہوگئی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The love whose seed you planted in our life’s field; by the grief of separation that love became more firm.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="59">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آہ! یہ دنیا، یہ ماتم خانہ برنا و پیر 
آدمی ہے کس طلسم دوش و فردا میں اسیر!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Ah! This world, this mourning place for the young and old! In what a strange ever-changing prison man is imprisoned!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="61">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کتنی مشکل زندگی ہے، کس قدر آساں ہے موت 
گلشن ہستی میں مانند نسیم ارزاں ہے موت
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        How difficult it is to live! How easy it is to die! In the existence’ garden death is cheap as breeze!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="63">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زلزلے ہیں، بجلیاں ہیں، قحط ہیں، آلام ہیں
کیسی کیسی دختران مادر ایام ہیں!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        There are earthquakes, thunderbolts, famines, afflictions: How diverse the daughters of the mother of time are!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="65">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کلبہ افلاس میں، دولت کے کاشانے میں موت 
دشت و در میں، شہر میں، گلشن میں، ویرانے میں موت
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In poor man’s hovel, in rich man’s mansion is death. In forest, house, city, garden, wilderness is death.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="67">
      <Text Language="Original">
        موت ہے ہنگامہ آرا قلزم خاموش میں 
ڈوب جاتے ہیں سفینے موج کی آغوش میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Death is tumultuous in the silent ocean; boats are drowned in the lap of death.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="69">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نے مجال شکوہ ہے، نے طاقت گفتار ہے 
زندگانی کیا ہے، اک طوق گلو افشار ہے!
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Neither there is ability to complain, nor power of speech; life is nothing but a yoke choking the throat.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="71">
      <Text Language="Original">
        قافلے میں غیر فریاد درا کچھ بھی نہیں 
اک متاع دیدئہ تر کے سوا کچھ بھی نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In the caravan nothing but bell’s wailing exists; nothing except the valuable weeping eye exists!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="73">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ختم ہو جائے گا لیکن امتحاں کا دور بھی 
ہیں پس نہ پردئہ گردوں ابھی اور بھی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        However, this period of trial will also come to its end; behind the sky’s nine orbits there are other orbits also.
(Allusion to the nine planets of the sun’s solar system and existence of other systems beyond it.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="75">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سینہ چاک اس گلستاں میں لالہ و گل ہیں تو کیا 
نالہ و فریاد پر مجبور بلبل ہیں تو کیا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What if the tulips and roses in this garden are afflicted? What if nightingales are compelled to wail and complain?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="77">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جھاڑیاں، جن کے قفس میں قید ہے آہ خزاں 
سبز کر دے گی انھیں باد بہار جاوداں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The bushes, which are burnt by the sighs of the autumn, will green up when the breezes of the invigorating spring flow.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="79">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خفتہ خاک پے سپر میں ہے شرار اپنا تو کیا 
عارضی محمل ہے یہ مشت غبار اپنا تو کیا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What if our spark is asleep in the dust of the shield? What if this handful of dust is our temporary abode?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="81">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زندگی کی آگ کا انجام خاکستر نہیں 
ٹوٹنا جس کا مقدر ہو یہ وہ گوہر نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The end of the fire of life is not in the ashes! This is not the jewel whose destiny is breaking!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="83">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زندگی محبوب ایسی دیدئہ قدرت میں ہے
ذوق حفظ زندگی ہر چیز کی فطرت میں ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Life is such a beloved in the eye of Nature; life’s preservation is in everything’s nature.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="85">
      <Text Language="Original">
        موت کے ہاتھوں سے مٹ سکتا اگر نقش حیات 
عام یوں اس کو نہ کر دیتا نظام کائنات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If the death’s hand could efface life’s picture; the system of the universe would not have made it so common.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="87">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے اگر ارزاں تو یہ سمجھو اجل کچھ بھی نہیں 
جس طرح سونے سے جینے میں خلل کچھ بھی نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If it is cheap then think that death is nothing; just as there is no break in living by sleeping.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="89">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آہ غافل! موت کا راز نہاں کچھ اور ہے 
نقش کی ناپائداری سے عیاں کچھ اور ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Ah! O imprudent one! Death’s hidden secret is something different! The instability of the picture exhibits something different!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="91">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جنت نظارہ ہے نقش ہوا بالائے آب 
موج مضطر توڑ کر تعمیر کرتی ہے حباب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The picture of wind over water is sight’s paradise; by break in the restless wave it makes the bubbles.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="93">
      <Text Language="Original">
        موج کے دامن میں پھر اس کو چھپا دیتی ہے یہ 
کتنی بیدردی سے نقش اپنا مٹا دیتی ہے یہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It conceals it again in the skirt of the wave! How mercilessly it demolishes its own picture.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="95">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پھر نہ کر سکتی حباب اپنا اگر پیدا ہوا 
توڑنے میں اس کے یوں ہوتی نہ بے پروا ہوا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If the wind could not create its bubble again; the wind would not have broken it so carelessly.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="97">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اس روش کا کیا اثر ہے ہےئت تعمیر پر 
یہ تو حجت ہے ہوا کی قوت تعمیر پر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What is the effect of this custom on the form of creation? This is the proof of the power of wind over creation.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="99">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فطرت ہستی شہید آرزو رہتی نہ ہو 
خوب تر پیکر کی اس کو جستجو رہتی نہ ہو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If the existence’ nature be not in search of longing it would never be in search of the better form!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="101">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آہ سیماب پریشاں، انجم گردوں فروز 
شوخ یہ چنگاریاں، ممنون شب ہے جن کا سوز
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Ah! The restless mercury, the sky brightening stars; the heat of these sparks is obligated to the night.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="103">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عقل جس سے سر بہ زانو ہے وہ مدت ان کی ہے 
سرگزشت نوع انساں ایک ساعت ان کی ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Their antiquity is bewildering to the Intellect; the history of the human race is a mere moment for them.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="105">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پھر یہ انساں، آں سوئے افلاک ہے جس کی نظر 
قدسیوں سے بھی مقاصد میں ہے جو پاکیزہ تر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Then this Man whose vision is directed to the celestial world; who is more immaculate in his goals than qudsis.* 
* They are the angels surrounding the Divine Throne.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="107">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جو مثال شمع روشن محفل قدرت میں ہے 
آسماں اک نقطہ جس کی وسعت فطرت میں ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Who is lighted up like a candle in the assembly of Nature, in the expanse of whose nature celestial world is a mere dot.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="109">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جس کی نادانی صداقت کے لیے بیتاب ہے 
جس کا ناخن ساز ہستی کے لیے مضراب ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Whose ignorance is restless to know the Truth, whose nail is the plectrum to the harp of existence.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="111">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شعلہ یہ کمتر ہے گردوں کے شراروں سے بھی کیا 
کم بہا ہے آفتاب اپنا ستاروں سے بھی کیا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Is this flame inferior than the sky’s sparks even? Is our sun less precious than the stars even?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="113">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تخم گل کی آنکھ زیر خاک بھی بے خواب ہے 
کس قدر نشوونما کے واسطے بے تاب ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The eye of flower’s seed is awake even under the soil: How restless for growth and development the seed is!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="115">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زندگی کا شعلہ اس دانے میں جو مستور ہے 
خود نمائی، خودفزائی کے لیے مجبور ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The flame of life which is concealed in this grain is under compulsion for self-assertion and growth.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="117">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سردی مرقد سے بھی افسردہ ہو سکتا نہیں 
خاک میں دب کر بھی اپنا سوز کھو سکتا نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Even with the grave’s cold it cannot become dispirited; even by being buried under soil it cannot become cold!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="119">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پھول بن کر اپنی تربت سے نکل آتا ہے یہ
موت سے گویا قبائے زندگی پاتا ہے یہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Becoming a flower, it comes out of its grave that is it gets the robe of life from its death.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="121">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے لحد اس قوت آشفتہ کی شیرازہ بند 
ڈالتی ہے گردن گردوں میں جو اپنی کمند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Grave is the organizer of its scattered powers, which is throwing its rope-ladder round sky’s neck.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="123">
      <Text Language="Original">
        موت، تجدید مذاق زندگی کا نام ہے 
خواب کے پردے میں بیداری کا اک پیغام ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Death is the name of the renewal of life’s taste; behind the veil of sleep it is a message of awakening.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="125">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خوگر پرواز کو پرواز میں ڈر کچھ نہیں 
موت اس گلشن میں جز سنجیدن پر کچھ نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The one accustomed to flight is not afraid of flight! Death in this garden is nothing but readying for flight!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="127">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کہتے ہیں اہل جہاں درد اجل ہے لا دوا 
زخم فرقت وقت کے مرہم سے پاتا ہے شفا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        People say that the pain of death is incurable; separation’s wound is cured with time’s salve.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="129">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دل مگر، غم مرنے والوں کا جہاں آباد ہے 
حلقہ زنجیر صبح و شام سے آزاد ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        But the heart where the grief of the dead ones is living is free from the loop of the chain of morning and evening.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="131">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وقت کے افسوں سے تھمتا نالئہ ماتم نہیں 
وقت زخم تیغ فرقت کا کوئی مرہم نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Mourning’s wailing does not stop with the spell of time; time is no salve for the wound of separation’s sword.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="133">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سر پہ آجاتی ہے جب کوئی مصیبت ناگہاں 
اشک پیہم دیدئہ انساں سے ہوتے ہیں رواں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When some sudden calamity befalls us; tears come out of the eyes constantly.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="135">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ربط ہو جاتا ہے دل کو نالہ و فریاد سے 
خون دل بہتا ہے آنکھوں کی سرشک آباد سے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The heart becomes accustomed to wailing and complaint; the heart’s blood drips from the tearful eyes.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="137">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آدمی تاب شکیبائی سے گو محروم ہے 
اس کی فطرت میں یہ اک احساس نامعلوم ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Though Man is deprived of the power of patience; this sub-conscious feeling always exists in his nature.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="139">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جوہر انساں عدم سے آشنا ہوتا نہیں 
آنکھ سے غائب تو ہوتا ہے،فنا ہوتا نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The essence of Man does not become annihilated; he disappears from sight but is not annihilated.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="141">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رخت ہستی خاک، غم کی شعلہ افشانی سے ہے 
سرد یہ آگ اس لطیف احساس کے پانی سے ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The baggage of life is dust with the flame of grief; this fire is cooled with this subtle feeling’s water.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="143">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آہ، یہ ضبط فغاں غفلت کی خاموشی نہیں 
آگہی ہے یہ دل آسائی، فراموشی نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Ah! This control of wailing is not negligence’ silence; this consolation is awareness, it is not forgetfulness!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="145">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پردئہ مشرق سے جس دم جلوہ گر ہوتی ہے صبح 
داغ شب کا دامن آفاق سے دھوتی ہے صبح
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        When the dawn manifests itself from the east it washes away the night’s stain from the world’s skirt.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="147">
      <Text Language="Original">
        لالہ افسردہ کو آتش قبا کرتی ہے یہ 
بے زباں طائر کو سرمست نوا کرتی ہے یہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It clothes the melancholy tulip in red garb. It makes the silent bird intoxicated with music.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="149">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سینہ بلبل کے زنداں سے سرود آزاد ہے 
سینکڑوں نغموں سے باد صج دم آباد ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The song is freed from the nightingale’s breast. The morning breeze is so full of hundreds of tunes.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="151">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خفتگان لالہ زار و کوہسار و رودباد 
ہوتے ہیں آخر عروس زندگی سے ہمکنار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Those who in rose beds, mountains and brooks were sleeping; at long last in the morning the bride of life are embracing.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="153">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یہ اگر آئین ہستی ہے کہ ہو ہر شام صبح 
مرقد انساں کی شب کا کیوں نہ ہو انجام صبح
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If the law of life is that every night dawn be! Why the end of Man’s grave should not his dawn be!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="155">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دام سیمین تخیل ہے مرا آفاق گیر 
کر لیا ہے جس سے تیری یاد کو میں نے اسیر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The net of my silvery imagination is universal in which I have imprisoned your remembrance!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="157">
      <Text Language="Original">
        یاد سے تیری دل درد آشنا معمور ہے 
جیسے کعبے میں دعاوں سے فضا معمور ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The affliction stricken heart is filled with your memory as in the Ka’bah the expanse is filled with supplications!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="159">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وہ فرائض کا تسلسل نام ہے جس کا حیات 
جلوہ گاہیں اس کی ہیں لاکھوں جہاں بے ثبات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The sequence of Divine commands which is called life; its manifestations are covering myriad of unstable worlds.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="161">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مختلف ہر منزل ہستی کی رسم و راہ ہے
آخرت بھی زندگی کی ایک جولاں گاہ ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The ways of every stage of life are different. Hereafter also is a marshaling place of life!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="163">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے وہاں بے حاصلی کشت اجل کے واسطے 
ساز گار آب و ہوا تخم عمل کے واسطے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Nothing is available there to the death’s field, but the climate is favorable for action’s seed.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="165">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نور فطرت ظلمت پیکر کا زندانی نہیں 
تنگ ایسا حلقہء افکار انسانی نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The light of nature is not imprisoned in body’s darkness; the expanse of the human thought is not so narrow.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="167">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زندگانی تھی تری مہتاب سے تابندہ تر 
خوب تر تھا صبح کے تارے سے بھی تیرا سفر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Your life was brighter than even the moon. Your journey was better than even that of the morning star.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="169">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مثل ایوان سحر مرقد فروزاں ہو ترا 
نور سے معمور یہ خاکی شبستاں ہو ترا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        May your grave be bright like the dawn’s mansion! May this dusty bed-chamber of yours be light-filled!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="171">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آسماں تیری لحد پر شبنم افشانی کرے 
سبزئہ نورستہ اس گھر کی نگہبانی کرے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        May the sky be spraying dew on your grave! May the freshly grown grass be guarding this house!
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>