<Poem ID="09" Name="در اسرار شریعت" BookID="10" BookName="پس چہ بائد کرد" SectionID="01" SectionName="پس چہ بائد کرد">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نکتہ ہا از پیر روم آموختم
خویش را در حرف او واسوختم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میں نے پیر رومی (رحمتہ) سے کئی نکات سیکھے ہیں، میں نے ان کے الفاظ (کی روح) کو اپنا لیا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE ESSENCE OF THE SHARI’AH
The essence of the Shari’ah I have learnt many things from the Master of Rum, especially have I burnt myself in (the fire of) these words of his:
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مال را گر بھر دین باشی حمول
"نعم مال صالح گوید رسول
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اگر تو مال کو دین کے لیے رکھتا ہے تو حضور اکرم (صلعم) کا ارشاد ہے کہ اچھے طریق سے کمایا ہوا مال کیا خوب ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        ‘If you carry money for the sake of the Faith, that money is a blessing, says the Prophet.’
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="رومی">
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گر نداری اندر این حکمت نظر 
تو غلام و خواجۂ تو سیم و زر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اگر تیری نظر اس حکمت پر نہیں ، پھر تو غلام ہے اور دولت تیری آقا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If you don’t keep this point in mind, you are a slave and money is your lord.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        از تہی دستان گشاد امتان
از چنین منعم فساد امتان
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        دولت سے بے نیاز لوگ ہی امتوں کے کام سنوارتے ہیں، سیم و زر کے غلام دولتمند قوموں میں فساد کا باعث بنتے ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The welfare of the nations is in the hands of the poor, while the rich man causes disruption to the nations.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جدت اندر چشم او خوار است و بس
کہنگی را او خریدار است و بس
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ایسے دولتمند کی نظر میں جدّت بے معنی ہے، وہ صرف قدامت کا خریدار ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In his eyes, novelty is something mean; he buys only old things;
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        در نگاہش ناصواب آمد صواب
ترسد از ہنگامہ ہای انقلاب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس کی نظر میں نا خوب ، خوب ہے۔ وہ انقلاب کے ہنگاموں سے ڈرتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What is wrong he regards as right and is afraid of the upheavals of revolution.
(This verse refers to the capitalist’s aversion to change and his striving to maintain the status quo at al cost.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خواجہ نان بندۂ مزدور خورد
آبروی دختر مزدور برد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ایسا آقا اپنے مزدور غلام کی روٹی اور اس کی بیٹی کی آبرو چھین لیتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The capitalist usurps the portion of the labourer, and robs the honour of his daughter.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        در حضورش بندہ می نالد چو نے
بر لب او نالہ ہای پی بہ پی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس کے سامنے غلام بانسری کی طرح فریاد کرتا ہے، اس کے لبوں پر متواتر ہائے ہائے کی فریاد رہتی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The labourer bewails before him like a reed, with constant cries issuing from his lips.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نے بجامش بادہ و نے در سبوست
کاخہا تعمیر کرد و خود بکوست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        نہ مزدور کے جام میں شراب ہے نہ اس کے سبو میں ، وہ (دوسروں کے لیے) محلات تعمیر کرتا ہے اور خود کوٹھڑی میں رہتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        His cup lacks wine; he builds palaces but is himself a homeless wanderer.
(These verses refer to the capitalist’s blatant violation of moral values which, as Iqbal seems to imply, is the natural consequence of amassing of wealth when divorced, motivationally, from spiritual orientation.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے خوش آن منعم کہ چون درویش زیست
در چنین عصری خدا اندیش زیست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مبارک ہے وہ دولتمند جو درویش کی مانند زندگی بسر کرتا ہے؛ جو اس زمانے میں بھی اللہ تعالے کو یاد رکھتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Praise be to the rich person who lives like a dervish and is God-oriented in an age like ours.
(Iqbal characterizes the present age as lacking in spiritual orientation. If amidst such an environment, a person, having wealth, lives a simple life of piety and abstinence; surely it is a matter of great significance.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تا ندانی نکتۂ اکل حلال
بر جماعت زیستن گردد وبال
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جب تک تو حلال کمائی کا نکتہ نہ سمجھے تیری زندگی معاشرے کے لیے وبال ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Unless people understand the significance of a lawfully earned food, life of society becomes miserable.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آہ یورپ زین مقام آگاہ نیست
چشم او "ینظر بنور اﷲ" نیست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        افسوس یورپ اس مقام سے آگاہی نہیں رکھتا، اس کی آنکھ اللہ تعالے کے نور سےنہیں دیکھتی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Alas! Europe is not aware of this principle, her eyes do not see through God’s light;
(Reference is to the famous tradition of the Prophet (PBUH): Fear the sagacity of the believer, for he sees through the light of God.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        او نداند از حلال و از حرام
حکمتش خام است و کارش ناتمام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        وہ حلال و حرام میں امتیاز نہیں کرتا ، اس کا فلسفہ خام ہے اور اس کا کام نامکمل۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        She does not know lawful from unlawful, her wisdom is immature and all her activities defective.
(Iqbal quotes in Bal-i Jibril Rumi’s verse: True knowledge is born of lawful food, love and compassion are born of lawful food.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        امتی بر امتے دیگر چرد
دانہ این می کارد آن حاصل برد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ایک قوم دوسری قوم پر پلتی ہے، دانہ یہ کاشت کرتی اور حاصل وہ لے جاتی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        One nation preys on another, one sows the seed, another takes away the harvest.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        از ضعیفان نان ربودن حکمتست
از تن شان جان ربودن حکمتست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        غریبوں سے روٹی چھین لینا اور ان کے بدن سے جان نکال لینا انکی ڈپلومیسی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It is ‘wisdom’ to snatch food from the weak and to rob their body of the soul.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="31">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شیوۂ تہذیب نو آدم دری است
پردۂ آدم دری سوداگری است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        نئی تہذیب کا شیوہ انسانوں کی چیر پھاڑ ہے اور یہ کام وہ تجارت کے پردے میں سرانجام دیتے ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The way of the new culture is to murder people; and this killing is done under the garb of commerce.
(Iqbal says: Believe me, Europe to-day is the greatest hindrance in the way of man’s ethical advancement (Reconstruction, p. 179). The reason for this, according to him, is that European culture is divorced from the spiritual basis of life, what he callsnur-i haqq here. A few lines earlier, he says in the same lecture: Humanity needs three things to-day-a spiritual interpretation of the universe, spiritual emancipation of the individual and basic principles of a universal import directing the evolution of human society on a spiritual basis.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        این بنوک این فکر چالاک یہود
نور حق از سینۂ آدم ربود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        یہ بینک جو یہودیوں کی عیار سوچ کا نتیجہ ہیں، انسان کے سینے سے اللہ تعالے کا نور نکال لیتے ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        These banks, the result of clever Jews’ thinking, have taken away God’s light from the heart of man.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="35">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تا تہ و بالا نگردد این نظام
دانش و تہذیب و دین، سودای خام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جب تک یہ سودی نظام تہ و بالا نہ ہو دانش، تہذیب اور دین کی باتیں بے سود ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Unless this system is destroyed completely, knowledge, religion and culture are mere empty names.
(Iqbal thinks that Western culture which is through and through secular in complexion cannot be expected to face the challenge of the new age. No change, superficial or far-reaching, can stave off its doom. What is needed is: total destruction of this culture. It is the same remedy that was suggested by Waliullah: total and complete revolution.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="37">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آدمی اندر جھان خیر و شر
کم شناسد نفع خود را از ضرر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اس جہان خیر و شر میں آدمی اپنے نفع و نقصان میں تمیز نہیں کرتا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In this world of good and evil, man seldom knows what is profitable to him and what is harmful;
(Iqbal thinks that human reason is not capable of arriving at the universal moral truth for which man has to fall back upon revelation. Conclusions in the field of morality arrived at by human intellect are more often marred by the natural prejudices to which man is subject.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="39">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کس نداند زشت و خوب کار چیست
جادۂ ہموار و ناہموار چیست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        کوئی نہیں جانتا کہ اچھائی اور برائی کیا ہے، صراط مستقیم کون سا ہے اور ٹیڑھا راستہ کون سا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Nobody knows the right and wrong of an act, which path is straight and which crooked.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="41">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شرع بر خیزد ز اعماق حیات
روشن از نورش ظلام کائنات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        شرع حیات کی گہرائیوں سے اٹھتی ہے اور اس کے نور سے کائنات کی تاریکیاں دور ہو جاتی ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The Shari‘ah grows out of life’s bosom; its light illumines the darkness of the universe.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="43">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گر جہان داند حرامش را حرام
تا قیامت پختہ ماند این نظام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اگر لوگ شرع کی حرام کردہ اشیا ء کو حرام سمجھیں تو یہ نظام قیامت تک پختہ رہتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If the world were to accept its judgment regarding what is forbidden, this system would endure for ever.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="45">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نیست این کار فقیہان اے پسر
با نگاہے دیگری او را نگر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        بیٹے ! شرع کا معاملہ فقیہوں کے بس کی بات نہیں ؛ تو شرع کو دوسری نگاہ سے دیکھ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It is not for the jurists to evaluate it, O son, look at it in another way;
(Looking in another way in contrast to the legal and formalistic attitude of the jurist, it is the penetrative insight born of spiritual regeneration which, though based on reason, goes beyond reason and is the essence of what Rumi and Iqbal call Faqr.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="47">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حکمش از عدلست و تسلیم و رضاست
بیخ او اندر ضمیر مصطفی است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        شرع کا حکم عدل، تسلیم (احکام الہی کے سامنے سر تسلیم خم کر دینا) اور راضی برضا رہنا ہے، شرع کا بیج حضور اکرم (صلعم) کے قلب میں ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Its legal formulations are based on justice and submission to Divine Will, its roots lie in the bosom of Mustafa (PBUH).
(‘Bosom of Mustafa’; innermost heart of the Prophet, i.e. the revelation received by him from God on his heart, as stated in the Qur’an, xxvi 194)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="49">
      <Text Language="Original">
        از فراق است آرزوہا سینہ تاب
تو نمانی چون شود او بی حجاب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اگرچہ اللہ تعالے سے فراق کے باعث وصل کی آرزوئیں سینے میں مچل رہی ہیں لیکن اگر وہ بے حجاب ہو جائے تو تو باقی نہیں رہتا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It is through ‘separation’ (from God) that desires warm the hearts. When ‘He’ manifests Himself, you will cease to exist.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="51">
      <Text Language="Original">
        از جدائی گرچہ جان آید بلب
وصل او کم جو رضای او طلب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اگرچہ جدائی سے جان لبوں پر آئی ہوئی ہے مگر تو اس کے وصل کی بجائے اس کی رضا کا طالب رہ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This separation is no doubt hard to bear, try not to seek union with Him, rather submit to His will.
(The ideal for Iqbal is not to seek unitive experience, experience of oneness with God, but to follow God’s Will which is given in concrete shape in the Shari’ah.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="53">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مصطفی داد از رضای او خبر
نیست در احکام دین چیزی دگر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        حضور اکرم (صلعم) نے اس کی رضا ہی کی خبر دی ہے، احکام دین میں اس کے سوائے اور کچھ نہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Mustafa (PBUH) communicated His will to us; the injunctions of religion consist of nothing else.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="55">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تخت جم پوشیدہ زیر بوریاست
فقر و شاہی از مقامات رضاست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جمشید کا تخت بوریے کے نیچے پوشیدہ ہے، فقر و شاہی رضا ہی کے مقامات ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The throne of Jamshid is hid under the mat (of a faqir), Faqr and political authority are both stations of (submission to God’s) Will;
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="57">
      <Text Language="Original">
        حکم سلطان گیر و از حکمش منال
روز میدان نیست روز قیل و قال
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        پادشاہ حقیقی کا حکم بجا لا ، اور شکایت نہ کر، میدان جنگ قیل و قال کی جگہ نہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Accept the injunctions of the Shari’ah and do not complain the field of battle is not the place to argue why.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="59">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تا توانی گردن از حکمش پیچ
تا نپیچد گردن از حکم تو ہیچ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جہاں تک ہو سکے اس کی حکم عدولی نہ کر ، تا کہ کوئی اور تیری نافرمانی نہ کر سکے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        So far as you can help, do not disobey its law, so that nobody may disobey your orders.
(This verse reminds one of Sa’di’s well-known verse: You too should not disobey God’s commands, that others shouldn’t disobey your orders.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="61">
      <Text Language="Original">
        از شریعت احسن التقویم شو
وارث ایمان ابراھیم شو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        احکام شریعت کی پابندی کر کے احسن التقویم کا مصداق اور ایمان ابرہیم (علیہ) کا وارث بن۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Be of the best make through the Shari’ah, and inheritor of Abraham’s faith.
(Reference is to the Qur’anic verse: ‘Certainly We created man in the best make’ (xcv 4). But if he fails to follow the true path, he is brought to ‘the lowest of the low’. Islam has a particularly intimate relation with the personality of Abraham. The Qur’an states that Islam is the ‘faith of your father Abraham’ who ‘named you – Muslim…)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="63">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پس طریقت چیست اے والاصفات
شرع را دیدن بہ اعماق حیات
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اے والا صفات طریقت کیا ہے؟ شرع کو حیات کی گہرائیوں سے دیکھنا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O man of lofty attributes, what is Tariqah: To see the Shari‘ah in the recesses of life’s heart.
(Tariqah, path: This is another term in mysticism that is sometimes opposed to Shari’ah. Iqbal tries to explain that Tariqah is Shari’ah when its laws are followed in their real spirit.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="65">
      <Text Language="Original">
        فاش میخواہی اگر اسرار دین
جز بہ اعماق ضمیر خود مبین
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اگر تو دین کے اسرار فاش دیکھنا چاہتا ہے تو اسے اپنے ضمیر کی گہرائیوں کے علاوہ اور کہیں نہ دیکھ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If you wish to see the essence of religion clearly, look but into the depth of your heart;
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="67">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گر نبینی، دین تو مجبوری است
اینچنین دین از خدا مہجوری است
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اگر تو یوں نہیں دیکھے گا تو تیرا دین ( باہر سے ٹھونسا ہوا ) ہے اور ایسا دین اللہ تعالے سے دور کرتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If you do not enjoy vision, your faith is only compulsion; such a religion is a veil between you and God.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="69">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بندہ تا حق را نبیند آشکار
بر نمی آید ز جبر و اختیار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جب تک بندہ ، حق (صداقت) کو آشکار نہ دیکھے وہ جبر و قدر کے چکر سے باہر نہیں نکل سکتا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If man does not see God fully manifest, he cannot rise higher than (the polarity of) free-will and determinism.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="71">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تو یکی در فطرت خود غوطہ زن
مرد حق شو بر ظن و تخمین متن
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تو اپنی فطرت کے اندر غوطہ زن ہو کر حق تعالے کا (اطاعت شعار) بندہ بن اپنے ظن و تخمین پر نہ اترا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Dive into your inner nature for a moment, become a man of truth, don’t rely on mere conjecture:
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="73">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تا ببینی زشت و خوب کار چیست
اندر این نہ پردۂ اسرار چیست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        پھر تو دیکھ لے گا کہ اعمال کی اچھائی اور برائی کیا ہے، اور اسرار کے ان نو پردوں (کائنات ) کے اندر کیا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        That you may see the right and wrong of things, and know what secrets lie behind these nine veils.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="75">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہر کہ از سر نبی گیرد نصیب
ہم بہ جبریل امین گردد قریب
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جو شخص نبی کریم (صلعم) کے راز (شریعت) سے حصّہ پاتا ہے وہ جبریل امین (علیہ) (جو حکمت کی علامت ہيں ) کے بھی قریب ہو جاتا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        He who shares in the experiences of the Prophet (S.A.W.) gets close to the faithful Gabriel.
(The angel Gabriel is described in the Qur’an as ‘the faithful spirit (ruh u1-amin) that has brought revelation on thy heart…’ xxvi. 193. ‘Close to Gabriel’ may signify that the person now enjoys the privilege of receiving direct revelation from God.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="77">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے کہ مے نازی بہ قرآن عظیم
تا کجا در حجرہ مے باشی مقیم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اے مسلمان ! تو جو قرآن پاک پر فخر کرتا ہے کب تک حجرہ نشین رہے گا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O you who are proud of having the great Quran, how long will you sit (inactive) in cell?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="79">
      <Text Language="Original">
        در جہان اسرار دین را فاش کن
نکتہ شرع مبین را فاش کن
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        (باہر نکل) دین کا راز اور شرع مبین کا نکتہ فاش کر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Reveal to the world the essence of religion, and the significance of the clear Shari’ah;
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="81">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کس نگردد در جھان محتاج کس
نکتہ شرع مبین این است و بس
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        شرع مبین کا نکتہ یہ ہے کہ دنیا میں کوئی انسان کسی دوسرے انسان کا محتاج نہ رہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        None need be dependent on another (for one’sprimary needs); this is the sum and substance of the clear Shari’ah.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="83">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مکتب و ملا سخنہا ساختند
مومنان این نکتہ را نشناختند
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        علماء اپنے مدرسوں میں محض باتیں بناتے ہیں ، نہ وہ اس نکتے کو سمجھتے ہیں نہ مومنوں کو سمجھتے ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The jurists and the theologians have spun long tales; the faithful have failed to grasp this point.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="85">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زندہ قومے بود از تأویل مرد
آتش او در ضمیر او فسرد
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مسلمان زندہ قوم تھے مگر احکام دین کی تاویلوں نے انہیں موت سے ہمکنار کر دیا؛ ان کے ضمیر کے اندر جو آگ تھی وہ بجھ چکی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A living nation met its death due to misinterpretations, her heart lost fire (of life).
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="87">
      <Text Language="Original">
        صوفیان با صفا را دیدہ ام
شیخ مکتب را نکو سنجیدہ ام
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میں نے صوفیان باصفا کو دیکھا ہے اور علمائے مدارس کو بھی خوب پرکھا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I have seen Sufis of pure heart and taken good stock of the teacher in school.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="89">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عصر من پیغمبری ھم آفرید
آنکہ در قرآن بغیر از خود ندید
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میرے دور نے ایک نبی (مرزا قادیان) بھی دیکھا ہے، وہ جسے قرآن پاک میں اپنے سوائے اور کچھ نظر نہ آیا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My age produced a prophet too, who could see in the Quran nothing but himself;
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="91">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہر یکی دانای قرآن و خبر
در شریعت کم سواد و کم نظر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        یہ سب قرآن و حدیث کے عالم ہونے کے دعویدار ہیں مگر شریعت سے بے بہرہ اور اس کے راز دیکھنے سے بے بصر۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Every one of them is fully conversant with the Quran and the traditions; but they are totally unaware of the true significance of the Shari’ah.
(Their knowledge is theoretical only; they lack fire of conviction and zeal for activity, for they have missed the true spirit of the message.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="93">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عقل و نقل افتادہ در بند ہوس
منبرشان منبر کاک است و بس
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ان کی عقل و نقل ہوس کے بند میں بندھی ہوئی ہے، ان کا منبر صرف کاک ہے (وہ صرف پیٹ کے بندے ہیں)۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Reason and tradition both have fallen prey to lust; their pulpit is a counter for the display of their wares.
(‘Reason’ and ‘tradition’ stand for two kinds of knowledge into which pursuit of learning was divided in classical Islamic period, corresponding to what is called ‘aql and naql.The latter stands for all those aspects of learning that deal exclusively with religious problems, while the former refers to all those branches of learning that today come under the title of science and humanities.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="95">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زین کلیمان نیست امید گشود
آستین ہا بی ید بیضا چہ سود
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        ان 'کلیموں' سے کوئی امید رکھنا لا حاصل ہے کہ وہ قوم کے حالات درست کر سکیں گے کیونکہ ان کی آستینیں ید بیضا سے خالی ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        There is no hope of salvation from these reformers. What is the use of the sleeve when it lacks the White Hand?
(Kaliman, plural of Kalim, the title of Moses. Kalim in Iqbal stands for an ideal reformer, prophet, teacher. ‘White Hand’ is a miracle of Moses.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="97">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کار اقوام و ملل ناید درست
از عمل بنما کہ حق در دست تست
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        قوموں اور ملتوں کے کام اس طرح نہیں سنورتے، اپنے عمل سے ثابت کر کہ حق (سچائی) تیرے پاس ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The problems of the nations cannot be set right by you, unless you prove by action that you are the bearer of truth.
(Translated by Jamil Naqvi)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>