<Poem ID="17" Name="لالہ" BookID="07" BookName="پیامِ مشرق" SectionID="02" SectionName="افکار">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آن شعلہ ام کہ صبح ازل در کنار عشق
پیش از نمود بلبل و پروانہ می تپید
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میں وہ شعلہ ہوں جو صبح ازل عشق کے پہلو میں ، بلبل و پروانہ کے ظاہر ہونے سے پہلے جل رہا تھا ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE TULIP
I am the flame which on creation’s dawn was kindled in love’s heart before the nightingale and the moth came to play their sacrificial part.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        افزونترم ز مہر و بھر ذرہ تن زنم
گردون شرار خویش ز تاب من آفرید
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اگرچہ میں آفتاب سے بڑھ کر ہوں لیکن ہر ذرے کو برداشت کرتا ہوں؛ آسمان نے اپنے شرر (چاند ستارے) میری روشنی سے پیدا کیے ہیں۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I am far bigger than the sun, and pour into each atom’s core a potion of my light: I lend my spark to everyone, and it was I who made the heavens so bright.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        در سینہ چمن چو نفس کردم آشیان
یک شاخ نازک از تہ خاکم چو نم کشید
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        جب میں نے سینہ ء چمن میں ایک لمحہ کے لیے آشیاں بنایا ؛ اور میری شاخ کے اندر سے نمی حاصل کی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Residing like its life-breath in the garden’s breast, in pristine rest, I was drawn up into its bosom by a tree-stem, delicate and thin, as sap that rises up towards the sky.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سوزم ربود و گفت یکی در برم بایست
لیکن دل ستم زدۂ من نیارمید
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        تو خاک نے میرا سوز چھینا اور کہا کہ تھوڑی دیر کے لیے میرے پہلو میں رہ؛ لیکن میرے دل ستم زدہ نے وہاں آرام کرنا گوارا نہ کیا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It quenched my inner fire and, wanting to beguile me, it said, ‘Stay awhile, and don’t go out into the day’; but my heart’s long-repressed desire could brook no more delay.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        در تنگنای شاخ بسی پیچ و تاب خورد
تا جوہرم بہ جلوہ گہ رنگ و بو رسید
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        میرے دل نے شاخ کی تنگی کے اندر بہت پیچ و تاب کھائے ؛ تب کہیں جا کر میرا جوہر رنگ و بو کی جلوہ گاہ تک پہنچا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I writhed and writhed within the tree, encaged, enraged, until the essence of my being found its way to summits of the ecstasy of self-display.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شبنم براہ من گھر آبدار ریخت
خندید صبح و باد صبا گرد من وزید
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        شبنم نے میرے راستے میں قیمتی موتی لٹائے؛ صبح ہنسی اور باد صبا میرے گرد چلنا شروع ہوئی۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        With its pearls of the purest water dew bestrewed my way, as if to say, ‘O what a glorious birth!’ The morning laughed its brightest hue: the breezes blew in hymeneal mirth.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بلبل ز گل شنید کہ سوزم ربودہ اند
نالید و گفت جامۂ ہستی گران خرید
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        بلبل نے گلاب کے پھول سے سنا کہ میرا سوز چھن گیا ہے؛ تو وہ رویا اور کہا: اس نے لباس وجود بڑا مہنگا خریدا ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The nightingale heard from the rose that I had thrown away my own primordial consuming flame. It said, because this crowned its woes, ‘He paid a heavy price to thrive. For shame!’
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وا کردہ سینہ منت خورشید می کشم
آیا بود کہ باز بر انگیزد آتشم؟
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        اب میں سینہ کھول کر آفتاب کا احسان اٹھا رہا ہوں ؛ ہو سکتا ہے کہ وہ میری آگ دوبارہ روشن کر دے ۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        I now stand by my breast rent open to the sun’s effulgence so that it may set ablaze again the fire of my prenatal days.
[Translated by M. Hadi Husain]
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>