<Poem ID="04" Name="گورستان شاہی" BookID="01" BookName="بانگِ درا" SectionID="3a" SectionName="حصہ سوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آسماں، بادل کا پہنے خرقہء دیرینہ ہے
کچھ مکدر سا جبین ماہ کا آئینہ ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        THE ROYAL CEMETERY
The sky is clothed in the cloud’s old tattered robe. The mirror of moon’s forehead is somewhat gloomy.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چاندنی پھیکی ہے اس نظارۂ خاموش میں
صبح صادق سو رہی ہے رات کی آغوش میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The moon light is pale in this silent panorama. The dawn is sleeping in the lap of the night.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کس قدر اشجار کی حیرت فزا ہے خامشی
بربط قدرت کی دھیمی سی نوا ہے خامشی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        How astonishing is silence of the trees; this silence is the soft tune of Nature’s harp.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        باطن ہر ذرۂ عالم سراپا درد ہے
اور خاموشی لب ہستی پہ آہ سرد ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The heart of every speck of the universe is pathos embodied and the silence is a sad sigh on the lips of existence.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آہ! جولاں گاہ عالم گیر یعنی وہ حصار
دوش پر اپنے اٹھائے سیکڑوں صدیوں کا بار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Ah! That fort, that universal mustering ground is carrying millennia’s weight on its shoulders.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زندگی سے تھا کبھی معمور، اب سنسان ہے
یہ خموشی اس کے ہنگاموں کا گورستاں ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Was full of life at one time, now is desolate; this silence is the cemetery of its past elegance.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اپنے سکان کہن کی خاک کا دلدادہ ہے
کوہ کے سر پر مثال پاسباں استادہ ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It is the lover of the remains of its old denizens. It is standing on the mountain top like a sentinel.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="15">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ابر کے روزن سے وہ بالائے بام آسماں
ناظر عالم ہے نجم سبز فام آسماں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        There from the cloud’s window above the sky’s roof that young green star is viewing the universe.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="17">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خاک بازی وسعت دنیا کا ہے منظر اسے
داستاں ناکامی انساں کی ہے ازبر اسے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The earth’s vast expanse is a mere child’s play to it. The story of Man’s failure is known to it by heart.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="19">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے ازل سے یہ مسافر سوئے منزل جا رہا
آسماں سے انقلابوں کا تماشا دیکھتا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This traveler is going to his destination since eternity; seeing revolutions’ spectacles from the sky’s seclusion.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="21">
      <Text Language="Original">
        گو سکوں ممکن نہیں عالم میں اختر کے لیے
فاتحہ خوانی کو یہ ٹھہرا ہے دم بھر کے لیے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Though quiescence of the star is not possible in the universe; it has stopped momentarily for saying prayer for the dead.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="23">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رنگ و آب زندگی سے گل بدامن ہے زمیں
سینکڑوں خوں گشتہ تہذیبوں کا مدفن ہے زمیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This earth is full of flowers of life’s variegations. This earth is the cemetery of many destroyed civilizations.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="25">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خواب گہ شاہوں کی ہے یہ منزل حسرت فزا
دیدۂ عبرت! خراج اشک گلگوں کر ادا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This grief-stricken stage is the resting place of kings; O admonished eye! Pay the tribute of rosy tears.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="27">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے تو گورستاں مگر یہ خاک گردوں پایہ ہے
آہ! اک برگشتہ قسمت قوم کا سرمایہ ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Though a mere cemetery, this dust ranks with the sky. Ah! This is the wealth of an unfortunate nation!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="29">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مقبروں کی شان حیرت آفریں ہے اس قدر
جنبش مژگاں سے ہے چشم تماشا کو حذر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        So astounding is the grandeur of mausoleums that the spectator’s eye evades even winking.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="31">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کیفیت ایسی ہے ناکامی کی اس تصویر میں
جو اتر سکتی نہیں آئینۂ تحریر میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Such an expression of failure is in this picture; which is impossible to reflect in description’s mirror.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="33">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سوتے ہیں خاموش، آبادی کے ہنگاموں سے دور
مضطرب رکھتی تھی جن کو آرزوئے ناصبور
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Far from the habitations’ crowds are sleeping; those who were restless with unfulfilled Longings.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="35">
      <Text Language="Original">
        قبر کی ظلمت میں ہے ان آفتابوں کی چمک
جن کے دروازوں پہ رہتا تھا جبیں گستر فلک
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The grave’s darkness holds the brilliance of those suns; at whose thresholds the sky used to remain prostrating.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="37">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کیا یہی ہے ان شہنشاہوں کی عظمت کا مآل
جن کی تدبیر جہاں بانی سے ڈرتا تھا زوال
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Is this the end of these emperors’ magnificence; whose diplomatic policies knew no decline?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="39">
      <Text Language="Original">
        رعب فغفوری ہو دنیا میں کہ شان قیصری
ٹل نہیں سکتی غنیم موت کی یورش کبھی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Be it the grandeur of Qaisar or Faghfur’s sway; the foe of death’s assault cannot be turned away.
(Faghfur and Qaisar: They are the titles of the emperors of China and the Roman Empire respectively. These two empires and their rulers were emblems of power, authority and grandeur, and they still represent these attribute in Urdu and Persian literature.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="41">
      <Text Language="Original">
        بادشاہوں کی بھی کشت عمر کا حاصل ہے گور
جادہ عظمت کی گویا آخری منزل ہے گور
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The result of kings’ life-efforts also is the grave. The last stage on path of magnificence is the grave.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="43">
      <Text Language="Original">
        شورش بزم طرب کیا، عود کی تقریر کیا
درد مندان جہاں کا نالۂ شب گیر کیا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Neither the happy assembly’s commotion nor the genius’ talk; not even the wailing people’s whole night’s compassion!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="45">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عرصۂ پیکار میں ہنگامۂ شمشیر کیا
خون کو گرمانے والا نعرۂ تکبیر کیا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Neither the tumult of the sword in the battle; nor the cry of blood warming Takbir!
(Takbir: It is the Muslim creed which is ‘Allah-u-Akbar’ (God is Great). It is usually called in battles and other difficult times.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="47">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اب کوئی آواز سوتوں کو جگا سکتی نہیں
سینہ ویراں میں جان رفتہ آ سکتی نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        No call can wake up those who are sleeping; no life can return to the desolate breast.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="49">
      <Text Language="Original">
        روح، مشت خاک میں زحمت کش بیداد ہے
کوچہ گرد نے ہوا جس دم نفس، فریاد ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The soul in the handful of dust* is enduring injustice; when breath enters non-existence’ flute it is a mere complaint.
* Allusion to the human body)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="51">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زندگی انساں کی ہے مانند مرغ خوش نوا
شاخ پر بیٹھا، کوئی دم چہچایا، اڑ گیا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Human life resembles the sweet singing bird, which sat on the branch a while, chirped, flew away.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="53">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آہ! کیا آئے ریاض دہر میں ہم، کیا گئے
زندگی کی شاخ سے پھوٹے، کھلے، مرجھا گئے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Ah! For what purpose did we come in the world, for what purpose did we go away! Sprouted from the life’s branch, blossomed, faded away.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="55">
      <Text Language="Original">
        موت ہر شاہ و گدا کے خواب کی تعبیر ہے
اس ستم گر کا ستم انصاف کی تصویر ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Death is interpretation of the dream of the king and the poor alike; this atrocious one’s terror is the picture of justice.*
* Allusion to the Islamic teaching that death is not annihilation but a change in location and condition. The necessary corollary of the above is the resurrection when real justice will be done to all and all injustices of the worldly life will be redressed. Both these things are ephemeral.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="57">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سلسلہ ہستی کا ہے اک بحر نا پیدا کنار
اور اس دریائے بے پایاں کے موجیں ہیں مزار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The stream of life is a boundless ocean and the grave is a wave of this boundless ocean.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="59">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اے ہوس! خوں رو کہ ہے یہ زندگی بے اعتبار
یہ شرارے کا تبسم، یہ خس آتش سوار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O ambition! Shed tears of blood as this life is unreliable; it is the smile of the spark, it is the flammable straw.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="61">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چاند، جو صورت گر ہستی کا اک اعجاز ہے
پہنے سیمابی قبا محو خرام ناز ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This moon which is a miracle of the Lord of the universe; clad in the robe of gold is slowly and proudly strolling.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="63">
      <Text Language="Original">
        چرخ بے انجم کی دہشت ناک وسعت میں مگر
بے کسی اس کی کوئی دیکھے ذرا وقت سحر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        But in the frightening vastness of the starless sky, its helplessness is worth watching at time of dawn.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="65">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اک ذرا سا ابر کا ٹکڑا ہے، جو مہتاب تھا
آخری آنسو ٹپک جانے میں ہو جس کی فنا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What was the moon is a mere piece of cloud; whose destruction is in the last tear drop.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="67">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زندگی اقوام کی بھی ہے یونہی بے اعتبار
رنگ ہائے رفتہ کی تصویر ہے ان کی بہار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Similarly unpredictable is the life of nations; their glory is a picture of the happy times gone by.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="69">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اس زیاں خانے میں کوئی ملت گردوں وقار
رہ نہیں سکتی ابد تک بار دوش روزگار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In this world no nation however prestigious it may be can continue its existence till the end of time.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="71">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اس قدر قوموں کی بربادی سے ہے خوگر جہاں
دیکھتا بے اعتنائی سے ہے یہ منظر جہاں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        So much accustomed to nations’ destruction is the universe that it watches this scene with indifference.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="73">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ایک صورت پر نہیں رہتا کسی شے کو قرار
ذوق جدت سے ہے ترکیب مزاج روزگار
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Nothing stays the same without change. The universe’ nature is made of change.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="75">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے نگین دہر کی زینت ہمیشہ نام نو
مادر گیتی رہی آبستن اقوام نو
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The beauty of world’s jewel is in ever-changing names. The mother earth has always remained expecting new nations!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="77">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے ہزاروں قافلوں سے آشنا یہ رہ گزر
چشم کوہ نور نے دیکھے ہیں کتنے تاجور
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This highway is acquainted with thousands of caravans. Koh-i-Noor’s eye is familiar with innumerable kings.
(Koh-i-Noor: This was the diamond in the crown of Shahjahan (the Mughal Emperor who ruled from 1627 to 1657, which was the period of the highest glory of the Mughal Empire). This verse alludes to the many kings who used the Koh-i-Noor in their crowns. These included the successors of Shahjahan till the attack of Nadir Shah in 1756 when he took it to Iran. It was taken from Iran by the British after one of the battles with Iran in the 19th century and since then is included in the jewels of the British crown.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="79">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مصر و بابل مٹ گئے باقی نشاں تک بھی نہیں
دفتر ہستی میں ان کی داستاں تک بھی نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Egypt and Babylon are annihilated, not a mark remains; the roll of existence does not have even their names.
(Egypt and Babylon: These are the countries of the ancient world which had reached the highest stage of civilization, including science and technology. Egypt is a country with the longest known history, though the dates of the period before 1600 B.C. are disputed. The oldest known history dates back to 3110 B.C. In the course of history through which Egypt passed several religious and ethnic groups, including Persians, Greeks, Romans and Muslims held suzerainty over it. Each of these periods has left its marks on the civilization and culture of Egypt. Babylon was also an ancient kingdom on the Tigris and Euphrates in South Mesopotamia (present day Iraq). Its history dates back to 3500 B.C. During this period its borders advanced and receded many times. For a great part of their history the Babylonians were traders. They were reputed for their law and administration and temples. They had attained high proficiency in astronomy, medicine and music.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="81">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آ دبایا مہر ایراں کو اجل کی شام نے
عظمت یونان و روما لوٹ لی ایام نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The evening of death has overpowered the sun of Iran. Time has robbed the grandeur of Greece and Rome.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="83">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آہ! مسلم بھی زمانے سے یونہی رخصت ہوا
آسماں سے ابر آذاری اٹھا، برسا، گیا
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Ah! The Muslim also from the world similarly departed; the Aziri* cloud appeared over the horizon, rained and departed.
(Azar: Sixth month of the Greek or Syrian year corresponding to the month of March.)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="85">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہے رگ گل صبح کے اشکوں سے موتی کی لڑی
کوئی سورج کی کرن شبنم میں ہے الجھی ہوئی
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The rose petal’s vein is a string of pearls with dawn’s tears; some ray of the sun is enmeshed in the dew.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="87">
      <Text Language="Original">
        سینہ دریا شعاعوں کے لیے گہوارہ ہے
کس قدر پیارا لب جو مہر کا نظارہ ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The river’s breast is the cradle for sun’s rays: How beautiful is the sun’s sight at the river bank!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="89">
      <Text Language="Original">
        محو زینت ہے صنوبر، جوئبار آئینہ ہے
غنچہ گل کے لیے باد بہار آئینہ ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Juniper is busy in beautifying; river is the mirror; for the flower bud spring breeze is the mirror.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="91">
      <Text Language="Original">
        نعرہ زن رہتی ہے کوئل باغ کے کاشانے میں
چشم انساں سے نہاں، پتوں کے عزلت خانے میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The cuckoo remains calling from the garden’s nest; remains hidden from the human eye in the leaves’ privacy.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="93">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اور بلبل، مطرب رنگیں نوائے گلستاں
جس کے دم سے زندہ ہے گویا ہوائے گلستاں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        And the nightingale, the flowery singer of the garden; by whose presence is alive the glory of the garden:
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="95">
      <Text Language="Original">
        عشق کے ہنگاموں کی اڑتی ہوئی تصویر ہے
خامہ قدرت کی کیسی شوخ یہ تحریر ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Is a living picture of the commotion of Love: How beautiful is this picture from Nature’s pen!
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="97">
      <Text Language="Original">
        باغ میں خاموش جلسے گلستاں زادوں کے ہیں
وادی کہسار میں نعرے شباں زادوں کے ہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In the garden the rose’s silent assemblies are holding. The shepherd boys’ shouts in the valley are echoing.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="99">
      <Text Language="Original">
        زندگی سے یہ پرانا خاک داں معمور ہے
موت میں بھی زندگانی کی تڑپ مستور ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        This old world is so full of life that in death also is hidden the zest of life.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="101">
      <Text Language="Original">
        پتےاں پھولوں کی گرتی ہیں خزاں میں اس طرح
دست طفل خفتہ سے رنگیں کھلونے جس طرح
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The petals fall in autumn in the same way as toys fall from the sleeping infant’s hand.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="103">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اس نشاط آباد میں گو عیش بے اندازہ ہے
ایک غم، یعنی غم ملت ہمیشہ تازہ ہے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        In this cheerful world though luxury is limitless; one grief that is grief of the Millat is always fresh.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="105">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دل ہمارے یاد عہد رفتہ سے خالی نہیں
اپنے شاہوں کو یہ امت بھولنے والی نہیں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Memories of the age gone by are still fresh in our heart; this Ummah cannot erase its kings’ memories form its heart.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="107">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اشک باری کے بہانے ہیں یہ اجڑے بام و در
گریہ پیہم سے بینا ہے ہماری چشم تر
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        These desolate mansions are excuses for shedding tears; insight has developed in the eye with continuous tears.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="109">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دہر کو دیتے ہیں موتی دیدۂ گریاں کے ہم
آخری بادل ہیں اک گزرے ہوئے طوفاں کے ہم
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        We give to the world the pearls of the weeping eye; we are the remaining clouds of a storm gone by.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="111">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہیں ابھی صد ہا گہر اس ابر کی آغوش میں
برق ابھی باقی ہے اس کے سینۂ خاموش میں
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        There are hundreds of pearls in this cloud’s breast; thunder still lurks in this cloud’s silent breast.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="113">
      <Text Language="Original">
        وادی گل، خاک صحرا کو بنا سکتا ہے یہ
خواب سے امید دہقاں کو جگا سکتا ہے یہ
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        It can change the dry wilderness to a flowery vale; it can change the farmer’s hope from slumber to awakening.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="115">
      <Text Language="Original">
        ہو چکا گو قوم کی شان جلالی کا ظہور 
ہے مگر باقی ابھی شان جمالی کا ظہور
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The manifestation of this nation’s majesty has passed, but the manifestation of its beauty has not yet passed.
(The 99 attributes of God are grouped into two main classes, known as Jalali (manifesting His Majesty) and Jamali (manifesting His Beauty). Similarly, the attributes of Islam the Din of God are grouped into Jalali and Jamali classes. The period of the rise of Islamic nations exhibited their material grandeur in all the sciences, technologies and arts whose examples abound throughout the Islamic world… Jamali attributes, consisting of the spiritual and esoteric powers of Islam has not been fully established. This aspect of Islam will manifest itself now.) 
(Translated by Dr M A K Khalil)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>