<Poem ID="16" Name="سرود" BookID="03" BookName="ضربِ کلیم" SectionID="04" SectionName="ادبیات فنون لطیفہ">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        آیا کہاں سے نالہ نے میں سرود مے 
اصل اس کی نے نواز کا دل ہے کہ چوب نے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        چوب نے: لکڑی جس سے بانسری بنتی ہے۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        MELODY
Whence does the zest of liquor come in mournful tune of hollow reed is its main-spring the player's heart, or does it from the pipe proceed?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دل کیا ہے، اس کی مستی و قوت کہاں سے ہے 
کیوں اس کی اک نگاہ الٹتی ہے تخت کے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        What is the source of heart's great might, wherefore to rapture it is prone; how does it topple with a glance the firm and mighty Achamenian throne?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کیوں اس کی زندگی سے ہے اقوام میں حیات 
کیوں اس کے واردات بدلتے ہیں پے بہ پے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Why does the heart bestow fresh life on nations on verge of decline: Why do its states, have constant change, are points that no one can divine?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        کیا بات ہے کہ صاحب دل کی نگاہ میں 
جچتی نہیں ہے سلطنت روم و شام و رے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Why is it that in eyes of man on whom God has bestowed a heart, the realms of Syria, Rome and Rai are fake effects in the mart?
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        جس روز دل کی رمز مغنی سمجھ گیا 
سمجھو تمام مرحلہ ہائے ہنر ہیں طے
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
        مغني: نغمہ گانے والا۔
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The day the minstrel grasps this point which is hid in depths of heart, take it for granted, you have traversed all the stages required by art.
(Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>