<Poem ID="14" Name="" BookID="02" BookName="‫بالِ جبریل" SectionID="02" SectionName="حصہ دوم">
  <Para Name="">
    <Verse ID="01">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دل بیدار فاروقی، دل بیدار کراری 
مس آدم کے حق میں کیمیا ہے دل کی بیداری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        A heart awake to man imparts Umar’s brains and Hyder’s manly parts: If watchful heart a man may hold, his dross is changed to sterling gold.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="03">
      <Text Language="Original">
        دل بیدار پیدا کر کہ دل خوابیدہ ہے جب تک 
نہ تیری ضرب ہے کاری، نہ میری ضرب ہے کاری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        Beget a heart alive and sound, for, if it be in slumber bound, you cannot strike a deadly blow, nor even I can daring show.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="05">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مشام تیز سے ملتا ہے صحرا میں نشاں اس کا 
ظن و تخمیں سے ہاتھ آتا نہیں آہوئے تاتاری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        If sense of smell be full and stunted, the musk-deer never can be hunted: If bereft of sense of smelling true, surmise and guess can yield no clue.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="07">
      <Text Language="Original">
        اس اندیشے سے ضبط آہ میں کرتا رہوں کب تک 
کہ مغ زادے نہ لے جائیں تری قسمت کی چنگاری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        My sighs no more I can withhold, when Muslims’ sloth I do behold: If Muslims do not mend their way, magians their luck might steal away.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="09">
      <Text Language="Original">
        خداوندا یہ تیرے سادہ دل بندے کدھر جائیں 
کہ درویشی بھی عیاری ہے، سلطانی بھی عیاری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        These simple thralls of Yours, O Lord, from every house and door are barred: For kings, no less the acolytes, are fraudulent and hypocrites.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="11">
      <Text Language="Original">
        مجھے تہذیب حاضر نے عطا کی ہے وہ آزادی 
کہ ظاہر میں تو آزادی ہے، باطن میں گرفتاری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        The freedom that this age does grant does ever freedom’s essence want: Though freedom seems to outward sight, yet is no less than prison tight.
      </Text>
    </Verse>
    <Verse ID="13">
      <Text Language="Original">
        تو اے مولائے یثرب! آپ میری چارہ سازی کر 
مری دانش ہے افرنگی، مرا ایماں ہے زناری
      </Text>
      <Text Language="Urdu">
      </Text>
      <Text Language="English">
        O Lord of Yathrib! Cure provide for doubts that in my breast abide: My wisdom to the West is due, girdled my faith like Brahman true. 
(Translated by Syed Akbar Ali Shah)
      </Text>
    </Verse>
  </Para>
</Poem>